♪
It takes a special breed to
live in a province like Quebec.
It gets cold in winter,
and winters are long.
It takes a special kind of
person for whom frozen rivers,
icy, wind whipped streets, deep,
seemingly endless
forests are the norm.
I will confess my
partisanship up front.
I love Montreal.
It is my favorite
place in Canada.
The people who live there are
tough, crazy people and
I admire them for it.
Toronto, Vancouver, I love
you but not like Montreal.
Why?
I shall explain.
All will be revealed.
In the meantime,
check this guy out.
What is the post office motto?
Neither rain nor sleet nor
driving snow nor plague of
locusts prevent the mail carrier
from delivering junk mail?
Here in Montreal the simple task
of delivering the mail in winter
comes with its own
set of hurdles.
Icy hurdles.
I got to ask.
You have special
equipment for this?
We got to like slip on boots?
We do have boots when it gets
icy with spikes on them.
And they give us also slip on
spikes for when it's icy.
Any sort of city ordinance
that you have to shovel if...
Not penalized financially snnchs...
No, nothing like that.
Any injuries in
the line of duty?
I had several incidents.
I broke my ankle.
What is the most perilous
aspect of the job?
Dogs or icy stairs?
In this area there's a lot of
dogs but also icy stairs.
It's one thing have to work
outside in this wintry mess but
takes a strange and wonderful
kind of mutant to actually find
it pleasurable like, well,
these two gentlemen.
Do you like the cold?
I mean... it cleans
the streets of Ebola.
The cold.
The frigid cold keeps the
riff raff out of
the city for sure.
Fred and David, chefs at
the legendary Joe beef.
Historians of their beloved
great white north.
Princes of hospitality.
And what do men like this do for
fun when the rivers turn to ice?
When testicles shrink and most
of us scurry for
warmth and shelter?
If like so many other Canadians
they would go ice fishing on the St.
Lawrence fever.
The cabin fever in the family
because we are confined,
perhaps, to spend so much time
indoors a lot of the families
love to do activities together
like go to the cottage,
go ice fishing.
It's like get you
out of the house.
It's very much a family thing.
Like many of their ilk they'd
seek one of the temporary, small
towns of sled borne cabins,
drill a hole in the
ice, and wait.
But these are not normal men.
So is Quebec better than
the rest of Canada?
Obviously.
Not bad.
Come on.
I mean, you didn't have
to think about that long.
No.
Wait a minute.
Are strippers paid hourly here?
Is that right?
It is considered an
art, a performance art.
So how does that work?
You don't tip a stripper?
You pay per song.
Then you can get a
dance in the back.
Which is a private dance.
Ten bucks a song.
Five bucks a song in public.
That's why I go there because
their songs are super long
and I am a bit cheap.
I go for the lap dance.
After a suspiciously stunned
fish emerges from the
deep it is ignored.
Because Fred and Dave
do things differently.
No crude fried fish and
bread crumbs for these men.
Oh, wow.
Look at that.
Instead a hearty lunch of French
classics accompanied by fine
wines and liquers as befitting
gentlemen of discerning taste
who have exhausted
themselves in the wild.
So this is how you live?
Well, more often than not, yes.
We always have to travel
well and eat properly.
White burgundy.
Glacier bay oysters as
well as thrown in there
delicious.
My prized possession.
The funnest part is the cutlery.
Fred has a wonderful
collection of table ware.
Without getting snobby or
elitist eating off vintage table
ware is one of the
great Joyce in life.
This is the interesting paradox.
You aspire to run a Democratic
establishment and yet you are
hopeless romantics when it
comes to painful nostalgics
the art of living, right?
Sustenance is required like say
a comsumme of ox tail to begin
followed by chilled lobster.
The art of dining is
disappearing much to our
chagrin.
I work super hard at being an
excellent dining companion.
When seeking excellence in a
dining companion what
qualities does one look for?
I turn my phone off, you know?
I never put my
elbows on the table.
Of course.
Come prepared with stories.
Don't drink too much.
Don't become sloppy.
Come prepared.
Absolutely.
No elbows on the table?
No.
It's not proper.
I am a total failure
as a dining companion.
What is that?
What's that, you ask?
An iconic classic of gastronomy?
Look at that sauce.
Holy crap.
The devilishly difficult dish.
A boneless, wild hare in a sauce
of its own blood, truffle,
garnished with thick slabs
seared directly on the top
of the cabin's wood stove.
Look at that.
We're in a wooden shack,
over three feet of ice.
You are hopeless romantics, gentlemen.
Oh, look at that.
The dish is perch atop
an etherial dish.
This is from the vineyard.
Nice.
Wonderful.
Yes, yes it is.
Really.
Is there a billionaire or despot
pot anywhere on earth who at
this precise moment is
eating better than us?
No.
Look at that.
Cheese.
There must be cheese.
In this case a voluptuously
filled dish which some less
hearty outdoorsmen might
call over ripe but not us.
This is awesome.
Here.
A few Cubans.
You guys have a much more
relaxed attitude toward the
importation of Cuban cigars.
Chartreuse of course and a
dessert as rare as it gets.
A dinosaur era monster
long believed extinct.
This is ghetto... who does this?
No one fries it is one of
those, like, painful,
nostalgic things.
Right.
Layers of almond and hazelnut
meringue, chocolate
butter cream.
Look at that!
That was good.
For these guys, this is normal.
This is lunch.
Some days it's like play
house in my house,
French play house.
Yeah?
What do you do?
Get dressed at their house.
No way.
Tell me about it.
The kids, too.
He's a dandy.
A Sunday dandy.
Last time I did I made salad la
orange, and then a huge cheese
Kurd about like 15
kurds of cheese.
Right.
And how many people
are in your family?
Him and his wife and
two young boys.
Right.
How many kids?
So you, your wife, and a
2-year-old and a 4-year-old.
They don't make it to the end
usually until
prematurely opened.
I'm thinking that's... I'm also
thinking I have to do that.
Actually my daughter would
totally be into it.
Once every so often a
nation will produce a hero.
Someone who changes everything
about their chosen field, who
changes the whole landscape,
life after them is
never the same.
This is such a man.
A here to foreunencountered
rugged outdoorsman, veteran chef
with many years of fine
dining experience.
Renegade, innovator, one of the
most influential chefs
in north America.
He is also a proud Quebec wa and
perhaps he more than anyone else
is define for a new generation
of Americans and Canadians
what that means.
He is an unlikely ambassador for
his country and his province but
maybe not so unlikely.
I mean, look at him.
Out for a day trapping beaver
with a local trapper, Carl.
So the bait is wood?
Yeah.
Just the bark.
They eat the bark.
Yeah, yeah.
In pioneer days beaver was
the financial engine of Canada.
Yeah.
Empires were built on it.
Every hat practically in the
world was made of a bever pelt.
That's why today it is
the icon of Canada.
To a lesser extent the
tradition continues today.
Carl continues to trap usually
called on by provision officials
to track beaver and clear away
dams and control what could
become a destructively
overpopulated situation.
Hello, my little friend.
This is a young one.
Those are the one
we want to eat.
What will you compare
the meat to?
Is there anything like it?
That's the thing.
There is nothing.
Nothing like it. When you
eat beaver it's beaver.
Along with an encyclopedia
knowledge of fine wines and
attachment to the music of
Celine Dion he is a big believer
in honoring history
and tradition.
If you still trap beavers you
should if at all possible
cook them and eat them.
Not just strip them
of their pellets.
As incredible as it might seem
you can cook beaver
really, really well.
Beaver tail on the other hand is
not actually beaver at all.
Rather, a quick spoon bread type
of thing that in our case goes
somewhat awry during an
inadvertent inferno.
The sauce almost looks like
chocolate it is so rich looking.
I love it.
When it is like that.
Some people don't put too much
blood but I like when
it is very thick.
Wow.
Absolutely delicious.
It is.
I wasn't joking about it.
It doesn't taste
like chicken at all.
This is your first time.
Wow.
Something I think you
almost eat everything.
Yeah.
At this point, you know, animals
see me and they're like, ah.
That guy.
There is a joke around here
somewhere but to tell you the
truth the stuff
is just too good.
It's like ten below zero
in this freaking town.
That generally does not
spell good times for me.
A good time for me is more like
a palm tree, a beach, a swimming
pool, but the only
cold thing is my beer.
But no.
They like to frolic
in the snow and ice.
More accurately, they like to
obey their genetic imperative to
risk dental and facial injury by
skating around slapping at a
hard disk trying to drive it in
each other's general direction.
I believe they call
this sport hockey.
This is not in my blood.
You skate?
We grew up on this.
Everyone in Quebec?
What else?
There is no reason to live
here if there is no hockey.
Hockey rinks pop up all over
the city to accommodate
Montrealers' desire to risk
teeth, groin, and limb.
Right behind Fred and Dave's
restaurant Joe beef a pickup
game of chefs, cooks, and
hospitality professionals
is under way.
Some of these guys have looked
to be a little long in the tooth
to be out there swinging sticks
at each other skidding
around on the ice.
This is normal behavior?
People actual dye this?
Absolutely.
This is every day growing
up playing hockey.
Canadian national sport, man.
This young one is already
being indoctrinated.
Hello, young man.
You going to play hockey?
Are you going to be a
goalie or a player?
A player.
Wow.
Oh, man.
Am I going to get like a mouth
full of puck by the way?
It's being catered with Fred
and Dave's usual restraint.
Come eat.
Hot coco in Styrofoam cups?
No.
Try a Titanic containing
flintstone sized hunks of pork
belly, bacon, home made
portions, smoked chops, plus
veal and pork links.
Oh, yeah.
This is a truly heroic dish.
Look at the beautiful work.
Awesome.
This is the single best argument
for sharing a border
with Germany.
And of course the finest
wines known to humanity.
German wine, pirate bottles.
Sweet.
What am I drinking?
Canadian.
This is Norman Hardy from prince
Edward county five
hours from here.
Amazing wine.
Here's an allegory
here somewhere.
I'm reaching for it.
Something about friend days,
reckless abandon coupled with
precision and technique.
A hockey metaphor perhaps.
The hell with it.
Look.
Sausages.
Montreal to Quebec city by rail.
160 miles of wintry vistas
whipped past the windows,
evocative for some
of another time.
Sturgeon and caviar.
I'm not sure about Dave
McMillan but in Fred's perfect
world we would all
travel by rail.
It would still be the
golden age of rail travel.
So tell me about the great
Canadian rail system.
It's purely emotional.
Really?
Nothing rational about it.
Fred is what one might call
conservatively an expert.
How extreme is your
railroad nerdism?
This is how bad it gets.
Operating manual.
This model train.
Yeah.
So you have other operations.
Books, printed
information, collectibles.
An enduring love for the great
iron horses that still take
passengers across the
frozen land he calls home.
But it is something more
than just nostalgia.
It's also an appreciation
for a dying art.
It's like the old cruise ships.
You transport your comfort.
You know?
For those days of cross country
rail there were lavish
dining cars, luxurious sleeping
compartments, a bar
car with attendants.
We look at the menus of how
people would eat on trains.
It was inspiration of how
we cook in the restaurant.
All the sweet breads and
fresh peas, leg of lamb.
Current jelly.
Very nice pictures in the
dining by train book.
The guy holding the Turkey
and cutting the Turkey.
Right.
You order a drink.
It comes from a bottle made out
of glass into a glass
made out of glass right.
Which is kind of cool
in our day and age.
It goes back to
service doesn't it?
Thank you.
We are presented with a
perfectly serviceable omlete.
There may no longer be a smoking
lounge with brass spitoons but
this does not mean a
traveler has to suffer.
You always travel
with a truffle?
As a gentleman must.
Wait a minute.
I got to get an action
photograph here.
Canadian rail.
All these people are going to be
expecting... wait a minute.
Where is my truffle?
Can I have the truffle
option please?
Oh, of course.
Don't forget the flop.
Quebec city.
One of the oldest European
settlements in north America.
Samuel Dechanplain sailed up the
Saint Lurns and founded
the site in 1608.
When the fighting started with
you know who Quebec city was the
French stronghold until the
bitter end when the French fell
at the plains of Abraham.
The French may have lost that
one but some things French
have stayed firm, unbowed,
resiliently unchanged
by trends or history.
The continental is the kind
of place about which I am
unreservedly sentimental.
When I was younger I ate here
with my grandparents
and parents.
The best restaurant in town.
Classic.
Unironic cuisine, meaning dishes
you haven't seen
since, like, forever.
Fresh, continental, ocean liner
classics such as... Ceasar
salad, tossed fresh to order.
Table side.
And beef char char also prepared
table side as one must.
Shrimp cocktail.
A shrimp cocktail the way
Jesus wants you to eat them.
All served by a
dedicated professional.
In culinary school
we were taught this.
Real customers is
your final class.
We'd have to do the fruits,
table side, all that which would
fly off the fork and
land in somebody's soup.
I was so bad.
Start with the orange.
Run into trouble.
I'll be right back.
Bite with my teeth.
Stripping the thing.
At least once a day.
One of the students would set
themselves or the
customers on fire.
The inferno would spill
and they'd light it.
There would be this line from
the thing down across
the floor up their leg.
No.
That doesn't happen here.
Like I said, professionals.
This is going to go
like a big fire ball.
Fire ball.
Good.
The kind who know how to
properly prepare these dishes.
Sweet.
Like a goose bump moment.
Yeah.
For Dave, another classic.
A sauce made of cognac, cream.
That is nice.
Look at that.
And for Fred, scampi Newberg.
Awesome.
Absolutely awesome.
For me, that most noble
of dishes, Dover sole.
This appears to be one of the
few remaining servers alive who
knows how to take that fish off
the bone, sauce it, and
properly serve it.
Thank you very much.
So happy.
Very comforting.
There is continuity
in this world.
Across town, another
thing entirely.
The younger, wilder
affaire cech ocech
cech ketchup which
means everything is cool.
Are they hipsters or am I just
crazy and thinks anybody
below 30 is a hipster?
I don't know but I admire them.
So how much did it cost
you when you opened?
Not much.
Look at this tiny electric
four burner stove.
At no point in my cooking career
could I have worked with one of
these without murdering everyone
in the vicinity before hanging
myself from the nearest beam.
How long did it take to adapt.
I would say three months.
In the beginning I was lucky I
didn't have a lot of guests.
I was like oh, man.
I was freaking out.
And yet these kids today.
Look at them go.
Serving a wild Liam Bishs and
quite substantial ever changing
menu out of this, this
Suzy home maker oven.
Tonight there's razor clams
and a cream of haddock.
Very cool.
Thank you.
I love clams.
And you'll notice that nobody in
Quebec seems to
skimp on portions.
Head cheese with mustard.
Oh, and truffled sweet breads.
And some goose hearts
for good measure.
Excellent.
Hearts in general.
Also you got your
grilled tomato bread.
That's salt cod for you Anglos.
I'm all swollen up like the tire
dude and ready to burst
on the directional mist.
Hotel/motel time for me.
How Canadian is Quebec?
Are they truly one
entity or two?
This is a question that has been
wrestled with for sometime.
Question Quebec
is certainly part
of Canada but in many ways
another thing entirely.
There is a lot of history
much of it contentious.
Go back far enough, and you get
a clearer picture of why.
The French arrived on the shores
of Quebec city in the early 16th
century and seccumbed to the
military might of Great
Britain in the mid 18th.
Thus began a gradual but steady
persecution of all
things French.
The Quebecwa have struggled
mightily to hang on to their
French heritage and language.
The issue of seceding entirely a
notion that persists to
some extent even today.
Journalist Patrick la gas meets
me for lunch to help me
understand a little bit of what
many Quebecwa feel is at stake.
I was going to talk about the
whole history, identity,
separatist movement but I have
to get right to the
pressing matter of the day.
Pastagate.
What do you want to know?
For those not up on current
Quebec politics, pastagate
refers to an incident where
local authorities notified an
Italian restaurant they were in
violation of French laws because
they used the word pasta
which is Italian.
Okay.
Stop apologizing.
Okay?
Don't get me wrong.
I lean French, hard.
I am enormously sympathetic
to the language laws.
You don't think it
is preposterous?
I do not but here we
have a situation.
It is stupid.
I agree with you completely
that this province 40 years ago
was in some respects
an English city.
We needed to have language
laws for signage and stuff.
Now, signage for instance
must by law be
principally in French.
French first in all things.
But every bureaucracy produces
by products of stupidity.
That was it.
You know what?
It will not stand.
The Anglo Canadian treated
French speaking Quebec law like
second class crap for
much of history.
I get it.
I'd want my own thing and when I
got it I'd want to make sure
there is no back sliding
to the bad old days.
The first sovereign to be
elected in 1976, it didn't
come out of a vacuum.
It came out from a couple
decades of awakening and
struggle.
50 years from now will people
still be speaking predominantly
French in Montreal?
Yes.
No doubt about it.
French first is something
most would agree with.
How far and how vigorously you
want to go with that, well,
do you think there is any
possibility or real majority
plurality who would have voted
in separate nation status?
In English you guys say
timing is everything.
The timing was never
better than in 1991, 1992.
From 1995 this country came
inches from being broken up.
Do you think it will happen
in the history of the world?
I don't know.
But I know one thing.
Anybody who says separatism is
dead in this country and
this province is a fool.
No matter how you feel about
Quebec, either separate from or
as essential part of greater
Canada, any reasonable
person loves this place.
Correct me if I'm wrong.
This is famous for the
sandwich special.
What tradition
does this fall in?
Basically eastern Europe.
It was a survival thing.
It was because they were poor.
And that's what they could make.
Wilensky's an old school
corner institution around since
1932 serving up pressed meat,
bologna, and salami sandwiches
or specials as they call them
with egg Greens and milk shakes.
So the special and an
appropriate beverage.
Very happy.
Here's how it goes.
There are rules.
The special is always
served with mustard.
It is never cut in two.
Don't ask why.
Just because.
That's the way it's
always been done.
A little respect for
tradition, please.
Hum.
I'm happy now.
Some things are beloved
institutions for a reason.
This is delicious.
Thank you.
The tradition of the sugar
shack is as old as maple syrup
here in Quebec where 70% of the
world's supply comes from.
Deeply embedded in the maple
syrup outdoor lumber Jack
lifestyle is the cabin in the
woods where maple sap is
collected and boiled down to
syrup.
Over time, many of these cabins
became informal eating houses,
dining halls for workers and a
few guests where a lucky few
could sit at communal tables and
enjoy the bounty of the trees
and forests around them.
This tradition has been taken to
what is somehow both its logical
conclusion and insane extreme.
Creating his own shack open only
during maple season and serving
food stemming directly from
those humble yet hearty roots.
It makes perfect
sense in one way.
I mean, 130 acres produced about
32,000 gallons of maple sap,
which run through these tubes
here where they're cooked down
to about 800 gallons of syrup,
which is more or less what
they use per season here.
Nothing leaves the property.
And it makes sense while you're
here to raise hogs and cattle on
the property and maybe keep a
cabin or two around for any
friends who get too
loaded to sleep it off.
But this?
This is there really
any reason for this?
What are you doing here?
Why do you have to
make life so hard?
If money were your primary
motivation, this doesn't seem
like the fastest road
to untold wealth.
You know, everybody had a
you can go back three
generations and they
had a sugar shack.
I am very proud of Quebec.
I'm very proud of Canada.
You know?
You celebrate Canadian history.
You celebrate
cannadian traditions.
You celebrate Canadian
ingredients in a way
that no one else has.
Are you some kind of patriot?
Is that what's going on here?
Is it national...
Very much a patriot.
I say it all the time.
This is one of most important
restaurants to me in north
America if not the world.
An art installation if
you actually look at it.
The meal begins with a
power of maple desserts.
Good lord.
Sponge maple toffee, maple
donuts, beaver tails,
maple cotton candy.
But wait.
There's more.
Almond croissant,
whipped biscuits.
Some nugget.
Yeah.
Ah.
There we go.
I think that is a first for me.
I've never seen that done.
Not with a hammer.
Then let the madness begin.
Next, a whole lobe of baked
beans on a pan cake cooked
in duck fat of course.
Cottage cheese and eggs
cooked in maple sirup.
Wow.
That's awesome.
There's a healthy salad.
Sauteed duck hearts, gizzards
and pig's ear topped with a
heaping pile of
fried pork rinds.
Good lord.
Oh, and a calf brain and
maple bacon omlete.
And these.
How this is made?
With love.
Panko-encrusted duck drum
sticks with shrimp and salmon
moose and maple barbecue sauce.
Good lord.
Wow.
This is a classic dish.
It is a meat pie.
Calf brain, sweet breads,
bacon, and with Martin
that is not sufficient.
Usually there is no
truffle but I just...
Yes, black truffles.
More truffle.
Too much truffle.
My blood is getting thicker
as I look at that.
Now the main course, a home
grown smoked right out front
local ham, with pineapple
and green beans almandine.
And with chicken, but with
Martin, chicken is
never just chicken.
Stuffed with foie
gras and lobster.
We pump lobster bisque
into the chicken.
Good god.
There is a light at the
end of the tunnel.
Oh.
Someone should be singing the
national anthem now,
I mean, really.
In practically prehistoric
old-schooled Canadian classic,
maple syrup is heated, then
poured on snow, making a kind of
Taffy, but the preferred
delivery mechanism does
present some issues.
No, no, no, no, no.
What?
Take a big one, and
you have to suck it.
Don't swallow it, you know?
Look, you have to go like
that, slowly, slowly.
You know?
Just slowly, slowly.
That's how it's good.
That's it.
Can I do that in a manly way?
You just sort of look
away in a distracted way.
I'm not really... the
best way is to look up.
Finally maple meringue cake
and maple ice cream with
chocolate shards.
Any suggestion on
how to attack it.
We did it once.
I went the chef suggests a cone
and the chef suggests
you eat it like that.
There's the thing.
I think there's too much
focusing on the food, wow, these
are very intellectual and wow.
I've done too much of
all those... you know?
I don't want to do that.
I don't want to play
games any more.
Because food is
feces in waiting.
This is CNN.
If there's one thing you
always need on a cold snowy
night, it's yet
another hearty meal.
I meet back up with Dave and the
Liverpool house, sister
restaurant to Joe beef.
I think we always compensate
a little bit with
overabundance of food.
Because of our insecurity of not
being, like, good cooks.
You know what?
It's a combination of low
self-esteem and generosity that
explains the amount
of food, perhaps.
First course... gravlax of char.
Salman gundi.
Beets and eggs.
Look at that.
Unbelievable.
Look at the aspic work.
This is smoked potatoes inside.
Salmon pastrami.
Wait a minute.
This is super classic.
Soft, boiled or poached egg
in clear gelatin broth classly
garnished with white ham,
tarragon leaves and black
truffles.
Oh, my god, I was pretty sure
I would live the rest of my life
without ever seeing this again.
Delicious.
But tonight after a full week of
Franco-Canadian full-on assaults
on our livers and our lights,
Fred and Dave thought it would
be good to take advantage of the
insanely delicious fare by their
brilliant chef Omar,
who's from Pakistan.
Amazing, authentic
Pakistani food.
What do we have here?
Butter chicken crab, tikka,
pomegrana pomegranate.
A little mushrooms.
Rabbit korma.
Fingerlings with a
fenugreek and fennel.
This is donkey hanarri.
Yes, he did say donkey.
The dishes continue.
Pakistani gumbo with okra and
coriander, a says my seed
and green pepper curry.
Hangar steak, scotch egg, and an
authentic goat biryani.
Wow.
Biryani's awesome.
Are you full?
Yeah.
Pretty close.
We did good work here.
In the end, and perhaps as a nod
to the Anglo tradition,
however, there will be stilt.
This is a genius meal.
These princes of gastronomy,
never a suboptimal moment.
Nothing short of
excellent accepted.
Beyond excellent.
Too much excellent?
Yes.
Possibly.
Over the top?
Yeah, definitely.
It all comes around in the end.
The circle of life.
We begin at the beginning, the
heart and soul of every
right-thinking Quebecois,
apparently.
Ice, a stick, and a puck.
Fred and Dave and Martin Picard
are joined by the original god
of Montreal gastronomy, the
great chef Norman la Pris to
watch their beloved Montreal
Canadians lay waste to
the Carolina hurricanes.
All the while eating, of course,
and drinking, as it turns out,
the finest wines
known to humanity.
And here we go.
Oh!