25 years later,
after the Wall fell,
Berlin remains complicated
and unfinished.
Complicated by history
and counter-history
with an urban fabric
that resists all attempts
to reorder it.
♪
Berlin fascinates
and people continue to be
drawn to its darkness
and its light.
♪ I took a walk
♪ Through this
beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪
♪ Found something good
♪ In this beautiful world
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪
♪ Sha la la-la-la
♪ Sha la la-la-la-la
♪ Sha la la-la-la-la la
♪
Berlin is never Berlin,
they say.
Pounded into rubble by Allied
bombs and Russian artillery
in World War II,
surrounded,
then hacked in two
during the Cold War,
then reunited and reborn,
Berlin is a city of ghosts.
An ever-evolving space
where memories and new ideas
live side by side.
♪
In between and after the wars,
Berlin has always been a place
where you find what you want
or what you think you need,
what you can't get back home.
A place where fantasies
could come true.
It's all here,
if you know where to look.
It's no coincidence,
it's a natural progression,
really,
that Berlin's nightlife
is excessive,
completely and proudly
uninhibited,
and never-ending.
There are clubs for everybody
and many are friendly towards
whatever your personal
lifestyle choices might be.
Club culture is the pride
of Berliners
and draws millions
of thrill seekers
from all over the world.
It is notoriously difficult
to navigate, however,
and finding the right place
with the right mix
that will actually
let you in the door
can be a challenge.
♪
Who decides who gets in,
keeps each place
with its own personal,
non-judgmental balance
are people like Frank Kunster.
For 25 years, he's been
the gatekeeper and bouncer
at some of Berlin's
most infamous club doorways.
♪
You were described
as a legendary doorman.
Yeah, maybe.
Older?
Well, the... the last three
years at [indistinct] bar.
Right.
A professional partier
in Berlin, what time do they
show up at the club?
6:00 in
the morning.
- No way.
- Oh, yes, of course.
So wait a minute,
you arrive at 6:00 am.
And then the clubs,
they go from Saturday evening
to Monday morning
without any break.
So people go there normally
Sunday morning
and then they dance Sunday
all day and all night,
then go home Monday morning.
So you're talking 24 hours.
No, 36 hours, no problem.
36 hours. What are you
doing for 36 hours?
Dancing, talking, chilling,
hugging, [...]ing,
whatever.
I don't want to do any of
those things for 36 hours
personally, I think.
Danke.
Um, I have to begin, sir.
Beautiful.
As a large man with
a physically challenging job,
Frank likes meat,
as I do.
So a long-established
butcher shop
like Fleischerie Domke
is just what
the both of us need.
♪
Pork schnitzel with murky,
delicious brown gravy,
and boulette, which I gather
is German for meatballs,
is the kind of working-class
food one wants
and needs.
So what attracted you
to this business?
The night had always, like...
I always was...
attracted to the night.
I think people in the night
when they are on alcohol
or on drugs
open their mind.
Because it's dark, they
are more free in their mind.
I found that interesting.
Berlin is world-famous
for its club scene.
Why here?
I think because we are
the last liberal city,
like real liberal, you know?
The people can afford being
here, it's cheap to drink,
it's cheap to live,
it's cheap to eat,
and people come here because
of the freedom to party,
to get wasted
as hard as possible.
How about the police
and the government at this time?
You know, you've got thousands
of people taking ecstasy
and dancing all night till
11:00, 12:00 the next night.
I think the government know...
I know policemen
and they know about, like,
people doing drugs
and they come to our clubs
to do drugs by themselves
or not or they drink,
but they accept
and everybody's cool with it.
Berlin is a party city.
It's no real industry
besides a party industry
and so, so many tourists come
here only because of that
from Spain, from Italy,
from Russia,
from U.S.,
from U.K.
to get totally lost
and totally wasted
but not in a bad way,
just like in a Buddhistic way.
It's like in the moment you get
lost you can find yourself,
and that I think
what excess is about.
Pure hedonism.
Come to Berlin, get high, party.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
♪
The Wall.
An absurd, tragic,
almost metaphoric,
but all-too-real expression
of humanity's failure
and depravity.
A 96-mile stretch of concrete
and razor wire
cut Berlin into an island
of capitalistic West
and gray, soul-crushing,
repressive communist East.
They keep
a few chunks of it around,
a reminder of terror,
of triumph,
or simply to take selfies
in front of.
Every day
fewer and fewer remember
that the world almost ended
right here.
♪
Even as the wall fell,
techno music seemed to
express something
that needed to be expressed.
Dance music and ecstasy
and mammoth nightclubs
exploded across
a reunited Berlin.
During that time,
DJs like Ellen Allien
were pioneers of the new sound
and a new generation.
♪
East and West, a unifying force.
Sausage is my favorite food.
As a German, you need sausage.
Mm.
Yeah, it's... it's good.
Mm, very good with apple
and, I think.
Lunch at Michelburger,
a joint on Friedrichshain.
♪
Sausage of chicken,
pig's feet, and sage
with smoked mashed potatoes
and apple.
Beef shoulder braised and
served with root vegetables,
potatoes, horseradish,
and, God help me,
kale.
When did the Wall come down?
That was what year?
- '89.
So everything started in '89.
Everything started in '89.
First, the club scene
was based on the...
On the West side
where the first
techno club opened.
Wall came down and then
everything moved to the East
because there was space,
a lot of industrial places,
and music was a meeting point
of the East and West
and a meeting point of young
people trying to move together.
It just happened in the club.
When the Wall came down, it was
our music to come together,
so it's very deeply
in our blood.
Right.
That's why it's
so strong for me,
so being a DJ,
because this time was a very
strong impact for my soul.
♪
Over time,
so many artists, musicians,
writers
from elsewhere
have come to Berlin.
It's always been sort of
a magnet for artists
for a lot of reasons.
Why do you think
here of all places
would be so welcoming
and attractive to
creative people?
I think after the second war
everything was burned here.
There was nothing.
Nothing was here, only like
broken stones, you know.
Everything was gone,
all the history.
So people start building up
the new Berlin or whatever
and we are still in that
process, you know,
and when you come here you
have... you have the feeling
that you have to help
to build something here.
I'm a part of it.
If I go to Paris, I'm not
thinking I'm a part of Paris.
I'm not, because there is
so much history
you can see, or Rome...
Right.
I think only about
the Rome history.
- Yes.
- 'Cause there's everything
you can touch.
It's an open air museum, yeah.
But here, you have to feel
you're building something.
I think that's why
so many people come here.
When I'm here,
I start being so creative
because it
means something to me.
It's a very quiet city
but also there is something
, you know?
Something that you have
the feeling
you want to be a part of,
and I think that's why
many people come here.
There's no past.
There's only a future.
- Mm.
- In a sense.
You can create
your own world here.
Yeah.
Exactly, yeah.
♪
You know, when I was a teenager,
the... the real punk rockers
were like [inaudible] us,
and we were like... so they would
all be like, "No, no, no."
Punk's dead."
By the time we go into it,
it was like [inaudible].
Hi, everybody, this is Anton,
and I'm gonna tell you about
what I did
to make dinner.
I used two legs of lamb.
I need to get a paper towel.
I washed them first,
and I laid them down
on the cutting board
and I stabbed them.
♪
And I sliced cloves of garlic
into small slivers
and I inserted those
into the holes.
Then I rubbed the lamb
with olive oil
and covered it in sea salt
and black pepper
and then...
I sliced potatoes
and parsnips and carrots
and a little bit of onions
and made a bed inside
a glass Pyrex dish
and I stuck those in the oven,
got them very hot for a second,
and then I turned it
all the way down to about 125
and I let it go.
Anton Newcombe is a legend,
a true believer,
the man behind
the ever-changing entity
known as
The Brian Jonestown Massacre,
which was always basically him.
Seen by many as perhaps
the greatest
and most promising
musical force since Bob Dylan,
he avoided mainstream success
with a notorious combination
of self-sabotage
and sheer determination
to do his own thing his own way,
completely independent
of the industry
he loathed.
♪
Anton, who comes from
Southern California,
has made Berlin his home,
his refuge.
We're gonna do it at 146.
- 146?
- Yep.
What's gonna happen is
there's gonna be two of it.
I'll go like that
and we'll just see, okay?
We're not going to a change yet.
I'll keep eye contact
about switching.
He makes music,
paints, and cooks
in his studio.
Still tours to sold-out shows,
collaborates with other
artists to brilliant results,
and continues to create
and record incredible music
his own way...
♪
Always.
Zero compromise.
He's not just one of the most
prolific recording artists
in history, but an excellent
and enthusiastic cook,
frequently combining both
callings at the same time.
So this has to come out.
♪
So it was cooking from
almost 1:00
to 6:00 maybe.
I also made sweet potatoes
and stabbed those
and wrapped them in foil
and I covered the bottom of
the oven with foil
because they tend to leak
of sugar.
It's very hard to clean that
stuff but that's what they do.
♪
I mash potatoes very simply.
It's good stuff.
♪
I think that's the... the
basic stuff that we cooked.
♪
Right there,
and the lamb turned out good.
So there you go.
♪
Today, Anton basically
prepared a delicious feast
for a large group of friends
and wrote, composed,
and recorded some new songs.
It is entirely likely that
he released the record...
♪ Yeah
In the following days.
For a guy with a reputation
for being... let's say difficult,
by the way, he was, with us,
always lovely,
kind, indulgent,
the host with the most,
and he made
a really good dinner:
an incredible soup,
a mind-boggling array
of side dishes,
serious cooking chops.
♪
You've been adored.
You've been the hot band
that everybody wanted.
You've had all the things that
a lot of people coming up,
you know, yearn for.
I wonder what thrills you.
I like...
Music's a puzzle to me
because I'm not...
I'm self-taught,
so I basically have to
teach myself every idea
that's going through my mind
and they're going really quick.
It's like a race to
accomplish it.
♪
What's your turnaround time,
because it's legendary,
like, between recording...
You're smiling...
And releasing?
Well, we have been
making a song a day.
Like, in between cooking
right here,
I was able to record with her.
It's no problem.
And I constantly
want to challenge myself,
and right now I want my music to
have a certain amount of energy,
because I'm 50
and I want to prove to people
that it's irrelevant
how old you are.
I just enjoy playing music.
That's why I'm 50 years old
and playing music.
♪
Yeah, you know what I mean?
It's like I just
want to remind people
that they can just do
what they want to do
and I'm gonna... I'm gonna go
ahead and do what I wanna to.
But meanwhile, I would love to...
The one thing that I could
accomplish in my life
was just to remind people that
they... it's a possibility
that they could do
what they want to do
if they want to do it.
Do you... do you make...
Did I hear you make schnapps?
Ollie's got it going on.
He's got... they have their own...
This bottle right here.
Oh, nice.
It's beautiful, wow.
Everybody makes their own
little aperitif thing.
There's... every different area
has their own types.
There's a million different
types, you know.
So this is ours.
♪
Wolf, are you gonna do one?
It'll put hair
on your chest, son.
Look everybody in the eye
and you gotta go...
Look, you gotta go,
"Skoal."
Say skoal.
Skoal.
Okay, you got it.
Now you say prosit, okay?
Ready? Get ready.
Ready? Here we go.
Ready?
Here we go.
Prosit, say it.
Prosit.
♪ It's all so plain to see
♪ What you hope
you make believe ♪
You got it.
I should point out here that
the young man is
drinking grape juice.
Right on.
Wow.
♪
People talk nostalgically
about Paris in the '20s,
the flapper era in the States,
but there was really no place
like Berlin in that time.
We vividly recall with horror
the rise of national socialism,
the Nazis,
but simultaneous to that,
a bubble of extravagantly
created ferment
of artistic experimentation,
sexual libertinism,
intellectual growth,
open tolerance of excess
in all things,
all the constraints
of the Victorian age
seemed to be crumbling...
for a while.
♪
During the Weimar Era,
as it's called,
people flocked to Berlin,
to its cabarets, its clubs.
Art thrived.
Its cinema led the world.
Escape from the hardships
of daily life
were everywhere it seemed.
This, right alongside
the rising tide of evil
that would soon
eat half the world
and reduce much of it to ashes.
♪
Do you see any parallels...
- Oh.
- Between Germany in the '20s
and where we are today?
- Yes.
Like, when you read Isherwood
or other people
from other countries
that have been to Germany,
they say...
Yeah.
"Oh, everything is so cheap
and affordable,
and you can get anything,
anything you want."
The thing here, it's just...
Just go for it.
I mean, people still
come here just to
disappear into the nightlife
and then live their fantasies.
And again, it was exactly
like that in the '20s.
It's the same
but just different.
Brendan Nash is a historian
who gives walking tours
highlighting the Weimar Era's
more famous expats.
Else Edelstahl
is a promoter of
'20s-themed events
throughout the city.
Le Pustra has been called
cabaret's darkest muse.
He's the creator of
"Kabarett der Namenlosen,"
a Weimar Era theatrical event
that reimagines cabaret culture of the '20s
with dark, brooding
sexual undertones.
We meet at Grosz in West Berlin.
Though promised 1920s style
classic fare,
I was, in this regard,
disappointed.
The food was excellent, though.
Germany's cool with, you know,
come to our country,
get high and... and... and party.
It's not Germany, it's Berlin.
- It's Berlin.
- Yeah, yeah.
And in Berlin we say,
Berlin is not Germany.
- Yes, yeah.
- True.
I remember the first time
I was in Berlin
when I was 14 years old.
And I remember
exactly coming here
and having this almost physical
feeling of freedom.
Like, I was a goth girl
at that time.
Like, I started to only wear
black and listen to dark music,
and when I came to Berlin,
like, I was like,
"Yes, here I can be
who I want to be."
And it all... it almost felt
a little magical.
Yeah.
Do you think the people who
came here from other countries
back in Weimar Era and now,
people are looking for
a dark side, do you think?
Certainly the people are
looking for things
they couldn't do at home.
- It's like...
- They're looking for...
They'll come here
for the forbidden.
Things that... you know,
you can tell the people
who've come and gone crazy.
It's captured people's
imaginations
and people come here in search
of that divine decadence.
- Yeah.
- And it is here.
It definitely is.
During the Weimar years
and later,
just before and after
the Wall came down,
Berlin became a refuge
for artists, writers,
and musicians at a crossroads
in their lives.
Most notably, in 1976,
David Bowie came here.
Have a seat.
Well, there we go.
There we go.
Jim Rakete is
a celebrated photographer
known for
his intimate portraits.
He began his career
as a photojournalist,
and in '76, captured the first
moments of David Bowie
stepping off the train
in West Berlin,
a city he would live and work in
for the next three years.
Bowie was exhausted
and burned out
and looking for a new way
to live and to work.
And the music he created
during that time
was something truly
groundbreaking and new.
The result was both
a professional
and personal rebirth
and some of the most powerful
and influential recordings
of all time.
Classics which
I'd love to play here
but cannot afford.
He wasn't a big name
at the time,
but it was a historical point
because he came to Berlin
the week after
he split with his band.
And from I.A.,
he went to Berlin.
He had to regenerate from...
Well, I.A. had been
really bad.
I mean, apparently existing
only on cartons of milk...
Yeah.
And cocaine, I think,
and not much else.
Yeah.
He essentially came to Berlin,
oddly enough,
given his reputation,
to clean up.
Yeah.
Clearly in really bad health,
in a really bad place.
Mm-hmm.
And yet the music
that he made here
was very different than anything
he'd done before.
What do you think he found here
that was good for him?
Well, he lived a pretty
low-profile life in Berlin.
I have to say that.
He could be anonymous here.
Like, everybody admired him,
but nobody talked to him.
That's a big advantage.
And a funny thing is
when you have that sort of
visionary pregnancy
that you say
something's gonna come,
something's gonna
fall from the sky,
it does.
Now, back in the early '70s
when David Bowie arrived,
a lot of people don't realize,
but Berlin was surrounded.
I mean, it was
essentially an island
during much of that period.
Yes, yeah.
Outside of
whatever Bowie was doing,
what was... what was it like
in West Berlin at that time?
It was like pressure cooking.
You know, it was like
pressure cooking.
West Berlin was
surrounded by the Wall
and there were just three
roads leading to West Berlin
and they were controlled by
the Russians, basically.
So why would a walled city
surrounded by hostile forces
be such a hothouse
for art, music,
and free expression?
West Berlin was always
very international.
We had, like,
people were flying in
from all walks of life.
Artists from all genres
were here,
and we were surrounded by East.
The Wall was a solid resistance,
and you need a strong enemy to
build a strong muscle.
And people who were living here
had to improvise a lot.
It's what is seen by many as,
you know, a golden period.
The Weimar Era was in fact
a hotbed for music
and culture and art
in between two
really awful events...
Yes.
Followed by the wartime years,
followed by,
postwar
the village was in ruins.
When were the good times?
I have a...
I have a very complex
answer to that,
and that is,
the best times are now.
We have all the freedoms
that we want, you know.
I think the best times are now.
♪
Sunday afternoon in Berlin
at the Mauerpark flea market
is a place where expat artists
and locals alike
can find what they want
and didn't know they needed.
Oh, there you are, Wolfgang.
Can't lose you.
Adidas tracksuit.
Oh, man, that's a good look.
Joining the throngs
of frugal shoppers,
Anton, Wolfgang, and I.
We have some purchases in mind.
So this is where I usually
take a cigarette break
because...
It'll be a while?
Well, what would you do if you
had a five-year-old brain?
This is like...
Yeah.
His synapses is going...
♪
Can we spend one second
with the records?
Oh, hell yeah.
The main thing that
I'm looking for is
always Beatles in mono,
anything in mono
from the '60s stuff
for when I DJ.
Yeah.
Okay, I'll get two records.
Quick enough, right?
Cool.
Thank you.
He asked me for the...
For, like, the third time
where I come from and he
remembers that I'm in a band
and that I've
lived here for years
and I see him every week.
He's an interesting guy,
kind of.
He tends to moan a lot.
♪
You know what
you're ordering for dinner?
I think... I think German food.
♪
I'm assuming that most days
you're working in the studio.
Do you take days off
when you just do nothing?
I should be doing that, see.
But, yeah, I like to
create every day,
and then sometimes
I'm just too tired.
That's why my studio is
just always set up as a house.
So I just go there
and lay on the couch,
listen to records.
Because the type of music
that I listen to
keeps my mind-set
exactly the same endlessly
so my month becomes like a day.
And my... my sleep
becomes like a nap.
I just pick it up
where I left off.
So I can think on ideas
on the back burner
of my mind for...
For weeks, you know?
It's like the...
What they would call, like,
alpha wave generation.
It's just like you keep yourself
going in the zone, you know.
It's weird.
Oh, no, that's him, actually.
Yeah, it looks good.
Super.
I love this. This is
what I come to Germany for.
They love it.
That's the real deal.
Eisbein is pork knuckle,
or more accurately,
a big freakin' shank.
Unlike schweinshaxe,
its crispy roasted cousin,
eisbein is brined, cured,
then boiled with spices
until tender
and falling off the bone...
♪
Usually served with sauerkraut
and boiled potatoes.
♪
Schnitzel, pounded, breaded,
and deep-fried
and served with brown potatoes
and creamed mushrooms.
What do people like here?
I mean... or do you even know?
Well, you know,
it goes from cheesy pop
to rock, garage.
People love techno.
It's known for techno.
Yeah.
And real ethnic
singalong get-drunk songs.
Do you play locally?
Do you play here a lot?
- No, no.
- No!
You just...
You live and work here.
You record here but you don't...
I'm not interested
in it too much,
'cause I have nothing to prove.
I mean, I've been playing
since I was 11 years old.
Do you... do you think you have
any responsibility as a musician
other than to make
the best art you can?
Well, I have self-set goals.
I believe it's
the duty of older people
to hold the torch just till
somebody gets it
and then even older people can
look behind them and go,
"Aw, somebody else got it.
They're following
down the road."
So that means like
an older writer
can go, "Okay, all isn't lost."
"It didn't end in the '60s.
Here's this younger guy
who's 50."
- Right.
- See?
But it's my responsibility
to hold that torch for other
people that are younger
than me down the road.
And even for the... the squares to
leave just this tangled mess
of your art and ideas
and let people figure it out.
Don't spell it out.
Right.
You know?
But I love it up here.
I think it's okay, 'cause
people stay out of my hair
and you can be invisible.
Well, that must be nice.
Crazy, right?
This is actually really good.
Mm.
No human could eat all of this.
Yeah, it's farmer style.
Yeah.
I ain't... I ain't farming
nothing after this.
♪
The ubiquitous and deeply loved
signature street foods of Berlin
are currywurst and doner.
And what better place to enjoy
such delicious treats
than in front of a classic
of German cinema.
In this case, Fritz Lang's
silent masterpiece,
"Metropolis,"
an artifact of the Weimar Era
that's still
politically relevant.
It's seen as a cornerstone
of cinema
and the mother of sci-fi movies.
Billy Wagner has invited me
to a midnight showing
at the booze- and food-friendly
Lichtblick-Kino movie house
in Prenzlauer Berg.
♪
He's the co-owner and sommelier
at the Michelin-starred
restaurant
Nobelhart & Schmutzig
in Kreuzberg.
The question of the day being,
what German wines
pair best with a utilitarian
treat like currywurst?
Fried pork sausage
smothered in ketchup
and a dusting of curry powder.
Now, how did this become
a beloved dish?
I have no idea.
A lot of flavor, it's spicy,
it's fat, it's salt.
It's roasted, then you have
fries with it.
- Mm-hmm.
- It's...
Oh, I understand why
people eat it.
Alcohol.
Drunk food, yeah, well, yes.
But at the end, it's
a very cheap thing, you know.
You get two sausage with fries
with a beer,
when you pay much, 10 Euro.
Oh, so like a quick
worker's lunch.
Yes, yeah.
So what wine would you
suggest with this?
We should try
[indistinct] champagne.
There's a place in Berlin where
they serve currywurst
with champagne.
Really?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Champagne
always works obviously.
Oh, I like this.
It's a good match.
Super.
It's a cool place
that you can come
and see movies like this.
The film premiered in Berlin
in 1927
presenting troubling issues
of its time.
And it turns out, ours:
corporate greed,
political corruption,
social inequality,
and in a figure of
Brigitte Helm's Maria,
the dangerous, yet powerful,
role of the individual activist
in an oppressive culture.
Her eyes, I mean,
she's a little cross-eyed.
Yeah, but that's sexy, you know?
Yeah.
Now, here we go.
Classic German food.
- Huge.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's... you eat one, you know?
I'm not finishing this, man.
Oh, my God.
It's enormous.
Kebab was introduced to Berlin
by Turkish immigrants
and doner kebab
is the German iteration.
You know, at the end
it's something which is
in every culture.
You have something grain
outside,
bread, and then it's
stuffed with something.
Mm-hmm.
You have meat in it.
You have salad with it.
You have spicy sauce,
a lot of chili,
and you're gonna find it in all
kind of different versions.
♪
We should maybe try the red,
see what it does.
Sure.
♪
This is also classic drunk food.
I mean, it's greasy, it's messy,
it's... it's wet, it's crispy.
It's got it all.
And it's very easy
to be done vegetarian.
Well, I need the meat.
I mean, that big loaf
that they put together,
I mean, I don't know how
they make it or extend it
or whatever the hell it is.
I don't really care
what's in it.
It's meat.
I don't want grass-fed
Colorado or Australian lamb
on my... on my doner kebab.
I want... I want a... I want this.
You know, especially again,
if I'm a drunk late at night
watching "Metropolis"...
♪
Berlin has a dark side
but you knew this.
You don't have to look too hard.
But renowned photographer,
Miron Zownir,
has been looking with a fixed
gaze on people in the margins
for decades.
♪
For over 40 years,
he's worked diligently
to capture the world's
darker shades,
its most marginalized people,
the outsiders,
the transgressive,
the forgotten,
the desperate and depraved,
always in a nonjudgmental,
unblinking way.
These are some of the shots
we can put on TV.
Many we can't.
I urge you
to find them.
You've shot a lot of hustlers,
dope addicts,
prostitutes.
How did you approach
your subjects?
Right up, right in, picture,
or do you establish
a relationship?
Well, it always depended
on the situation.
Some were not aware of me,
others were exhibitionists.
I had fights,
but most of the time
I didn't have any problems
because they were
situations I knew,
okay, now I better retreat
or I get my ass kicked.
I had a very good sense of
how far you can go.
♪
In recent years, Miron has
been making films as well.
Shooting in abandoned spaces,
celebrating all that is taboo,
all that is wrong...
All that is right
about Berlin...
With an unflinching gaze
and a genuine affection
for his subjects and characters.
♪
Berlin has a reputation
as a place that you can come
and be anything you want,
behave pretty much as you want.
Nobody's gonna hassle with you.
Mm-hmm.
Is that true,
do you think, and why?
Endemic art is still possible.
This is really important.
You can create here
independently,
affording your little space...
Mm-hmm.
And do what the [...]
you want to do.
Of all the capitals in Europe,
it's still the cheapest
and more affordable.
Maybe you don't get anywhere
and maybe
you don't make much money,
but you can create freely.
- Right.
- No artist
in New York City,
Paris, or London
can do this anymore.
Well, you said,
you can't even rent a space.
- No. Yeah, yeah.
- It's impossible.
You can't... only if you're
really established artist,
you can live in these places.
So you can come to Berlin
and you can have maybe
a little show in
some basement or cellar,
and at least it's a start
and it's an interaction,
and this is good and this is
really good about Berlin,
it was always good about Berlin.
♪
Echoes of lives lived,
lives lost.
No other city has
been repeatedly so powerful
then fallen so low.
Few other cities
have been so shaped
by individual imaginations
either brilliantly creative
or unspeakably evil.
Start again, start again.
Look back at the past.
Never forget it.
Like an Irish playwright said,
"You must go on.
I can't go on.
I'll go on."
♪