And vacation over as he... we
headed home to our regular
beds, our daily lives of school
and homework and ordinary
things.
Maybe my little brother, maybe I
would wake up and look out the
window at the night sky and
suddenly it would fill with
stars and golden mist, and we'd
pretend for a second we were
somehow deep inside the milky
way, a million winking lights,
but we knew where
we really were.
We were almost home.
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ Sha, la, la, la, la
♪ sha, la, la, la, la, la,
♪ sha, la, la, la, la
♪ sha, la, la, la, la, la, la
O enchanted land of my
childhood, a cultural petry dish
from which regularly
issues forth greatness.
New Jersey, in case you didn't
know it, has got beaches,
beautiful beaches, and they're
not all crawling with raging
trolls with reality shows.
I grew up summering on those
beaches and they're awesome.
Jersey's got farmland,
beautiful bedroom communities.
Even the refineries, the endless
clover leaves of turnpikes and
expressways somehow beautiful.
To know Jersey is to love her.
Ft. Lee, you may
have heard of it.
Some of governor Christie's
minions allegedly conspired
to jam up traffic a few days.
It's a town with a joky history
of corruption, it's also
where my beloved Hiram's is.
Opened since 1932 and unchanged
since, my dad started bringing
me and my younger brother here
in the 50s and they
still honor tradition.
Sometimes I just the
need that old flavor.
It seems like a chew food.
Basically my dad
would take me here.
It is a great point of pride and
satisfaction and I've convinced
my daughter this is the
finest hot dogs in the land.
She gets very excited to come
out here, which makes me happy.
Thank you.
This is heat.
The toothpicks are
just like 1958.
Some things just
shouldn't change.
My dad used to love relishing
that I loved this stuff.
Look at that beauty.
Oh, yeah.
I come here to feed my soul, the
cultural wellspring
that's new Jersey.
It's the antidote to
every other place.
The place is perfect.
The dogs are amazing.
There are not a lot of people in
this world courageous
enough to not change.
Down the shore, yeah, we
actually talk like that.
It was what we did,
go down the shore.
Not just our family from Bergen
county near the bridge, but
families and working-class
families from all over who
packed up the kids in the
station wagon for the
intermable trip to long island.
There was always drama.
Once we were over the bridge,
the excitement would ratchet up.
Ship bottom, then surf city,
love ladies, ticking off the
town names until finally,
finally, Barnegat light.
New.
These are all new.
That's original.
Yeah, definitely.
I think I know who lived
there at one point.
That's definitely old school.
Let's face it.
It's been how many years?
40... 400, I think.
Jesus, we're old.
The lighthouse.
Definitely remember going
to that lighthouse a lot.
Definitely the good old days.
I want some fried clam strips.
Absolutely.
Our options are limited,
shall we say, but holy crap.
This place is filling up.
I think it's because
it's the only place.
Who lives out here year round?
We're about to see every
single one of them.
Let's be honest.
When we came here in the sum
summers, I was the bad one.
Yes, yes.
Your recollection is correct.
I didn't smoke dope for
the first time here.
I was looking for dope, but as a
12-year-old it was
hard to come by.
I remember you vaguely walking
off with some sort of
cute girl.
First kiss.
This is good.
It is good.
I realize now I
hitchhiked regularly.
Yeah.
Mom, dad, I'm going to go to
ship bottom tonight
with some friends.
How are you getting there?
Hitchhiking.
Okay.
Have fun.
That's how you got places here.
Summertime.
You know that sound?
Just out of the water, eared
pressed up against the beach
blanket, the squeak of bare
feet on sand nearby, classics
illustrated comics waited
for me back at the house.
I'd play with my little plastic
army men in the dunes and
there's a smell of beach
grass in the dunes.
You remember it?
I still crave it.
I love it.
And on special occasions
clams in drawn butter.
I remember this place with
nothing but fondness.
I can't remember a
single bad memory here.
People you knew from
last year we were here.
The parents didn't
need to be with you.
Have a campfire on
the beach at night.
All this stuff they wouldn't
let you do at home.
The beach would look different.
For a couple of days, the beach
would be this weird foamy surf.
Now we're talking.
Or there would be the jelly
fish delivery sometimes.
Infestation of
jelly fish, right.
I try to block that out.
Love the clam strips.
These are great.
These are awesome.
So far, so great.
I'm happy.
Battered piece of fish with
some good tartar sauce.
What were your
favorite activities?
Building a campfire
on the beach.
Firecrackers on the beach.
I have some firecrackers
in your car, by the way.
Just saying.
Set them off at the casino.
Perfect.
♪
It was paradise.
America's first dream vacation.
The beach as far as America was
concerned, meaning bathing suits
and swimming in the surf, was
pretty much invented here.
Atlantic city, rich or working
class, it was here for you.
Back then you dressed up
to walk the boardwalk.
It was capitalism at its
purist and most assertive.
It was a Democratic dream
designed from the beginning for
everybody.
Flashy, utilitarian, upright,
deeply, unapologetically,
corrupt.
In many ways its story a perfect
reflection of changing times.
Established in 1912, the second
floor had curtained alcoves
and a separate lady's lounge.
Vicky's dad was the chief
photographer for Atlantic city
from the 1930s to the 1960s.
He saw it all and by
extension so did Vicky.
What was it like here as a kid?
It was fantastic.
Walking down the boardwalk in
the summertime was like
walking a carnival at midway.
There was still
remnants of the 20s.
Yeah.
Handle bar mustaches,
Victorian graphic art and
illustration was still very much
in evidence, even in my
time here in the early 60s.
The boardwalk was over six miles
of amusements, entertainments,
parades, and pageants.
A never-ending carnival.
Every place you went down the
boardwalk was something else to
see and all the stores were mom
and pop stores, all very unique.
Yes.
The world famous steel pier,
amusement arcades,
salt water Taffy.
I loved the joke shops.
The joke shops.
It was a wonderland of
juvenile delinquency.
It was just something very
sinister and forbidden.
The menu has changed
somewhat since the original.
For me, a very tasty pretzel
crusted swordfish
over lump crab meat.
For Vicky, pan-seared scallops.
Times were not good.
It was largely empty, but it
was a magnificent structure.
You and I like the nostalgia.
The people who like coney island
like it, but I don't know
about the young people.
Beautiful buildings are
beautiful buildings.
A beautiful view is a
beautiful view forever.
There's no other place with this
kind of history and legitimacy.
This place has deep
romantic allure.
I agree with you.
I believe in the
transition that's coming.
I really, really do
with all my heart.
Hundreds of businesses
used to be here.
It's not a matter of, gee, that
would be great if
that happened again.
It is inevitable that
it will happen again.
Atlantic city can be chic easy
because the bones of the
city are beautiful.
I'm glad you feel that way.
A beautiful old restaurant
with really great food is much
more interesting than a
glass box with good food.
The names of Atlantic city
streets were imprinted on
generations of Americas who
grew up playing monopoly.
You see history, the ebb and
flow of America's hopes and
dreams played out in the
buildings and homes you see as
you pass by.
Cheap takeout, the
footprints of a lost world.
The riviera of the northeast
still there if you look in
between.
With jet travel in Miami and an
expanded highway system,
things declined as they do.
But a few visionary geniuses
presented a solution, a cure
that would overnight make
everybody well, make Atlantic
city shiny and new and
prosperous again.
Men like Donald Trump.
I think it's going to be
really very beneficial to
everybody.
We look forward to operating the
Taj Mahal for many
years to come.
They rushed to Atlantic city
eager to tap into what was
assured to be a never-ending
gusher of prosperity, casino
gambling.
When casino gambling was sold
to New Jersey and to Atlantic
city as the cure-all,
did it change anything?
Do you think it helped?
No, I don't.
Brian Donohue is with 20
years experience focusing on
south Jersey.
Dock's oyster house, an
establishment that survived
prohibition, two world wars,
numerous declines, and rebirths.
Still here, still great, a
symbol of what Atlantic city
was, should be, and
should be again.
It was seen as an easy answer.
It sure sounded
like a good idea.
They were going to bring 12
casinos here and bring everybody
up from the top down.
It hasn't worked.
When you're left with
just 12 casinos...
If you're looking for an example
of lemming like lurch of
cliff face from which to tumble,
look no further than this
$2.4 million goat rodeo.
It opened in 2012 and closed
less than two years later.
The most expensive casino
in en engine history.
What were they thinking?
Short-term money at a time
when other casinos were opening
all over the east coast.
It's nuts.
It's economics 101.
Casinos, by design, neglect
the city's assets, salt air,
a walk by the glorious north
Atlantic, the classic
attractions, the restaurants.
This is what it is going to
take for Atlantic
city to come back.
It's going to be
places like this.
Celebrate the ghosts.
Some nice crab cakes at dock's,
a big freaking lobster
stuffed with crab imperial,
plum sou souffle.
Those things are bad for
business, the business of taking
your money.
Thank you so much.
That'll work.
That's good.
I don't want to sound like I'm
down on Atlantic city, because I
see it as an incredibly almost
ludicrously hopeful place.
Whatever is left should be hung
onto because it is
going to come around.
There's nothing funny about
losing all your money, yet
casinos are steady employers
of that most hard-working
entertainer.
It's so much money to live here.
I drove three exits on
the Jersey turnpike.
It was $7.
If you drive a whole New Jersey
turnpike, when you get to the
end you have to
give them your car.
I'm going to tell you
something that I don't tell
people right away.
I'm vegan.
I do cheat a little.
I eat veal.
It's so tender.
How do they get it like that?
I'm very sentimental about
Jersey Italian, particularly
spaghetti and meatballs.
I've eaten here at least five
to ten times and I've
never had a bad meal.
I wouldn't get the meatballs.
Proud long-time residents
of New Jersey.
I've lived here for nine years,
but have only been proud
for the last two.
One was the first time you
played Atlantic city?
There was a club at the sands.
Many times I would get paid on
Thursday and then I would lose
it all and then I'd
have to work for free.
There's no worse feeling.
Oh, I know that feeling.
Have you ever watched a
couple in Atlantic city?
Hold this money.
Don't give it back to
me no matter what I do.
An hour later, give
me my god damn money.
You better give me my money.
You're the reason I'm losing,
touching my arm when I'm
shooting craps.
Is there a specifically
Jersey sense of humor?
Yes, I love Jersey
audiences now so much.
I have never one time said
anything where people in the
audience have said, ahhh.
They never get offended.
I have my trigger words.
As a white woman, the
word I don't like is no.
I don't hear it that often,
but when I do huh-uh.
Here's the deal with Jersey.
People land up north and
they drive up the turnpike.
Refineries.
That's New Jersey.
How sick is it that I
think it's beautiful?
More horses per capita
than any other state.
I worked for an
embroidery company.
I swear to god.
I'll call her right now.
Will people ever come across
the bridge and the tunnel
in the other direction?
No.
No?
Okay.
I did not have to
think about that.
Let's go out to a
club in Jersey.
It's all relative.
A 6-year-old person is going I'm
getting the [ Muted
] out of this city.
There's your answer.
Never going to be you.
Where does hipness stop?
Hipness is overrated.
Yeah, it is overrated.
I love living here.
Pine valley, the best golf
course in the country.
Trump... trump, I'm not a fan.
Who is?
Every minute that he walks,
the man has a certain... it's
like if you have
a disfigurement.
That's too much to ask
of me in trump's case.
I want to screen.
Do you know why he puts his
names on the building?
So the banks know which
ones to take back.
At least he's a humble guy.
Jesus.
There are few American cities,
places where things have
gone as disastrously wrong
as Camden, New Jersey.
It's like a poster child for
everything a city can screw up.
Once a manufacturing power
house, home to the New York
shipbuilding company,
a company town.
About 80,000 people
live here today.
That's the same number of
people employed in its heyday.
The entire police force
replaced by the state.
More than 1/3 of city residents
live below the poverty line.
Voter turnout not good.
If there's any place one can be
forgiven for just throwing your
hands up in the air and
giving up, it's here, but no.
Cities with serious problems
need extraordinary people and
Tawanda Jones is clearly an
extraordinary person.
When you give, especially to
someone who is really in need,
you know, I feel... it
makes me feel complete.
Her late grandfather Walter
green Jr. was a
former military man.
He was just like the protector.
If you need anything, you go to Mr.
Dynamite.
That was his nickname.
When Tawanda was 15, she was
asked to lead a local drill
team.
Unfortunately, it soon
lost his funding.
Walter purchased uniforms and
drums to get it its start.
Today CSS, the Camden
sophisticated sisters drill
team, which includes the
distinguished brothers in taps,
the almighty percussion sound,
have over 320 participants.
Good job, babies.
Good job.
Clap it up for yourself.
Clap it up.
We meet at stalwart
Tony and Ruth steaks.
What was Camden like back
in the good ole days?
Oh, my god.
It was so different when...
Coming up when I was younger.
That sense of community
was strong back then.
You were talking about your
childhood as if it was a real
long time ago.
What the hell went wrong?
People can blame it on the
politics, but I think
that's too easy.
Know what your child is doing.
You're putting it
principally on the parents.
Absolutely.
This is tasty.
This is delicious.
So the conventional wisdom
seems to be get out of Camden.
Why are you still here?
Because the need is
still in Camden.
If every decent person leaves
Camden, then we never a chance.
In order to be a part of the
program, they have to maintain
a C average or better.
It's all about the academics.
It's all about
nurturing these kids.
What's right, what's wrong.
They believe this.
They say it so much
until it is embedded.
Tawanda has helped support it
with financial assistance.
Surprisingly with a group of a
national profile no lasting
support from official
organizations public or private.
Yet she perseveres.
We've been under
Bridges, everything.
Over 28 years, we've
been outside.
Their safety is the most
important to me, but it's been a
blessing and a curse.
You'll have the corner boys come
up and ask you are you having
practice outside today,
today is not a good day.
Okay.
All right.
Thank you very much.
That's nice.
I appreciate it.
Trust me.
How do you keep the
kids off the corner?
I'm quite aware that times
are hard, but I just try to show
them an alternative route.
There's so much more
out there than this.
Some call me major pain,
but it's all out of love.
They need to discipline in life
to go to work, to go to school.
They're doing it
because it's fun.
Right.
But it's hard.
Yeah.
You're asking people to do a
hard thing and they're doing it.
Yeah.
And I got to ask, I'm going
to guess in the years that
you've been doing this you've
had to have had your
heartbroken many times.
You've had to see kids that
you've really believed in fall
by the wayside and
I'm guessing a lot.
How do you go on?
We have a lot of sad stories,
but our good outweighs the bad.
I keep going just
for that reason.
You know, before I was a little
hard on myself and I used to
think that I could save all the
kids, I know that's
not the case.
I just do the best
that I can do.
And I just pray the next kid
doesn't fall by the wayside.
How do you not become cynical?
Do you harden your heart?
No, actually I have to
replenish myself or I'm not
going to be good to
them or my own family.
These kids are
precious cargo to me.
Some of them have the
responsibility of a
30-something-year-old.
They're holding
down their homes.
25 years down the road, what
do you think Camden
is going to be like?
I'm praying that it turns
into the Camden that I remember,
and I know that I'm helping our
future leaders to become
a part of that change.
There's no doubt in my mind that
there's going to be
a positive Camden.
No doubt.
You're going to say?
I'm not going anywhere.
My pop-pop didn't leave.
I'm not leaving.
Yeah, I know.
Philadelphia is
right over there.
Right across the Ben
Franklin bridge.
The center of the Cheesesteak
universe, but what if it isn't?
They're better than that.
They're bigger than that.
And the best Cheesesteak in the
area might well come
from new Jersey.
Donkey's opened by Leon
Lucas 71 years ago.
A heavyweight contender in the
Olympics in boxing he was known
in his time of the
Calvary as the donkey.
This is what they do here.
Behold the Jersey Cheesesteak.
Pleasure to meet you.
So this is the best
Cheesesteak in south Jersey,
unless I'm mistaken?
New Jersey.
New Jersey, period?
Yeah.
Is there a difference?
We do ours on a round
Poppy seed roll.
It's round.
It's got steak, spices, browned
onions, real American cheese,
such as it is, and
a Poppy seed roll.
Fantastic.
Thank you, sir.
And it is sublime.
Relish, what do you think?
Hot pepper.
A little bit?
I drove a long way for this.
Thinking about it the whole way.
Man, this should be like
national landmark right away.
This sandwich is
unbelievably good.
Thanks.
Really a thing of beauty.
That's a good thing to here.
We get a lot of
people from Philly.
Wow?
That's treason.
Do they change their plates on
their car or wear a disguise?
It's delicious.
Jersey cheesesteaks, I'm not
saying they're better than
Philadelphia... yeah,
I am actually.
This is great.
Glad you enjoyed it.
The forests and empty spaces
of New Jersey are vast and often
empty of everything but legend.
You live here if you like a
quieter life of not
being messed with.
1.2 million acres of Atlantic
cedar, swampland, forests.
It goes on and on, seemingly
at times forever.
It's easy to get lost.
♪ In the back water marshes
where the Cranberries grow ♪
We'd joke about Pineys.
The strange, possible inbred
tribes of people who lived out
there, somewhere
between the trees.
That's what we believed anyway.
Paul Evans Peterson, jeweler,
musician, author, and proud
piney.
We meet at the Lucille's in
Warren grove for a delicious
breakfast.
The legend of the New Jersey
devil was mother
Leeds had 12 kids.
Found herself pregnant with a 13
and said may this
child be a devil.
It morphed into this creature
and went up the
chimney in the night.
It's supposed to have the head
of a horse, wings
of a bat, hooves.
People have seen horns on it.
It breathes fire.
It has a real long tail
with a triangle on it.
It sounds like my little
pony with a fork tail.
It doesn't sound
frightening to me.
Head of a goat.
Goat is a little bit scarier.
♪
♪ They say you still hear him
screaming when the
conditions are right ♪
♪ Yeah I swear it's
true what's out there?
Who are Pineys?
Do the roam the forests at night
searching for souls to capture?
Pineys are people who
live in the pine barrens.
People like to be thought
of as living off the land.
How do you make your living?
It is good to farm
blueberries and Cranberries.
A lot of fishing, a
lot of clamming.
Hopefully the oystering is
coming back in the Delaware bay.
The pine barrens have
settled it for a long time.
Some of the people who came
here with the glass makers.
It is perfect for making glass
to the point where it didn't
have to be washed or processed.
There was hundreds
of glass workers.
They're just ruins now.
Thank you.
All right.
So, it's not like the
rest of Jersey here.
No, and I hope it
stays like that.
It's like a Jersey unto itself.
It's a long drive
to get anywhere.
That's good, by the way.
That's really good.
Ain't it great?
You want to talk mythic,
epic, storied, that sort of
thing?
Welcome to Asbury park.
Wellspring of American
music of a certain kind.
Home to, yes, the boss.
And the Jersey national
anthem "born to run."
♪ $9 for driving to Haiti
Springsteen, Bon Jovi, little
Stephen, but before them there
was this man, Southside Johnny,
who pretty much created the
template for the Jersey sound
and it could have only been this
place that changed music
and lyrics forever.
♪
Asbury park, it's had a
reputation as being a happy
hunting ground for
musicians because what?
A lot of bars?
The town was started not to
have alcohol and not that kind
of music, but after awhile the
pressure was too much for
entertainment for people to come
here and it morphed into an
Rb rock and roll history.
This is the Jersey shore.
The Jersey shore means
people want entertainment.
Atlantic city didn't
have that reputation?
Well, we're not Atlantic city.
We're Asbury park.
As I always like to say,
good is good forever.
Great music, great songs, and a
classic Jersey Saint leech.
Sliced ham, provolone and your
oil and vinegar that marries
it all together into a glory
vehicle of deliciousness.
Thank you.
It's such a beautiful that
they shred the lettuce and
everything.
You used to come here as a kid?
Yeah.
My father would order a pastrami
so we had to order
what he liked.
He could really eat.
Asbury park, like its close
cousin, Atlantic city, who it
had so much in common
suffered the same problems.
4 years ago, last time I came,
it was a shell of itself,
a sad and forlorn place.
Unlike Atlantic city, Asbury
park sought to fix itself to
become the kind of place that
anybody would want to live in.
They didn't look for a magic
bullet like casino gambling.
To a great extent, they
succeeded by keeping alive what
made Asbury park special.
They hung on to
what was important.
Like this place, where any
overgrown child still wants to
play.
Thank god.
What?
Tilt.
Oh.
No, way.
That's delicate.
Come on, hit, baby.
Hit.
Oh, man.
Oh.
This is important for children.
I think so.
Your first exposure to racy
images of women are all set in
some sort of 20s universe and it
teaches you shame and
humility when you lose.
Exactly.
The limits of how much you can
break the rules before it tilts.
I think they should have tilt
for all sorts of things.
I think so too.
Step over the line in a bar
talking to a young lady, tilt.
That way you know you
got to start again.
I tilted it already.
I barely touched it.
What are you talking about.
That's what they all say.
Let me play!
Oh!
As I like to say,
good is good forever.
The Atlantic ocean will
always be magnificent.
Looking at it always a humbling,
even educational experience.
It teaches us that
men come and go.
But no matter how foolish or
outsized their dreams, how badly
they screw up, what we do here
at the ocean's edge, the
sea will outlast us.
We'll always draw us to her
edges, when necessary it will
crush us.
We look at the Taj,
completely oblivious to
everything going on around her.
And that has got to be the
most butt ugly building ever.
I noticed last night that some
of the lights on the sign
of the building are out.
Like truck.
Something like that.
Or tump.
Or rump.
It is perfect, actually, if you
think of Trump as carnival
barker, and empty, a perfect
metaphor here.
I hate sweets.
But I'm a sucker for nostalgia.
You can't go back.
I can't go back.
How I wouldn't, even if I could.
I sure don't want to ever
have to be a teenager again.
But those tastes and smells of
childhood, they work still.
You're telling me you were not
a big saltwater Taffy fan.
I remember it was hard to chew.
You had braces, remember?
This was probably
problematic for it.
I can't remember having
braces at that point.
These have a
mystical hold on me.
Even the color of the wrapper
has this weird, you know, like
there should be music
playing in the background.
Molasses, I remember that.
Getting a bunch of those.
I don't know why.
Certain flavors really resonate.
The peanut, I know exactly
what that tastes like.
I remember the vanilla
really powerfully.
I'm not even a vanilla guy.
I'm more of a chocolate guy.
I think I remember pink ones.
They must have had strawberry.
Winter green I remember.
Licorice sounds good.
Peppermints.
Keep these in the car.
Cookies and creme.
Does it melt?
That's a lot of Taffy.
Yeah.
This stuff isn't bad for you.
Eat as much as you want.
Is it gluten free?
It's all natural.
That's what I thought.
Atlantic city will never die.
Good is indeed good forever.
And Atlantic city
will be great again.
Asbury park, Camden,
all of my home state.
I'm convinced when the tide has
come and washed all the greed
heads away, we'll
once again be magic.
I hope I'm there to see it.