For most of my life Libya
was a word with bad
associations.
Libya meant Gaddafi.
Libya meant terrorism.
Pan am flight 103 went down
in a blazing fireball.
Libya, a bad place where a
comical dictator was the
absolute power.
Nobody in Libya,
however, was laughing.
Reports of explosions.
Clashes between rioters
and security forces.
In 2011, what was previously
unthinkable happened.
The Libyan people Rose up and
fought for their freedom.
Heavy battles raging
around the Libyan capital.
They fought like hell, the
rebels are about to force
Gaddafi's complete departure.
They recorded the whole
thing on their cell phones.
Libya!
♪
It's amazing arriving here
after all you see on TV these
days that Libya is, in
fact, functioning at all.
But it is.
The fountains across from
the kornish are operating.
Traffic works, kind of.
At the Rattison, club sandwiches
arrive on time in the lobby.
The occasional flash of camo and
a security scanner are the
really only discordant notes.
Don't want to take the...
Inside the old part of the
city, men slaughter a camel,
while a girl records
it with her iPad.
Okay.
He said no.
Kids are setting off
fireworks in the Medina.
Incoming.
Tomorrow is the prophet
Muhammad's birthday, and people
who have not known freedom for
nearly 50 years are
ready to celebrate.
The square is filled with
families, kids, teenage
skater boys and hot shots on
motorcycles.
It's wild.
An almost giddily happy.
Young men in the camouflage
pants of the militias, most of
whom were civilians until
last year, do their best to
sporadically keep order
or just join in the fun.
Every kid above the age of 5
seems to have been issued a
lighter and a fistful of
fireworks.
Ambulances idle on the margins
of the square to treat
fireworks-related injuries,
which there will be many.
This is Tripoli.
After 42 years of nightmare.
How to build a whole society
overnight and make it work in
one of the most contentious and
difficult areas of the world is
what people are
trying to figure out.
♪
So before the war, did you
think it would ever be possible,
did you dream some day
this will change?
No.
In Gaddafi's country,
you can't say a word.
You'd get killed.
It was impossible.
Then I joined the
group, you know?
The militia.
Omar is young and was even
younger when the fighting
started.
He like so many Libyans from
around the country and many who
had left heeded the calls for
revolution on
Facebook and Twitter.
They fog in Tripoli, Benghazi,
Mizrada and everywhere
in between.
Who won this war?
Young people or everybody?
Everybody.
But the young people... what
was your life like as a
revolutionary?
You do this for the next
generation, for a better
country, a better life.
You have a future now.
There was no future in Libya
before Gaddafi's regime.
A seafood restaurant on
the Mediterranean coast.
One of the best foods in
Libya, I think, the seafood.
The menu is not
printed on paper.
It's laid out right
there for you on ice.
We have... what do they do?
They just grill that?
Yeah, they grill it.
Some garlic, some sauce.
You pick out the stuff that
interests you from
the daily catch.
Okay.
Let's get one of these.
One of these.
Some shrimps.
Ca calimari, too.
They cook it for you
the way you want.
Oh, beautiful.
Wow.
That's delicious.
This is the stuffed
calimari, Libyan style.
So many seafood
stuffed inside of it.
Like a Turkey.
Good sauce.
Man, we are living large today.
Yes, we are.
So what were you doing
before the war?
I was a travel agent.
You were a travel agent?
Yes.
And I was studying,
too, medical school.
Many of the people who
started the revolution who
fought in the streets with
makeshift weapons were like
Omar.
They transformed themselves in a
matter of months from kids
playing PlayStation
to hardened fighters.
Nobody believed that he
can be removed, really.
How quickly after the uprising
started did you begin
to think that, wow,
this is possible?
That we might actually win?
The first day.
First day?
Yeah.
The day before, you figured,
impossible, we'll be stuck with
this son of a bitch forever.
A few hours later it's like,
wow, this might work.
Seeing groups with you going
toward the martyrs square,
demanding their rights, at that
moment you feel that
you can do anything.
That this is going to happen.
If it didn't, we'll
die trying to do it.
♪
So much has changed around town.
So much is changing.
New music, graffiti.
These things, they
mean something.
♪
But centuries of strict social
and religious values keep some
things solidly the same.
Alcohol, for instance,
is strictly forbidden.
Men and women follow
hierarchal roles as before.
Since the revolution, there's a
tug-of-war over
what is acceptable.
♪
Outside a mosque in the Medina,
men fill the narrow street to
celebrate Muhammad's birthday.
Snacks are passed around.
Women watch and record
from the rooftops.
♪
There aren't a lot of
conflicts in the world where
there's a clear bad guy.
Clearly there's a bad guy here.
Exactly.
The one thing about Gaddafi is
he believed he was the most
important human being
almost that ever existed.
I mean, he changed the
names of the months.
He changed the date of
the Islamic calendar.
Such megalomania.
Anyone outside, if you mentioned
the name Libya, anyone
would say Gaddafi.
Gaddafi stole the
Liberty of Libya.
Michele cousins is the
co-founder of "the Libya herald"
and has known several different
Libyas in his lifetime.
For so long the news has
been the personality.
Gaddafi turned up to
open a shopping center.
open an envelope.
Those of us who knew Libya, knew
there was another Libya,
wonderful people.
We'd talk about it as you
talk about a dead person.
Do you remember this?
Do you remember that?
Then in February 2011, suddenly
there was resurrection.
The dead came back to life.
We meet at a Libyan coffeehouse.
A traditional male
only sort of a joint.
Cafe culture is big here.
A holdover from the days of
Italian colonization when
Mussolini tried to rebuild
Rome's long lost empire.
It's just been the most
amazing experience.
Seeing the rebirth of a
country, of a people.
I mean, last night's fireworks.
There was a general sense of
exuberance bordering on anarchy.
I mean, I felt very
happy there last night.
If somewhat in peril.
It's Christmas.
It's whatever, it's
the fourth of July.
Rolled into one.
Also there are people who
are trying to stop it.
Those puritans, extremists, if
you want to say militants.
What has happened, people have
come out in defiance of that.
They're showing, we
want to have fun.
For a long time in Libya,
you couldn't have fun.
The biggest misconception is
the place is turning into
another Afghanistan and Iraq
where you have bombs
go off, attacks.
But it's not, as you've seen.
Libyans have gone through an
awful time having
fought for freedom.
People have died.
People have struggled.
And that's going to
hold them together.
Kids are selling fireworks
across from the arch.
One is constantly reminded that
Libya was once a vital part of
the ancient Roman empire.
That was nearly 2,000 years ago.
Tonight I was told was going to
be an even bigger, Wilder
celebration in martyrs square.
But something has happened
since last night.
The British foreign office has
just told all UK citizens
to leave Benghazi.
Libya's second largest city.
Due to an unspecified threat.
The Libyan government, such as
it is, has denied any basis
for such drastic action.
A lone cherry bomb now and
again, an awkward flurry of
Roman candles.
The buzz of last night's chaotic
party parched, big time.
Whether or not this is the
larger geopolitical decision,
the vibe toward this western
film crew seems apprehensive.
Uncertain.
The following day feels better.
Somewhat.
Fresh produce is for
sale on Tripoli streets.
If you were a small restaurant,
or shopping for a big family,
you'd bring cash, a wheelbarrow,
and load up on what you need.
But the revolution has
brought changed tastes.
Libyans, especially young
Libyans, hunger for
more than just freedom.
They hunger for
places like this.
Kentucky fried chi
chicken.
The colonel, his buddies, the
king and the crown have not made
it here given the uncertainty
of the situation.
In the meantime, places like
this have been popping up.
Uncle Kentucky.
Awesome.
You know where Kentucky is?
Kentucky is from USA.
A part.
Yeah.
This place is new?
It's new.
Before Gaddafi... not possible.
Now it's normal.
Oh, that's nice.
How you found it?
Spicy, delicious.
Johar, like many Libyans his
age, fought to overthrow
Gaddafi.
He was there, gun in hand, when
they stormed Gaddafi's
palace compound.
Happy, excited?
Nice feeling.
Nice feeling that Gaddafi
he killed my cousin.
I don't want anyone
to die in war.
He's killed for nothing.
The first thing I think
that killing people is bad.
He's leave me do that.
Because if I don't kill
him, he kills any.
It's nice to see freedom.
It's nice to see
the bad guy done.
It's nice.
I feel welcome here.
Finally.
We say no on him.
He's now died.
That's what we wanted.
To Johar, a few pieces of
greasy fried chicken eaten in a
brightly colored fast food
setting means more.
My country.
I want the feeling of
the taste of freedom.
The taste of freedom.
It's a nice taste.
♪
Good.
Good food.
Outside Tripoli's
center, there's this.
One time axis of all
power and untold evil.
Sinister offices, barracks,
residences, on top of secret
tunnels and underground
facilities.
Gaddafi's enormous compound.
Most everything belonging to or
associated with Gaddafi
was destroyed.
On August 3rd, 2011,
it fell to rebels.
Gaddafi and his
family having fled.
This is what's left
of Gaddafi's palace.
♪
So when's the last
time you were here?
Last time is when the
revolution is finishing.
The machinery, going in fast.
After then, coming
a lot of people.
Listening about something
expensive here.
Pardon?
Like the salt.
What?
He wants us to stop
filming right now.
Okay.
While talking, we didn't notice
several pickup trucks of local
militia had closed in on us.
Stop.
I'll stop.
Just relax.
Relax.
This is their turf, or their
area of operation or somehow
under their control.
Whatever the case, they're
the group in charge today.
An argument ensues between
our guys and their guys.
All of whom fought against the
same forces on this
ground a year ago.
Okay.
Let's go.
Hold it down.
Libya denied there's an
imminent threat to safety of
westerners in Benghazi.
This follow's Britain’s advice
on Thursday that westerners
should get out of the city.
Warning of a specific
and imminent threat.
If you follow the news you'll
be reminded about how the lack
of centralized power in the wake
of the 2011 conflict has seen an
increase in Islamic
militancy in lib Libya.
Westerners and Libyans are
still very concerned.
What you see is not encouraging.
Kidnappings in Algeria,
unrest in Mali.
Terrorist cells to the south.
Deadly riots in Egypt.
Of course, extremist attacks in
Benghazi that killed the U.S.
Ambassador.
All those things are
very real concerns.
But if you only look at what's
on the news, you can miss maybe
what's a bigger picture.
Another morning in Tripoli
and life goes on.
Vendors are out.
People go about their
daily routines.
This is our traditional
breakfast.
What is this dish called?
An overstretched
doughnut, I suppose.
Right.
With an egg.
With an egg on top.
What's a little pancake
they put on top?
Just to hold the egg in?
Just to hold the egg in.
It's like a hat to
cover up something.
You can get them with cheese,
you can get them with chili
paste, with honey, with sugar.
How do you like yours?
I like mine cooked,
to be honest.
What's the name of
this neighborhood?
This is a cradle
of the revolution.
This was the first
neighborhood to rise up?
Yes.
This is the first
place to rise up.
Why do you think
this neighborhood?
It's been always liked
here by the regime.
They made them feel like they're
not from this country,
to be honest.
Uh-huh.
And we go for it.
Oh, yeah, dip.
Right in the egg.
Dip it in the egg.
Delicious.
So where were you
when it all started?
I was in London.
Actually, Manchester
at the time.
Why?
By the 27th, I was in Libya.
We went out to see
his house yesterday.
The compound.
I was one of the guys who
entered from the Southern gates.
The northern gates.
Akram is in the
security business.
A thriving industry here as
you can probably imagine.
A lot of things happened in a
lot of different parts of the
country sort of simultaneously.
Kind of amazing all these people
came together pretty fast.
How did it happen?
Ease city.
Twitter.
Twitter?
It was really like that?
Yes.
We sent so much information.
We get a phone call from Tripoli
or Benghazi or whatever.
Google earth.
We verify that's the location
that needs to be hit.
Then it's gone.
Really?
How does that feel knowing you
can call in a tomahawk
missile over there?
It's out of the movies.
Did anyone think in their
lifetime they'd see the end
of this son of a bitch?
A lot of people said
they never dreamed.
I don't know if you call
them hope, dreams, wishes.
It was just something
in the sky.
Something I look at every night.
When I hit that point and got in
and stood on Gaddafi's body,
any dream will come true.
What's the situation now?
It's fluid.
It can swing any direction.
Well, look, what happened in
Benghazi a few months ago, I
mean, what does this
mean to the country?
I think there is a dark
mysterious hand that doesn't
like this country to prosper.
They see system and organization
as a big enemy to them.
These are slowly
getting diminished.
A matter of time before
we can get rid of them.
How hard is that going to be?
Not at all.
We got rid of Gaddafi.
Nothing else is hard.
I like your attitude.
The fluid situation in Libya has
been intensifying
since our arrival.
We've had to change our
behavior, constantly moving.
Should I be wearing one of these
cool journalist safari
jackets at this point?
So it seemed a good
time or maybe not.
Saddle up.
To go to Misrata.
Okay, guys.
We can go.
Roger that.
Since the revolution, Misrata
has been the most secure city in
Libya, but over the last two
weeks in a hail of bullets and
hand-thrown grenade attacks, an
imam, security forces and a
police officer have
all been killed.
I want you to move forward.
Come past me.
All along the narrow
congested highway, there are
checkpoints manned mostly by
local militias, and I want to
stress most of them
are friendly enough.
We are, however, in a hurry to
get to Misrata before dark.
Traveling at night around
here is not advised.
Drop the camera.
Yep, yep.
Stop the camera.
Pulling in a town after dark,
it doesn't feel like a happy
place to be right now.
Misrata is where some of the
fiercest and most heroic
struggles of the war occurred.
Resistance was the most
determined, and the response by
the Gaddafi forces
especially merciless.
We've just learned that earlier
in the day, a city councilman
who was a hero of the revolution
was assassinated, and it's not
clear who's responsible.
Misrata is on full lockdown.
Another checkpoint.
Looking around at the price
this city paid for freedom, you
can see why they don't want to
lose what they
fought so hard for.
Morning in Misrata?
How is it?
Daylight reveals the extent
of the fighting that took
place here not so long ago.
This here used to be
a vegetable market.
Close, one of Gaddafi's
soldiers here closed.
He left him here and ran?
That's what they did in Tripoli.
Just lose their clothes and run
away in the streets
so nobody would know.
This is Hanid, one of the
guys we called the Misrata boys,
basically militia members from
the area who looked out for us
here and Tripoli when thinks
started getting hinky in
neighboring areas.
Hujab these days is hunting down
former Gaddafi supporters.
So the Gaddafi forces rolled in.
They'd use these tanks to
fire... around the city.
Around.
This was the
operation room here.
♪
Now if you had any doubt about
the terrible odds these
young revolutionaries were
facing during the early days of
the fighting, especially in the
months before NATO came in with
air support, check out
Misrata's war museum.
What did this fire?
Fired a rocket.
Homemade.
There's a rocket here.
You had to have some serious
courage to ride around
with this thing.
Why?
We trust our people.
There are a lot of
homemade things here.
This is homemade, too.
Fires rockets.
This is homemade.
This one.
This was from... yes.
We got it.
You took it off a helicopter
and you put it on a car?
Uh-huh.
And you know what this is for?
So it's basically a cross bow
that fires Molotov cocktails.
Try it sometimes.
You're shooting this at
people who have mortars.
And tanks.
Tanks.
Yeah.
You're shooting this at tanks.
That's what we got at the time.
It's what you had.
It's awesome.
The next president of Libya,
the one who's going to be
in charge, this is his.
He has to think twice
before he sits on it.
Never screw your people.
Here, this is Gaddafi stuff.
This was all taken
from the compound.
That's his chair.
Preferred hair products.
His shaving kit.
See he was wearing a mask.
Beauty mask.
I could use some of that.
Gaddafi, he's
beautiful, you know.
And this is the first.
That's the first.
Yeah, that's the first one.
That's a normal guy that went
out to protest the first rally
and somebody come
in and shoot him.
So next day the whole
city came out.
That's when everything started.
These are photos of those
killed during the uprising.
Combatants and bystanders alike.
Her name is Muna.
She was 6 days when she died.
Killed in their homes,
tortured to death in prisons,
snipers.
They killed him, with,
like, a grenade.
Yeah.
You know what he was saying?
He's saying, what's
going on, guys?
Why are you doing that?
We still have the T-shirt
with the blood in it.
Do you know any of these people?
Yeah, I know a couple of them.
I knew a couple.
This guy's Egyptian.
Not even his fight.
He didn't want to leave.
This died in Tripoli.
These are brothers and sister.
One, two, three, four.
They died on the same
day, the same house.
The mother when we found her,
she was holding the kid.
They were both dead and
holding each other.
It was a very sad moment.
I don't know if you noticed,
I'm going full blitzer
on this shoot.
The Mediterranean sea defines
Libya's northern border.
In shacks built along the coast,
people get together on weekends
to do what people do everywhere
in the world in one form or
another since the
beginnings of society.
Like barbecue?
Who does not like barbecue?
There he is.
They sure like him here.
Chase down on animal.
Kill it.
Cycle of life.
Cut it into pieces.
And throw it on a flame.
Freedom fighters.
Ex-freedom fighters.
Chilling, having fun,
making barbecue.
To start, they grill a lamb
in small pieces with a few
veggies.
A beer.
Been a week without any
alcohol of any kind.
I'm enjoying my new
clean living lifestyle.
That's hospitality.
I said it before.
I'll say it again.
Barbecue may not be the road to
world peace, but it's a start.
Awesome food.
Yeah.
Laid back.
In America, laid back.
A stew made of kidneys, liver
and heart served family style.
Feel free to eat with hands.
Right hand only, please.
And a really traditional thing
left over from the Italians,
basically pasta with ragout.
What's this dish called?
It's good.
The Italians left
you one nice thing.
A few nice buildings and pasta.
So the story of Misrata, the
story of Libya seems to be
ordinary people suddenly called
upon to do extraordinary things.
Where were you when
war broke out?
I was in Canada, Montreal.
Studying medicine.
Yes.
The doctor put her medical
studies on hold to help tend all
manner of horrible war injuries.
What kind of procedures were you
doing on a regular basis?
Everything.
Everything. Without prior
practice and practice and
trying to pick up things.
How many patients did
you treat a day?
60, 70, like a lot.
The whole hospital was full.
When you heard he
had been killed?
Relief?
Relief.
I was like realizing that, okay,
it's over and trying to heal my
own wounds because in the middle
of it you just go, go, go, and
you never realize how much
injuries and trauma you get
inside yourself.
Right.
Because before you never
think we're going to survive and
we'll have a fry Libya.
Just like going with the state
of mind that I'm going to do my
best and I'm ready in peace with
myself if I die, and then
you find yourself here now.
It's like... now
it's the gray area.
She risked her life along
with the men, but traditional
rules of conduct do not allow
her to sit with
them during dinner.
She's relegated to what might be
the called the kids' table.
What can one say, we who think
of ourselves as more
enlightened in this area?
I don't know.
Rightly or wrongly
I said nothing.
What does freedom mean?
I don't know that
either, I guess.
For sure it does mean the
freedom to enjoy be a afternoon
no one thought possible only a
little while ago, the freedom,
at least, to joke, to laugh, to
be for a while
relatively carefree.
♪
The road to Tripoli, a
healthy supreme court fast.
Oh, liver sandwich.
When they talk about a high-risk
environment, I think they
were talking about this.
That's good.
Halfway back to Tripoli, the
magnificent ruins
of Leftus Magna.
Arguably the most intact remains
of a Roman city in the world.
It's worth noting that the
emperor was himself Libyan.
That's pretty amazing.
Born right here.
Someone chipped
off all the legs.
No that I was looking.
Everyone else in the world is
overrun with tourists,
but, look, no one.
You're free to
wander as you wish.
Quite a backdrop, you know,
seeing a little dinner theater
production of "our town" a
couple thousand years ago.
Not bad.
The only other visitors today
are a troupe of
Libyan boy scouts.
Bizarrely enough, Gaddafi
himself was once a scout and
this is one of the only
organizations allowed to remain
independent of the government.
Maybe I ought to go down there
and introduce myself,
exchange some boy scout lore.
Yes, yes, I was once
a boy scout, too.
Hello.
Drilled into their heads is
something that was long
ago drilled into mine.
I promise to be trustworthy,
loyal, helpful, friendly,
courteous, kind, obedient,
thrifty, brave, clean and
reverent.
You know, it's been a really
difficult shoot for a
whole lot of reasons.
It's not easy to shoot here.
But in spite of all of that, for
me this was a happy show.
It's Libya.
It was supposed to be the bad
guys, a bad country filled
with bad people, right?
I don't think so.
I met a lot of really
nice people here.
Nobody is saying we're going
to be perfect tomorrow.
Everybody seems to be saying,
you know, look at
us in five years.
Today that's a pretty
reasonable attitude.
This is a place that's filled a
lot of extraordinary people who
have done an extraordinary thing
on very short notice under very
difficult circumstances and at a
very difficult time who are
continuing to do the best they
can, and I wish them well.