Seattle, a city with
a collective identity
constantly in flux,
always changing,
but what it's always been
and continues to be
is a magnet for creators to
come experiment
and to make their own.
♪
Whoa, and weed is legal here.
♪ I took a walk
♪ Through this beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪
♪ Found something good
♪ In this beautiful world
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪
♪ Sha la la-la-la
♪ Sha la la-la-la-la
♪ Sha la la-la-la-la la
♪
Seattle has always been a place
where you can go
to reinvent yourself.
♪
It's a place that,
on the surface,
would seem to require
commitment.
♪
Famously gray, rainy,
not particularly friendly,
and all the way up there
in the far corner
of the country,
a place where you could get
work in the aircraft industry
or make music
or, rather notoriously,
become a serial killer.
Whether outfitting prospectors
during the Alaskan gold rush
or looking for some kind of
cred from the music scene...
it's always boom or bust.
Now, it's a new kind of boom.
Microsoft, Google, Twitter,
Expedia, and Amazon
are the big dogs in town.
A flood of them,
tech industry workers,
mostly male,
derisively referred to
as tech boys or tech bros,
rapidly changing the DNA
of the city,
rewiring it to satisfy
their own newly empowered
nerdly appetites.
Meet our new apple
martini-drinking overlords.
- ♪ Tech boys
♪
♪ Tech boys
- ♪ Tech boys
♪
♪ With your mustache
and your paycheck ♪
♪ And your blue badge
♪ And your limp dick
♪ With your mouth full
of the party line ♪
♪ And your weekends
working overtime ♪
♪ Overtime, overtime,
overtime, overtime ♪
Fish and chips is
the thing, right?
- That's the thing.
- Yeah.
Astra Elane and Dustin Patterson
are members of the local band
The Gods Themselves.
They wrote a song
about the new kids in town.
Okay.
Pacific Inn Pub is a holdout,
a place that has, so far,
managed to resist the temptation
to appease the invaders.
For lunch, fish and chips.
♪ Tech boys
You know, bitter old...
like me, of course,
are gonna complain any time
we hear about, you know,
a lot of high-fiving white guys
coming to town.
And yet, you've created this
sort of iconic hate anthem
Can you tell the tech people
from the non-tech people?
Yeah, they have the badges.
♪ Tech boys
Neutral-colored clothing.
They're kind of easy to spot.
They have a walk.
- They have a walk?
- Yeah.
They're just all the same.
There's nothing that
really stands out about them.
They're so dull.
♪ Feel that rhythm
that algorithm ♪
♪ You gotta feel that rhythm
♪ That algorithm tech boys ♪
You know, dating apps
are really big here.
I have a few girlfriends...
That's right.
Who have dated
a couple of tech boys.
Is their personal
hygiene an issue?
Like, the nerdier tech boys
will have that smell,
that mildewy smell.
Yeah.
You know what I'm talking about?
Wow, you really have
a low opinion of these people.
Well, we're generalizing
now, Tony.
No, I'm all for that.
Everybody in Seattle
is a musician,
a serial killer, or a chef
as far as I'm concerned so...
In a lot of ways, I mean,
this was always a company town.
You know, Boeing, before
Boeing, it was a logging town.
And the new company is tech,
and it is flooding money
into the place.
I looked out my hotel window
and, I mean,
it's cranes as far as
the eye can see.
You realize, like, okay,
all those cranes out there,
they're for high-rise condos.
They're for a certain
type of person.
They're envisioning a certain
type of future for the city
and it's tech people.
Or, you know, somebody
who likes to drive around
and pick up hitchhikers
and dismember them.
Yeah.
Capitol Hill is Seattle's
established gay-borhood
going back to the mid-1960s,
old-school cool,
but with every passing day,
change.
The Hill has become the new
weekend stomping ground
of breeders from
the tech companies,
and the locals are displeased.
♪
John Criscitello, street artist,
is waging a one-man war
against the rent hikes
that are pushing people like
him out of the neighborhood.
♪
Are we talking about
an infestation of tech bros?
Is this...
What, ten years ago, would
this be a gay neighborhood?
It was sort of unclaimed
for artists
and for queer people.
And so what's happening now?
Big tech corporations that
have moved into the city
and people needed someplace to
live, so a lot of
development companies
bought up every corner.
If they keep this sort of
facade, they can build taller.
- Ah.
- So this was just this
and then they plunked this
down in the center of it.
So they're keeping the
character of the neighborhood
sort of kind of.
They call it facadomy.
I've heard it termed facadomy.
♪
The problem, of course,
is that rents double.
- Right.
- So you used to be able
to get a studio
apartment for $700.
Now, all of a sudden
the entry point is $1,500,
which is considerable for
artists, anybody.
You know, that's
the sort of lament now is,
where are you gonna go?
Where are you gonna go?
- Yeah.
- Where are you gonna go?
Right.
So all these outsiders coming in
are renting
expensive apartments.
What kind of businesses
are opening to accommodate
these new arrivals?
Well, in this neighborhood,
that construction over on
that side is a Whole Foods.
Oh, no, that's a sign
of the apocalypse.
- That is the end.
- That... that's the official
indicator that
this neighborhood is...
That is the end.
That's it right there.
Because of the boom
and everything
that's been happening,
you do have that kind of have
and have nots here.
And I think there's
an identity crisis
where people are starting to
really question
what is Seattle and who is it?
But historically,
you go back to the '90s,
I mean, it was
the city of grunge.
And now, I would say
it's the city of geeks.
It's... it's... it's boom town
right now.
And yeah, this kind of boom
does happen in other places,
but then again, it doesn't.
John Cook and Todd Bishop
of GeekWire,
an industry-leading news site
that started covering
the tech industry
back in 2011.
Lunch is at Revel right down
the street from their offices.
The chef is Rachel Yang
and the food is Korean.
♪
To eat, cilantro noodles,
yu choy, and thinly sliced
flat iron steak...
♪
Kimchi pancakes with
braised pork belly
and bean sprouts...
♪
Marinated short rib rice bowl
with house sambal daikon,
kimchi, and egg.
♪
And short rib dumplings
topped with
pickled shallot
and scallion salad.
♪
Of course, I'm hearing from
a lot of people
who are bemoaning the loss of
the old Seattle...
Right.
This invasion of outsiders.
Certainly the community
is going through
a lot of growing pains
and there's an element
of the city here
that is rebelling
against the progress,
especially as we talk about
a company like Amazon
that controls massive amounts
of the downtown
real estate footprint now.
And that's what scares
a lot of people here,
including myself.
Because I see how the trends
of history change,
especially in technology,
that one day Microsoft's hot,
the next day Apple's hot,
now Amazon's hot.
They go through these cycles
and they don't always
live through them,
and we're left with a city
that's totally transformed
because of it.
What percentage of the total
dollar-generating space
on the Internet
is occupied by porn?
Well, you know,
this is Todd's expertise
so I'll defer to him.
Historically the adult industry,
even if it's not completely
dominating the economics
all the time, it is the...
The leader of technology.
It... it's the first with HD.
It's the first to try out
a new wave of 3-D technology.
Virtual reality,
augmented reality,
and then you see it
over and over again,
the latest is VR now.
Yeah.
Do you know the...
Do you know the number one
search term on porn websites
for the Seattle area?
♪
Stepmom.
Who wants to...
their stepmom?
♪
Jesus.
Jen McEwen and Jesse Adams
are two nice people
who've chosen the porn business
as a way to make a living.
They launched MiKandi,
the world's first
mobile app store
for masturbators and aficionados
of graphic erotica.
But they are looking ahead,
the next levels of porn...
Personalized, interactive,
virtual reality porn.
I'm gonna tease you.
And I can tell you, my friends,
it's chillingly realistic.
♪
Generally speaking,
who are your customers
demographically?
Mostly male, but, yeah, it's
really from all over the world.
Right.
They're looking for more
unique experiences
and I think that's why VR is
very important for them.
And just also
a lot of people who say
they discovered their sexuality
and their identity
through stuff like this.
What the adult industry
is really good at
is whatever your
specific interest is,
we'll find the exact
person for you
or the exact piece of content.
Like... like Amazon does.
- Yeah.
- So, Tony, based on
your previous purchases,
you know, we can recommend
the following
stepmom-related materials.
Yeah.
Do you want to see some VR porn?
- Yeah.
All right.
Okay.
♪
Oh, my God, here we go.
Now, should I look behind me?
'Cause I don't want to get
spit roasted here. Okay.
Hey there.
Wow.
Yeah, that's kinda scary.
♪
It's good.
Weed, smoke, ganja, reefer,
call it what you will,
it's marijuana.
Oh, I could go on all day.
Long story short,
Washington State
legalized weed in 2012,
and I plan to make
the most of it
while scrupulously adhering to
the lay of the law
like I always do.
♪
The options available
in places like this,
Emerald Haze, are mind-boggling.
♪
Well, how can I
help you out today?
Well, I... where to begin?
Where to begin?
There is a dizzying array
of products.
You got dozens of strains
of bud,
oils to vape,
weed-infused edibles,
mints, syrups, ointments,
probably lube.
Remind me to ask.
My advice, don't even try
to shop stoned.
Decision making was never,
in my case, a strong point
while baked.
Which... which... which is sleepy...
I forget, is it indica
or sativa that's peppy
and the other one is sleepy?
The indica will put you
"inda" couch.
- On the couch.
- It's gonna be
your sleepy body high.
Right.
Sativa is gonna be more of
your awake alert high
kind of mostly feeling
in the head.
Right, like crouched
in the bathroom
in the fetal position paranoid
or what?
Not like that crazy.
Yeah, no, okay, good.
I think let's do some of both.
- Some of both?
- Yeah.
What do you have on offer here?
We do have a deal on
our pack of three today...
- Mm-hmm.
- From Hollingsworth,
which they had
the Blueberry Kush...
- Yes.
- The Alaskan Thunder...
and then also a Dutch Treat,
which will be more of a hybrid.
I mean, I have to...
Alaskan Thunder...
I mean, you kind have to.
This... this is from
our friends at...
Yeah, these are from
Hollingsworth,
which is very nice.
♪
Two hours outside of Seattle
lies Hollingsworth
Cannabis Company Farm.
The woods are alive with, well,
weed.
Rows and rows of weed
carefully grown and tended to
by one family,
third generation Seattleites
the Hollingsworths.
And at the helm of the
company, these guys,
brother and sister duo,
Raft and Joy Hollingsworth.
Oh, hi!
Didn't see you there.
Wait, hold on.
Oh, hi. Didn't see you there.
- Didn't see you there.
- Let me say that.
Then you say
the rest of the shit.
- No, I can't remember...
- Okay, we're gonna do it.
I'm Joy Hollingsworth.
I got it.
Oh, hi.
Say it, say it.
Let's take a... let's take
a closer look, shall we?
♪
While some corporate outfits
are rushing to cash in
on the new crop, the
Hollingsworth Cannabis Company
is doing it a slower,
more personal way.
Solar-powered greenhouses,
hand-trimmed buds,
and hand-packed bags
ensure the freshest and
highest quality of product.
They're keeping it
all in the family.
Raft runs the manufacturing
and growing.
Joy does the processing
and sales.
Auntie came out of retirement
to assist with
the oil cartridges.
Dad puts labels
on the packaging,
and mom fills
the [indistinct] rolls
and assists in
quality control...
That's fine, that's fine.
As I will and have
and will again.
♪
Back in the city,
Mamnoon Restaurant on Melrose.
Have you been here before?
Absolutely.
This is a good spot.
How you doing?
I've been smoking some of
your product,
so if I'm a little unfocused...
Before this you did?
- What's that?
- Before...
Before this, yes.
He said, what, what, what, what?
♪
Mamnoon is a modern take
on traditional Syrian
and Lebanese food.
And it's done well.
♪
There's baharat spiced beef
and lamb kebabs...
♪
Fried cauliflower with tahini...
A summer fatteh with local
squash and charred tomatoes
topped with sizzling
brown butter and pine nuts.
That's sweet-and-sour rice
wrapped in grape leaves.
♪
This looks so good.
The hummus is great.
This is my favorite cuisine.
♪
So how's business?
It's been an interesting
three years,
because I feel like every year
we've been, like,
refining the process
and trying to get better.
We're the little guys.
Right now
we're mom-and-pop.
Yeah, we're the mom-and-pop,
but see, the difference is
Washington State set up the law
to try to help mom-and-pops
get started.
How did you convince the family?
- Yeah.
- This must have seemed like
a sketchy venture.
- Yes.
- It was a gamble.
He said, hey,
I got a family meeting.
I need you here tonight.
And we're all sitting there
and he puts on
his little PowerPoint on the TV,
and it's about 32 pages,
and he tells us,
"Hey, we need to go to
Mason County,
grow a ton of weed,"
and we're all like,
what are you talking about?
And my mom raises her hand
and she goes, "Wait",
I have something
really important."
We all look at her and she
goes, "I wanna be R&D."
Can I smoke and tell you
if the weed is good?"
And then all of a sudden
he starts moving.
My business plan ended at
"get a license."
To get a license
it was to build a fence,
put up some cameras...
- Right.
- And get out the way.
Then they'll come,
give you a final inspection,
and now you are licensed
to grow weed
in the State of Washington.
How many people grow weed,
do you think,
in the Seattle,
Washington State region?
- Oh, yeah, there's a lot.
- There's a lot.
There's over 1,100
producer processers
in Washington State
and about 400 licensed
retail stores.
We... everybody's going to win.
There's so many people of all
different types that smoke weed.
We did a store visit and we saw
people come in and out,
grandmas, moms, professionals.
Like, I'm sure if that store
took demographics
of their clientele...
Right.
They would have a spectrum
of different type of people.
People like to get high.
What do they want these days?
There's so many choices.
Our biggest seller are
the pre-rolls.
People like ready-made cannabis.
They want to buy and get high.
- Loose joints.
- Loose joints, most people...
- Really?
- They don't... people don't
like to roll their own...
They don't know how
to roll joints.
No.
People, teach
your children well.
I mean, this is
a basic life skill.
- What do you smoke?
- Well, I like to smoke...
As I... as I said,
I like to smoke weed.
Now, the Alaskan Thunder...
it was an irresistible package.
- Alaskan Thunder...
- Yeah.
That's old-school Hells Angels,
that's their... that's
their old-school strain.
- Did you smoke it?
- Yeah.
I can't compare and contrast,
because I've been trying them
all one after the other.
Right.
I mean, I've been
smoking weed since I was 13.
- Right.
- You know, all the bad shit
that... that was supposed
to happen if you,
you know, smoked too much weed,
didn't really happen.
But looking into my own life,
you know, I've seen my ambition,
you know, there were things
I was thinking about doing
but, you know, once I start
smoking some good weed,
it's like...
eh.
♪
Okay, I'm good.
In a nondescript-looking
building in Bellevue,
some very smart people are
looking into things
like how to stop hurricanes
before they happen...
♪
Ending malaria,
and how to make
the perfect hamburger.
Nathan Myhrvold is the former
Chief Technology Officer
of Microsoft.
A genius, an inventor,
and a very wealthy man
who's free to indulge
his passions,
most noticeably for cooking
and all things food.
♪
Over the last years,
he and his team
have published
an incredibly lavish
an authoritative series
of books,
"Modernist Cuisine,"
dedicated to debunking
popular misconceptions
and documenting the results
with the best
high-tech photography
and graphic art imaginable.
♪
Head chef Francisco Migoya
is leading the team
into a new mission now,
demystifying bread
for all of us.
♪
People like me,
someone who's cooked
his whole life,
I live in terror of... of bread,
Anything that rises, in fact,
like a horse, senses my fear...
and insecurity, and misbehaves.
I mean, I'm tenuous
with any doughs.
You know, I've seen people who
work with it all the time.
They're slapping it around
like it's nothing.
I'm...
like this and it always
goes wrong on me.
It's just never...
Yeah.
Quite right. Will
your work help me in my...
It will help you, Tony.
♪
Bread is actually
amazingly robust.
Although we've got
lots of recipes,
recipes aren't as important
as understanding sort of
the fundamentals
of what's going on.
And once you do,
it's... it's really
quite forgiving.
♪
Few things are more mysterious
and unknowable than the bagel.
Can one, perhaps,
create the perfect bagel
and with toppings
that don't fall off?
As a New Yorker,
I'm inclined to say no,
but now I...
I'm not sure.
And what is this,
bread in a jar?
But... but what?
What... what is going on here?
This is the kind of
sick thing we do.
We wondered,
could you can bread?
By God, you can.
This is rum babas...
Oh, I love them.
Which is a bread in
the sense it uses yeast...
- Yes.
- And we canned them.
Now, watch what happens
when we open it up.
Isn't that awesome?
♪
It's really good.
And how long will this
stay in there?
Nine months and it's good.
So I'd have perfectly
fresh bread in nine months
if I just pop the top
on that thing?
♪
Look, you know, jaded cooks
and chefs like me...
♪
They still find there are
certain unknowables
or things that cause them to
pause in the kitchen
and gaze with wonder
at the magic
of something like bread.
Aren't you afraid that
in some way
you're doing Satan's work
here by quantifying magic?
Food is a very romantic thing.
It's usually experienced at best
in an emotional way.
Absolutely.
By explaining it...
Absolutely it's emotional.
Absolutely it can be art.
But knowing how to do it right,
to me, doesn't diminish that.
Hmm.
Across the water from my hotel
in the Puget Sound,
just outside the city limits,
the wilderness opens up
and it's beautiful.
♪ Lord of fire in the sky
♪ Getting level neon devil
♪ Holy, holy in my mind
♪ To abide and crucify
♪ With blue, blue sea
♪ Far away
♪
On Vashon Island,
a clambake with Dungeness crab,
spot prawns, mussels,
corn, and potatoes
covered in kelp and steamed
together under burlap.
Old-school.
♪ Lord of fire in the sky
"♪ Getting level..."
- Dig in.
- ♪ Neon devil
♪ Holy, holy in my mind
♪ To abide and crucify
♪ With blue, blue sea
♪ Far away
♪
Chefs Grant Crilly
and Chris Young
worked with Nathan
at Modernist Cuisine
before breaking off
to do their own thing,
ChefSteps, a high-tech outfit
dedicated to help people
cook better
with step-by-step video apps
and interactive content.
Essentially the way
we look at it is
our job is to help people cook,
cook a meal for their family,
cook a meal for their friends
where they're happy and didn't
know they could cook that well.
- Yeah.
- 'Cause we're kind of
technologists, too,
we think, you know, there's
a roll for technology,
but there's also a roll
for... for craft
and tradition.
I think there's
an element of uncertainty
and risk that is very exciting
to me when I cook.
You know, it's
the imperfections in life
that are most interesting.
If everybody knew how to
sauce pasta correctly,
I don't know that
that would make me happier.
The kitchen is a pretty scary
place for a lot of people,
and so if... if you can
bring technology
and it takes that fear away
because they know that
it's gonna come out well,
they're gonna be happy
with the result, that'll
get them to cook again.
Coming from the guys who, you
know, wrote "Modernist Cuisine,"
we're trying to find that
21st-century blend
between YouTube and Instagram
and technology...
- Right.
- And tools like that
with the things that
are great about cooking,
which is sharing a meal.
I think you're missing
a central dynamic here.
I mean, why do people
Instagram pictures of food?
To share their wonderful
eating experience? No.
It's to make other people feel
bad about what they're eating.
It's like, look, I'm eating
all these incredible crabs
and you're sitting at home
in some, you know,
dirty underwear eating Doritos.
I mean, hopefully.
I mean, Doritos
are pretty tasty.
It is probably unfair to suggest
that the Pacific Northwest
and Seattle area
could have been home to a
disproportionally large number
of serial killers,
but I'll do it anyway.
- Shucked Taylor oysters here.
- Wonderful. Thank you.
Anything else
I can grab you gentlemen?
Oh, I'm good for now.
Good for now?
All right, enjoy.
I'm gonna try a Fat Bastard,
that sounds interesting.
Fred Moody is a writer
and bartender.
Jack Whisner is a transit
planner for King County Metro.
And Knute Berger is
a journalist and columnist
for "Seattle Weekly."
Old-school Seattle all.
Taylor Shellfish Oyster Bar
in Pioneer Square
is old-school, too.
The Taylor family has been
farming more than 12,000 acres
of tidelands in the Puget Sound,
Willapa Bay, and the Hood Canal
for over five generations,
since 1890.
With three restaurants in town,
they know what they're doing.
Are you gonna eat these whole?
Head, tail, bones and all?
Yes.
Whole, local smelt flash fried
and served with
pepperoncini sambal aioli,
local Dungeness crab
cooked and chilled
with pickled ginger sauce,
and oysters, lots of oysters.
♪
Seattle has been for...
For a very long time
considered one of
the more foodie,
for lack of a better word,
foodie cities.
- Yeah.
- If you ask me why, generally
it's said the sheer abundance
of really good ingredients.
Yeah, exactly. I mean, you
got the ocean there.
You've got cattle country
and orchard country
just over the mountains.
Yeah.
They say one of the things
that's changed in Seattle
is there's not just
the Pike Place Market
but every neighborhood
has a market now.
- Has a green market.
- Yeah.
So those entrepreneurs
have a place to sell.
They can go to all the markets
or just some of them,
but it's really fantastic.
So everybody born
and bred in Seattle?
I was, yeah.
- Born here?
- Yes.
Bellingham, which is...
Oh, sure, serial killer
capital of the world.
There's a bar there
where both Ted Bundy
and the Green River Killer
had been patrons, yeah.
Bundy was born in Tacoma
and that's...
- Right.
- There are two, right?
- The Hillside Strangler...
- Hillside Strangler also.
- Also the Beltway Sniper.
- Right.
The worst one was
the Green River Killer.
Yeah.
Why is Seattle,
the Pacific Northwest,
such a magnet for
serial killers? Any theories?
You know, people come here
to hide out.
They... they think, well... they
look at the map and it's like...
Got two mountain ranges
are just a couple hours away.
Literally, you can hide
bodies like a short drive
from wherever you are.
So convenient body dumping?
Body dumping.
I mean, that's
gotta be part of it.
You have all that lush greenery.
If you're looking
to dump a body, Seattle.
Yeah.
I've always thought the rain
was kind of part of it.
You got to that stretch
from maybe October
to February, and by the time
you're in February,
I mean, you... you want to... you
want to become a serial killer.
I mean, you know.
That's part of it.
But apparently you can.
Is Seattle a teeming hive
of serial killers?
Or am I just an idiot with a
morbidly overactive imagination
and an attraction to
the dark, ugly side of life?
Meet retired homicide
detective Mike Ciesynski
who, for over 12 years,
specialized in cold cases
in the region.
We meet at the Shanghai Room
in Greenwood
where Fred Moody tends bar.
The North Star Diner next door
provides nourishment.
Crab, bacon,
and melted cheese is,
when discussing dump sites
and ligature marks,
a must.
Why does it seem that there's
a disproportionate number
of serial killers in the Seattle
and Washington State area?
Do you have a theory on that?
Well, I don't think
that most serial killers
are... are... went shopping
for areas where they live.
This is just where
they ended up.
- Mm-hmm.
- When you're a detective
for as long as I've been
a detective
and you're around
very evil people,
it's a place where I don't want
you to have to come and look at
through my eyes.
I mean, I can talk to you
about it and all that,
but I hope you never have
to see it like I seen it,
'cause, you know, it's not a...
It's a different place.
It's a place you
don't want to be, and...
How many... how many
working serial killers
do you think are
out there right now
in the Washington State area?
I would say, I mean,
easily right now,
easily over 75 people out here
that are probably
serial murderers.
The FBI list it as...
- Whoa! 75.
- Oh, yeah.
I don't care
how nice it is here,
you know, fun Seattle
and stuff, you know.
I know how many evil people
are running around here.
♪
So...
do you think these guys are
holding down regular jobs?
Well, yeah.
They can... they can just go on
and have their,
you know, regular,
what would seem to us
as a regular life.
They could also have wives.
Yeah, I was wondering
about that.
I always wonder about the wives.
It's like, don't you notice,
you know, the mementos
and the unusual odor
coming from the crawl space?
I mean, what...
John Wayne Gacy, exactly...
- I mean, what the...
- you know, and just
what's with the whole
clown outfit?
I mean, first of all, all you
gotta do is put on a clown suit
and already you're...
You're a suspect.
♪ I have given to you, Jane
♪ A torn and tattered love
♪ But do you hear
the tolling bells ♪
♪ That ring down from above?
♪ I Thought I'd rule like
Charlemagne ♪
♪ But I've become corrupt
♪ Now I crawl the promenade
♪ To fill my empty cup
♪ And you're free
♪
♪ You're free again
♪ One more time
♪
Mark Lanegan is to my mind
one of the greatest living
singer-songwriters
making music today.
His songs and lyrics
reflective of a long, hard life
cut me right down to the bone.
His career has spanned
two decades
beginning with the
Screaming Trees in the '90s
and continuing through numerous
brilliant collaborations
with artists like
Queens of the Stone Age,
PJ Harvey,
Kurt Cobain,
Unkle, Mad Season,
The Gutter Twins,
Isobel Campbell,
and Massive Attack.
Maybe you know him from such
theme songs as...
this show.
♪
Wow.
Spicy.
Yeah, that's good.
Dinner with Mark and touring
guitarist Jeff Fielder
at Ocho in Ballard,
where they serve up
generous drinks
and Spanish-influenced tapas.
♪
You grew up around, what, two,
two hours outside of Seattle?
Yeah, in Eastern Washington,
which is like the countryside,
ranching, farming community.
You don't live here anymore.
You live in I.A. now?
Yeah.
How long since you left?
Oh, it's been 20 years.
Oh, wow.
But I come back here, you know,
a couple times a year.
I play shows.
I still have family in...
In the city,
and I think of it
as home, still.
You know, I always will.
It's just...
It's the home
I don't live in anymore.
♪
♪ Will you put on that
long white dress ♪
♪
♪ While I burn
when there's no more ♪
♪ Tomorrows?
♪
♪ Will you walk with me
underground ♪
♪
♪ And forget all the sadness
♪ And the sorrows?
♪ Ba da da da
♪
♪ Ba da da da da
So how long have you been
playing music professionally?
Well, kind of
the whole time, you know.
I mean, I played my first gigs
when I was 13.
I've been touring with...
With Mark
since about 2010.
What was the first band, first
time you were ever onstage?
And where was it?
It was in my hometown, I was 15,
and some guys I worked
in a restaurant with
had a band.
They were older.
And I sang at one pool party
that they had.
What was the set list
there, covers or?
A lot of Van Halen.
Oh, wow.
Styx.
Oh, brutal.
You have played and played with
a lot of different people
from different styles of music.
I think a lot of musicians
I know and have met would...
Would have a hard
time with that.
You seem to move
effortlessly around.
I don't know,
I've just been blessed
with a lot of opportunity.
I get to play with a lot of
people whose music I really love
so I'm happy.
You know, after having been in
my own band for many years,
and suddenly, like,
I'm taking jobs
where I'm just playing part
of somebody's set,
at first it was
a little awkward,
but then I grew to
really love doing it
because it was easy
and fun
and there was no pressure.
I did that for
quite a few years,
and I'm available
to do that again
if anybody wants me.
♪
♪ On the marble street
♪ A procession spills in
♪ At the White Sea wall
♪ Waves crash and crash again
♪
♪ Darkness shining
♪ Then disappearing
♪
♪ Day follows night
♪ Night follows day
♪
♪ Good-bye
♪ Good-bye to beauty
♪
You... are you
at all sentimental
about how Seattle used to be?
You know, I guess it's...
It's like being sentimental
about grade school
or, you know,
any time of your life
that isn't around anymore.
I miss... I miss some of the guys
that were around then
that aren't around
anymore, you know,
some of my friends,
but, you know, that's life.
♪ Good-bye to beauty
♪
Next to making a proper omelet
or like wiping your own ass,
knowing how to roll a joint
is an essential life skill
for any self-respecting
member of society in my view.
Pay attention, people.
♪
♪ Can you stay here
next to me? ♪
♪
♪ We'll just keep drivin'
♪ Because of you I see a light ♪
♪
♪ The Buick's a Century
♪ A '73 like you
♪
♪ Some strange religion
♪ I get my hands on
some money, Mama ♪
♪
♪ And a shot in the night
♪ Stared down the past
and just scarred my eyes ♪
♪
♪ I almost called it a day
so many times ♪
♪
♪ Never known what it felt like
to be alive ♪
♪
♪ Till you been a friend to me ♪
♪ Like nobody else could be
♪ Mm
♪
♪ Keep my hands
on the wheel now, mama ♪
♪ Gonna honestly try
♪
♪ She looked past the scars
and the burned out eyes ♪
♪
♪ You could see
I'm no easy ride ♪
♪
♪ She's just the kind
who might get you to buy ♪
♪
♪ Some strange religion
♪ This jack of diamonds
kicked her heart around ♪
♪
♪ Should-a known they were
walking on holy ground ♪
♪
♪ And this life
might eventually ♪
♪ Just be the end of me
♪ Will I still be with you
♪ Mm
♪
♪ Then get in next to me
♪ Just keep drivin'
♪
♪ Because of you I been alive
♪ And the Buick's a Century
♪ A '73 like you
♪
♪ Some strange religion
♪ And the Buick's a Century
♪ A '73 like you
♪
♪ Some strange religion