How does the joke begin?
Three men in a bar,
but it's not a bar.
Imagine the Bronx.
A corner, or maybe
a lunchenette.
Three men find themselves in the
same place at the same time.
Sitting at the counter
is Africa bombada.
Across the room is Milly Mel.
Door opens and who
walk compromises, D.J.
And created the musical style
that's become the sound track to
well, the whole wide world.
They nod at each other, screwed
over, cut out of the big money,
or just laugh of a the
absurdy of it all.
Hip hop came from nowhere else,
it could have come from
nowhere else, but the Bronx.
♪
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found some something good
in this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha, la, la, la, la,
♪ sha, la, la, la, la, la
this the Bronx.
You've probably heard about it.
You may even have a pretty solid
image in your head of
what it looks like.
What it is like.
Or maybe you can't
picture it at all.
The south Bronx sounds
familiar as a bad thing.
And the Bronx at one time was
said to be burning, wasn't it?
For the most part, the
Bronx is overlooked, the never visited
borough in New York City, which
is a shame because the Bronx is
a magical place with its own
energy, its own food,
vibe, and rhythm.
You've been to Brooklyn, maybe
it's time you took a
look at the Bronx.
August of 1973, the sister of
D.j. Cool herd was holding a
birthday party for herself in
the basement of 1520
central Avenue.
As he was playing the music on
his two disk turntable, he began
to slow the music down slow the
people stood up and took notice
and began asking him to do it
again, he did it again, they
asked him to do it again, again,
he did it again and attracted
more and more people to his
performances, and people began
to imitate him, and that was the
beginning of hip hop music.
It started in the Bronx.
Moody's records, inside
rummaging for records just like
he used to do is the man, the
legend, one of the very select
few who started it all.
Who created the sound that
hundreds of millions of people
now claim as their own.
Google, who created hip hop?
Go ahead, you get, D.J. Cool.
It's a national landmark, right?
No, it's not, we're
working on it.
It's still the birthplace of
hip hop undisputed because I
didn't start it with four guys
in a club, I was inside
a residential building.
At the time, it wasn't really in
eye over the recreation room.
So she would watch for any
disturbance, it never happened,
and that's how it survived
because good music said itself,
good drug set itself, good
anything set itself, and
this was something good.
Was there a moment when you
realized this is big, this is
going to be, this is going
to spread way beyond my
neighborhood?
Never looked at it as that.
I saw it spreading, but it
reminded me of Fred Flinstone.
It's not going to be nothing.
So to say I don't have money and
all that, I'm rich in other
ways, but time magazine said
when music was created inside
the United States, Louis
Armstrong for jazz, Elvis
Presley for rock and roll, him
and Chuckie Berry, and
cool herc for hip hop.
Feel good?
Very good.
Historically, from the last
third of the 19th century in to
about 1920, it was Germany.
From about 1930 to about 1960,
the second language spoken
in the Bronx was Yiddish.
From 1965 onward, the second
language is Spanish, and
that's the way it is today.
It's got a reputation as a
tough place, crime, street
gangs, a lot of which goes back
to the way it was and some of
which, well like I said, it's
got a reputation as being tough.
The Bronx is, let's face it, a
big blank space in a
lot of people's minds.
Even people like me who live
what, ten minutes away, we don't
know anything about that big
area between Yankees
stadium and the Bronx zoo.
What you should know is
that the Bronx is big.
Really big.
And that it's a patchwork of
ethnic enclaves, a cross
section of the whole world.
Every immigrant group
you could think of.
Justin, aka, Barren Imbrosha is
serving at the
culinary ambassador.
Let the dinner begin.
This is the porcupine.
For the cause of introducing
the delights of this mighty
borough to the ignorant,
well like me.
He's got a show on the TV, and
he throws parties where he
serves creatures that would make
Andrew Zimmer turn gray and
slump unconscious to the floor.
Explorer, and gourmet.
Bronx, it's so multifacetted,
but for some reason this is the
first place I take people.
This is oozes and imminents
that flavor of the Bronx.
And he knows what I like.
Places like this.
188 on 188th street and
the grand concourse.
Old school New York
Puerto Rican good stuff.
Get within 20 feet of this stuff
and prepare to lose
your freaking mind.
It is fried pig.
Ear, tongue, chopped
up and deep fried.
Off cut pig parts, deep fried.
What's not to like about that?
Yeah, the shoulder.
We're going to get
that in there.
Oh yeah.
Big piece of the skin,
just chopped up.
So skin.
Skin and fat?
Yeah.
It's almost like a
little meat candy bar.
That's amazing.
Amazing.
And then what else?
We need this.
Yes.
Puerto Rico on a skew.
The Bronx to me became a
place where I could really
engage my sensibility.
You could really just come here,
eat, drink, wine,
and just indulge.
This is pretty much the center
of the pork universe as
I've ever seen it in New York.
I don't any place porkier
than what I'm looking at.
This is exactly the kind of
thing I thought we'd lost in new
York, that one after the other
faded away in the neighborhood's
I lived in and all along, all
along it was there, underfoot, a
gusher of porky goodness.
There's a great line, which
is they say, in
France, Se la Bronx.
What do you think
this is the Bronx?
And this idea of music's really
mad or someone's making a mess.
To me I take that as
a point of pride.
To be the Bronx, it is where the
music is loud, men are tough,
women are sexy, and
food is spicy.
If those things weren't true.
You wouldn't know
what the Bronx is.
Its bad reputation
is what protects it?
I think the perception, the
perception of it being a place
where the funk is alive.
Incredible, incredible spread.
Yeah, man, this is great.
This is one of the places you'll
dream about, was I really there.
I'm going back to see if
that place is really there.
Lay off this pork.
It's insane.
I'm actually going to
get a to go order.
Yo, love for my haters,
forgiveness for my enemies, move
spectators I'm dead
if they shot Kennedy.
I'm from the Bronx, New York,
and I don't beg your pardon, I
was 12 or 13 when hip
hop was started.
Go and take a minute to listen
to what those fools speak,
it's clear uncut garbage.
Just let me bump,
fill my energy up.
No logic, a bunch of false
profetes pushing a false
positive.
I'm not hard to find, I'm by
the zoo, holler at me, baby.
Watch it.
♪
First to call himself
an emcee, Melly Mel.
In 1982, and he grand master
flash wrote and
recorded the message.
An album that was a complete and
ground breaking departure from
the lyrics and content
up to that point.
Before we started doing hip
hop music, there was none, we
played everything, disco, we
played ray gay, we played hop,
watched hehaw, that was
the favorite in my house.
And all of those things kind of
became the components of
what became hip hop music.
♪
I started out as a break dancer.
I used to break dance, my
brother used to do graffiti, and
all of those individual elements
wasn't really happening
anywhere else.
It was just something that could
only have went on right in
that area in the Bronx.
Yeah, okay, you may be
thinking, what about the sugar
hill gang, what about them?
They were an industry band like
The Monkey or Archies, built in
catch in quick on a fad.
And they did cash in.
Where were you when realized,
[ bleep ], there's
money in this?
Well that first record was
king Tim the third, the
second and rappers alike.
I used to live on a fifth floor
walk up, somebody was playing it
next door, fourth floor, the
third floor, second floor.
First floor.
Somebody had a boom box
outside playing it.
The car that drove by had it on.
Nothing that was like a plague,
it was like, it was like locust.
And that's when I realized, you
know, it's something that was
beyond what we was doing
out in the street.
Critically, it's not a great
record, but if you play it right
now, it's still, you know,
it's still a good record.
In this case at least,
history has come around.
Today nobody looks back as
originals or innovators.
People know who did what.
As far as hip hop now, as far
as the music now, these guys are
not trying to tell a story
of their time at all.
Okay, yeah they popped a lot of
bottles, had sex with a lot of
women and drove expensive cars
and nothing else happened.
You would never know there was a
black president, you would never
know there was two wars, it's
not reflected in the music.
And at some point, somebody was
supposed to step up and make
those songs, 20 years from now,
they'll be talking about the
message and planet rock and
all the classic records.
You know what I mean?
That's what it is.
Robert Moses has been
dead over 30 years now.
And people in the Bronx, for the
most part, still hate him.
His role as magser builder...
Master builder, he ran the
parkway system straight through
dozens of working class
neighborhoods, seemingly
uncaring about the destruction
of whole communities.
Massive housing projects
conceived as utopian solutions
to stacking the poor or the
centralized vertical Ge toes
were also his bright idea.
He did leave some pretty
impressive dam works behind
though, like the bridge,
flushing meadows park, the
bridge, the Bronx happens to be
the home of the two largest
parks in New York City.
Helm bay, and you see stuff here
you ain't seen in central park.
It comes from Honduras,
Guatemala, and bell please and
traced they ethnic group back to
a single slave ship that crashed
off St. Vincent and freed
Africans, then mixed with
Indians.
Where is home for many of the
community living in the U.S.?
You guessed it, the Bronx.
Living in the Bronx, you're
able to kind of travel the world
without leaving the borough.
Right.
And you know, it's
like an addiction.
When you go to another country
and the first day in the market,
and all your dreams and smell
the diesel, and you're looking
around, last one thing
you're looking for?
To do that in your own
backyard, it's... cool.
That's coconut soup
with fish... uh-huh.
Over here, we have a tapo.
That looks good.
Banana, and coconut soup.
That sounds good.
Yeah, neck bones and it.
Yeah, let's do it.
So let's put some
plants in here.
Mashed plan tans come with
just about every dish.
Plantations are part of me.
You'll never have it without it.
Yeah.
Same method, same right
hand, same everything.
There's fish and coconut soup.
What kind of fish is this?
Blue fish.
Awesome, I love blue fish.
And nice smoked neck
bones with bananas.
That's officially
awesome already.
Oh, that's tasty.
It's really good.
Underexploited fish,
one of my favorites.
So you know what I've noticed
already, the Bronx is big.
How ludicrous and shameful is it
that I can literally see my
house from here and I
have no idea where I am?
No fault on your own, but I
think that's what keeps the
Bronx so amazing, you have all
these in touch ethnic enclaves.
I didn't know there
were Hondurans here.
I would say the neck is the next
big thing for years now.
Still waiting.
People from all over the
world reside in the Bronx, as a
matter of fact, we have
residents from every continent
on the face of the earth, and if
you count the penguins in the
Bronx zoo, that includes
Antarctica.
♪
The wellspring of hip hop is
right around here, a mostly
Jamaican community in Bronx
river in the south Bronx.
Jamaicans began arriving here
back in the 50s, and still
today, Jamaican food, culture,
the music, is all over.
Sun dial international
headquarters, makers of
traditional tonics and herbal
remedies, a Bronx
institution since the 70s.
This is enough ingredients,
this is the oil.
This one is used for any
type of bodily weaknesses.
Pops Baba as he's called,
grassroots bush doctor, healer,
he uses recipes passed from
mothers and aunties, roots,
spices, herbs, barks, and woods.
Wood root in the morning and
at night, it'll cure
what's wrong with you.
You're going to
have improvement.
Whatever ails, he is a cure.
Root wood cure for the
blood, bodies, nerves.
Intestinal cleanser and man
back, hopes to get your manhood
back among other things.
About 1956 that I
came to America.
So I could make it in the
apartment in the Bronx river.
And project smell up this roof,
they used to drive them.
Hey, what are you
doing in there?
What kind of hoekus poekus in there doing.
And I'd go in the car, and
I'd sell it in the Bronx.
The Bronx is the best
place in America.
Nowhere like the Bronx.
Up north a ways in west
Jamaica, another working class
community where subway service
is limited and yet people to
have to get up, go to work, and
make the long hump
to another borough.
Afterwards, a person
could use a drink.
And if you're a Jamaican person,
you could use the every day
drink of back home, any time of
day and night, ray and nephew.
It is a very strong Jamaican
white rum that we use from
everything to drinks
here in this bar.
You get it with cranberry
juice, milk, or water.
Water would be in every nephew
would be ray and
nephew in the Bronx.
It's a very fast, free form
riff diatribe about life in the
Bronx and what's happening on
the news, in hip
hop, or last night.
Growing up in the Bronx
the city. Olated from the rest of
you know what I'm saying, the
other city has like city bite,
the Bronx doesn't get that.
People on a boat and go to
Staten island before they
ride up to the Bronx.
I have to reluctantly have to
be part of of the problem.
It's going en to junk if ied,
that's not happening
any time soon.
It's not.
There's no owner right here.
This is the man right here
who made today possible.
Thank you.
I am happy here.
Andly drink more of your ray and
nephew, regardless of what it
might be doing to my brain,
but then, I will eat.
What is this?
Pigtail.
Yeah.
Awesome.
Oh hell, I love this.
Oh.
Man, that looks good.
People sort of, stop paying
attention to the Bronx when
it wasn't burning anymore.
When fort Apache was something
we didn't have to think about.
Let's say this is the
neighborhood where they
perfected it.
Right.
Do you remember your first time?
I remember my first time.
How do you feel, first time?
I cried.
And that summer, 15 times, stop
and frisk, thrown up against the
gate, fingers to our genitals
cops looking for gun.
But you remember that, you
remember your first time.
When you lose your stop
and frisk virginity.
I wonder why?
Is it because off CNN show
or it is it just because...
I've been arrested.
If you hang out here long
enough, I can get you
stop and frisked.
They talk about DIY culture,
about do it yourself.
And you better be able to do it
your [ Bleep ] self in the Bronx
because often, nobody sells
going to do it for you.
When you go in the Bronx,
you're going back in time.
There are certain crimes that
will happen here that won't
happen here in Brooklyn or
Manhattan.
Purse snatchers.
Really?
There's still crackheads.
There's crackheads in front
of that over there, and they are
getting their cracks, and
they're not bothering anyone.
And they are respecting
parts of this community.
You see them every day.
There's a crackhead that's
been here for 25 years.
That takes some
determination now.
Listen, if I could be a
crackhead, I would be the best
crackhead possible.
I was a crackhead, and oh
listen, people have been
there.
No judgments.
Hey, what's up?
All right.
Look, I'm thinking curry goat.
His uncle Vernon used to own
this place, but that
was three owners ago.
Now it's lammy's, people put too
much cinnamon in the goat,
which is a sin against god.
Lammy fixed things.
Curry goat and stewed ox tail
with rice and peas, collards,
and yes, Mac and cheese.
I can't resist.
I mean, correct me if I'm
wrong, there's a lot of good
food in the Bronx.
There is, there is.
If people would like you know
get over their bias and come
above 96th street,
they would find out.
I mean if the Bronx were a
neighborhood in Manhattan, sort
of shrunk down, you'd have
hipsters crawling over over.
Oh my god.
If you live in the Bronx it's
not necessarily that you're
going to leave the Bronx.
Why would you go
past 149th street?
So all that, repping my
neighborhood, the ethnic pride
and all that, people
hold on to that.
And that's true of Rylander
Avenue, that sort of stuff.
Even this.
Neighborhood was all
white until the '50s.
It's very recent the
whole immigrant...
Who lived here in the 50s?
All white people.
What kind of white people?
White white.
Like we enjoy milk white, we're
kissing dogs on the mouth.
It's moved forward, and there's
definitely this whole, you know,
like I'm from 233rd, you're from
225th, every ethnic
group has that.
And the next group that will
take over here is definitely
Mexicans, and the thing is, it's
an immigrant neighborhood.
It's not a matter who have owns
it, it's who owns it at
that time and they're next.
I enjoy good case Dee Yas.
We made the good decision
to come to Lamny's today.
Yeah.
Lammy's, I'm here all the time.
I live right there.
I'm always here for the curry
goat, Mac and cheese, you know.
Lammy's don't play, man.
The twos and the fives here
are the greatest trains because
they go from Bronx through
Manhattan all the way
through Brooklyn.
It's the only number of lines
that will get three
boroughs visibility.
The Bronx still here.
Yeah, it's still here.
But you know, like even that, I
mean that brings me
back, Tony, that sound.
Do you remember the first
time you put spray
paint on a wall?
Yeah.
When was that?
Uh, summer of '70.
Back then, seemingly overnight,
they were everywhere,
princes of the city, their
pieces stretching across city
blocks, whole trains, evermore
audacious, some, by
this man, were artists.
In the late '70s, to be on of
a rooftop like this with a brew
or whatever, hanging out, we're
waiting for something to come
through with a cool letter or
like oh my god, look at that.
And kids are screaming, like, oh
my god, look, here it comes.
There's my mine.
There's mine, but what if you
thought the train was
on the left side.
Then you kind of messed up.
Oh no, it's on the right side.
And no, you're not screwed, you
wait until this train goes all
the way to Brooklyn
and comes back.
This was the audience
you had in mind?
Does matter?
I think all of us spoke
to each other back then.
Other arts.
It was just the rush of the
event, and then the accolades
you may or may not receive.
Not from the public,
but from your peers.
Futura 2000, his style
spread across the globe.
I miss those trains.
Others, not so much.
I get it, it went on and on
until it seemed there wasn't an
untagged, unmarked, bit of wall
or window in New York, but for a
while, it was a golden time.
Well the whole point
of being here... yeah.
Was to me what the Bronx was
about, not just the music and
the scene and coming up with the
parties of Bam and Herc and
everyone of that era, but
it's watching trains.
We used to call it benching.
You were watching work go by?
Absolutely.
Art lovers.
This was his museum.
Where he and his fellow artists
would meet and exchange ideas
and admire each other's work.
And it's jarring coming to learn
all those years later that it
was really all about this, about
a few seconds as their pieces
rode by to be
evaluated by peers.
There for a moment, then gone.
Like well all of their work from
that time, long since
removed or painted over.
Ultimately, the legacy...
Here, here's our legacy.
We don't have a
movement anymore.
The movement has been
given to the world.
And if you go to trains in Milan
and Paris, certainly not the
Russian system, but if you go
around the world,
they're bombed.
Their rail systems
are destroyed.
But I mean, today, if I could
have a train running...
It would be nice.
It would be epic.
I think any artist, Picasso,
if that concept was available,
like here is some public art
guys, threat run through
our countryside.
♪
Take the six trains to the ♪
take the six trains to the
end of the line, then do the
same for the number 29 bus.
Technically you'll still be in
the Bronx, but it kind
of won't feel like it.
City island is a fishing
village turned what?
A parking lot for pleasure
boats, and a long established
restaurant row for new yorkers.
Pick the perfect day
to come out here.
Desus says this place, and
Desus is always right.
How far from the
neighborhood by car?
Maybe 15, 20 minutes.
20 minutes.
That seems like a world away.
Yeah, but I want to buy
some nautical stuff.
This is New York City?
This is Cape Cod in the Bronx.
Many of my childhood memories,
get there and they're like oh
the beach is closed
far medical race.
It's not a day you go in the
water and come out with like
a maxi pad stuck to you.
Been there.
So you were here like
when, yesterday?
I was literally here yesterday.
Wow.
For my sister's graduation
because every time you have an
event of note in the Bronx, you
have to come celebrate
at city island.
I notice all the big
catering halls.
Yeah, get married, arraigned,
baby's not yours, come here.
Seashore restaurant, a
massive fish factory on the
water of a type I'm very
familiar with, having started my
cooking career in
one just like it.
I'm also a sentimental fool, and
I love this kind of thing.
Steamers, a true
taste of childhood.
Boiled striper and some snow
crab and a nice cold beer,
yes, thank you, Desus.
It's like a knighting ceremony.
Just kind of sit up, and
like oh, take it all in.
Enjoy guys.
Thank you.
I could have done
that myself, but...
That's part of it.
Part of the ambience.
This is the perfect place far
date, but it's the
worst food for a date.
Either a huge turnoff
or a huge turnon.
You might give a lady a preview
of what they're
about to get into.
All the little bib,
little sucking action.
Just let them know, in an
hour, this could be you.
Wow.
This is pretty awesome.
Saturday night, city island,
that's where people are going.
The first European settler
to come to the Bronx
came in 1639.
His name was Jonas Bronck.
In 1874, all the area west of
the Bronx river was the city and
in 1895, all the area east of
the Bronx river was the city,
and 1898, the city decided that
the two areas previously inexed
should also become a borough.
But what to call it since
it never had a name before?
They looked at the map and right
smack to the middle of the
territory ran the Bronx river,
so they named it after the
river, the borough of the Bronx,
and that is why it is called the
Bronx and not just plain Bronx.
If off question about the
Bronx, chances are Lloyd
Alton has the answer.
Born and raised here, he's never
really left for
over seven decades.
This is a disappearing
aspect of New York for sure.
The real thing Jewish deli,
it is one of the last.
There used to be dozens of
places where you can get your
police cut, pastrami,
pickles with soda to drink.
The world series is going
on, Howard is on the air.
Suddenly you see a tongue of
flame licking up into the sky.
And he says, this is the kind of
thing that Jimmy taught us all,
ladies and gentlemen,
the Bronx is burning.
The old image of the Bronx as
middle class, mobile, healthy
area had survived up until
1977, this shattered it.
Right.
The Bronx was burning with
the story, and that stuck.
Politicians making the south
Bronx a poster child for what
was hopelessly wrong, would
always be wrong, would never, we
were told, get any better.
So we now have what you call
a slum lord essentially.
Snapping up large
numbers of buildings.
First of all, he takes out a
huge fire insurance policy.
So as he goes to the junkies and
says listen, you see that
apartment on the top floor?
I'm going to turn my back.
You take all of the lead pipes
that are in there, but I have
one request, please, before you
leave, turn on the
water, and the
they then hire an arsonist and
sets fire to the building, they
collect all the money,
and they leave.
I remember it well.
I remember those years.
Things were bad.
Are things boroughwide,
are they getting better?
Is the Bronx better?
Absolutely.
There is more home ownership in
the south Bronx than had
ever existed in history.
That doesn't mean that
we've reached utopia.
How long it will take,
I'm a historian.
I look in the other direction.
I would say my crystal
ball is cracked.
I got four cheeseburgers.
Is it the best hamburger
in the world?
Far from it, my friends.
Is it even, strictly
speaking, a burger?
I mean, it's small and
square and steamed.
It can be, especially when you
eat a lot of them, as one tends
to, a hate yourself in
the morning experience.
But if you grew up with white
castle like I did and like
handsome dick Manitoba did, this
connects with some deep dinosaur
part of the brain, evoking
an emotional response.
This is a big part
of my childhood.
We'd come here 24 hours a day.
There were guys on their dates.
There was a bunch
of punk rock kids.
So along with that potpourri of
humanity I just described you
had these guys from the
mental institution.
Ah, that's community for you.
That was the Bronx.
That was the Bronx, man.
It was great.
Maybe you know handsome dick
from such prepunk legendary
bands as the dictators.
Dick grew up, where else, the
Athens, the cultural guyser, the
font of art and music
that is the Bronx.
And back in the day like me,
this was his special
warm and happy place.
I can go by and eat a full
2 1/2-hour meal, be stuffed, and
see someone eating a white
castle, I stilt want one.
You can forget Mickey D’s.
You forget burger king.
You fork all those places.
If you need a white castle
scratch, none of the cheap
places will do.
I can't stop eating.
The Bronx academy of letters
is something of a cause for me.
An institution whose mission I
see as absolutely vital.
If kids like these kids from a
tough neighborhood, often coming
from tough family situations,
are going to dot things that
they're capable of, of
having the things they want.
I believe that there is no way
to realize your dreams if you
can't articulate them, if you
can't with words convince others
to give you the opportunities,
the chances you need to grasp.
So I wanted to talk today...
Really I'm going to tell you
in a short period of time
everything I know about writing.
Today I'm dropping by in my
role as substitute teacher.
I'm from Manhattan.
And I don't know anything
about the Bronx really.
I'm ridiculously,
shamefully ignorant.
Do you think people know about
the Bronx, what it's like
to grow up in the Bronx?
Everybody perceives the Bronx
as the emergence of hip-hop
and all that, the culture.
But apart from that the Bronx is
actually lively at all times.
At night, in the morning.
You hear people screaming
from outside your window.
Since I was like 7.
And it's happened that way.
Community's the biggest thing.
I've been teaching here for
eight years, and I think that
what people forget is a lot of
times we talk about this in
class, they focus on lots of
diseases, health issues,
lack of education.
But I can be out with them just
walking to the train to go to a
field trip and they say
hi to at least 30 people.
They know everyone.
What other Bronx specialties
should I be paying attention to?
Montano's.
That works for you.
Yeah.
I like bacon, egg and
cheese sandwich.
That's a classic.
That's a New York classic.
Sort of a bodega classic.
Love that.
I walk outside and
have the Italian icee.
Soon as the weather gets nice
and you hear cohito,
they've got the best.
What is chopped cheese?
I have to see.
Where does this come from?
This mutant cheese.
This thing, whatever it
is, it'll do just fine.
As long as you're reading
Orwell's essays while you're
eating it, kid.
I think it's someone who
experiments in their home.
Because it tastes so different
than like a cheeseburger, which
is what it kind of is actually.
But it's... people uptown or
like downtown say chopped cheese
and they're like, what?
Here you're like...
So this is a regional
indigenous special.
And it's newer, too, right?
It hasn't been around that long.
I've been everywhere in the
world, and I mean just about
everywhere in the world
that you can think of.
As beautiful as many cities
around the world are, it's
really in your blood,
particularly if you grew up
here.
You're living in Paris, you
don't want a chopped
cheese sandwich.
You'll be angry you
that can't get one.
So there it is.
A peek, a narrow slice of an
old, deep, and noble subject.
♪ Causing the co-existence
♪ to morph into a
relentless illogical ♪
sitting right there,
relatively unexplored.
A cross-section of the
tasty, original good stuff.
♪ So gritty I'm grimy ♪
got my city behind me
a petri dish for
talent, for culture.
The great unknown.
Go look.
The X.
Armageddon.