Peru is a country that's
historically driven men mad, mad
for gold, for cocoa, for its
magical ancient history.
Now, there's something else
drawing outsiders to its
hidden mountain valleys.
We love the stuff.
We obsess about it, gorge
on it and felty size it.
I'm talking about chocolate,
once a common treat, it's now
becoming as nuanced as fine wine
making the pursuit of the
raw good stuff all the more
difficult.
Item joining that hunt in
remotest Peru, but not before
I've reimmersed myself in the
booming Lima food scene.
♪
I'm in Peru with this guy, Eric.
He was looking at this,
he went into the tree.
That's funny.
Chef of the world famous
restaurant in New York.
To look at where chocolate comes
from, particularly our
chocolate, the very expensive
limited run designer chocolate
barbs Eric got me
into last year.
So that's why we're in Peru.
Before we get all Indiana Jones,
we're spending some time in
Lima, as we like the
capital city just fine.
We have both of us, from
previous trips, friends here.
Lima is the cultural hub and
culinary capital of a country
that has exploded in the last
decade with scores of world
class cooks, chefs and
restaurants.
It has long been considered to
be one of the best food scenes
in all of south America.
Good.
Five minutes.
One of our friends here
is chef restaurateur as
circumstance er, one of the best
most successful chefs
in the country.
His family is a beloved culinary
dynasty in Peru and a small
fishing village about an hour
south of Lima is where
they spend their weekends.
His mom is like Peru's Julia
Childs and James beard
rolled into one.
Thank you for having us.
An icon of Peruvian astronomy.
To say one is fortunate to enjoy
her hospitality would
be an understatement.
Warm, generous, welcoming
beyond belie belief.
Too bad you have
to leave so soon.
Yeah.
Normally, we have lunch
late, like 5:00.
Do you nap before
lunch or after?
Both.
Sounds like paradise.
Wow.
Look at this.
Every weekend, Marissa opens
the house to an ever changing
mob of friends, visitors,
drop kins and family.
This is fantastic.
They do not skimp on the food.
Delicious, delicious things pour
out of the kitchen, a torrent, a
deluge of traditional
Peruvian favorites.
I do this with crab meat,
yellow potato and avocado.
We love avocado.
It is like a touring of crab
meat, avocado and mashed
yellow potatoe potatoes.
This is from the coast.
Beautiful.
Basically raw king fish
fillets dressed with lime juice.
Perfect.
That's scallops cerricha.
Fresh scallops and lemon
juice and garlic.
Drum fish, braised with
a corn based beer.
They look fantastic.
This is spicy.
Very spicy.
And stuffed riccotti peppers
filled with ground beef and
raisins, served with cheese.
Wow.
Are we lucky or what?
We are lucky.
That's just the beginning.
There's so much more food
there's no way we can show it
all much less describe it.
It's incredible, overwhelming,
invariably fresh and delicious
and different than
what I'm used to.
That's fantastic.
I could get out of the
chocolate business right now,
put up a pup tent on Marissa's
porch and dig in
for the duration.
This is living.
They're so fresh.
I want to be her
next door neighbor.
It's so good.
So as Peruvian cuisine always
been this diverse and this
delicious and we're just
discovering it or has it changed
over the last 15 years?
It's challenging any way.
What you're eating now
is the traditional food.
There's so many products in
Peru different than the states.
When you eat this food,
it's something like.
Not kind of like anything.
It's all year-round.
It is very good.
What do you do when you're
homesick for Peruvian food
and you're traveling?
There's really... we
take some chiles with us
in the luggage.
I hate to say good-bye to
this but it is what it is.
Things to do and places to go.
Wild and apparently extremely
rare cocoa trees to visit.
Incredibly rare.
So happy.
♪
All I can say if people are
anywhere near this nice on the
rest of this trip,
it's going to be okay.
Lima, city of kings, home to
a third of Peru's people.
Locals escape by hanging
out at the beach.
Why not, when you can maybe get
a tattoo while you're at it.
Is that sanitary?
You've been here before.
Oh, yeah, man.
I take Eric's suggestion and
we head over to see chef Wang,
the uniquely nonconformist
seafood specialist, famous
for his incredible and
uncompromising food and
his flaming wok.
If Peru has a national
dish, it's probably this.
The fresh estfish only needs the
right cut, a little
citrus and no heat.
What's the most common
thing people do wrong?
The quality of the ingredients.
You don't do it with
something that is not fresh.
The cut and the thickness.
Right.
When you do it, you don't
do it ahead of time.
The whole place is served
whatever men you he's doing that
day, same for everybody.
Today, the flounder he got from
the market is particularly nice,
so that's what we're getting.
Generally thicker pieces to
stand up to the
supervises and acids.
Octopus and flounder.
I don't know what
to tell you, man.
It's damn good.
It is good.
Is this spicy or not?
You ever been spanked in
your life and enjoyed it?
Me neither.
I don't like pain.
As painful as the pepper.
Brutalized with a pepper.
That's really hot.
It's flounder dressed with
pecan, lime, limo and sesame
oil, clearly Eric likes.
So you're not like foraging
in the Catskills for your
inspiration?
You basically rip your ideas
off small businessmen?
It's okay?
Circumstance.
Superb.
Chinese and Japanese immigrants
came to Peru in great
numbers in the 19th and 20th
centuries as contract laborers
and farmers and their influence
is felt here, particular there
in food, to a greater degree
than anywhere else on the
continent.
It's that influence and the
ingredients of Amazonia and
Andes that really distinguishes
the food here as
something special.
What is this?
Tofu?
This is not traditional.
It looks Asian to me.
I believe it's probably
his name is want.
Unless he's a retired porn
star... this shouldn't
be good but it is.
Working up a sweat on that one.
Might have a couple
more beers after this.
Have a nice nap, midday nap.
One more day in Lima, the
chance to delve a bit further
into the cuisine before things
get a little more old school.
A special one we prefer here.
Colentro?
It's like cilantro and much
more powerful in flavor.
It would be wrong to point
out it is at the
forefront of create I
creating flavor unique to the
Andes and Amazon, flavors you
find no place else on earth.
There seems to be a lot of
interest in the last decade to
the Amazon because of its
amazing spectra entirely new to
most of us of ingredients.
At the cutting edge of exactly
that territory, his restaurant
Amaz explores the rivers and
landscape of Peru highlighting a
range of products stunning in
their diversity and
to us, their newness.
You have tuna, plantain vinegar.
The nut is a fruit in Brazil.
Hmm.
We make these scallops
with wild almond.
It is very very soft, the
flavor of it and complements
very well.
This one is fresh water shrimp.
Whole new flavor
spectrum, all new.
Almost like you need a new
section of your tongue.
It must be exciting Ba
because they're an amazing
garden with the Amazon.
That looks good.
This is a soup made of ham
and peanuts and corn.
Hmm.
I like the food.
I've enjoyed these
cocktails, to too.
We're going to be wasted.
We'll be fine.
Oh, whoa.
This is also tradition.
They seasons the fish, put
it on a Leif and cook it.
The fish is catfish.
In the Amazon we have like
200 types of catfish.
And the flavor from
the Leif, too.
Here, we have the second
biggest fresh water
fish in the world.
Underneath you have a puree that
is a Pam fruit and a
production of fermented yuka.
Fermented.
Or poisonous.
And it becomes...
You can eat it.
These fish are unbelievable.
They get up to 600 pounds
swimming in water no
deeper than a rice paddy.
Really?
Giant.
They're like dinosaur fish.
Everyone has been saying for
years Peru will be
the next big thing.
It is.
This really prove it.
We offer a chi chili pepper
with under the circumstances
nuts and ants.
They're big.
Huge ants.
You want to try it?
Yeah.
Totally.
You're not loving that, are you?
No.
Imagine, you took a lot of
acid and then you ate that whole
bowl of ants and you go home and
you experience violent diarrhea,
you're tripping, it's like 4:00
in the morning and you turn
around and look at the toilet
and all these ant heads
floating around in there.
It would be cool.
It would be cooler
only I can't wait.
Now that we've confirmed what
the we already knew, that Peru's
food is unequivocally awesome,
it seems proper we take a trip
back in time to meet the
forebearer's of this country's
rich cultural legacy.
The museum in Lima has a massive
collection of
pre-Colombian artifacts.
Looking at them, you get an idea
of what these ancient peoples
were like, how they lived.
Wow!
This is like the real stuff.
I think so.
The real deal, yeah.
Gold necklaces.
You see where the Spanish just
freaked-out when they came here,
turned into men Ni
call greed heads.
History does not have
to be boring.
It can be sexy.
I don't know whether you knew
this, I have an aficionado of
early erotica of post Colombian
heiress, you know pottery
of people doing it.
I should have known that.
Turns out things can get
pretty interesting
back in the day.
Oh, yeah.
Those guys can get crazy and get
wild and apparently very kinky.
The erotic gallery.
There you go.
That's a conversation starter.
I take Eric to the
pre-Colombian boning section,
actually the erotic
pottery section.
Slip of the tongue.
Amazing.
Which sounds about as much
fun as an all nude renaissance
fair, actually pretty crude.
Nothing new under the sun these
pre-Colombian horn dogs
didn't think of first.
A chicken.
I'm not sure I
understand this one.
I think we frown on
that these days.
Wow, they're doing
it under a blanket.
This must be after the Spanish
arrived to teach them shame.
Ew, skeletons with boners.
They are zombies.
Getting zombie old-fashioned.
I really appreciate your
knowledge.
Was this decorative
or really porn?
I think they put ain't
closet somewhere.
I bet this was right
on the table.
Come on in, have a cup of tea.
Sit down.
Oh.
Here's some animal
and manual action.
Pretty awesome.
Yeah.
This is interesting.
I'm happy we made it here, Tony.
That was an enlightened moment.
Something about steamy xxx
pre-Colombian erotica
always makes me hungry.
Luckily at night, Lima comes
alive with the smell and
familiar enticing sound
of sizzling meat.
It's time for delicious
screamingly hot garlicky spicy
flavor Jack street meats.
As any knows me is well
aware I love me some.
Really?
Why?
The neighbors complain?
Complain.
They brought us to this
place, a street stall named for
the lady who runs the joint.
They specialize in one thing.
It is catch you want
for skewered meat.
This stuff, they say, goes back
all the way to the Incas and as
popular with the Spanish
conquistadors as today.
Which is to say, I
must have some.
Traditionally a mixture of beef
hearts and other animal hearts.
Hearts and gizzards.
Marinated in garlic, cumin,
onion, a little vinegar.
Oh, yeah.
Grill it up and pile it on high.
These are not small portions.
These are mountains of food.
This does not get any better.
Let's do it!
Man, that's awesome.
Yeah.
That is some magic right there.
It's very garlicky.
Nice.
Chicken heart.
That is seriously tasty.
The beef heart or the chicken
heart, the texture is so nice.
All right.
I'm maxed out.
Really delicious.
Excellent.
The city lies about 400
miles northwest of Lima, Peru's
largest city with over half a
million people living there.
It's our next stop, the staging
area for our trip
to the mountains.
Chocolate.
We know we like the stuff.
How is it made?
Where does it come from?
Columbus was the first European
to encounter cocoa beans
off the coast of Honduras.
He's said to have grabbed both
crew and cargo and brought
them back to Spain.
A few decades later a Spanish
conquistador was said to have
found the drink of the gods and
the European royalty did their
best to keep what was fast
becoming a craze for hot
chocolate to themselves.
But it soon found
its way to America.
In 1765, the first chocolate
factory opened in new England.
Chiclayo's main market is a
massive one stop shop for all
things chocolate as well as just
about everything
else under the sun.
Oh, you have your animal skulls.
That's tempting.
Haircut?
I'm good.
Wow.
This is the raw beans?
That is toasted.
Then she... grinds it.
Then puts it in a mold.
Gracias.
Bitter.
Not sweet at all.
No.
Actually, here we are in the
market, I believe, where they
have what I believe
they call santarias.
He is how should I put it,
let's say he has more of a
spiritual side than me.
You need it to bless
the rest of the cow.
Okay.
So he has us shopping for
what I guess I'd call
chemanic supplies.
Medical medicinal herbs with
properties to help us
bless the cocoa crop.
[ Speaking foreign language ]
This one is amazing.
Smells really good and
supposedly purified.
Smells like hippie.
Interesting, they're very
well respected in the region.
They cure everything,
do ceremonies.
Good?
Yes.
Our journey continues by road
as we leave and head
east towards the Andes.
Originally two hours
north from here.
You have the Indians welcome
you... with blow darts.
Yeah.
Before we get too deep into
the mountains, we're stopping
off to meet someone.
[ Speaking foreign language ]
Anthony, he's going to teach
us how to do the bath for
the plants and for us.
Okay.
[ Speaking foreign language ]
He's cleaning.
All the negative vibrations.
Close your eyes.
He cleaned you and he wished
you a lot of success.
[ Speaking foreign language ]
Especially in the back,
the neck and the back.
That's here, and the chest.
We wanted a blessing
for our Coca harvest.
We got this.
My aura is now cleaner than
Gwyneth Paltrow's colon
after a juice cleanse.
But we're not done.
We have to transport this stuff
to our trees and finish
the job ourselves.
I know you won't believe
it but he has change.
I'm serious, not joking.
I have an open mind.
Eric and I are heading to the
canyon, eight hours by car from
Chiclayo, well into
the Andean highlands.
On the way, we stop for lunch
and meet up with this guy.
[ Speaking foreign language ]
Chris Curtin, master
chocolateer and business
partner in this adventure.
So, basically a hen soup.
That's good.
Where in the world does
chocolate come from?
Well, 45% from Ivory
Coast in Africa.
We don't deal in those beans
just because of political
situations.
There was this stuff,
the special chocolate.
Yeah.
Which pretty much what
we're here to look at.
Yes.
Absolutely.
Where it comes from,
what's involved.
After Eric ate some of Chris's
chocolate and heard about these
wild trees he was sourcing in
Peru and got me involved.
I'm a rather famous guy and I
never cared about desserts.
You on the other hand,
eat chocolate everyday?
Everyday.
So here we are, three men
and a chocolate bar.
Good thing for the world or
exploitive opportunism,
yet to be determined.
What do I, after all,
know about chocolate.
Next, the nut.
The canyon where we're
headed to meet some of the
farmers that supply the beans
that make our chocolate and get
me an education in
all things cacao.
It can be tricky so we have to
take care of the vigilante dudes
that run a roadblock
outside of town.
It looks like a shakedown but
they're a welcome sight.
This hill, where cars have to
slow down, was where all sorts
used to waylay
travelers like us.
So these guys stepped in
to take care of business.
Wow, that was a big shotgun.
That will shoot through
an engine block.
Actually, I don't really
know but I'm assuming.
At this time of year, there's
also the rain and mud, which can
mean flooded streets and streams
that cut right across the roads.
And there's this, the river.
In the best of circumstances, a
fairly adventurous way to get
your vehicles across, a long
line across a fast moving
current, ferry propelled
only by the flow of water.
But today, the river is too high
and the current too fast.
River running a little high.
It's these smaller
boats or nothing.
When dealing with complex
transportation issues, the best
thing to do is pull up with a
cold beer and let somebody
else figure it out.
Yeah.
Let's go in the boat.
To my crew, I say good luck.
We're headed for what looks like
bar on the other side.
Let me tell you,
it's quite a ride.
I'll go the last.
Water inside the boat.
The boat is sinking.
You got to go down and
then up, just right!
If we make it to the other
side, reasonably dry.
Beer?
The canyon is home to a wide
range of species including
and strange us to the cacao
previously thought to
be almost extinct.
A few years ago the trees were
tested at a DNA lab and had the
rare estforms of cacao in
the world, this stuff.
Don is our cacao connection, a
farmer whose family has been
working these mountains
over 40 years.
They're absolutely beautiful
when they start out.
Really cookie looking pods
when they come off the tree.
They sort of look like someone
glued them to the
side of a tree.
This is a once a year crop?
It grows continuously but
this is a peak seasons.
Try that.
Put one in your mouth.
Bite it and see the nibs inside?
Where does chocolate come from?
The bean.
Okay.
Here's where chocolate
comes from.
The trees produce pods.
You split open the pods
and take out the beans.
The buyer sun drys the
beans, then roasts them.
After roasting, the beans are
extracted from their shells and
ground up, producing
chocolate liqueur.
Mix this concentrate with milk,
sugar, cocoa butter and you get
what we call
commercial chocolate.
Our chocolate bar sells for a
nosebleed price that's high
by even premium chocolate
standards.
Where does the money go?
Most importantly to me and Eric,
are we doing a good thing?
Here's how it breaks down.
The raw cacao costs one chunk.
Lei Bo labor, the inner
sleeve, this much.
Design, box,
packaging, this much.
Various equipment and
miscellaneous, another small
chunk.
Chris, me and Eric get a
slice out of every bar.
That leaves this much,
which the retailer takes.
Chef bleeding heart hippie here
has already convinced me to give
whatever meager profits we make
off our first bar
to a local charity.
What's unusual about these pods?
These beans?
Extremely high quality flavor.
Thought not around?
This was over 120 years ago
and making a guy and comeback.
The chocolate here is once
in a life (..) find.
About 40% of the beans from
these trees have white
cacao beans mixed in.
The rest are purplish in color.
We heard of an ultra rare group
of trees further up the
mountains that produce pods of
100% all white pure beans
something me and Eric are very
interested in down the road.
But for now, Don for fun Naoto's
daughter has prepared us a
traditional Peruvian
mountain meal.
Wow.
Kuinas.
It's rice dumplings with
boiled chicken inside.
This is amazing.
Not surprisingly some Guinea
pig of which there seems to be
many around for the taking.
This preparation served
with a cacao sauce.
That's good.
All of this food is delicious.
So chocolate, say it
is a luxury food item.
Yes.
This is an area abundant with
coffee, chocolate, fruit.
How's life for the locals?
[ Speaking foreign language ]
Le.
He says up 20 years ago, 25
years ago, it was
easier for him.
He was planting
soybeans and coffee.
Right.
He was making much more money.
And then he didn't plant
soybeans any longer and the
coffee production went down so
therefore he had a financial
struggle for a while and now
with the cocoa trees they are
planting, he has no more stress
and fairly up beat himself.
I'm in the Cannon in Peru
with my partner in chocolate
bars, chef Eric.
And these are the white
chocolate beans from a farmer
and we set up a meeting with
another farmer elsewhere
in the valley.
We thought it would be a nice
gesture given all the culinary
talent between us to make a nice
dinner for he and his family.
How about that?
You could do that
with a nice sausages.
Which would be nice to
throw in with stew.
Onion, peppers, a
little bit of spice.
And potatoes?
We're kind of moving into the
Spanish and what's it called?
And we can use
shrimp from the guy.
Shrimp and chicken works.
That sounds like a plan.
[ Speaking foreign language ]
Yeah.
Successful.
Yes.
So far.
Wait until we arrive there.
It's interesting.
Don't be a downer, man.
I'm optimistic.
We arrive at the village
who will lead us to the trees.
We're going to follow him.
What was depicted as a short
walk up a slight incline turns
out to be an epic hump up
one hill after another.
When you tire up, you tell us.
When you slump to the ground
and urinate all over myself,
that will probably be a tip that
I probably want to stop.
Another reason I hate
the Swiss, mountains.
I love mountains.
Eric, who grew up in the
Pyrenees, is up the
slopes like a gazelle.
Me, I feel every year of my
misspent life with every step.
Oh, geez.
This is... are we there?
No, no, we're not there.
He's a baby.
Only 22 trees.
I wish I could hear you over
the sound of my exploding
capillaries.
Okay.
By the time we get near the
fabled trees, I'm toast.
Gasping for air, waiting to puke
from the altitude and
the exertion.
So, tell us again, what's
unique about these trees?
Just because they are all
white beans, all white.
Which is a rarity.
So these are the only
known all-white 100 pure.
That's right.
And why is that good?
It's a new variety and gives
new flavor profiles to it.
I assume because I've
humped up a... excuse me.
Oh, nice catch.
Watch your fingers, man.
Yeah.
That's it.
There we go.
And I'm going to repeat myself.
All white.
Remember the shamin.
Well, we still have stuff to do
with the package he gave us.
We do, presumably,
want a good cop.
Better get right with
the spirit world.
Oh, geez.
Shamin juice thrown around,
the purified soil and there you
go, chocolate magnates.
Well, good luck, dude,
to a good harvest.
The trip downhill
unsurprisingly is a lot easier
on me.
Time for me in chef
Repare to get cooking.
Bake to basics, wood fire,
ingredients from the morning
morning and this old
recycling system.
Here, fila.
I'm ready for the chicken.
And red wine.
Notice how I neatly maneuvered
you into the chef job.
Now we have to maked the
mashed potato and we're good.
Eric's mashed potato
secret, around 50% butter.
The glory that is France.
I think they call it gout.
Okay.
Let's do it.
Gracias.
You guys can cook.
Some say.
[ Speaking foreign language ]
The only guy, he asked all
the founders of the village here
to do exactly what he has done,
so the farmers are
starting to copy him.
Right.
And he's happy because it's
going to bring wealth, in the
legend, in the valley
and the community.
After Don makes a traditional
unsweetened hot chocolate
preparation, ground cakau
anybodies, no sweetener, no
nothing, just like the
ancient kings liked it.
There we go.
Gracias.
The real deal.
Only water, and they will use...
Before chocolate hit Europe.
This is what the Aztec
kings would drink.
They would be jealous right now.
You'll get yours eventually.
Gracias.
Mucho gracias.
Salud.
That's good salud.
Gentlemen, to education.
Yes.
So, did we do the right thing?
Is it all right for two new
yorkers to make money, however
much, or however little, off the
work of struggling farmers
in a faraway Lane?
For the nada, Alberto, Chris,
everybody down the line, all the
way to the families who pick the
pods off the trees, seem pretty
happy to be doing what they are
doing, but do I want to be
in the chocolate business?
That's something I'm going
to have to figure out.
But for now one last thing needs
to be done to fulfill our
shamanic obligations.
Guys, you need to get out.
The guy is coming with his
bike, and he doesn't care.
A San Mateo-Hayward bridge, a
bundle of uke luptus leaves, a
badly working lighter,
got to get right.
Do you have a lighter?
We need to burn this stuff
and pass it around our
bodies three times.
Got something.
Oh, too moist.
Oh, you got it, man.
Okay.
Smoking.
That's smoking.
I'm going to get it.
Hold on.
Now I've got it.
Let's do it.
Okay.
That's coming.
I got it.
We did it.
Over.
Okay.
Done.
Hey.
We have a problem with chocolate
I'll tell you that.