♪ I took a ride ♪ Through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain
♪ On my shoulder
♪ Found something good ♪
In this beautiful world
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la, la
♪ Sha la, la, la, la, la, la
♪
Do you smell that?
Motorbike exhaust,
fish sauce, incense...
The faraway smell of
something... is... is that pork
grilling over charcoal?
♪
Vietnam, it could
be no place else.
♪
Listen to me.
There is no other way to
see this city, Hanoi,
than from a motorbike
or a scooter.
To do otherwise would
be to miss it all.
♪
-Whoa!
It is one of the great
pleasures of my life
to join the river of people
rushing through the streets.
♪
Vietnam, it grabs you
and doesn't let you go.
Once you love it, you
love it forever.
I've been coming
here since 2000,
the first time I'd been in
this part of the world,
and it's held a special
place in my heart
and my imagination since.
I keep coming back.
I have to.
♪
Vietnam has changed since
last time I was here.
It's changing every minute.
But some things, for now
anyway, remain the same.
Important things
like this stuff.
That's gonna be good.
Bun oc, first meal in Hanoi,
and it's something they do here
better than anywhere else.
Okay, I'm officially
in Hanoi now.
Mmm, magic.
A spicy, wonderful broth
with tomatoes and herb
and noodles and fresh snails.
Plump and delicious.
Look at those beauties.
Come to me, plump,
little love muscle.
Mmm.
Hanoi, capital city of Vietnam.
Seven and a half million
people live here.
In the winter, it's
chilly and damp.
In the summer, hot,
humid, subtropical.
The boulevards and many of
the buildings are French.
But its heart and soul is
always, always Vietnamese.
Americans coming here as
tourists for the first time,
especially veterans of the war,
are shocked by how
friendly the place is.
People are genuinely
happy to see you.
♪
This is Hanoi's Old Quarter,
but it's looking less
and less old these days.
Man, this area's changed though.
I mean, the Irish/Czech-
themed pub next door?
♪
Vietnam is a young country.
Almost half of Vietnamese
are under the age of 30.
Fewer every year even
remember what they call here
the American War.
Those years were a defining time
for just about everyone,
Vietnamese or American,
who lived through them.
And though there are still a lot
of conflicted feelings back
home, for most Vietnamese
these days, the war has
become an abstraction,
not even a memory.
Vietnam is still a poor nation,
but the standard of
living has improved a lot
with the relaxing of hardline
communist economic policies.
More and more foreign
tourists every year.
Western chains inevitable
are everywhere.
And President Obama is
visiting for the first time,
taking another step
on the long path
toward normalizing relations
between the two countries.
That is good.
Ooh, hot.
Ooh, I hit that chili hard.
- Nice to meet you.
- Yes.
- It's such a pleasure.
- Oh, and we have -a
beer ready to go, great.
- Yes.
So we're doing by bottle,
or we're going to pour it
in a glass?
How would you do it
if I wasn't here?
- I would pour it in the glass.
- Okay.
In Vietnam, particularly
in the North, it would be
very improper for
a woman to drink
- straight from the bottle.
- Oh, really? Oh, really?
- Yeah.
- Okay, well, I'm glad I know this now.
Cheers.
Thao is an Eisenhower Fellow
and a Fulbright scholar.
She's devoted her career to
help strengthen the bonds
between Vietnam and the US.
Today, we drove to the
outskirts of Hanoi.
- Uh-hmm?
- Cranes, tall buildings.
People moving from the
country to the city?
- Uh-hmm?
- Marc Jacobs, Prada,
I mean, this is
a very young country now.
Oh, very much a young nation.
They like to eat the
Kentucky Fried Chicken.
They like to spend a lot
of their time on the internet.
The history of our country
is a history of war.
We had a thousand years
under the Chinese,
and then we had eighty
years under the French,
and then the Japanese came in,
and when the American
left finally in 1975,
we got involved with Cambodia,
so we only have peace
since 1989.
Just in the matter
of a few decades,
the entire population
will be those
without any war experience.
And that's a great thing.
And what are we eating today?
Well, we are going
to have a banh cuon.
- And that means?
- Rice roll, very thin.
- Like a crepe?
- Yes, it's like a crepe.
And inside, ground, minced
pork and wood ear mushroom.
Ah.
♪
And you dip it in,
and there you go.
Mmm.
Oh, that's very good.
Everything we do internationally,
someone refers back
to the Vietnam experience.
You know, "Let's not
do that again," or...
-Let's not repeat Vietnam.
- But I find it interesting
that the people
who had perhaps the
most painful experience
were among the first
to reach out.
- I think the John McCain story...
- Yes.
Is particularly interesting
because here's a guy
who had an atrocious
experience here in prison,
and yet he has been among
the most vocal supporters
of normalizing relations.
It took several
trips to Vietnam,
and so he could see Vietnam
in a different light.
It's no longer a war.
It's a country with people.
Have you been out with
returning veterans from...
Oh, yes, all the time.
Do they often want
to go to the area
that they served?
- Oh, yes.
- Do they often even meet
with the people they fought?
- Yes.
- B-52 pilots come to the areas
they unloaded their bombs?
Yes.
♪
What is that experience like?
What do you see when they come?
Extremely emotional,
extremely emotional.
♪
People burst into tears.
"The memory I kept of you
45 years ago was an enemy."
"I did anything and
everything to protect my life
and to protect the
people in my platoon."
"But today, when I see you again
not as an enemy, as a person."
Everything just disappear.
All the bad feeling
disappear, and now
"Oh, are you married?"
You know, "How many
children do you have?"
You know, "What are you up to?"
Their life turn into a new
chapter, and this chapter
is a good chapter.
[woman speaking
Vietnamese over PA]
Hanoi in the morning, the
usual high-pitched whine
of thousands of motorbikes.
People and the things they
carry coming out to work,
to set up shop, the
sound of commerce...
Of a wildly free market
economy in a system
that's decidedly not.
♪
Ohh!
Hey!
-Whoo!
- Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey!
-Hey! Hey!
- [woman sings in
native language]
When I first came here,
it was Tai Chi at dawn,
and that's still here.
But there's also this.
♪
-Good to see you.
- It's nice to see you too.
- This is An, my friend.
- Nice to meet you.
She's also my Zumba instructor.
Ah.
No Zumba for me.
Breakfast, though, sounds good.
How often a week do you think
the average person
cooks, and how often
do they eat out?
Mostly we just cook
at home for dinner
because that's the
only meal in the day
that everybody can be together.
But for other meals,
normally we eat out.
♪
Whoo!
I meet my old friend Ha
on the edge of the Old
Quarter, a place known
as Cussing Noodles.
This is my favorite,
favorite restaurant.
- This place?
- Yes.
The name comes from
the owner, this lady,
known for the free and
frank way she communicates
with her customers.
-I hear she yells at people.
-Yes.
What are you standing there for?
If you're going to
order, hurry up!
I want the vermicelli with
tongue and ground pork.
I don't have that.
If you like ground
pork go to the market,
they've got lots of it.
If you go to her counter
and order something
and then you indecisive like,
"Oh, can I have these?"
"Oh, no, no, no, no, no,
no, no, maybe I have
these instead,"
she's like, "I don't have
lots of time for you,
so just get out of here."
- Really?
- Yeah.
It's best if you just
go home and eat.
And what's the specialty
of the house here?
"Bun chin zou."
"Chin zou" means pig knuckles.
- Pig knuckle?
- Pig knuckles.
We know that's gonna be good.
You put up with the abuse
for this glorious,
steaming bowl of rice
noodles with spicy chilies,
a rich, hearty, porky broth
with pig's knuckle and snout.
It's the only item on the
menu, and it's good.
- You know taro?
- Yes. Ah.
So this is the stem
- of the taro plant.
- Uh-huh.
And to prepare this, you
have to be very careful
because if you
don't do it right,
- then you get itchy mouth.
- Toxic, right.
No, no, not toxic.
- You won't die from it but...
- Right.
It makes your mouth
really itchy, so...
Interesting.
♪
Mmm.
Wow, that's delicious.
When people talk about
Vietnam, they always say
about spring rolls or pho,
but I think this should be
in... in the mix.
- In the mix?
- Yeah, in... I'm easy.
Give me some spicy
noodles, some pork,
I'm happy every time.
Get out of here.
♪
Hello.
It's a maze of narrow
streets and alleyways
behind the old French cathedral.
♪
Vendors set up stools, and
it's happy hour in Hanoi.
♪
Every doorway, every window,
a little slice of life.
♪
A story all its own.
Lives lived, being lived,
caught for a second,
a moment, then gone.
In Vietnam sometime,
to be truly friend,
- to be friendly...
- Yeah.
We have to drink
until we a drunk.
Well, well, okay.
- Yeah.
-We must. We must.
Cheer for friendship.
Linh Dinh, my oldest
friend in Vietnam
from the very beginning.
Many happy memories, my friend.
We've been to Saigon,
Can Tho, Nha Trang.
He was my original minder
for Vietnam's Ministry
of Foreign Affairs.
We became, in spite of his
official responsibilities,
-fast friends.
- One, two, three.
- Welcome back.
- Cheers.
- Thank you.
Linh has brought me
to a great and proud
and uniquely Hanoi
tradition, Bia Hai.
Bia Hai refers to
the roadside joints
where locals gather to
consume keg-dispensed,
freshly brewed draft beer.
Oh, that's good.
It's not strong at
all, my friend.
Just, like, between
three to four percent.
Ah, so we need to drink a lot.
- Yeah.
Cheer for Hanoi beer.
♪
It was something
luxurious 30 years ago.
- Yeah.
- Right.
- And now it's for everyone.
- Yeah.
- It's not expensive.
- Right.
- Ten thousand dong.
- So that's...
- Forty cents.
- Forty, forty-five cents, yeah.
- Forty-five cents a beer?
- Yeah.
I'll have another.
I can afford that.
♪
The country's changed so much.
When I first came,
bicycles and motorbikes.
-Now, lot of cars.
- More cars.
Yeah, now look, money.
People are making
mo... business is good.
- Yeah.
- Right?
I mean, much, much,
much more tourism
- every year, yeah?
- Yes, yes.
People also enjoy life more.
♪
Search the globe, and you
will find no other place
that looks remotely like this.
♪
"Ha Long" means "where
the dragon descends
into the sea".
And legend says that this is
where a great dragon
charged, protecting Vietnam
from foreign invaders.
War is a constant theme
in Vietnamese mythology
and history.
The Chinese, the French, the
Japanese, the Americans,
the Cambodians,
again the Chinese.
♪
Ha Long Bay has become,
for better or worse,
one of Vietnam's most
visited destinations.
♪
Fortunately, this
time of year anyway,
you don't have to go too far
to lose yourself in the
past, find a quiet place
where you can still imagine
the great dragon's
tail thrashing and
churning and kicking up
these great karsts of rock.
♪
Chosen mode of transportation,
the "Emeraude,"
an old French-era steamer
refitted for more
current-day needs.
♪
A big freaking boat.
And it's all mine.
Along with friends
and crew, of course.
♪
I like this boat.
We're living a little
larger than last...
Last time the boat
was not this nice.
All the modern conveniences
but the charms of the past.
It fits perfectly with my
over-romantic delusions.
And in general,
it does not suck.
Hello, gentlemen.
- Hi, Tony.
- How you doing?
We've having some gin and tonic.
Gin and tonic, traditional
Vietnamese drink.
Well, not really,
but... all right.
This my first time trying this.
- Yeah?
- His first time.
How old are you anyway?
Wait a minute, you were
five years old last time
I was in Ha Long Bay.
-Yeah, just five. He 20 now.
-Wow.
Linh and I came here for
another show what feels like
a lifetime ago.
Back then, I got to
meet his son Minh,
who's apparently grown up.
These are pictures
of you and him.
- Whoa.
- Fifteen years ago, fourteen years ago.
Oh, my God.
Look at my hair.
♪
It's changed a little bit.
Like over eight million people
are coming to Ha Long Bay now?
Yeah, every year, tourists.
All of this is protected, right?
You can't do anything
on these rocks.
- No.
- No, no.
And how many of these
islands... is it 1,900
of these rocks out there?
One thousand nine
hundred and sixty-nine,
and this is a good
number, you know?
It's a lucky number?
- Six is for fortune.
- Right.
- And nine is for forever,
so fortune forever.
♪
A drink or two on the
top deck, check.
Now for the rest of
the day trying to do
as little as possible.
A nap, sunset, maybe
some more drinks,
and what about dinner?
- One for you.
- Oh, thank you, sir.
- Cheer, my friend.
- Cheers.
So we're eating some squid?
- Tons of squid.
-Tons of squid?
We try to get as many
tons as possible.
Cue the majesty of the squid.
At night this time of
year, the bright lights
of Ha Long Bay's fishing
boats are unmistakable.
They can only catch the
squid in the evening.
The light attract the squid
- so they can catch them.
- Right.
They say that because
of global warming,
all the fish are dying
but that the squid
and cuttlefish populations
are increasing,
so soon the whole sea will be
filled with plenty of squid.
We'll be eating it every day.
♪
Oh, yeah, those are
cute, little squid.
Oh, those are gonna be tender.
- Ooh.
- Mmm.
Oh, yeah, the tentacles
are the best.
To catch squid is
a very hard job.
- They work all the night.
- All the night.
- The light, it turn on all the night.
Right, and then sleep all day?
- Yeah.
- It's got to be hot out there, man,
- sleeping in the day.
- Yeah.
-Cheer for the day.
- Cheers for the day.
♪
A morning swim, a bowl of
spicy noodles, and a view,
perfect.
♪
How many in the family?
Six. Young couple and
their three kids
and then the grandma
is living with them.
The oldest kid is a girl,
and she was sent into the
shore with some relatives
to go to school -because
they have no schooling here.
-Right.
♪
Floating fishing villages
like this used to be found
in nearly every sheltered cove
or corner of Ha Long Bay.
But as Vietnam becomes a more
popular tourist destination,
authentic fishing villages
are starting to disappear.
The government has
been relocating
fishing families inland,
hoping to minimize
their ecological impact.
The people living on
floating villages,
they're just generally
nice and willing to open
their home to us and... -
They basically farm oysters?
-Yeah, yeah.
A lot of pearls for
sale in Ha Long Bay
and in Vietnam.
They come from places like this.
♪
It takes over a year
to grow each pearl,
and there's no guarantee
an oyster will even yield one.
♪
Water spinach, I think
that's called, right?
Water spinach.
♪
That's the most common
vegetable for Vietnamese
- in the summertime.
- Yes.
- Mm-hmm.
- Yeah.
♪
What kind of fish are these?
-Little fish?
-Yeah, Ha Long fish.
- Ha Long fish.
- Yeah.
♪
It's delicious, yeah.
- It's good fish.
- Mmm.
This is a pretty prime
piece of real estate,
and they've lived here how long?
For many generations.
This old grandma is 78 years
old, and she said that
her grandparents lived here
before this all become, like,
a big tourist attraction.
Is their situation
protected by the state?
They're allowed to
live here by special...
Because they've
been here so long?
Actually, the government
now is encouraging them
to move back to shore
because it's better
for their children's education.
To tell the truth, we would
like to move on land.
If the government did
offer us anything,
then we should take it.
But right now we would
need help to live ashore.
For someone like me
who isn't educated
and got skilled in the
kind of work on land...
I'm just used to working
on the ocean, fishing...
They said that they're happy
to move back because it's
better for their children,
but they've been living
here for many centuries,
and all they know
is just fishing.
Right.
♪
Just another day in paradise.
A tropical downpour in a
working class neighborhood
on the outskirts of Hanoi.
♪
The lady selling vegetables
and gum and cigarettes
taking a nap under a
piece of corrugated tin
has no idea what's
about to happen.
Turn around for me, sir.
Thank you.
♪
♪ Paid the cost to be the boss ♪
♪ Look at me ♪ You
know what you see
♪ You see a bad mutha
♪ Look at me ♪ You
know what you see
♪ You see a bad mutha -Mr.
President.
-Good to see you.
Good to see you.
Mr. President, how are
you liking Vietnam?
Love it.
Markets like these
I grew up with.
When I was a kid in Jakarta,
these were basically
the only markets available.
You know, you would buy
pretty much everything
in stalls like this.
Yeah, I wouldn't
mind going in there
and haggling and seeing
what I could find.
This country, when I
first arrived here,
it smelled like a place
that I would like.
Certain countries
just... pheromonically,
- they just smell good, and I know they're
- gonna be good.
Do you... do you kind
of smell that?
You know, there's certain
spices that you can smell
in certain countries
that you just don't
smell back home.
Now, you know, there are
some smells that aren't
as appealing as well, but
that's part of the mix.
- It is indeed.
- So, yeah.
♪
♪ Head for the turnaround
How you doing, guys?
How are you?
♪ Heading for the turnaround
I love you, Obama!
♪
There's something magical
about the smell.
The minute you touch down here,
it grabs you, captivates
you, and chances are,
it holds you forever.
I'm not the first
to feel this way.
There is no better place
to entertain the leader
of the free world,
in my opinion,
than one of these classic,
funky, family-run noodle shops
you find all over Hanoi.
Dinner and a beer cost
about six dollars.
I'm guessing the President
doesn't get a lot
of state dinners like this.
♪
How often do you get to
sneak out for a beer?
Very rarely.
First of all, I don't get
to sneak out, period.
But the... once in a while,
I'll take Michelle out
on a date night.
The problem is part of
enjoying a restaurant
is sitting with other patrons
and enjoying the
atmosphere, and too often
we end up getting shunted
into one of those private
rooms in the back.
Well, I'm glad I could help,
and to many more cold beers, Mr.
President.
I appreciate it, absolutely.
Mmm.
♪
All right, you're gonna
have to... I will walk you
through it.
You're gonna have to
walk me through this.
We're about to eat bun cha... ♪
And it is about as typical
and uniquely a Hanoi dish
as there is.
These beautiful
little pork patties,
some grilled pork belly.
Bun cha is served in a
broth of vinegar, sugar,
and the ubiquitous nuoc
mam, or Vietnamese
fermented fish sauce.
Chilies to taste.
I mean, if you have
an important state
function after, you
might not want
to go too heavy on it.
- You know what?
- I'm going with this thing.
You know, we're gonna
do what's appropriate.
- Vinegar.
- All right.
And then you just
hack off noodles,
and just drop them
into your bowl.
Yeah, it's not too
elegant, but I'm managing.
And you dip and
stir and get ready
for the awesomeness.
I'm ready.
Now, is it appropriate
to just pop
one of these whole
suckers in your mouth?
Or do you think that you
should be a little more...
Well, slurping is
totally acceptable
- in this part of the world.
- Oh, is it?
It takes some
skills, by the way,
to handle these
sticky, cold noodles.
But whatever your opinion
of the man, the President
has those skills... -Mmm.
- I got to say.
- This is killer.
- This is outstanding.
- That's so good to hear.
- It's really good.
And we share, apparently,
a sentimentality
about Asian street food and
Southeast Asia in general.
One of my favorite meals of
all time, there's an area
between Jakarta and Bandung,
another city in Indonesia
called Puncak, and it's
up through the mountains.
So you'd have these
roadside restaurants
overlooking the tea fields.
There'd be a river running
through the restaurant itself,
and there'd be these fish,
these carp that would be
running through, and
you'd pick the fish.
They'd grab it for you and
fry it up, and the skin
would be real crispy,
and they just served it
with a bed of rice, and it was
the simplest meal
possible, and nothing
tasted so good.
♪
Now, as a Chicagoan...
Trickier question
fraught with peril.
Is ketchup on a hot
dog ever acceptable?
No.
No, I re... I mean that.
That's one of those
things like...
Well, let me put it this way.
It's not acceptable
past the age of eight.
My daughter's eight, and
she put ketchup on eggs
the other day, and I... I
wi... I didn't know
what the good...
What good parenting
called for at this point.
- An intervention.
- I think so.
I think you just got to
say, "You know what?
That's not acceptable.
I'm sorry."
♪
We are at a point where we
seem to be turning inwards.
I mean, we're actually talking
about building a wall
around our country.
And yet you have been
reaching out to people
who don't necessarily
agree with us...
Gaza, Iran, Cuba.
- I mean, I just wish that more Americans
- had passports.
The extent of what you can
see how other people live
seems useful at worst and
incredibly pleasurable
and interesting at best.
It confirms the basic truth
that people everywhere
are pretty much the same,
the same hopes and dreams,
and when you come to
a place like Vietnam
and you see former American
Vietnam vets coming back,
when you see somebody like
a John Kerry or a John McCain,
two very different people
politically and temperamentally,
but who were able to
bond in their experience
of meeting with their
former adversaries
and you don't make peace
with your friends.
You make peace
with your enemies.
♪
As a father of a young girl,
is it all gonna be okay?
It's all gonna work out?
My daughter will be
able to come here
in five years, ten years?
She'll be able to have
a bowl of bun cha,
and the world will
be a better place?
Yeah.
I mean, I think progress
is not a straight line.
You know, there are
gonna be moments
at any given part of
the world where things
are terrible.
But having said all that...
I think things are
gonna work out.
- Thank you so much.
- Cheers.
Cheers.
[woman sings a cappella
in native language]
♪
The vast majority
of this country
don't remember the American War.
-They don't remember any war.
-No.
You used to be a tour guide?
-Yes.
- For how many years?
-Fifteen years.
- Fifteen years?
I know you have to bring
people over to the museum,
the American War museum,
what, every time, right?
Yup.
In your lifetime, is
there gonna be a time
when that's not gonna
have to be a stop?
It won't be necessary, it
won't even be important,
no one will remember?
Or should people
always remember?
I think it's good to
remember so we don't make
the same mistake, you know?
Some people choose to be
angry, to hold grudge.
But then some people
chose to let go
and... for the peace
inside themself.
That's up to the person.
And I think it's good that...
It's important that we
know about history.
And to make sure it's
never happen again.
I met a lot of war veterans,
and surprisingly,
a lot of them don't feel...
Don't have any anger
against their old enemies... ♪
And that's... that's amazing.
That's... that is amazing.
I learned so much from them.
♪
For Vietnamese, we
have so many legends.
But the majority of legends
related to our tradition
- of fighting against foreign invaders...
- Uh-hmm.
And to protect our country.
♪
Over the last 20
years of my life,
I've seen a lot of changes.
And we know that there's still
a lot of shortcoming...
♪
But everything needs time.
We need to be patient.
We can't rush because
we really don't want
another war.
General William Westmoreland,
who commanded US forces
here in the mid-'60s,
famously said,
"The Oriental doesn't put
the same high price on life
as does a Westerner.
Life is plentiful.
Life is cheap in the Orient."
♪
It was an extraordinarily
grotesque
and wrongheaded
observation from a guy
who, if nothing else, was
expected to understand
his enemy on the battlefield.
He could not, it turned
out, do even that.
♪
Maybe, I hope, we are a
little bit smarter now.
♪