♪
Who are those ugly white men?
They don't like friendly.
Who are those... anyway.
Some ugly Dutch guys it
looks like with guns.
I'm guessing particularly
friendly to the current power.
They look like they're going to
or coming from
oppressing a black man.
First order of business, man.
When I take my country back,
first order of business
is to take that... down.
Am I right or what?
I'm kind of amazed.
Tear that [ Muted ] down.
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la la
♪
>in July 2013, when I went to
South Africa, 95-year-old Nelson
Mandela was critically ill.
In the country he freed from
white minority rule was
already in mourning.
And already fearful of what the
future might be without him.
I pray that he... somebody
takes Baton from him.
I wish him a speedy recovery.
And come back to his people.
♪
So a good friend of mine, a
really great travel
writer, said something.
The more I travel
the less I know.
I feel that particularly
strongly in South Africa, a
place I came in a state
of near total ignorance.
Loaded with preconceptions.
For the first part of my life,
the South Africa I knew was not
a happy place or a good place.
It was a pariah state.
Outrageously divided
into black and white.
A throwback to attitudes we
thought we'd long
learned to reject.
♪
The nationalist government in
South Africa enacted
apartheid laws in 1938.
Who you could marry.
Where you lived.
Where you could walk, be
educated, everything decided by
racist laws backed by police,
army and secret services.
The institutionalized racial
discrimination was designed to
maintain white minority power
and economically suppress the
black and mixed race south
Africans who lived in
townships, mostly in poverty.
In 1923, the African national
congress was formed.
By 1961, it had been radicalized
by the influence of a young
Nelson Mandela, among others,
and formed an armed wing called
the spear of the nation.
Do you see Africans being
able to develop in the country
without being pushed out?
We have made it very clear in
our policy that South Africa is
a country of many races.
There is room for all
the various races.
In 1963, Mandela was charged
with sabotage and conspiracy and
sentenced to life
imprisonment on Robin island.
It would take another 27 years
of silence and injustice before
the inevitable would happen.
Do you believe in apartheid?
I believe according to god's
will that the white race
should be preserved.
South Africa's white minority
under international sanctions,
internal political pressure and
the decline of the communist
threat, Mandela was we
leased from prison in 1990.
In '94, he was elected president
of the new, free South Africa.
♪
There have been very few figures
in the entire history of the
world as revered or as
important as Nelson Mandela.
But the question is,
what happens next?
♪
Johannesburg or Joe
burg or Josie.
The largest city of
population in South Africa.
And the economic
powerhouse of the country.
Southwest of
Johannesburg, Soweto.
Originally an acronym for
southwestern townships.
Now the area is
considered a suburb.
[ Speaking in foreign language ]
In 2010, South Africa played
host to the world cup.
The blackjacks who played for
the opening celebration
are a Soweto based band.
They are also, not
surprisingly, soccer fans.
♪
We're here on game day.
A grudge match in a country
where soccer approaches
religion.
You can feel it in Soweto
or rather you can see it as
everywhere you look people show
their love for the local Orlando
pirates or Johannesburg
kaiser chiefs.
Mawilies inn.
The perfect place to talk about
a game, drink yourself silly
over the results of a game, or
just have a very fine
local style meal.
It is, however, a
little hard to find.
There are a lot of
places like this?
This used to be the garage
or the carport, right?
Yeah.
Definitely.
In what was once a garage
are now six tables.
A lawn turned lounge out back.
Closed on Sundays if
grandma's visiting.
These kinds of bars were born
during apartheid times when
black south Africans not allowed
to own businesses in white areas
adapted and improvised.
They did their own thing.
Created these little Mike crow,
under the official radar
restaurants known around
here as eat houses.
Back in the days,
obviously, it was illegal.
Right.
During apartheid.
So they will have meetings to
actually plan what
they're going to do.
Right.
This would be considered
a hotbed of sedition.
Exactly.
Now it's just a hot
bed of drinking.
Yeah.
Different kind of sedition.
The blokes have just finished
watching the game when
I join them for food.
Are these good times
in south Africa?
Bad times?
Transitional times?
1994 was the peak of the
good time in South Africa.
Then now with the other politics
and other parties fighting,
it's quite tense right now.
It's not like it was before
where everybody's... you
know, it's black and white.
Literally.
We're unified on this.
They're unified on that.
These days, the party that
freed the country from white
rule, the ANC, is not
universally loved anymore.
In recent years they've been
criticized for inaction,
corruption and cronyism.
And opposition parties
are gaining strength.
Anything that's maybe new to
us, I think we're trying
to navigate reality.
How do you deal with
so many opinions?
The party that you loved the
whole time, that brought about
this freedom, is
fumbling the ball.
So what do you do?
In democracy, you should act.
Smileys.
Fire roasted sheep’s head.
Lips shrivelled back in a joker
like riktus of deliciousness.
Chopped into tasty, tasty bits
and eaten with cold beer?
Yes, of course, yes.
Just needs a little
salt and pepper.
Good stuff.
That looks good.
It's pap.
What is it?
It's like maize.
It fills the role grits do
in the American southwest.
Rice in much of Asia.
It's tasty, relatively
nutritious and cheap filler.
It sops up gravy when you have
something like this
stewed beef real good.
That's a dumpling.
That's a dumpling?
Dumplings.
Important throughout
the Africa diaspora.
Made with flour and yeast.
A spongy, bread type tool
for mop it up sauce.
Stewed Greens, carrots,
beans and more gravy.
That's awesome.
Tell me about your band.
How long have you
guys been together?
About ten years now.
Whoa.
A long time.
Yeah.
Would you say you
were an indie band?
Is there an indie theme?
What I guess I'm getting
at, is there a...
I was getting there.
♪
In terms of south African
street culture, people are
really pushing the
boundaries now.
You didn't really
have when we started.
You look around.
It's like, man, like
demographic is crazy.
What do you mean by that?
It's not just racial,
but classes, you know.
People are being
pushed and pulled.
It's like an
aspirational culture.
What do you think that means?
The whole rainbow nation
notion was quite romantic and
ridiculous.
You know, like racism is
not on a piece of paper.
Just because we voted it out
doesn't mean people
stop being racist.
It's ridiculous in that sense.
But we've lived something
else for 20 years.
People want it.
It's no longer like a
coffee table idea.
[ Speaking in foreign language ]
This is Sanza Sandile.
Pioneer of sorts.
He's taken a traditional cook
shop space in the neighborhood
of Johannesburg and done
something different.
Yoville is a neighborhood where
just about everybody comes
from somewhere else.
I came here around ten
years ago from Soweto.
Up in Soweto. Then when
we heard about the bells
of change, we all ran to the
central part of the city.
With the end of apartheid and
South Africa became a
beacon and a refuge for millions
of Africans from all
over the continent.
Black south Africans fought hard
for their freedom
and their country.
As I understand a lot of them
are pretty pissed off about
we're just getting our [ Muted ]
Together and all these Congolese
and Nigerians are coming here.
Sanza has no formal
culinary training.
He's completely self-taught.
Picking up bits and
pieces when we can.
Often from the women
in the neighborhood.
You're plucking the best of
everybody in the culture.
Every day.
Every day I learn.
What are you eating?
From you from?
I've been taught by some men.
That's not how it's
cooked at home, you know?
Go to that auntie.
To the back of some dingy cab.
There's a small kitchen.
Look, there, it'll be nice.
Hey, auntie, you know, I'm
really keen on knowing how you
make your particular sauce.
They'll show you?
I pick up.
Then I rush back to the
shop and I try it out.
At his cook shop he mixes
recipes, ingredients, techniques
and traditions as he sees fit.
One reviewer described his style
as gastronomic smuggling.
Moving people across borders
with dishes that slightly
partake of elsewhere.
On today's menu it sha...
I made this for you.
This is egusi and beef.
Beef stewed with melon
and pumpkin SIDS.
There's futu.
The you biktous
cornmeal porridge.
Made from a texture more
crumbley than pap.
Good taste.
Oh, yeah.
Awesome.
Good food here.
Menu change every day?
You do a lot of great
food in a small space.
There were no seats.
His customers remain part of the
constantly unfolding
street theater of Yoville.
They mingle, talk, observe.
With food, I knew food
is a way to engage.
Got to put something in your
mouth to get your
ears open, you know.
♪
Across town, another
pioneer of sorts.
An urban settler in a very
different neighborhood.
This is Hillbrow.
A notoriously
dangerous district.
And this is DeeJay Lez.
When I came here, I always
dreamed of being a musician.
I see myself singing in front of
huge crowds, you know,
making money in the process.
That's what I dreamt about.
He spins records and promotes
acts and events in nightclubs.
We meet in his favorite spot.
Sympathy's restaurant.
What's good?
What do you like?
That looks good.
Is that fried chicken?
That's the fried chicken.
The place is heavy with the
smell of frying chicken,
stewing Greens.
Walk right up.
Place your order.
And be sure to get
some mill pap.
Heaped on a plate with beats and
coleslaw that's a
nice, heavy base.
Tell me about the neighborhood.
When I first came, it
was rough, my friend.
Before '92, it was like
white business district?
Residential district?
Back then, it used to be clean.
Used to be respected.
Once Hillbrow was an elite
whites only center of town.
But when things started to
change, so did Hillbrow.
Becoming one of the first gray
areas where whites
and blacks mixed.
Hillbrow became aspirational.
A symbol of everything black
Africans had long been denied.
But was now accessible.
People poured in
in large numbers.
Many of them squatters from
all over the continent.
People come here, they come
here with one intention.
Making a living.
Making money.
Started coming here.
White landlords and tenants
simply walked away
from their property.
The disenfranchised who moved in
legally, semilegally, illegally
or just squatting, an influx
of gangs and criminal
organizations, the area
soon slipped into anarchy.
There's a saying around here.
Okay?
This building's been hijacked.
Everything that could
go wrong, did.
People make a living
from different things.
Some hurt people
to make a living.
Some they sell their bodies.
Sometimes things aren't always
according to what you plan.
This is where I live.
This is where my life is.
I'll show you.
We talk down the street and
one of the many enterprises
doing business on corners and in
doorways around us becomes
alarmed at the sight of our
cameras.
Soon there's a mob of very
angry people coming our way.
We do not turn around our
cameras for obvious reasons.
These days things are
slowly, slowly improving.
But before, we wouldn't
walk this freely.
Now we are free.
There's actual law enforcement
going on in fits and
starts.
And that's making a difference.
Black owned legitimate
businesses have gained a real
foothold.
There are new revitalization
projects like farmer's
markets springing up.
Buildings are being reclaimed.
And people here hope that
Hillbrow is past the bad old
days.
There's no fear now.
You have to relax.
Nothing will happen to you.
>What's in a name?
If the name is Soweto, you best
believe it means plenty.
This is Madu.
For over a decade he's been in
what has at times been the very
difficult business
of driving a taxi.
You should probably know that
the word taxi in Soweto means
something a little different
than, say, New York.
How many taxis do
you have in Soweto?
This coming from a particular
passenger means Soweto.
Also this and this.
Johannesburg has an elaborate
system of hand signals
indicating desired
routes of travel.
You're looking at the hand
signals and say I'm not going
there, I'm not going there.
I'm looking at hand sayingals.
In 1994 Soweto came into
being as workers lodging.
A place to put black laborers
comfortably removed
from white society.
A ghetto.
By the 1950s it had become the
center of resistance
to white rule.
Synonymous with the struggle
against the whole
rotten racist system.
Now there is a definite carhe
to having lived in Soweto.
A very real pride back at being
in the center of things when it
was hard and dangerous
to have an opinion.
Nelson Mandela lived here.
Desmond tutu.
When you're of certain age and
you say you were born and bred
in Soweto, it means something.
Do mostly people own
their homes or rent?
Mostly people own their homes.
Things start to get
a little better.
Can you build up?
You can build up.
Look at the streets here and
you see what that
kind of pride does.
It may not be a rich area,
but it's immaculate.
Squared away.
An emerging middle class coming
up, rather than
fleeing to elsewhere.
You know where
you're going, right?
Yeah.
I know where I'm going.
Next exit?
Smoky delicious meat over flame.
Under the overpass, all sorts of
mystery meats for sale.
The taxi man's lunch.
We order some brisket,
some sausage, some heart.
Beautiful thing.
Meat, a cutting board, a knife.
You chose well.
These guys are good.
♪
Here, spread over thousands
of square feet, the remnants
of white colonial rule.
What's left from the descendants
of Bible thumping Dutch settlers
who came here to farm, to ranch,
to build their own world
on top of an existing one.
They came in the 1600s.
If nothing else can be said
about them, they
were a tough bunch.
In the 1800s the British came.
Diamonds were discovered.
Greed heads jockeyed for power.
There was war, and an ugly one.
In the end there was an
uneasy shares of power.
The boars been known
as Afrikaners.
In the 20th century racist
Afrikaners ideology grew.
Ar par tide was enacted.
White domination because the
rule for almost 100 years.
But look.
Meat.
You want to see an ex-pat south
African weep, wave some
of this under their nose.
It's like a Mussolini
themed restaurant?
Yeah.
That's it.
Neofascist butchery.
In the good old days.
Doesn't look like any
butcher I've been into.
Our north of northwest by
Johannesburg is Pretoria.
Still the administrative
center of South Africa.
Once the heart of apartheid.
Here you can find a father/son
butchery, restaurant
and themed museum.
I just don't know how I
feel about this place.
It doesn't fit in with my white
liberal guilt sensibility.
It just wouldn't be accepted.
Couldn't exist.
As any south African butcher
would, they sprinkle salt,
brown sugar, more vinegar.
Pack in layers, repeat.
After 24 hours remove and
hang to air dry for a week.
Voila.
A tasty jerky treat we
can all get behind.
Chef Andrea Burgener, south
African by birth, English and
German by background, with
usually be found in the trenches
of her Joburg restaurant,
the leopard.
She's known for her playful
menus but loathes culinary
fashion.
She strives for a locally
grounded cuisine.
Today, she's my guide
through this twilight zone.
♪
It's weird here.
And though I'm told the place
usually reflects the changing
demographic of modern south
Africa, today, not so much.
The customers may or may not
have feelings about the
Afrikaner memorabilia.
Really they just come for meat.
Choose t-bone, rum steak.
Spicy sausage made
from beef and pork.
Our secret ingredient
is monkey gland sauce.
Every steak house has
monkey gland sauce.
It's barbecue sauce.
They cook it up along with
some pap and fries and presto.
A colon clogging pile of
meat in the ruins of empire.
Yeah.
I mean, meat is a
very big thing.
There's enough of it, I think.
Good lord.
I can swim in it.
Tastes like oppression.
After this show airs, I'm
going to get a huge amount of
mail says why didn't
you go to Capetown?
Great modern restaurants.
Cutting edge chefs.
Is it all right I
missed all that?
I feel like those particular
restaurants in Capetown are not
really representative of what
most people in this
country are eating.
I think a lot of our most basic
stuff is really what we do best.
This food is absolutely got
no interest in fashion.
It's never going to change.
There'll still be the
monkey gland sauce.
You think the white chefs
here understand the greatest
advantage they have is that this
enormous pan African larder of
ingredients and flavors?
No.
If you're a whitey in the city
you're probably going to eat the
worst food of anyone in
the city, quite honestly.
In every country, obviously
food is political.
It always feels like it's a
bit more political here.
That there are these layers of
things that you couldn't have.
Like restaurants.
I go to restaurants.
I think to myself, wow, this
many years ago, I couldn't have
come here with this person.
They were not allowed
to sit in here.
And I remember very
clearly being around 8.
The cafe owner would regularly
not pay the customer who
was black with change.
He would pay him
with bubble gum.
And the guy somehow,
he couldn't argue.
If you were a black guy, you got
your change in bubble gum.
I was 8 years old feeling like,
oh, my god, it was so terrible.
But you couldn't say anything.
Because that would
have been worse.
It represented such badness.
It just seems mad.
>This is an elan.
The largest antelope
in the world.
It is also, unluckily
for him, delicious.
[ Gunshots ]
Got him.
I think that was very good.
It's a little sad.
You know what?
That is such good meat.
That's really what we do.
Though this one weighs in
around a ton, rest assured,
every bite, every
scrap, will be eaten.
Some of that, tonight at dinner.
Chef Andrea Burgener, Dionne, a
local hunting expert, and myself
join Prospero Bailey
on his game farm.
His dad was the legendary
publisher of the slyly
subversive magazine.
A black oriented investigative
magazine slickly disguised
as glossy pop culture.
Prospera's farm is mere 20
miles from Johannesburg.
You see the city there?
Yeah.
To have all this in
sight of the city.
Near his farm and hidden
within the city's shadow is
what's known as the
cradle of humankind.
A UNESCO world heritage site.
An incredible look back at where
we, the human animal, came from.
It's a classic little sink hole.
There are loads of these.
This is what this area is.
The cradle.
It's called a cradle.
Now a world heritage site.
Because 60% of all the evidence
for human evolution comes
out of the valley.
It's from caves like this
that keep the record.
That geology just conspires
to preserve fossils.
They're very, very rare things.
But they're found more here in
the last ten years than
they're found anywhere.
So you're home.
This is where you started.
This is my ancestral homeland?
This is your ancestral homeland.
♪
That sound makes me happy.
What does that sound
remind you of, guys?
What does that evoke
for you, that sound?
Prime evil.
Your enemy's genitals
frying in hot oil?
Nothing?
I get to work on the heart.
Something I strongly
suspect will be delicious.
And I'm right.
Andrea works her
magic on the liver.
Dredged in flour and sauteed.
This loin seared and
glazed with booze.
There's elan papricash.
A riff on the Hungarian stew
with paprika, peppers,
onion, tomatoes and cream.
As the sunsets over the belt,
Johannesburg lights blinking
in the distance, a feast.
Meat on the plate.
Blood on my pants.
Life is good.
I've been very, very, very
confused by my visit here.
You've got basically
a goulash here.
The bread someone referred
to as Portuguese?
Yep.
Portuguese but it's from Madera.
That bread.
Flat bread.
South Africa depending on who
I talk to is a completely
different construct.
So some people someone who comes
from somewhere else in Africa
and brings good stuff with them.
Other people Malaysia, east
Indyes, Dutch, English
influence.
There were so many different
colonials colonialists.
One at this table is originally
African and does that
have a meaning?
This wood is pine.
I arrived in this country
spectacularly ignorant.
I will leave
>Ramadan.
At this hour, all
over Johannesburg.
Members of South Africa's
sizable Muslim community
observe.
The religion of Islam as well as
many of South Africa's most
beloved and most delicious
dishes and ingredients like
sambal, cutny and bunny chow
come from Malaysia,
Indonesia, India.
During apartheid many south
Africans would have been
referred to as colored.
Colored didn't mean black.
It meant everybody else
who wasn't exactly white.
Asians and mixed race.
It's garlic, ginger
and chil chiles.
In the observatory
neighborhood of Johannesburg,
the Rasdian family prepares for
the meal at sundown when
fasting for Ramadan is broken.
Joey is a standup comedian, an
actor of cape Malay background.
This dish, panang curry
with beef and eggs.
Joey's wife, Cindy,
prepares a chicken pie.
Son, Hakeem, makes the
traditional Ramadan shake.
Daughter, Laya.
♪
Everything smells terrific.
That's soup.
It's nicer to have soup after
you've not eaten the whole day.
It's light and nourishing and
filling and all of
those good things.
There's also cheese
and beef yes, I was.
So how are things?
It depends on what you
are speaking about.
Society operates the
way society should.
But on the other hand, many
ways this is a new country.
It is.
It's 19 years old.
I think the Africans from the
other countries see South
Africa as a place of hope.
Because if there's a lot here,
then there are a lot of
opportunities, lots of
people might get from here.
Africans would corm from far to
find a little bit
of something here.
So how do you find
south Africa so far?
I'm very comfortable here.
I like a country where people
have a sense of humor.
There's a lot of ball
busting doing on here.
All the time.
From the top to the bottom.
20 years from you, what's
it going to be like?
The ones that's giving our
current president lots of hell.
The ones born in
the new democracy.
Or just before the
first election.
Right.
The born frees are like, look
here, we went to school.
This is right and this is wrong.
What you're doing is wrong.
But we're at a struggle.
I don't care.
Thank you for the struggle.
I want five bars on my 3g, I
want Wi-Fi, and it
better be high speed.
Absolute.
I don't think the current
politicians foresaw that.
Foresaw the born frees
not supporting them.
There's a critical mass of
young people that wants to
change South Africa
in a positive way.
How they do it or how they go
about it, I don't know
the answer to that.
Neither do they know
But their intentions is clear.
>No more hipster jokes.
It's low hanging fruit.
And one can no longer argue
against the steady creek of
their foodie sensibilities.
Cheeses, yes, right over there.
Hand made, yes.
There.
Thin crust pizza, a very
respectable piayya, yes, yes,
and yes.
It's official.
They're here and they
aren't going anywhere.
I like the idea of a burger for
breakfast or is there something
perverse about that.
Throw in a crowd of much more
diverse and hungry people, and
you might think
you're in Brooklyn.
Surely, this is not a bad thing.
This is neighbor goods
market in Johannesburg.
My dining companion features
writer Percy Mumbando says
we should hold out for this.
One with lots of cheese.
Flattened ground beef
sered over flames.
Cook the food right.
Add mozzarella cheese, fold
it up, pick your condiments.
Ka badge, tomato, onion,
lettuce, hot peppers.
Up to the roof with
a view and eat.
Spicy.
Good.
I guess I want to talk
about Nelson Mandela.
Because what I was not aware of
at all was the degree to which
he was personally responsible
for really the nuts and bolts of
the transition from white
rule to majority rule.
Now he's very ill.
Reporter:
Yeah, yeah.
What happens after Mandela?
We go on.
And I think through god
we have him as a symbol.
I think Mandela
represents our nation.
The test we use to
check the way forth.
All the things that could
have gone terribly wrong, it's a
remarkable thing
how well it went.
Between 1990 and 1994, tough
times, you know, into
the city fighting.
Black-on-black violence.
Black-on-white violence.
But we transcended that coming
together regardless of
the unresolved issues.
What extent are
things getting mixed?
We like to think we live in a
rainbow nation, but in fact, in
the states like to a great
extent in different
neighborhoods.
In some ways it looks to me
outside looking in a little more
gracefully mixed up than
we've managed in the states.
Here you've got black, white,
colored, all sorts
of people here.
Also once you have the knowledge
that the economic disparities
are managing to keep
us divided as well.
I think what we need to do is
unpack what we mean by rainbow.
I think being diverse also means
that there'll be
moments of discord.
And you think things will
continue to improve?
Yeah.
I think we've seen our worst.
And that's not to say that we're
getting it right all the time.
But it's an experiment you need
to find as you go along.
That's really the
south African story.
The dream is there.
We all agree that the
visions are there.
But these are not
bigger than our hopes.
What did I know about south
Africa before I game here?
Exactly nothing,
as it turns out.
But I think based on what I've
seen, that if the world
can get it right here.
A country with a past like south
Africa's, if they can figure out
how to make it work
here for everybody.
Absorb all the people flooding
in from all over Africa,
continue to make Mandela's dream
a reality, maybe there's
hope for the rest of us.