Prosperity is productivity
not just hard work.
You can be very hardworking
and still be broke
if you are not productive.
♪
Your life condition today
is an outcome of choices
and decisions made in time past.
Good choices, bad choices,
easier choices,
or no choices at all.
♪
♪ I took a walk
♪ Through this beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪
♪ Found something good
in this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪
♪ Sha la la la la
♪ Sha la la la la la
♪ Sha la la la la la la
Lagos, Nigeria's megacity.
One of the most dynamic,
unrestrained,
and energetic expressions of
free market capitalism
and do-it-yourself
entrepreneurship
on the planet.
When you have a place
of 20 million people,
they have to eat,
they have to wear clothes,
they have to do
all sorts of things.
I mean, Lagos is a testament
to the resilience
and to the ingenuity
of the Nigerian spirit.
♪
Buy, sell, trade,
hustle, and claw,
make your own way
any way you can.
Nobody does any one job
in this country.
I mean, they say you
have to have three hustles.
Yes. You see people
making watches from scraps.
There are people who make shoes.
I'm wearing something
that's made by a Nigerian.
♪
I provide my own water.
I provide my own power,
because I have a generator.
I have a convertor.
There's an energy in Lagos,
the hustle and the bustle.
♪
♪ Nigeria,
here's you're boy... ♪
With the ridiculously
overburdened infrastructure
and a history of
egregiously bent leadership,
they long ago learned that
ain't nobody gonna help you
in this world.
Pick up a broom, a hammer,
buy a taxi or a truck,
build a bank
or a billion-dollar company
and get to work.
♪
I will push myself.
I will do what I need to do.
I'll do whatever it takes
to take care of myself
and my family.
♪
♪ We can't know our future
♪ Which is just why we
got to live it ♪
♪ The way life goes
♪ What?
It's like a... ♪
♪ Deep and sudden
Am I on Victoria Island
right now?
- Yes.
- So this is the promised land.
This is Manhattan.
♪
Victoria Island,
the garden of dreams.
Where the winners work
and play.
There's money in Nigeria,
lots of it,
mostly from oil, agriculture,
and services like banking.
Lagos alone is
the fifth largest economy
in Africa.
9,000 millionaires
and billionaires,
many of Africa's richest people,
live here.
♪
50 years ago there were
300,000 people in Lagos.
There are now...
- Almost 20 million.
- Around 20 million.
- Yeah.
- There's a whole lot of people
leaving wherever they were...
Yeah.
Coming to the big city,
looking to get a job,
looking to make it big.
Absolutely.
The smartest,
the fastest, the best,
the brightest make it over here.
Yeah.
It's that place, it'll make
you or it'll break you,
sink or swim.
Shina Peller owns Quilox,
one of Africa's
most exclusive nightclubs.
I built the nightclub by myself,
my construction company.
Banky Wellington is
an artist and businessman.
I'm a record label owner.
I'm an actor.
I'm a director.
I do videos and TV commercials.
I'm in advertising.
I'm in real estate.
I'm training to be a chef.
Why work so hard? I mean,
you don't have to hustle.
Your life is good.
Business is good.
Why are you doing
so many things?
That is just something that is
common in Nigeria, you know.
There's the eternal
Nigerian optimism
that tomorrow is going to be
better than today.
Yeah, where does that come from?
Why are Nigerians so...
So optimistic?
I think that it's
born out of necessity.
You know, you're either
going to make it
or you're gonna be screwed.
You almost don't have a choice.
You need to try
everything possible.
I must make it.
I must be successful.
♪
Right over there,
Victoria Island.
That's the Nigerian dream,
right?
If I just hustle enough,
if I figure out a way,
I have a master plan,
God's help,
I'm gonna end up over there.
It's close.
It's really close.
How do you get
from here to there?
It's impossible.
The government
and the people in power
make poor people
perpetually poor.
♪
This is the other Lagos, Makoko,
a city within a city.
This community has been
in existence for over 100 years.
This used to be
a little fishing village.
- Yeah.
- People started showing up,
no plan, build your own house.
The community had been built,
not based on government plan.
It is an ingenuity
of the people.
How many people live here?
- The whole waterways...
- The whole waterway.
The whole waterways
would be about 100,000 people.
Mm-hmm.
♪
It's a fully functioning
community.
I've seen barbershops...
restaurants, groceries, hotels.
Hospitals, private schools.
Self-made, self-run,
self-policing,
independent of everything.
It exists because it has to.
I mean, there's electricity,
there's water.
All of this, you provide, yes?
Yes.
Yeah, we provide.
Udato Abganigi is a musician
and activist.
This community started
from nothing.
Now it's booming,
and the government is
coming to seize it.
They... they want to
get you out, right?
- Yes.
- They like to build hotels.
Yes.
Yami Maisu, the son
of a neighborhood leader.
But they've been forced to stop.
No, it's not...
They're not stopping.
- They're never stopping.
- We've been...
We've been able to halt them.
Two, three weeks ago there was
another community
on the other side of Lagos...
On the island.
On the island,
was also demolished.
They just come and demolish.
The people living here,
their source of livelihood...
The bans on fishing,
they are fisher people.
So if you take them
to the mainland,
it's like taking a fish
out of water.
Out of water, cant survive.
They can't survive.
Can't survive.
- What have we got here?
- It is called moyu.
- Moyu.
- We eat this with
You eat this with...
Mmhmm.
- We call this ebà.
- All right.
And here we've got garri.
That looks good.
♪
Mmm.
Good. Delicious.
♪
All the children I see...
Yeah.
- Go to school?
- Mm-hmm.
What will they do?
Will they stay here
and take up the family business
or are they gonna move on?
Well, some will grow up to
become accountants,
they'll become professionals.
But what... what would...
What would a lawyer do,
what would an accountant do
when there is no food?
Most of the fishes that have
been sold
to the rich men in government
were actually taken from here.
From this village.
- Right.
- We need people
that do fishing, do family.
But you're gonna need lawyers.
- That...
- You're gonna need...
You're gonna need...
Everybody needs everybody.
♪
Ah.
To do well in business,
don't just be religious,
be hardworking,
and be full of ideas.
You need all these
to birth a real miracle.
♪
Where are we?
Computer Village.
Yes, this is
This is Computer Village.
It's your tech hub.
They sell everything here.
Mobile phones, computers,
any kind of digital equipment
you're looking for,
this is where to find it.
It's said to be
a $2 billion-dollar market.
Public money is
generated in Lagos
not so much by oil,
but by the free market,
a wild west free-for-all
of private enterprise.
It grew organically,
not by government intervention.
- It just happened.
Everything is cramped into
this small ecosystem.
You have one small store,
somebody selling mobile phones
right and left,
and in front of him
you have another guy
whose selling applications
for the phones,
a repair guy, he is right there,
and it works.
That's the amazing thing
about it.
Tunji Andrews is
a journalist, radio host,
and an expert on
the Nigerian economy.
The guys who fascinate me
are these kids sitting there
with phones all opened up.
Like, if I want my iPhone
repaired in New York,
I have to go to the Apple Store.
I got to wait on line.
I got to say good-bye
to my phone for a while.
But here, they know how to
take apart my iPhone,
fix it,
and put it back together.
This is how the Computer
Village ecosystem works, right.
A young boy trying to make
a better life for himself
finds his way to Lagos,
then one of his brothers
is working here,
and then he starts to learn how
to repair mobile phones, right?
Right.
And sometimes I tend to think
they deal with trial and error.
- Right.
- So your phone might be
just a practice...
A practice-
- Yeah, but...
- They get there eventually.
And that's the success story
of almost all the people
you see here.
Most of them came into this
particular market with nothing.
Okay, this is Stella's Kitchen.
Oh, yeah.
Well, let's get some food.
Exactly.
Pounded yam is the ubiquitous
starch of Nigerian cuisine.
♪
Here it's served with
egusi soup...
♪
A stew of goat meat,
melon seeds,
fish stock, and chilies.
♪
This is very, very good.
So I've heard this market
described as
the perfect market.
Now, what does that mean?
Right here you can find,
on the same street,
about 20 people doing
exactly the same thing.
So you go to the first guy
and you say, "Hey",
I want you to
repair my phone."
And he says, "Okay, I could do
it for you at 5,000 naira."
Now, all you have to do is
look across the road
and find somebody who could do
exactly the same thing,
and he knows that, right?
So he starts to think
to himself,
I better give him the best price
I can possibly give him...
- Right.
- So that I can get his market.
Completely unregulated
as far as prices.
Completely unregulated.
So it's really the free market
at its purest.
Exactly.
Lagos has been able to grow
and expand its borders
and that comes from the sweat
of people on the street.
- Right.
- Once government interferes
in private activity,
more often than not,
they make it more complex
and they move it
towards extinction.
♪
A lot of people are
outside of tax nets...
- Right.
- So the state government
has to be very genius
in trying to get taxes.
Right.
Flex up!
Who really runs the streets?
The de facto front line
of law and order
are area boys.
The government tries to get
people on the street...
like the foot soldiers.
An area boys crew
levels street taxes on,
well, everything...
reporting to their regional
boss, a king of boys.
Taxis, buses,
any target of opportunity
pays.
You don't depend on
government, fine,
but you're running
your own business.
- Right.
- So you pay a bribe
because that's the only way
to get things done.
Every person seems to be
tainted a little.
Police, politicians,
business leaders,
everybody gets
their piece of the action.
It's a daily fact of life
in Lagos.
This is a big, oil-rich country.
Why doesn't it look like Dubai?
Well, I hate to be on this show
and talk Nigeria down,
you know what it is,
because you hear all
these things all the time.
So, yes, there is corruption.
It is about corruption.
It's about the fact
that the resources
that are supposed to
be used for people
aren't being used for people.
Kadaria Ahmed is
a progressive journalist,
editor, and TV host
who moderates
the presidential debates.
Years of military rule
meant that people
were brutalized.
There was a fight against
thinking.
There was an anti-intellectual
movement...
- Absolutely.
- Where you were
punished for...
Shamed.
- Shamed for reading...
- Yes.
For having an education,
for aspiring to those things.
Yeah, you saw
a decline in education
that continued for 30 years.
The biggest obstacle
in this country
is the political class.
Because what we've had,
you know, in Nigeria is
if you lose elections,
you then jump to the other party
and you win elections,
and then if you lose,
you go back to this other party.
- Right.
- So it's the same people.
They're going to fight
tooth and nail
to stay in office
and to keep the system
the way it is.
♪
Pepper soup
is the food of the night
in dark places.
It burns,
it burns real good.
Delicious.
This is a very IT savvy country.
Nigerian Internet scammers
are world-renowned.
They are a tiny minority,
I must tell you.
It may not be
a legitimate enterprise,
but you've got some very smart,
hardworking people.
They're very talented.
Imagine if they were
all well-educated,
if they had access to finance.
I believe if
you're a black person,
whether you're African
or you're African-American,
you're never going to
get any respect
unless there's a successful
black nation.
♪
It is unwise
to hold other people,
your employer,
or even the government
accountable for your success.
That is the only way people
are going to respect you.
You must do it...
Yourself.
♪
Queen Elizabeth
came to Nigeria in 1959.
The 33 million people
of England's most prosperous
African colony
were ready for independence.
♪
A friend of mine sends me
a text, and it says,
"Are you aware of
Nigerian psych rock
of the '70s?"
Yes.
There was a war in the late '60s
and that caused
a whole shift in the sound,
because before the war
was high life.
♪
And after the war, it was rock
and all sorts of sounds.
♪
This is mind-blowing,
like, amazing stuff.
This was...
This was a game changer.
♪
It's as if everybody took acid
at the same time.
It was less the acid
and more, let's just freak out.
♪
These new sounds, mutations
on funk, jazz, and rock,
marked an explosive change
in Nigerian culture.
♪
How'd it do when it came out?
It was wildfire.
It was a hit.
Really?
It was a massive hit.
Kemi Castro is a collector
and aficionado.
♪
This is really where
it started from.
- Uh-huh.
- Blo.
They had a very trippy song,
which I'll play for you.
Yeah, let's hear it.
♪
This is... freaky.
That shift in music
had to do a lot with the war.
♪
Nigeria's rebel eastern state,
the Republic of Biafra,
declared its independence.
♪
That music was needed to
translate the darkness.
Soldiers of
the breakaway province
suffered heavy casualties
and ultimate defeat.
A thousand Biafrans a day
died of starvation.
The music was a defiant
middle finger to war...
to corruption,
and repressive military rule.
You know how military dictators
try and control everything.
But of all the music
of the time,
nothing and nobody took it
directly to the people
in such explicitly
confrontational terms
as Afrobeat and its architect,
Fela Kuti.
The government were
giving Fela a hard time
because he was protesting
by name...
- Yeah.
- Specific things.
I mean, they identified him
as a existential threat,
and he was.
People would show up
at the Shrine.
- Exactly.
- Like, what's he gonna say?
What's he mad about today?
Fela was an African superstar,
a loud, persistent, and
unwavering voice of opposition
and resistance.
♪ Zombie no go, go
unless you tell him to go ♪
♪ Zombie
♪ Zombie no go stop
unless you tell him to stop ♪
People protested
but they didn't name names.
- Right.
- But Fela would name names
and... and say, you know,
you're a... thief.
♪
♪ Uh-huh
♪ Quick march slow march ♪
♪ Left turn right turn
♪ About turn double up
♪ Salute open your hat
♪ Stand at ease fall in
♪ Fall out fall down get ready ♪
For one decade, Fela's voice
was the only voice here
opposing the dictators.
And he paid a very high price.
His house was burned.
He was stopped from playing.
Fela died in 1997 of AIDS
after a social life that could
be best described
as complicated.
He married 27 wives
in one day, for instance,
but he left behind an enormous
legacy and a family,
including two internationally
celebrated musicians
in their own right,
Femi and Seun Kuti.
♪
Because of Fela,
we are able to voice
our opinions today.
If things are not right,
you can't just gloss over it.
There is no reason why
this country
cannot be ten times better.
Daughter Yeni runs this place,
the New Afrika Shrine...
We have more money,
we have more oil,
but we have bad leaders.
Both a musical venue
and political pulpit
with a vital position at the
epicenter of Nigerian music.
♪
So you drink beer.
If Anthony is drinking beer,
I'm drinking beer, too.
How can you say
because he's drinking beer,
you're drinking beer?
- I'm a fan.
- Of him drinking beer?
No, of him.
No, I'm a fan of beer, too,
but you know, he's drinking
beer, I'm drinking beer.
You grew up at
your dad's compound,
and I know at one point,
he wanted you to become
an area boy.
He thought that
that would be good street cred.
That's to put it kind of mild.
He just wanted me to be...
like, from the streets.
We've been running into
area boys constantly
through this week,
and I kinda want to know
how the structure works, like...
If you wanted to go for
elections, for instance,
you needed... you'll need to see
all the area boys.
You'll have to give
a lot of money
for him to get all his
gang members to vote for you.
And if you do a good job
in dealing with this,
you probably would win.
That's not quite democracy,
though, is it?
No, it's not.
Nigeria is not really,
you know, a democratic state.
♪
♪ Struggle music
♪ Struggle sounds
♪ Struggle people
♪ Struggling now
♪ Struggle music
struggle sounds ♪
♪ Struggle people struggle now
♪ Struggle music
struggle sounds ♪
♪
What is going on
in Africa today for me,
I think, is a perverse
kind of hopelessness,
working for a system
that is oppressing you,
and you know they're oppressing
you but you've given up that
there's nothing
I can do about it.
I mean, is that what you see?
Because honestly...
Yeah.
I've never been in a country
where everybody was
working so hard at something.
- They're hustling.
Look, I've been to the DRC,
to Goma and Kisangani, and those
were not hopeful places.
Yeah, but... but Nigeria
is the same way as DRC
and the North are because we
have the Boko Haram insurgency.
People are being killed, but
nobody wants to talk about it.
Nobody wants to act as if it's
as serious as...
Because Nigeria, we play...
We play the game.
We are the kings of the game.
We were so proud
when Nigeria arrived in Kenya
for the Africa Summit
because we brought the most
amount of private jets.
You understand?
This is their mentality.
They are all elitists, you know.
They have yards, you know,
in the country
where 90% live on...
Live in poverty.
It's self-esteem.
- Self-esteem?
- Yes.
- There's something to that.
- No, I don't think
that self-esteem is about
what you can buy.
Excuse me,
that's not what I said.
As much as Nigeria is bad,
there is...
hope.
♪ On the weapon
of the future ♪
When I grew up, we were like...
We couldn't sit here like this.
The police would come here
and beat everybody up.
A generation will come where
they will say enough is enough.
Let's take back our lives.
Femi Kuti for President.
Don't listen to him.
FKFP, Niger resistance.
♪ Drop the sound on the weapon
of the future ♪
♪
♪ Drop the sound on the weapon
of the future ♪
♪
It is the melody
of the angels of death.
Do not be afraid.
♪
The Hausa are the largest
tribal group in Nigeria.
Known originally as cattlemen,
they have become powerful
politically as well.
♪
This is Dambe boxing,
a very old and very brutal
fighting art
deeply ingrained
in Hausa traditions,
particularly among
the butcher class.
It is a way for tough young men
to earn a few bucks...
♪
We are African men!
Prove themselves,
and break up the grim routine
of their daily lives.
♪
All Hausa versus Hausa.
Yeah, Hausa versus Hausa.
♪
You hit with one hand.
Yeah, and the other one
is to block.
♪
Ooh!
Oh!
♪
Thank you.
Interreligious
and intertribal violence
has been a fact of life
for years in Nigeria.
There are over 300 tribes
and tens of thousands have died
during such conflicts.
In Lagos, some are trying to
rewrite that narrative.
The neighborhood of Agege is a
melting pot
of different tribes
and religious groups.
This was originally
a Yoruba area, yes?
Yes, yes.
But the Hausa people
have been living here
for a very, very long time
cooperating...
Yes, for a long time.
54 years ago.
The intermarriages
in between us and them,
so that is what we... there
are a lot of understanding.
♪
Masa, rice cakes made from
Nigerian sticky rice,
sugar, and potash,
a mineral-rich salt.
This is fura.
It's made from millet and milk.
It's more like a yogurt,
slightly sour.
- Yes.
- Oh, that's great.
This is one of
the surprising foods
that's also made of beans.
- This is all beans?
- Yes.
Danwake, high-protein
bean-flour dumplings
served with tomatoes, onions,
and a peppery sauce.
Mm, delicious.
Moringa.
And Moringa salad,
made from the leaves
of the zogale tree
and said to have
medicinal properties.
Kuli kuli powder is
a garnish or condiment
made from ground peanuts.
What do you see the future
of this area
and your people?
Anything relies on education.
We promote both western
and Arabic knowledge.
The whole Africa,
even the whole world,
is represented in Lagos,
so we have to work together.
The prophet of Islam,
Muhammad...
Sallallahu Alayhi Wa Sallam.
He lived with crystals
and jewels peacefully
without any problem.
We believe if there is no peace,
there will be no progress.
You cannot go to mosque,
you cannot go to church,
you cannot got to school,
you cannot go to wake.
We love Lagos.
We love peace.
And we pray to almighty Allah
to continue living in peace.
God bless Lagos.
God bless Nigeria.
♪
Good cooking takes time.
As more and more
Lagosian men and women
enter the workforce,
fewer and fewer
cook the old way,
long low and slow preparations
that can take hours.
♪
The Lagos upbeat style
makes it impossible for you to
cook everything at home,
so you go, you buy it
from the streets.
♪
So who blogs about food here?
- We all do.
- We all blog about it.
- All of you.
- Yeah.
Ateem, her mom, Iku,
and friend, Oz,
are all hard workers,
holding down multiple jobs
between them,
but they hang on to
their fierce love of food
and cooking.
Who are your readers?
- Primarily Nigerians.
- Homesick Nigerians also,
- I would think, in the states.
- Yes.
Particularly homesick.
But then people that are
married to Nigerians
that want to learn the cuisine.
Ahh.
These days,
one often eats quickly
at a place like this,
Yakoyo, serving traditional
Nigerian dishes
made the way
they should be made.
This is called ewedu.
It's jute leaf.
Ewedu is a soup from
the Yoruba tribe,
crayfish, chilies,
locust beans, and jute leaves.
Mm. This is good.
Have you had jollof rice?
It's rice cooked with...
- Tomato sauce.
- Spiced tomato sauce.
- Yeah.
- It's almost like
Spanish red rice.
♪
Jollof rice,
a staple across West Africa.
Country of origin?
Don't get into that issue.
It's contentious.
All I can tell you is
it's delicious.
Who runs these businesses?
You walk in and you see and
old lady sitting by the corner?
- Yeah.
- Her eyes are darting.
- You know, she's checking.
She's counting tables, you know.
Has the girl brought
back my money?
- Yeah.
- So she sits there
to control her money.
In the back, you see a guy
cooking big batches to refill.
Yeah.
♪
Goat meat, okay.
This is pounded yam.
Of course.
This I've seen.
And this is amala.
Pound it and cook it
kind of like this.
No.
This is yam raw, sliced,
ground into a flour...
Yes.
- And then cooked into a meal.
- Yeah.
- Kind of like grits.
- Yes, yes.
♪
It's about what you want,
how you want to combine it.
Thank you.
You don't... you don't tilt your
glass when you're pouring there?
I do, I'm just lazy.
Man, you guys are harsh.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no!
I'm gonna be reading
about myself on your blog.
He's an animal at the table.
The food here is
really, really good.
We're seeing quite a bit
of evolution going on.
Mm-hmm.
We're not all
sit-at-home moms anymore.
Not many people
want to pound yam.
She certainly does not
- Nope.
- And I'm sure
when she's getting married,
one of her gifts
to her husband's house
will not be a mortar
and a pestle.
- Unlike 20 or 30 years ago.
- It will be
a food processor, most likely.
Right.
And personally,
I think, maybe people...
Women, my generation, might have
failed people like her
by not passing things on.
But now,
thanks to food bloggers,
the younger ladies have...
- An avenue to learn.
- An avenue to, you know,
get this information without
depending on their mom.
How much interest in food
is there these days?
More?
More.
- Nigerians are big on meat.
- Yeah.
- Yes.
- So when you see
that we have a few
vegan chefs, people...
- Wow, vegans.
- Yes.
In... in Nigeria.
Yeah.
I think that shows you
just how much where people are
finding their niche here.
- Yeah.
- But you know,
that's for a certain
social class.
The bulk of the people still...
I mean, they don't have
access to the Internet.
- I don't think they care.
- They don't care.
- Yeah, that's the difference.
- You know, the guy
just wants to fill his tummy
for the day, you know.
So, yeah, food is changing,
but it is not a...
Not a revolution yet.
♪
And these kids
with no education...
now they're fixing iPhones.
♪
I mean, imagine if they were
all well-educated.
♪ Of Africa
♪
They say that
where there's a will,
there's a way.
And there is plenty of will
in Nigeria.
♪
Find a niche, create a business,
build a home, a school,
a community,
or look beyond to
creating a new society.
♪
Andela, cofounded by
Iyinoluwa Aboyeji
and run in Nigeria
by Seni Sulyman,
is a rigorous training program
that teaches coders
and engineers
with the goal
of creating no less
than a continent-wide ecosystem
of high-value
software developers.
My mom had, like, a mobile shop,
something like what's
in Computer Village,
like, that's where I grew up.
She'll see mobile phones,
they'll fix it there,
and she just used to run that.
I tried other, like, jobs,
but the jobs I got,
I'm like, no, I don't want
to be a salesperson.
I don't want to be a secretary.
So that's why
I got into programming.
Shalom and Blessing
are trainees in the program,
people who will someday
rewrite the way Africa works.
As you can see, there are a
lot of issues in Nigeria today.
The average Nigerian is
struggling to...
Just food, water,
clothing, shelter.
We all believe that
this will change,
and we all believe that
we will change that.
In the U.S.,
for every software developer
that's looking for a job,
there are five openings,
which means there's
a massive opportunity
to get these awesome people,
who are really smart
and really driven, to be ready
to take on Africa's challenges.
But that's what's special
about this place.
I mean, most people are
kind of resigned
to the reality that...
That they have.
We're creating
an alternate reality
where there's always gonna be
power for you to do your work.
- Yeah.
- You know...
Africa, it should be stressed,
is home to seven
of the ten fastest growing
Internet populations
in the world
with a huge young
and mostly untapped labor pool
of eager and ambitious people.
The impact in a very short
period of time is incredible.
Before we started, people would
rarely hire African developers,
and now they can.
Many of us have been products
of multinational experiences.
I grew up in Nigeria,
spent time in Paris,
went to the U.S.,
and eventually I came back home.
Well-connected, we know what's
happening around the world.
And you ask yourself, if that's
happening literally
just a few hours by plane
away from here,
why is it not happening here?
Technology is gonna change
this continent.
There is no other place
in the world
where you have the opportunity
to build the future
from scratch.
♪
♪ Revolution now, now
Where will Lagos be
in ten years?
Or 20?
Change is inevitable,
the problems enormous,
but the desire,
the hope is there...
♪ Now, now
to change not just Nigeria,
but the world.
We've got all the conditions
for a revolution.
♪
Don't just build a CV,
build a life.
Be better in real life
than on paper.
♪ Now, now
♪ Revolution now, now
♪ Revolution
♪ Oh!