Detroit's the city of champions.
The whole world knows that
Detroit is the American city
whose products have
revolutionized our way of living.
And only in Michigan, when you
find the men and women whose
talent made us the arsenal of
democracy in wartime and the
economic pace-setter in
peacetime.
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la la
It's where nearly everything
American and great came from.
The things the whole
world wanted made here.
The heart, the soul, the beat of
an industrial,
cultural superpower.
A magnet for everyone with a
dream of a better future, from
eastern Europe to
the deep south.
American dream, you came here.
The one straight ahead
with the green roof?
The big building,
completely empty.
Empty?
Unbelievable.
The white one is being rehabbed.
There's some money coming in.
The one next to it on the
right is completely empty.
The gray pyramid with the spire
on top sold for $5 million.
$5 million for that?
You can't buy a garage in the
Hamptons for that basically.
$5 million for a skyscraper.
It's post-apocalyptic.
It's like a science
fiction film.
What the hell happened here?
Well, it is post-apocalyptic
except for the fact that there's
several hundred thousand
people living here.
Detroit 2013.
Charlie la duff is a writer,
journalist, television reporter.
He grew up here.
But it used to be
two million people.
That was rubber.
That guy was steel.
That guy was a doctor.
This was what made America.
The road started here.
The automobile.
Frozen peas started here.
Credit on a mass
scale started here.
What was this like
just before this?
20 years before.
It was insane.
And this is when it was like
twice as many people here.
This is a consequence because
all the whites went, they took
their money, they
took their factories.
The black middle class
maintained for a while.
And then it got too
rough for them.
So there's little pockets of
Ferrell hippies and older black
folks, a couple white
folks and Arabs.
But this is 140 square miles.
So you're going to get grass
because it's back to the wire.
It is one of the most
beautiful cities in America.
It speaks of those industrialite
dreams of an endlessly
glorious future.
The people who built these
structures, they
were thinking big.
They were.
They were looking at a new
Rome and they built it,
actually.
It's awesome.
♪
Maybe the worm started
to come here.
The Packard automotive plant.
Opened in 1903, it was
considered the most advanced
facility of its kind
anywhere in the world.
Huge, especially proportioned.
I mean, 3.35 million
square feet.
Now, one man lives here.
Al hill.
My name is Alan hill.
Welcome to my home.
This room right here was a
former Packard motor car
company.
I started living here
about seven years ago.
I was semi apprehensive
about the goings on here.
But turns out it's about as
peaceful as the north woods.
Not having a credit card or
mortgage payment or car
payment is a real blessing.
There's a few nails here.
Yeah.
So what's happened here in
Detroit is unfortunate, but
it's a sign of the times.
We find out it takes an entire
world to support one city.
One city is suffering or one
community is suffering, the
entire world should pitch in and
help elevate it instead of
sit there and stare at it.
People have lost faith
in a lot of things.
Probably had to do with the
faith they had in Detroit.
Once the industrial leader
of the entire world.
It's enormous.
Yeah, it is.
A mile long, maybe a
quarter of a mile wide.
I've got a pretty good
view from up here.
Yeah.
How many people worked
here at its peak?
During the war, there were
like 33,000 people working here.
It went out of business in '56.
Brought Studebaker in as a
partner and Studebaker
pulled them down.
This has been abandoned
since the '50s?
Actually, what happened, in
1956, they rent out to
various entrepreneurs.
Truck and companies,
guys were storing cars.
So how long has it
been like this?
Most of this damage happened
in the last five years.
Within the last five years?
Yeah.
China had this Olympia effort.
Scrap metal went
to a high price.
They took the windows out, they
just destroyed everything.
The place is pretty much open
to anybody who wants to come in.
Sure.
A lot of urban explorers.
People shooting music
videos, taking pictures.
Oftentimes you see a
wedding party come here.
And they use this as a backdrop
for their wedding and
take pictures, videos.
Wow.
You want to take pictures here.
The place, like so much
of Detroit, invites it.
Urban exploring, as they call
it, sifting through the remains
of Detroit's great ongoing
American tragedy,
photographing them, posing
in front of them is an
impulse.
Detroiters hate it.
All the visitors like us, I
point out, wallowing in ruin.
Where are we standing?
This right here is where
the assembly line was.
This is a paint booth where
they spray paint the cars.
You can see on the car where
they have the washer
with the spray.
The assembly line ended
35, 40 feet over here.
There's Bridges between
here in the main building.
Actually came
across the Bridges.
Assembly line three
quarters of a mile long.
You're talking hundreds of
thousands of people all
working on the process.
This is sort of a... it's not a
perfect model for Detroit, but a
perfect model of when a big
factory goes down, it's
not just 33,000 people.
That's 33,000 families who are
going to be eating
dinner out less.
You've got a point
there on that.
Most people I would guess
have no idea what a
Packard even was.
We're talking about one of the
great luxury cars
in the world, yes?
It was the kind of car that
everybody would love to have.
Kings and queens, every president
wanted to ride in one.
Popes and Indian chiefs.
A luxury car maker
went out of business.
Little did they realize that was
a trend that started here in
Detroit and when it affected
Detroit, it affected the entire
world because it
followed everybody home.
50 or 60 years later, but it
started here and then everybody
else experienced the same
problem that we're having.
Another 20 years, this place
probably won't be here and
people won't have any idea
what went on over here.
It's hard to look
away from the ruin.
To not find beauty in the decay.
Comparisons to Anchorwatt,
ancient Rome are inevitable.
Magnificent structures
representing the boundless
Greens of the dead left to rot.
Yet unlike anchor,
people still live here.
We forget that.
You tell people you go to
Detroit, and chances are
somebody from the home team is
going to say "be sure
to get a coney."
I never really understood that.
I mean, I'm like 30 minutes from
a place called coney island
where presumably, they know
something about freaking
hot dogs, right?
Maybe the early Greeks
or Macedonians who first
experienced that golden land by
the shore then took what they
saw with them to Florida,
Michigan, and beyond.
Maybe they knew something.
They've been doing coneys at
duly's for over 90 years.
That's almost as long as
the hotdog's been around.
I can't tell you how deep
this creation runs here.
Deep dish in Chicago,
cheesesteak in Philadelphia.
You'll find some ambivalence.
Not here.
How are you, sir?
Good.
Now, if I were from Detroit,
would I be eating this with
my hands or with a fork?
Probably with your hands.
All right.
I'll do my best.
Logistical problems.
That's delicious.
This is the best of my only
three coney experiences.
You're open 24 hours.
Yes, sir, 24/7.
The lunch crowd, seriously
drunk people trying to eat this.
We have a fun time.
A skill you learn overtime?
It takes practice.
It's like kung fu.
You've got to practice
and practice.
Exactly.
Practice makes perfect.
That's good.
I think I better have
another one of these.
Yeah, you should.
I'll be better at it
the next time around.
One coney with everything.
It seems like a simple thing.
Hotdog, chili, raw onion,
mustard, steamed bun.
But the delicate interplay
between these ingredients
when done right is symphonic.
Detroit's problems
are well-documented.
A lot of attention has been paid
to a history of spectacular
mismanagement and corruption.
Detroit is hardly alone in this.
New York was a pit
of corruption.
Chicago, Boston, machine
politics, they wrote the book.
But Detroit differs in that its
scandal seems so squalid.
Through all of it, one man seems
to have known what's going on.
Adolph Mongo, political
strategist, oracle, survivor.
He's seen it all.
I know what I'm having,
but I'd love a beer.
I thought you drank, man.
You drinking beer?
What are you drinking?
I'm drinking vodka.
I'll fold under pressure.
Okay.
Then I'll think about a
burger down the way.
You having something to eat?
I'll hold back.
I will stick with...
I'll get you your drink.
Thank you.
I have to ask, you're born and
raised in the Detroit area.
An academic star.
Marine corps.
Journalism.
Why did you never
run for office?
You got to be crazy.
You know what?
They don't want straight
forward politicians.
They don't last.
You got to be real cold-blooded.
Men are elected officials like
working for the drug cartel.
You can't get anybody any mercy.
It seems that whatever might
be in your heart and however
pure you might be, when you
finally arrive in office,
somebody brings you a big
dossier and opens it up and says
Mr. President, Mr. Mayor, Mr.
Governor, this is
the real situation.
At which point it's an ocean
trying to start making some
serious accommodations.
Yes.
Kwame Kilpatrick.
Greedy.
He was greedy.
I didn't support him
in the beginning.
And I was one of his
biggest critics.
But when he got in
trouble, who he call?
He called me.
I should have
listened to my wife.
She said don't be
messing with him.
Are there good guys out there?
There's a lot of guys, yes.
But they don't want to run.
There's a lot of people.
Why don't they want to run?
Because you've got to take
the badge that come
along with it.
You got to take the garbage.
Why should a bright young guy
fresh out of law school start
thinking about running for
anything in the city of Detroit?
Sooner or later, it's
going to be all right.
It's going to be all right.
It's a tough town.
Is Detroit going to
turn things around?
I could lie and tell you yes.
But you know what?
This city is screwed.
Only place I've ever been that
looks anything like Detroit
does now, Chernobyl.
I'm not being funny.
That's the truth.
Abandoned.
But you have to admire the
bold, proud, ferociously
enterprising survivivors who
decided to hang on, hang in, and
figure out a way to not only
survive, but do something
extraordinary.
There's Tyree's Hidelburg
project, a loony outdoor
community art project that began
in 1986 and now attracts 35,000
visitors per year from
around the world.
That was a buck in
gas right there.
I love Detroit.
They got this in the summer,
the neighborhood lit it on fire.
Another block and more decay.
And a liquor store.
This neighborhood, the
only store for miles.
Just be right back.
How you doing?
Hey.
I love you.
Awesome spirit on you, man.
God bless you.
Hi, how are you?
Ain't nobody do it like you.
See you later.
Cheers, man.
You want one?
That's the benefit of a college
education right there.
People seem to like
you in this town.
Who hates you in this town?
Who hates me in this town?
Nobody.
Politicians?
I'm guessing there are a
number of politicians and former
public employees who
are not too happy.
I don't know.
You know, yeah.
Let's face it.
There's a whole lot of people
out there who would be perfectly
happy with just
letting Detroit go.
It already went!
Look at this.
See those lilies there?
I call those the ghost gardens.
Like they're all over like the
houses that used to be, the
gardens still come up.
♪
Off the main drag... girl,
you're wearing the hat
and everything!
A backyard.
Thanks for coming.
I never had such a good time.
A well-tended home surrounded
by many neglected ones.
An example of Detroit-style
entrepreneurship.
Greedy Greg's, a do it yourself
barbecue joint started
by these two.
Rochelle and Greg.
I'm greedy Greg.
On the menu, absolutely
delicious straight from the
grill ribs and rib tips.
But the really good
stuff is inside.
Superb smoked pork loaded
collards, and Mac and cheese.
Thank you so much.
This is perfect.
That's good.
I'm going to use
this spoon here.
It's unbelievably good.
The Mac?
The Greens are incredible.
Oh, those are good.
So the greens, is that
like smoked hammock?
I can't tell you my secret.
Those are some of the best
Greens I've ever had.
I've been all over the south.
I've had a lot of Greens.
They're not just delicious.
They're luxurious.
Big hunks of you won't
tell me what in there.
I can't give away my secret.
Will this kind of
entrepreneurship lead Detroit
out of its sinkhole?
Probably not.
I can't believe there's not a
line of cars around the corner.
That was good.
But it's no longer
about winning, is it?
It's about surviving.
There are approximately
80,000 abandoned buildings
within Detroit's 140
square miles city limits.
What that translates to,
unfortunately, is about
14 acts of arson a day.
Nearly 5,000 a year.
That's just arson.
That doesn't include the
thousands of other types of
fires and medical emergencies
the Detroit fire department
responds to every day.
With an ever-lower valued
housing market where you can buy
a home for as little as $500,
many houses are burned
down for the insurance.
Many because angry neighbors
desperate to hang on see
abandoned structures taken over
by crack heads or drug gangs.
With law enforcement stretched
ridiculously thin, they
resort to burning them out.
They won't say it.
I will.
The Detroit fire department is
underfunded, underequipped,
often badly and incompetently
led, and up against what seems
like a neverending war.
A city on fire.
Their safety equipment, their
boots, their clothes are often
moldering and shambolic.
But they fight on.
This is the second time
they've been to this house.
If it happens to be arson,
chances are no one will ever
know for sure.
Given the ever-shrinking
resources available to the
department, most fires can't
even be investigated.
This fire is out within an hour.
And after the fire, dinner.
The cliche is that
firemen are great cooks.
In this case, the
cliche is true.
Lieutenant Mike Devons and the
boys of squad three are
cooking up a family meal.
Is ever firefighter expected
to cook reasonably well?
If they don't, they catch hell.
Really?
It's almost a perfect
society in that sense.
Because in a perfect society, I
believe everybody should be able
to feed themselves and their
friends or their family,
at least reasonably well.
If they're not able to do that,
they should be shunned and
demonized and marginalized.
Most of the firemen are
known for their cooking.
We cook some outstanding meals.
We learn to shop.
We learn to shop with
less to feed more.
You don't want to
be a belly robber.
You better bring some
food back for the boys.
Firefighters, in my experience,
are a lot like the
marines I've met over the years.
No matter how badly led,
ridiculously underequipped,
underappreciated, no matter how
doomed their mission, they take
a bizarre and quite beautiful
pride in at least being screwed
more than anybody else
and doing it with style.
They seem to do what
they do for themselves.
It's not a job.
It's a calling.
This is where the guys
store their gear.
As you can see, the
gear is very weathered.
How old?
This gear is only a
couple years old.
But it gets beat up quick.
Yeah.
One new coat hanging in there,
so there's a lucky guy
that's got a new coat.
But that gear's
seen a new action.
Where's the fire pole, dude?
They took them.
Aw, man.
Late '90s, management
took the poles out.
Every boy my age, it was about
sparky the fire sliding
the poles.
I used to slide the pole.
Headquarters was three stories.
You had to really hold on
because you were going for a
ride.
The old running board,
we put up here.
We don't use the running board,
but this is how many
companies we used to have.
What percentage of
that number now?
Less than half.
And we're fighting
a lot more fires.
You know, I've got to say,
the kitchen is
looking pretty good.
It's one of the best
kitchens in the city.
Tonight's meal is
being cooked by Paul.
He's squad three's
best, they say.
He's reading the can.
That's a good start.
Tonight's menu, crabcakes
with a mix of actual
crab, and this stuff.
Sea leg.
Maybe you know it from such
beloved menu items
as California roll.
Hey, firefighters can't afford
100% jumbo lump crab meat, okay?
Do you know what this
stuff is, by the way?
It's fish, isn't it?
Pollack.
It's a miracle fish.
You can actually make
beef out of this.
Or beef-like substance.
It should be pointed out that
every meal is paid for
by the crew on duty.
They pool their money
and shop as a unit.
What's the fire house
favorite by consensus?
Steaks, man.
If I were the regular cook
here, the whole fire house would
be in totally open rebellion?
Why?
I'd be making stews because
they're cheap and I think
they're delicious.
I'd be trying it out with
tripe and guts on you guys.
That would not go.
You'd be eating like Italian
peasants every day if
I was to cook here.
You'd have a big bowl of stew
with a big hunk of bread.
And I would be pocketing
the difference.
Yeah.
Lamb chops seared in the pan and
finished over the grill.
Then Caesar's salad
with chicken.
How are the other firefighters
eating around the city?
What are you guys
having for chow?
You ever tempted to say
oh yeah, we had truffles.
All the time.
I'm going to be cooking
lobster in a minute.
Lobster again.
I keep telling the guys no more
lobster, I just can't take it.
We're free to eat?
Yes.
Nice job on the crabcakes.
Yeah.
Full of meat.
Very tasty.
So if it's not good, you're
not diplomatic about it.
No, not at all.
We tell them nice try.
A lot of cooks, they look at
that kitchen, there's a lot
of room, a lot of spices.
You can pretty much
make anything in there.
It's a good place to be a cook.
Nice job there, Paulie.
Yes, well-done, sir.
Generally speaking,
you eat fast.
Because you never know.
In all likelihood, you are not
going to get to
finish that meal.
Well, obviously Tony is
not doing any dishes.
I'll do all the dishes.
No.
Hell, no.
Wouldn't be the first
time, won't be the last.
No way.
At this point, you may be
asking, what about all the cool
stuff I hear about Detroit?
That's what you're thinking.
The vibrant new do it yourself
culture of urban renaissance,
young entrepreneurs transforming
the city one block at a time.
Where's that?
Well, that is happening.
Young, idealistic hard-working
people are indeed doing their
best to bring light and hope and
beauty to this
greatest of cities.
You've got to start with the
deeply felt and absolute belief
that Detroit is indeed a great
city and that it
is worth saving.
As utterly screwed as Detroit
may be, you have to be a
twisted, unpatriotic freak
to not believe that.
Behold the future.
What, like cooking
in a back alley?
Yes.
This chef has done what many
would call a very unwise thing.
After working at Gotham grill in
Manhattan, instead of staying
where the money inarguably
was, he returned to Detroit.
He's been working to get a
brick-and-mortar establishment
going by first doing regular
pop-ups here at guns and butter,
tucked into the back room of an
art gallery under an overpass
in downtown Detroit.
You have a really weird attitude
towards food in general.
Yeah.
What's that?
You've got liquor, cigarettes,
you've got coffee.
Or all of those things.
We're going to eat well.
Charlie may have a Pulitzer
prize, but his appreciation of
fine food and dining is, shall
we say... is that truth?
Lacking.
Worn egg yolk with a
generous helping on top.
Egg with eggs?
Yes, please.
He scarves his like
he's at Ruby Tuesday's.
How is that going to play out?
Will there be
political leadership?
A place to manage that fairly?
It will be fine.
Everybody likes a nice thing in
an egg shell with caviar.
Everybody.
It's just all about
keeping cool.
No, it won't be fine, David.
It will not be fine if there's
not political leadership.
It will not.
Well, sometimes political
leadership grows up out of
what's happening.
And we don't have any political
leadership and this is
happening.
Are you an optimist?
I'm an optimist.
I'm here in this
garage with you.
Chilled summer soup with
melon, tomato, lemon broth.
Summer soup.
All the melons from the market.
The coriander blossoms were
picked from a farm
right here in Detroit.
Thank you.
It's good, isn't it?
I would describe
that... may I, chef?
As a light, airy gaspacho.
I wouldn't even go that far.
He sees an opportunity to make a
melon... you put
gin in your soup?
The soup is delicious.
You're on your own, dude.
You know, when I was chef and
you poured gin in my soup, I
would have stabbed you in
the neck with my fork.
I'm dying somewhere inside.
Your like the worst-case
scenario customer.
Next up, smoked mussels, lightly
steamed in white wine and
butter, served in a lobster
broth with fried
onions and honey.
Quite delicious.
Baby Greek salad with
beets, tomato and fennel.
All sourced locally.
A tribute to the Greek diners
where Craig grew up
dining with his family.
A restaurant in Vegas, and
here he is in Detroit.
Guess what?
The head aches are less.
You're appreciated here.
This would be considered a
foolhardy venture
in the chef world.
We like food, too.
We're not space aliens.
People often say thank you.
We lived in Chicago
the last six years.
We lived in L.A. the
last six years.
Thank you, this is
exactly what we wanted.
What you've done is
counter intuitive.
There is a conventional
cheer path for chefs.
Instead, you decide
to go to Detroit.
Hell yeah.
Come back home.
People think I'm crazy for
going back to Detroit.
Potato simmered this white
wine, thyme and fennel seeds.
Finished with butter pine nuts.
Followed by locally sourced
lamb cooked perfectly.
Topped with sour cherries,
toasted pistachios,
coriander, and yogurt sauce.
In what way does opening a fine
dining restaurant in Detroit
benefit the majority of
detroiters?
How is it not making it better?
How is sitting back not doing
anything making it better?
How is it only buying my
products from farmers in
Detroit not helping Detroit?
I'm supplying from Detroit.
I'm hiring people from Detroit.
Everybody here lives in Detroit.
If I were asked the same
question, I would say I don't
know.
I'm doing what I do well.
I'm doing it in a place that I
love and I'm demonstrating that
yet another person gives a...
About Detroit and believes
in it enough to be here.
You're 100% right.
I never really thought about it.
Until you asked that question.
To me, it's just obvious.
What will the Detroit of
the future look like?
Whatever you may think it should
look like, it will
probably taste like this.
Somewhere in this unassuming
neighborhood, one can sit
down for an excellent meal.
But you won't find this place on
yelp, and unfortunately, I
cannot tell you where it is
exactly.
Why not, you ask?
It's not exactly a restaurant,
you see, which means it's not,
strictly speaking, legal.
What is this place?
Pupusa house.
I call it pupusa house.
It's a cultural thing.
Traditionally they're
out of houses.
It's just something that people
bring over and they come.
So this is about as traditional
as it gets right here.
It's just like home.
Yep.
This is what's called
a pupusa house.
Literally, a house.
This one serving home-cooked
Salvadorian meals.
Once a living room, now
the main dining area.
The woman running it, we can't
show her face, but she's been
here for ten years serving a
mostly Salvadoran clientele,
looking for a taste of home.
First up a staple done a little
differently than the norm.
Tamales wrapped in banana
leafs and steamed.
Delicious.
Next the dish of the house,
tortillas stuffed
with ground pork.
You have pupusas in
Nicaragua, in Guatemala.
But for some reason, Salvadorian
pupusas get the most respect.
General consensus seems
to be they're the best.
How come?
I would agree.
George Azar is our
Detroit fixer.
He's been coming here with
his friend Joe for years.
This is what makes
it right here, this.
Cortido.
It's pickled.
I don't know if you
can hang, man.
It's turning into it.
Mexican spice.
Salvadorian, not spicy.
They don't do it that spicy.
This is porky goodness,
that's for sure.
It's fried pork, ground
with pepper and tomato.
Simple.
Taking the Liberty of ordering
some Detroit beverages
that we've overlooked so far.
It's like a cross between
ginger beer and ginger ale.
It's in the middle.
It's my favorite
beverage in the city.
I needed this to enhance
my street cred in Detroit.
Then pollo asado.
This is where it's at.
Got lives in there.
Butter, garlic.
Simple, delicious.
It's the low-fat butter.
That's good.
It's like a big hug.
How did you find your way here?
Honestly, it's only
word of mouth.
But you have annoying
foodie websites, right?
But they're not coming here.
They're not coming here?
Oh, no.
There are thousands of foodies
with ironic sunglasses
and fedoras and they're just
waiting to get in here.
I get mad at him when he
starts bringing different
people.
You hate a line of people?
I don't want to
wait for my plate.
Who hates money?
With her, it's not
about the money.
It's about keeping
the tradition alive.
What happens when a
city goes bankrupt?
When it's at the point that it's
actually considering selling
what's left of itself in chunks.
In Detroit, city services are
reduced or cut out come plately.
Fewer buses, fewer cops,
fewer firefighters.
Answer, they turn to
each other for help.
Or figure out how to
do it for themselves.
Detroit has a reputation as a
tough town, but that toughness
is about resilience, too.
The insistence on sticking
with it, no matter what.
On not giving up in the face of
the utter failure of
leadership year after year.
If the city abandons its parks
and leaves them to become
overgrown and eaten like much of
the city by tall grass and
weeds, then somebody has got
to do something, right?
Meet the mower gang.
Started by this guy.
Tom Nardone with a simple
mission of doing what they can
to keep the parks maintained.
Who are you and what
are you doing here?
We're the Detroit mower gang.
We clean up the abandoned
parks and playgrounds.
Why would you do that?
Kids need a place to play.
If you're under ten years old,
you deserve some justice in
this world, don't you think?
Yeah.
How did this thing start?
I guess I started it.
I bought a lawn tractor when the
city announced closing 72 parks.
They're going to stop
maintaining it or physically
shut it up?
They don't physically
shut it up.
Because there's no money here.
They just take the trash
barrels away and stop mowing.
Crazy.
It's a strange place, Detroit.
When we're done here, it will
not look like a nice park.
But still a playable park.
And a visible park.
So if you had kids, you could
see what they're
doing in this park.
It's safer.
All right.
Well, let's cut some grass.
Come on, you'll like it.
It's fun.
♪
There's grass in my beer.
In Detroit approximately 40
square miles have been reverted
to basically unused green space.
In many cities, so-called urban
farming may be looked upon
as cynics like my as an
affectation.
Here in Detroit, it's not.
With nature taking back the
landscape block by block, the
urban farm is really the
last line of defense.
D-town sits on the western
border of Detroit.
Where are we?
We're in the largest park in
the city which is
called Rouge park.
Did you just come in and start
digging or did you have
permission to come in?
We had permission to come in.
Was that difficult?
It was very difficult.
We negotiated with the
city for two years.
Part of the difficulty was they
didn't know what hook
to hang our request on.
They would come saying I want to
build a strip mall or
parking structure.
They're not used to people
saying I want land to build
a model organic farm.
Malik started growing the
farm for people to have greater
access to fresh produce in a
area that grocery stores
had completely abandoned.
That's basically all of
Detroit's inner city.
Other than whole foods that came
in, not a single
national food chain.
No.
In 2007 farmer Jack closed
his last stores in Detroit.
That was kind of the end of
the big chains in Detroit.
Assistance farming,
not cash crop.
You're not going to be
anticipating selling outside of
Detroit.
There's greater demand in
Detroit than all of the local
farmers can supply.
First we want to supply the
demand in the city of Detroit.
To what degree do you think
this model can be replicated
in and around the city?
We think it has great potential.
One of the things we have in
Detroit is access to huge
amounts of land.
If we're able to produce even a
small percentage of the food
which is consumed in Detroit and
circulate the revenues from that
food within our community, then
we're able to create a more
vibrant, healthy, economically
strong community.
So we think it has
tremendous potential.
Who will live in the
Detroit of the future?
There's no question, is there,
that Detroit will come back?
In one form or another, a city
this magnificent, this storied,
this American cannot, will not
ever disappear into the weeds.
There are too few places this
beautiful for it to be allowed
to crumble like Angkor or Rome.
Someone will live in a smaller,
tighter, no doubt hipper,
much contracted new Detroit.
But who will that be?
Will it be the people who
stuck it out here, who fought
block-by-block to keep their
city from burning, who struggled
to defend their homes, keep up
appearances as all around them
their neighborhoods emptied.
What will Detroit look
like in 20 years?
Or 50?
That's not just a
Detroit question.
That's an America question.
♪