♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha, la, la, la, la
♪ sha, la, la, la, la, la
♪
Nearly a year on the road,
all those miles, all those
airports, infinite variety of
awful plumbing, it was time
for something low impact.
So off to Jamaica.
♪
This is the first time I've ever
driven a car on the
wrong side of the road.
I mean, knowingly.
How hard can it be?
Oh, I get to pass
on the right too.
Thankfully we have a roll bar.
But this time a different angle,
you probably know of Jamaica has
a vacation paradise, it's worth
mentioning, this is a divided
country and has been in one form
or another since the
days of slavery.
There's a small minority who
controls almost everything, and
there's a poorer, darker-skinned
majority, less
connected, left out.
Jamaican cuisine, a lot of
it reflects this conflicted
history.
Red fruit, salt fish, this was
slave food, cheap,
long lasting, filling.
Introduced basically as feed.
♪
Day one, first order of
business, get my, some jerk
chicken.
Can you blame me?
No, I think not.
♪
Oh, that's good.
Yeah, yeah, I know this
routine, believe me.
It's brown, it's murky, and
it burns, mommy, it burns.
And there are still all these
years later, two Jamaicas.
There's the Jamaica that most
Jamaicans live in, cook in,
struggle to survive in.
The real Jamaican.
Then there's the Jamaica which
you're probably
more familiar with.
♪
But tourists have been coming to
Jamaica for a long time.
When this part of the island,
particularly port Antonio
threatened to become an
international jet set location.
He was ship wrecked here on his
yacht in 1947 and promptly
fell in love with the place.
Before Flinn, there's been
an empire of bananas.
A huge industry that later
became united fruit.
Bananas went out,
tourists came in.
The banana business eventually
went elsewhere and when tourism
shifted to the other side of the
island with the construction of
an airport at month tee go bay,
that was pretty much it.
The northeast coast was
largely forgotten.
♪
It has the feel, still,
of a forgotten paradise.
There are those who believe that
the area can come back,
that it must come back.
That the future is in hotels and
resorts and restaurants for
wealthy visitors as it once was.
♪
Take this place, for instance,
the trident hotel, luxurious,
best of all, I'm the only guest.
Oh, did I mention it
comes with a castle?
What kind of person would
own a building like that?
Who?
Why?
Then, this man arrived and kind
of answered that question.
All of this belongs to Michael
Lee Chen, local boy turned
millionaire, one of the richest
men in the world, and my host.
He's invited me for dinner.
Right, yeah, that
sounds like a plan.
But first, we need crabs
for that dinner I'm told.
Caught in the traditional style.
A drink is in order.
Cheer's man.
Crab in.
♪ S man.
♪
A lot of crab holes.
This time of year the port
Antonio is crawling
with crabs, I'm told.
It'll billion really easy, just
scoop them up and it's
back to the pool.
I'm looking, a lunge at them.
It's hot.
I think it's that rum.
It's sweltering
freaking hot, and dark.
Did you find something?
Yeah, yeah.
Awesome, man.
But it doesn't seem to bother
the hotel chefs who risk
dismemberment for
a tasty dinner.
We want him alive.
We have questions to ask him.
Where are your friends?
Yeah.
One crab down, 49 left to go.
We've got to get
some more tonight.
I'm frankly anxious to get
this over with, so when the
opportunity arises to stick my
hand in a holing with there's a
crab looking to clamp down with
its pinsers, I could care less.
Nothing.
Nope, nobody home.
Oh [ Bleep ].
Are those fire ants?
Wonderful, please
attack my nut sack.
Anything to get this
over with quicker.
He's running.
Hey man.
I don't to want kill
the little guy.
That's it right there.
Right, left, whoa.
Expert.
Nice one.
Next.
What seems like several
sweltering hours later, it's
mission accomplished and it's
back to home base and time to
get ready for dinner at the
castle followed by
a party I'm told.
Do you recognize these?
I put this guy in a bag.
I'm joined by Michael, his
partner John baker, music
producer and hoteler, John's
wife, Flinn's grandfather Luke
Flinn, and his wife, sky.
You grew up in this... yes.
In this area, what was port
Antonio like in the '50s?
Port Antonio was, it was
vibrant, banana, lots
of wealthy tourists.
So port Antonio was
a happening place.
♪
You're a man with a diverse
financial interest.
Uh-huh.
Banks, communications.
As a veteran of 30 years in the
hospitality business, why?
Why would you do such a hard and
probably unprofitable thing?
Usually unprofitable.
You're being very kind.
It's really... business,
I thought you were
smart, brilliant, but your
behavior shows that you're dumb.
No, no, I know the answer.
Are you a romantic?
♪
Great things will happen when
you dream, you aspire, you see a
vision, and you settled
to achieve that vision.
Trident is here to capitalize
and for people to and to
discover again.
Where does it cross over why
where all of the things you love
about this area, where all of
the villas are spanking new, and
people are building 400 room
hotels, is there a threshold
where things start to not be the
things that you loved about the
place in the first place and how
do you guard against that?
You know, Tony, port Antonio
is a long way from getting
there.
It has not progressed
out of the '50s.
Its had very little
tourism in recent years.
Why, everybody logs ray gay,
Bob Marley, everybody loves
spicy, delicious food.
What's the problem?
Because you don't get off a
plane and go hundreds of
yards to an all inclusive.
You have to get here
it's that simple?
It's as simple as a lift and
simple as we're surrounded by
the blue mountains and it's
an effort to get here.
So it filters out certain
form of travelers.
We have to make it easier db.
You get beat out bay
lot of... exactly.
Nooen Jamaica, lamer areas for
me, if someone says I've been to
Jamaica and not port Antonio, oh
really, you didn't get a
real feeling of Jamaica.
You can go many places in the
world and find natural beauty,
people genuinely warm, where
there's a strong culture of
food, strong culture in terms of
music, and at the same time, be
able to be part of a community
and you can be a visitor without
being a part of a
tourist industry.
♪
Hello.
During world war ii, British
naval intelligence officer Ian
Fleming came to Jamaica on a
secret mission to investigate
possible u-boat activity.
Like the legendary character he
would later create,
he was a spy.
The mission came to nothing, but
Fleming fell immediately in love
with the island and
vowed to return.
Which he did.
Buying this place, golden eye.
At the time considered very
spartan, a cottage, single room
really, few smaller rooms in the
back, but an incredible view.
He spent much of the rest of his
life here writing a book
each year at this desk.
You know those books.
♪
Today, Fleming's cottage has
been enlarged and made more
luxurious as a hotel, but the
original house still stands
along with some improvements.
Grotto, eh.
What did every male
want born in 1956?
They wanted a grotto.
It sounded good to me at 12, as
I got older, who was in the
grotto before me becomes a
concern.
Like Ron Jeremy just
leave the grotto?
Am I the first one?
Someone changed the water?
These were concerns
later in the life.
This was it, I wanted a grotto.
I still kind of do.
♪
Thank you so much.
This is totally better
than the playboy mansion.
You know that the playboy
mansion totally smells
like old man ear stink.
The current owner of golden eye
is another unusual man, Chris
Blackwell, legendary music
producer turned hotelier.
Over the years, Blackwell
expanded the property into a
resort, gates reaching right
up to the fishing beach.
Blackwell has big
plans for the area.
♪
The next day I live golden eye's
luxurious embrace, headed into
town for something,
well I just had to have
a long time favorite.
What do we have here?
Oh, Oxdale.
Yeah man.
Goat.
Sweet.
I don't care whether it's the
Bronx or Kingston or wherever I
can get it, ox tail, and of
course rice and pigeon peas.
Got to have that.
God, I love the food
in this country.
It's the best.
It's such a mix.
African.
A lot of... people
totally miss out.
Goat.
East Indy is what
they used to call it.
That's true.
Chef Chris's cook shop became
a thriving business in a town
that's seen better days.
How long you been open here?
I've been open, in this
little shop for 13 years.
13 years.
Yeah man.
The town changed in that
time or stayed the same?
Right now, our economy
is not good right now.
Why not?
It's one of the most beautiful
areas in the world.
For real.
We have a beautiful water front.
Beautiful weather.
What more could a guy ask for?
What do you think went wrong?
I mean, why would
people stop coming?
I guess the guys in the top
seat messed it up, they're
trying to correct
it now, you know.
It's expanding fast.
Yeah.
It is.
You're going to be
building all the way...
All the way down there.
All the way around.
So that's thousands of tourists.
Thousands.
To be honest, I'm
waiting for the moment.
I don't want to think.
♪
We really need that, this town
was dying fast, real fast.
Chris Blackwell came back
and he's booming the town.
That's a good step in
the right direction.
Oh, thank you.
Oh yeah, see now, now I'm happy.
That is just beautiful.
Nice place to grow up?
It is.
That's what like being a kid?
My childhood days, I used
to spend it on the beach.
That's good.
Who gets to do that?
Well, I guess only
me and my friends.
Do you ever take it for
granted, like do you get...
We do.
You do?
We do, we do.
See the thing about it when we
really need it, that's the
time we can't have it.
A lot of our water
fronts have been gone.
We have very little right now.
You know, it's okay.
We have James Bond beach like
ten minutes walk from the house.
We're one of the lucky ones.
It's inevitable of course
that next door to golden eye,
there would be a
James Bond beach.
All of the bond movies were
conceptualized and written here.
♪
When Blackwell heard I wanted
to visit the local fishermen, he
hit me up with his good
friend Carl for good company.
I'm here to hit a local rum bar
where one can indulge in a
fishermen's breakfast, rum.
So we drinking rum here,
beer, rum and beer?
All I know is hard core.
But you're recommending just
like beer and rum together?
Better now.
All right.
Right.
Then one part of rum.
Yep.
And four parts of beer.
No water.
No ice.
Try that.
Steel bottom.
Meaning... good.
And you could take it
to your dimension.
So who fishes here?
You fish?
Yeah.
What are you fishing for?
Multiple fishing.
Yeah.
Snapper, your parrot.
Business better or worse?
Okay, worse.
Fishing is a problem.
This is a fishing village
for now, at least.
All throughout the Caribbean,
fish stocks are in decline and
making a living from the sea is
getting harder and harder.
So right here, it's
actually the fishing area.
We're trying to revive the fish
stock around the island.
So if this becomes a protected
sanctuary, what are
you doing far living?
We'll have to go
further out to sea.
That means more gas.
More gas, and less fish.
So it's a strain, right.
Is there a future for the
traditional fishing industry in
Jamaica or do you think like
every place else in the
Caribbean, is it going to end up
an entirely tourist economy?
It's going to belong
to the tourist.
This place, I can tell you
something, I live up the
road, love the spot.
Blackwell, I cannot
fish in there.
Here's what I'm kind of getting
here, rich people want
to live what they see as a
simple life, in their minds,
they want to live the life
of a Jamaican fishermen.
They want to live the life of
somebody that doesn't
have a lot of money.
But the people who actually do
that now are giving up their
living and essentially
given the tourist sector?
There's weird irony
at work here.
Who gets to live in paradise?
Nobody.
Because guess what... you
have a point, there's a
lot of things going
on here, right?
I read a piece of paper a couple
months ago that's going
on down here, all right.
Native here, there
are no beaches.
This architect's model sits
in one of golden eye's offices,
showing what the coastline will
look like if all goes
according to plan.
They've going to
come inside here.
I'm no expert on local
politics, whatever is going on
here has clearly stirred
up some strong emotions.
The school kid, they
also want to own that.
Wait a minute, I'm talking
wait a minute.
Stop that.
Stop talk.
All right.
Big man, stop talk.
Why?
Come here, come here.
Sit down.
Don't do that.
Which is better, to be your
own man, uphold family tradition
in a dangerous, evershrinking,
ever more difficult business
trying to catch fish in the sea
or carry a golf bag for
a wealthy tourist?
I couldn't tell you.
I was in the service industry
cooking people's food for most
of my working life, so it's not
like I have anything against
it, but I don't know.
Let us find the spirit
in man and travel.
Because we are here in the
present, this is coming.
And we are going to
go on into there.
If one man die, all man dead.
And if one man live,
all man live.
One moon, one sun, multipurpose
in the energy on life.
Black, blue, green, pink,
yellow, river, sea, mountain,
bird, dog, man.
The money, everything is
connected to the universe.
So if we are one person does not
realize or wherever we
are within the time.
Earth will not disappear.
Who gets to live in paradise?
It's Jamaica, let's accept as a
basic premise this is as close
to paradise as it gets, right?
This place I'm staying was built
by a guy who lived here two
months out of the year.
That place down there,
probably the same.
And two months a year.
Sad to say, I think it's
unlikely that 50 years from now,
anyone but the extraordinarily
fortunate, the extraordinarily
connected, and the
extraordinarily rich will be
able to even look at
a vista like this.
That is my personal theory.
Look, here I am.
Fully aware of the irony
of the situation.
It's like the whole preservation
thing, preserved for who?
Save the reef, for who?
Save the beach, for whom?
Not you.
Probably.
♪
Later that evening,
Blackwell invited know his
private bar just down the cliff
from Fleming's old villa.
There are very few pieces of
land anywhere on earth like
this, especially with this
kind of legendary status.
Legendary status, yes,
bond's best space.
This Blackwell is the founder
of island recorders.
He's credited with discover, Bob
Marley and spreading the gospel
of reggae in the mainstream
all across the world.
To the extent that one person
can sort of be responsible for
the sound track of your life,
you are responsible for much of
the soundtrack of my life.
He signed Brian both... yes.
Did you have any idea signing
Bob Marley, the extent to which
his image alone would blow
up to, you know, the level?
Bob somehow managed to touch
people in every corner of the
world in different cultures,
different societies.
No, I never could have imagined.
I don't think anybody could have
imagined, it's so unbelievable.
Having sold island recorders
for some rumored to be in the
hundreds of millions of,
Blackwell spends his time, well,
doing whatever he wants.
You have a number of hotel
properties, rum business...
Uh-huh.
What's the master plan?
Or are you just having fun?
Always is to have fun.
That's part of the master plan.
I only live one time.
I'm very excited about here.
What I'm doing here.
I'm trying to break a little
resort town into something that
filters into the town, filters
into the parish, filters
into the country.
Lately the project at hand is
the fish sanctuary, set up to
protect the local fish habitat
and breeding grounds.
The noble cause, but one that
has put Blackwell squarely at
odds with some of his neighbors.
It seems to me that most people
who come to Jamaica pretty much
stay within the compound of, you
know, sandals or whatever, and
don't really get out there much.
It's a business model, and
that business model
works well for people.
♪
The market that I'm going for
are the ones on the high level,
in terms of high cost level.
Is it inevitability that all
of the Caribbean will end
up as a service economy?
Yes, I think, yes,
I think mainly so.
And then it's based on tourism.
It's based on people
tough balance.
The engine that's going to
preserve or safe is depended on
who's coming to look and what
they're willing to pay
to come and look.
Uh-huh.
Can there be a balance
do you think?
Can a place this
beautiful be unspoiled?
Forever.
I think it could be a couple
hundred places like
this in Jamaica.
As long as there are people who
can go and spend some money in
communities, go to little
restaurant, go to a little bar,
go to, you know, shopping.
That's essential for
Jamaica to really thrive.
If life were a bond film, who
would you be in a bond film?
Well, there's only one
hero in the bond film.
You'd be the hero?
I'd have to be, yeah.
I don't know that I'd be the
villan, I'd be like number 17.
He doesn't have a happy end,
and his end is kept short.
Yeah.
What we're all looking
for, isn't it?
The perfect beach.
Remote, uncluttered,
cold, local beer.
The perfect end to a long,
and well, bumpy road.
Winnerford's beach is that
beach, mostly locals, a few
clued in visitors, bright
sand, clear, warm water.
And of course, local food.
This is aki, Jamaica
favorite dish.
Typically in Jamaica, we
use it as a breakfast.
Cynthia and Dennis run
this place and come highly
recommended.
I'm told this is the spot for
the got to have it or you ain't
been to Jamaica
aki and saw fish.
Rehiydrated and cooked, it
happens to be toxic if you
don't handle it right.
Now they say the
best... in Jamaica.
Anywhere.
And yeah, also some banana.
That is delicious.
Cynthia's friends joy and
Margerie have restaurants on the
beach, here too it's in
danger of redevelopment.
And all this might disappear
into the everchurning
wheel of, well... ♪
It is a public beach.
It has been one of the
best beach in Jamaica.
The beach was left to give
the poor people of Jamaica.
So the government takes it
over, supposedly to make it a
public space, but they want to
sell it to, what a hotel group?
Yeah, they want to
make like a resort.
There were a lot of islands
on the Caribbean where you're
not allowed to own a beach.
Meaning all beaches are public.
Even if it's an exclusive hotel,
at least theoretically,
anybody can go.
Right.
Here it's different.
Here if you can buy a house and
the beach, if you, you're a
hotel, you can make
it a private beach.
Meaning, they don't let
the locals or venders.
They can keep people out.
Right.
How many public access beaches
are there in this area?
Just one.
One.
This one.
No more.
No more beach.
We have other beaches around,
you know, we have like blue
lagoon which is a private beach.
And this is the only public one.
You know.
Yeah, what happens if, I
mean, that would be sort of
ridiculous if Jamaicans can't go
to the beach in Jamaica.
Exactly.
There are two sides to
every story, of course.
And the government claims
they'll still have access to
their beach.
We don't trust them.
We do not believe what they say.
They can do what they want.
If they want to get us off and
they don't do anything on it.
Right.
What kind of monstrous human
being or organization would
disblas the people
from their own beach?
Or their freedom?
Thank you very much.
We would like... we are
like we're in prison.
We have nowhere to come
and swim when it's hot.
So we the people, we are in
court with the government
because we do not want them to
take our one and only beach we
have in Jamaica, Portland.
What do you think
your chances are?
Do you think your
chances are good?
You're going to win?
Yes.
I've been fighting for
over seven years.
Seven years?
Seven years.
I said I'm going to fight
until I reach the top.
When I reach the top and I
lose, I feel much better.
But I'm not giving up.
Let's face it, there are only
so many beaches in this world.
Even fewer unspoiled beaches,
and even fewer
beaches like this.
I mean that's one of the
things that's nice about this
area is it's not a big resort
area like some of
the other parts.
And the food is amazing.
Right.
Delicious.
You can't get this at the hotel.
Not like this.
So fresh.
Right.
Really, really, really tasty.
I have to come back
here like tomorrow.
Okay.
Whenever people come here and
they have a problem, they go to
the sea and they look over there
and the ocean and when they're
finished, they never
have a problem again.
It goes right in the
water and down.
And I hope that the world can
see what is going on and that
they can come out and enjoy the
beauty of the beach and the
people and the love at the
beach.
Right.
>Next day and I know
where I'm going.
♪
Because you never know.
Because it may not be here not
that much longer, not
like this anyway.
Sun, sand, rum, and ting
and some more food.
♪
Oh, yeah.
Hi.
Wow.
What a spread.
I'm not going hungry today.
Beautiful.
Thank you.
I'm so excited.
That is actually
quite delicious.
I'm missing out on starches.
You have yam, fruit, rice,
beans, corn, carrots,
dumpling, festival.
Like the man said, eat dessert
first, life is uncertain.
That's good.
I knew I was coming back here.
It was a smart move
to come back here.
These ladies can cook.
Point being the way the world
turns, the inevitable grind of
history seems to indicate the
places like this and people like
this get plowed under,
pushed aside, paved over.
Who owns paradise after all?
Who in the end gets
to own paradise?
Use paradise or even visit it?
That's a question that's
probably worth
paying attention to.
Before there's none left at all.
♪
Can you do this and
be a good person?
I don't think can you.
Like if you wanted to do this
regularly the rest of your life,
I would like to spend three
months out of the year in a
hammock looking out at the
Caribbean in a secluded
beach like this.
You'd have to do bad
things to do this, right?
♪
James Bond doesn't get this.
James Bond is a hustler.
He gets this for a couple days
before he moves on to
the next location.
The guy who lives here is the
bond villian, not James Bond.
♪
Ian Fleming was closer
to Hugo Drachl.
You know, they have
lots of leisure time.
Sitting in hammocks figuring out
how to take over the world.
A lot of down time
in world domination.
Bond was a working class man.
This is what I've been missing.
All right, go wide.
Here's my cocktail.