This is where I bought
my first bag of heroin.
It was 1980, I was 24 years old.
But in a lot of ways, my whole
life up to that point was
leading to this address.
Western Massachusetts, the
unlikely new frontier of
America's war on drugs.
Where heroin has become an
exploding problem that's begun
to touch nearly every family.
♪
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha, la, la, la, la
♪ sha, la, la, la, la, la
♪
There's nothing like
the north Atlantic.
It's majestic.
I love the beach.
Pretty much had my first
everything on a beach.
You name, first time
I did it, beach.
I was miserable in love, happy
in love, alternately, as
only a 17-year-old could be.
This is where I lived.
Very happy summer in the early
'70s, and that was
my room on the left.
It's an amazing spot if you
think about it, a bunch of
knuckle heads working as dish
washers, way or
its, beach servers.
We could work on a
beach like this.
Happier, stupider times.
You know, I can still hear the
play list, the brothers Johnson.
If you put on Marvin Gaye right
now, I'd burst into tears.
What do you do?
You're young, you go to the
beach, you get laid,
and you get high.
It was here, all the way out
at the tip of Cape Cod,
Provincetown, Massachusetts,
where the pilgrims first landed.
And it was where I first landed.
1972, washed in a town with a
headful of orange sunshine
and a few friends.
Provincetown, a wonderland of
tolerance, long time tradition
of accepting artists, writers,
the badly behaved, the
gay, the different.
It was paradise.
The joy that can only come with
an absolute certainty
that you're invincible.
None of the choices that you
make will have any repercussions
or any effect on
your later life.
We didn't think
about those things.
I don't know what I thought
I was going to be.
At that point, I certainly
didn't think I was
going to be a cook.
I don't know what I thought
I was going to be.
I was just, you know, hanging
out in a beautiful place.
A golden time, I look back on
those fuzzy memories and
they seem golden anyway.
Oh, there's John waters.
First love, and there's me.
This guy, Johnny was sort of a
sinful figure in
all of our lives.
Well, my name is John, and
this is spiritist pizza, its
been here since 1971.
This town is everything to me.
Provincetown is a really special
place where people
can be themselves.
We all did drugs, acted young
and crazy, and Tony was, he was
probably a little Wilder than
some and not as wild as others.
But he was always the
guy who I always liked.
And you let me sleep on
talk of the walk in.
I remember that.
I cannot tell you how frequently
I freem about the pizza.
I'm walking down commercial
street, and I'm dimly aware that
spiritist has moved and there's
a sense of dislocation and a
loss as I stumble around this
Provincetown dream
scape of 40 years ago.
I was still here and
living in hope.
Unbelievable.
Many of the old places
in p-town are gone.
But the lobster pot is still
going strong, all
these years later.
And still has what
I want and need.
The essentials.
My friends worked in the kitchen
here, starting the tradition
that cooking work
was noble toil.
I never intended a
career as a chef.
It's great to be a cook.
I was getting to that.
Yes.
This is homemade Portuguese
Kale soup, made on the premises.
Its ban long time, thank you.
Enjoy.
Portuguese soup, a P-town
version and just what I
remembered.
Kale, kidney beans, potatoes.
Oh, I missed you.
I missed you bad.
And that was precisely what I
loved about the food here.
The Portuguese thing, dishes
like this stuffed COD crusted
with sausage, bread crumbs,
stuffed with scallop and crab.
Some Sherry, read sauce.
I hadn't been working for a
while, I was a deadbeat.
Just scarfing for
everybody else.
And he comes from work and says
our dishwasher didn't
show up today.
You are our new dishwasher.
And I said really.
And the next day I put on the
apron and didn't take
it off for 30 years.
I'd wake up, all of us go to the
beach, hang out until
like 2:00, 3:00.
Yeah, it was fun.
Roll into work.
Work all night.
Drinking, getting high,
drilling out food.
You have all the food you
wanted, all the liquor you
wanted?
All the sex you wanted.
It was true, it was fun.
And still an essential
part of the economy.
It was a lot of fun,
believe me, I remember.
The flagship, it's where
my cooking career started.
Write started washing dishes,
where I started have
pretensionings of
culinary grandeur.
It was a good gig for anybody?
You had to be in a band, here we
were, we were dish washers.
Yeah you get older and more
sense and you realize that like,
you know, you got to like
pace yourself a little bit.
Otherwise, we still
wouldn't be here.
Well, you know, many of our
friends from those
days didn't make it.
Many of my friends
are dead, yeah.
Keep drinking, keep drinking.
Thank you.
Thank you, Tony.
This place has
been here forever.
That used to be the back room.
Back room's still there.
See, it's all falling
into place again.
Yeah.
It's not that much different.
It's early spring now, but
come Memorial Day, it gets crazy
around here, and doesn't
stop until labor day.
Provincetown was always
gay-friendly, in my time and
way, way before my time.
And this place, the Atlantic
house known always and forever
by locals and visitors alike as
the a house as America's
oldest operating gay bar.
Everybody has come through
these doors, so to speak.
Most notably, naked and
frolicy Tennessee Williams.
No.
That's too bad.
Everybody got seasick.
They all save cocktails so I
can get my sea legs back.
Oh really?
Yeah.
April owns the joint now.
Taken over for her father,
the legendary Reggie, a
forward-thinking dude
if there ever was one.
It was built in 1798.
How long in the family?
Over 75 years.
My father during that time, he
had Billy holiday appeared, he
had Cy Moan, El Fanlts,
all the big names, jazz.
How has town changed?
Has it changed?
I think tremendously.
Gay lifestyle is
much more accepted.
Okay, 1972, my feeling was
that this was a gay town and
that I was here at the pleasure
of, you know, somebody else.
Which is sort of the opposite of
everywhere outside of
here at that time.
Oh yes.
This was largely catholic,
Portuguese, conservative
community, but it was
also known as hell town.
Hell town, there's where the
pure tins sent their rejects.
Yeah.
Provincetown had the mixture
really of the bohemian people
and the fishermen, pirates,
writers, drunks, all that.
The lifestyle outside of
mainstream was welcome here
pretty much.
Whatever floats your boat.
You know.
It's all good.
♪
Over a century ago,
Provincetown was a hard working
fishing village with
multigenerational families of
fishermen.
My name's Bo Gribbon.
My father fished, and I was
pretty much raised
here my whole life.
Where I'm from.
This is who I am.
But it used to be like two out
of three families in this town,
this community, were
fishing families.
Most of them are now gone.
And we're really
like a minority.
Used to be a fishing community
with a homo sexual problem.
The first Portuguese fishermen
arrived here in 1840.
The main families created a
community built around fishing,
and this town lived off that
industry well into
the 20th century.
It persisted even when I was
here, keeping up the
blessing of the fleet.
These days however, there are
fewer and fewer boats to bless.
My name's Scott roe, I'm a
commercial fishermen, fourth
generation.
It was cool back then,
started when I was five.
70 and 80 boats here, five or
six feet now, now it's just down
to like seven or eight.
Now I'm proud of my heritage and
I would never do anything else.
This is my office,
man, look at it.
I'm going to do this until
I can't move anymore.
We were all on the town like
clock work, 2:30, 3:00 in the
morning, it's quiet, the town's
been ripped up all night long.
We come down here,
hit the water.
What could be better?
Good time to be here,
and nice weather today.
Yeah, nice day.
Little breezy.
Might be a little nautical.
A little bit.
I'm sure I'll be fine, I've
watched the deadliest catch.
Are you ready?
I'm ready.
Time to press the fun button.
♪
Clear.
All clear.
Used to be this was the
best thing in the world.
The greatest thing about
fishing, you were kind of like a
cowboy, like a pioneer, you
could go out, and as hard as you
could push, competition
was welcomed.
We were fiercely independent.
Independence is like little by
little by little taken away.
Is there a limited number
of stuff out there?
Well, there's a total allowable
catch we're on a 600
pound trip right now.
And the payout ain't much.
Do the math, a good day brings
in Se 9,000 bucks, from that
9,000, take away 3,000 for the
lease, 1,000 for fuel, and split
the remainder amongst the crew.
And on top of that, fishing
is a just a crap shoot.
Many days, there's
simply nothing to catch.
Where the [ Bleep ]
are you doing this?
We love to do it.
It all turned to ship
around the break water.
Once we get out to there, and we
feel like we're at home.
Like I said, it ain't easy.
Today, according to Bo, Scott,
and Zeb, this was
just a little breeze.
How rough does it have to be
when you look out and say
I'm not going out today?
It starts like
blowing like 30, 35.
We like days like this because
the competition stays
in.
Really?
I doubt you should stay with
your dry, you're not making any
money... my dad used to say if
you're staying dry, you're
not making any money.
We're fishing.
So it's not going to snap
until... not too often.
No.
I hate when that happens.
Yeah, it's a bummer.
The summer, you'd be able to
smell the coconut, another
big trick we have.
Now the guys decide they like
this part of the beach, right.
So they're all out
here, nude sunbathing.
So I pick um my glasses and I
tell them, wow, look at
the breasts on that girl.
And you give it to them and they
see something they weren't
expecting to see.
Works every time though.
I can't believe you
didn't cook nothing.
I can't believe it, man.
What?
Got Anthony Bourdain on deck
and we don't have
nothing to eat.
The best part of it, the
anticipation to see what's in
there.
Oh every time.
I'm like I can't wait.
You're like look and you're like
what's going to be in there?
What's going to be in there?
Sometimes it's a disappointment.
But a lot of times
it's disappointment.
How many did we get?
A few.
Is there?
All right, we're out.
That's why it's fishing
and not catching.
Yep.
Taste all that much better.
♪
This place was, has been here
forever when I rolled into town.
How long that has
place been open?
For a long time.
I think this is the only
place in town that's unchanged.
Yeah, how long do I have to
drink here to get
my face up there?
40 years?
Couple more years.
Back when I worked in town
for fishermen, there was the
folks cookies, tap
room, and this place.
The old colony.
Of the three, it's
the only one left.
Yeah, baby.
Oh wait a minute, I
recognize these.
You guys eat scallops.
Yeah.
That's brawny, hard working
men of the sea, we deserve these
beers, these finest of all
oysters, the well fleets.
Wow.
Finest oysters known to man.
These are fantastic.
Wow, what a treat.
Is there going to be a next
generation of fishermen
in the family?
What happens after you guys?
The next generation of
fishermen that are like coming
on to our boats, they're
opportunist for the income, it's
not for the love of
being on the water.
The fishing is going to die.
Cheers.
All right.
Thank you, guys.
Cheers.
This is going to end badly.
♪
This is a nice house.
Man, it just feels like I
never left in a lot of ways.
But it was 40 years
later almost.
That was the the sea over there,
a big candy store for, horny,
stupid, 17-year-olds with
a taste for chemicals.
You know, I was an
angry young man.
What the hell was
so I angry about?
It came as a rude surprise
because I figured I'd
be dead by then.
I was still quite some time away
from my first bag of heroin,
but, you know, it was a fore
gone conclusion, my whole life
was leading up to that point.
To my first bag of dope.
♪
I left Provincetown with
restaurant experience, a
suntan, and an ever deepening
relationship with
recreational drugs.
I went to culinary school, then
to New York City,
and never returned.
Today however, I'm staying in
Massachusetts, heading over to
the western part of the state,
one of the most beautiful areas
of the country, the gorgeous
mill towns, Victorian houses,
deeply felt famously upright and
wing values, Norman Rockwell
America was something really
inexplicable and
unexpected has happened.
New England is a new
mecca for heroin use.
Emergency room emissions, law
enforcement areas dealing with
crimes, but never
happened before.
Detectives are working
around the clock.
Dealers are making a killing.
Not New York or Baltimore or
L.A. or Chicago, but rural
towns like this one are now
statistically ground zero
for the heroin epidemic.
What the hell happened?
The next couple years, if this
heroin use trend continues to
grow, it may be beyond
getting a handle on.
I'm a detective with the
greenfield police department
here, and my focus is undercover
and narcotic investigations.
This is a well-known area
to us, and very active.
Heroin use in the past year,
its just increased to a level
I've never seen any other
drug come into an area.
People are all going
to be affected.
It hasn't topped out yet.
Someone you known, someone
you went to school with,
someone you work with.
So, sunny crocke terms and
conditions Ge... gates Ferrari.
Heroin-use, heroin related
crimes, overdoses, how
does that happen?
I think once this area
realized we had a heroin
problem, we were already behind
trying to play catch up.
We are on the 91 corridor.
Route 91 has been dubbed the
heroin highway at this point.
It's a widely used road
to go north and south.
There's opportunists here and
for low money input, they're
getting a high profit.
That's the typical
heroin packages.
Bundles of ten, 50 backs here.
60 to 80 bucks for ten.
They can charge what they want.
It's supply and demand.
One dose for most people?
Multiple bags, three to five
backs at the same time.
Up to 30 bags a day.
And the current economics of the
town, I am the only one assigned
to the narcotics position.
How many heroin addicts are
walking the streets of
greenfield right now?
I'm going to say we're
in the high hundreds.
Wow.
We're in the high hundreds.
High hundreds.
It's hitting every age group,
economic household,
it's out there.
We don't have cribs and bloods
taking over motel rooms,
the person selling you dope more
likely to be familiar
than a stranger.
We're going to meet a past
distributor I've known for
several years.
We meet Carmen, a powerful
local heroin dealer turned paid
confidential police
informant out in the woods.
How'd you get into the
business initially?
I needed the money.
I needed to support my family.
Couldn't get a job.
How easy was it to get
into the dope business?
Not hard at all.
Because it's cheap.
Was there money in it?
Oh, hell yeah.
Yeah, oh yeah.
It's like mayberry out
here from looking around.
Who's using heroin now?
I mean... kids.
Kids.
Today's heroin epidemic is
different than the one that
raged through America in the
1970s, the few significant ways.
Back then, heroin was mostly
seen as a poor people problem,
somebody else's problem.
The sort of thing that musicians
and criminals got into, marginal
people, far from the white main
streets of mayberry USA.
But those people did to
themselves, well it was
unfortunate, but
not our problem.
Until somebody broke
into your house.
Today, it's absolutely
the reverse.
The new addicts are almost
entirely white, middle class,
and from towns and
areas like this.
How do you think you
make it better?
I don't.
Whoa.
You don't?
No there's going to be more
robberies, there's going
to be more killings.
Take one person off the street
here, two more come in.
How many customers do you have?
Practically all of greenfield.
What happened?
How did the kid next door, along
with mom, pop, and grandma too
become users of hard core
illegal narcotic drugs, the
worst drug, with the
worst reputation?
♪
Well, maybe start here.
Once you found the right
doctor and have told him or her
about your pain, don't be afraid
to take what they give you.
Often, it will be an
opioid medication.
Here's a 1996 promotional
video from the fine folks at
Purdue pharmaceuticals.
It encouraged them to prescribe
the latest, newest, more
wonderful drug for long-term
pain management, Oxycontin.
Some patients may be afraid
of taking them because they're
perceived at too
strong or addictive.
That's far from actual fact.
Less than 1% of patients
taking opiods become addicted.
Sales initially and falsely
proclaimed as not addictive,
absolutely skyrocketed from $45
million in 1996 to
3.1 billion in 2010.
That same year, perdue tweaked
the way that we're making it in
an attempt to they said, limit
its addictive qualities.
Finally the government and law
enforcement took a harsh look at
the drug and it became much
harder to get legally.
Which sucked for the thousands
and thousands who by now
had a serious habit.
I am Ruth, a family physician
in greenfield, Massachusetts,
and I grew up here.
My dad was a small
town doctor out here.
I'm a total generalist, but for
the last four, four and a half
years, a larger part of my
practice has been focussed
on addiction to opioids.
I got put on pain medication.
Then when they started
disappearing, everybody else is
doing it.
The heroin?
Yeah.
I can get a bag of heroin easier
than I can get a joint.
Once they start, they just
slip down that rabbit hole and,
you know, maybe
they make it out.
That's our goal is to get them
out and live healthy again.
We've created this
mess we're in now.
♪
In downtown greenfield, the
people's pint, and ecoconscious,
local pub that brews its own
beer, uses only farm fresh
ingredients and composes
its own ingredients.
I meet up for din per.
Who's doing dope?
Everybody starts with the pills.
Nobody that goes from
marijuana to heroin.
There's an in between step.
Always pills, it's pills that
people get from their doctor.
From me.
Particularly the young people.
Had an injury, a sports-related
injury, had their wisdom teeth
out, and they felt awesome on
the drug, and they were like how
can I get more of that?
After three to six months of
looking more, they couldn't
find it, then they jumped.
Is it a big farm ma
pseudocalls felt?
Doctors fault?
Who's fault is it?
It's complicated.
I'm not going to say there's one
entity here that's responsible,
but there was a lot of money to
be made by promoting the
treatment of pain to
the highest level.
Big pharma made a lot
of money on this.
I was taught in residency,
you give people as much pain
medicine as they need.
Get them out of pain, we'll
judge your hospital, emergency
room based on your pain scores.
That's how we were taught.
And also told that they're
not all that addictive.
We started handing out
pills like crazy.
100 million Americans
have chronic pain.
So, we did a disservice as
doctors and as prescribers, like
we took data that was [ Bleep ],
and then we went forth with
it and said prescribe it to
everyone, they won't
get addicted.
Guess what, we didn't
know what we were doing.
A few miles down the road
from greenfield is a Shellburn
falls, the good old days
everyone used to talk
about when I was a kid.
Sundays, church and picnics.
Saturday nights, Sox
games, beer, and bowling.
The Shellburn falls bowling
alley is where time seems
anyway to have stopped.
First opened in 1906, this is
the second oldest bowling
alley in America.
Dedicated to old school new
England-style candle pin
bowling.
The holy rollers, crowd who grew
up in Shellburn and plan this is
a reasonable expectation
to kick my [ Bleep ].
They've been playing
here since the '50s.
I was never allowed to come
near the bowling alley.
This was my aunt did not
think this was a good idea.
Oh it's a tiny little ball.
This looks really hard.
It's very different,
Shellburn falls.
I grew up here.
Very different.
People don't know each other as
well as everyone used
to know each other.
When I grew up in greenfield,
everybody had jobs.
I worked from the time I was 13.
If I had to go back there, now,
I don't believe in drugs, I
don't have anything to do with
them, but, what
choice would I have?
Stand on the corner, I would
probably get into a business.
What's a good business?
Well-paying business?
I'm sorry.
That's where we are.
♪
Yes, it used to be a very
different world towns
like this one.
And there were many.
But like everywhere else, it
seems the mills, the factories
closed down, and with them a
certain kind of social contract
with the people
that worked there.
My name is ed Gregory,
originally from Terrence falls,
born and brought up
here, born in 1945.
My father was an employee of
the draft mill, as was my
grandfather.
During the hay day, there
were three paper mills, cotton
mill, a beehive
of activity here.
Back then, a company town
like this, the company
actually took care of you.
They built and provided
homes for their employees.
Schools, the river
provided energy.
The company provided
nearly everything else.
The hay day is gone.
People are definitely
struggling to find work.
The town just kind of
died during the '80s.
When the folks came to work,
they were immigrants...
Attracted by the
manufacturing here.
Correct.
Made it a possibility of owning
a home in a decent part
of the county here.
♪
So my father was here,
millwright, millwright's job is
a Jack of all
trades if you will.
If there was something
to be repaired.
You could work in a mill and
live in a nice home, send your
kids to school, make a
living all on a mill salary.
You bet.
It's unthinkable now.
What happened to the business?
Things are going to other
countries, but not coming
back to the United States.
This time it's redundant?
Correct.
Again and again all over the
country, I keep running
into situations like this.
Where industry has died or
fled or simply relocated.
I meet people like Charles
Garbel, hometown heroes who for
some reason could go anywhere,
take their skills, and return
to where they grew up.
Shady Glenn diner, today's
special, a contribute to the old
European immigrant culture of
the area, the new
England boiled dinner.
So I hear rumors of corned beef
and cabbage, is that right.
Every week a corned beef
and cabbage dinner.
Corned beef, boiled
potatoes, steamed cabbage.
That's a beast,
awesome, thank you.
How long have you been here?
Two years.
Are you from the area?
I grew up here, been coming
through here since a kid.
Who are your customers
generally speaking?
Most are retirees, they've
been coming since they were 30.
This, you don't see
so much anymore.
Homemade pies and lots of them.
All baked on premises.
Raspberry cream pie
for me, thank you.
This is not something
we see a lot of.
Old school pie like this
and this number of them.
Serving made here.
And they're all the original
recipes from the '60s.
The index cards are so old,
they're all faded yellow.
Exotic for me.
Really?
Oh yeah.
How's business?
It's getting better.
The drug problem has
gotten rampant.
Took over may 1st, 2012, I
was broken into four times.
It wasn't just me, it was
multiple businesses
time after time.
I came in one morning to open
up, and I had a guy in front of
the rebel star and he got
up, pulled a knife out.
I realized it really wasn't
worth anything over a knife.
What you're doing
here is terrific.
A man can go and get a pot open
Turkey sandwich and good slice
of pie, it's a beautiful thing.
My name is Heather Taylor.
I'm a mother of three.
The two older kids
experienced my addiction.
My addiction started with pills.
I started sniffing heroin.
I shot up for the first time,
and shortly there later I
found out I was pregnant.
I had my daughter.
She was in the hospital for six
weeks because she was addicted
to the methadone and I had
to watch my baby go through
withdraws.
My son was four, and my daughter
was six weeks when
they were taken away.
I lost my kids for 33
days shy of two years.
I became serious
about my recovery.
So is this the bad part of
town or is this just a place
where you're unlikely
for people to find you.
Just a place where people
are unlikely to find you.
I wouldn't necessarily say there
was a bad part of greenfield.
I mean, it's probably pretty
spread out, bad, I
guess you'd say.
What would you do?
Come here to shoot up?
Yep.
You know we'd go down here and
just hang out down there.
I bet if we walked along here,
we'd find needles and bags.
You know.
Basically you'd come down
here, shoot up, and what
are you going to nod out?
Just sit down... just
sit down and hang out.
A day like this, hang out under
the underpass over there.
Not exactly la vida loca.
As you can see the trash and
yuck, it's dirty and gross.
There's probably people
who live down here.
Really?
Yeah, there's a lot of
homeless people in greenfield.
What do you think now when
you see somebody who's
junk sick on the street?
It gives me that
yuck, sick feeling.
And it scares me.
It reminds me why I don't
want to be out there.
It's just scary.
A friend of mine overdosed
January 1st of this year.
And my brother-in-law overdosed
in Wendy's bathroom
and they found him.
And they brought
him back to life.
He was dead in the bathroom.
Uh-huh.
So this is my narc cam.
I carry this around, I have one
of these in my house and
I have one in my car.
I have a fear that my husband's
going to relapse and I'm
going to find him dead.
You just put this in here and
squirt it up their nose.
Now in most cases, as I
understand it, they're
right out of it.
They're right out of
it and instantly sick.
They don't wake up happy.
But they wake up.
Somebody's blue there.
On the floor.
Are you saving that life?
Yep, saving that life.
Absolutely.
And then kicking
their [ bleep ].
Better now?
Life better now?
Absolutely.
My kids have been
home three years.
You know, I no longer
have to watch my back.
You know, I live a pretty
straight and narrow life.
Which, you know, people might
say is boring, but I
love my life today.
I'm grateful.
Where are we headed?
This way.
Oh, okay.
To the recover projects.
This is where my
recovery started.
Started near lay decade ago
in one of the two main streets
of greenfield, the recover
project is community-based.
An open arms program aimed at
helping addicts stay clean.
Given the opioid heroin
addiction in our community, we'd
like to start the conversation.
What happened at that point of
our life, what that was like.
So as a child growing up in a
home of addiction, I didn't
understand how they could do all
the stuff that they did to me
and my brother and sister.
Like don't you love me enough?
Then I became a mother, and then
I became a heroin addict.
And I did all that
stuff to my kids.
My doctor was my
biggest drug dealer.
Married, had a baby, fell
down the stairs, two jobs,
college on top of it.
Next thing I know I'm on the
prescriptions, that's where
it all began for me.
What are the odds you're
going to own a house?
What's the odds to
have a nice car?
Any car?
A place to live, all that stuff?
Seems less and less
likely all the time.
When you stick a spike in
your arm and I wouldn't.
So I have this picture in my
head which got the phone call my
daughter's father had been in
the accident and I just had a
c-section and come in with this
need toll give me at Van and all
I needed was a hug, like I just
needed someone to give me a hug,
I care about you, Kaitlyn, and
everything is going to be okay.
I'll tell you something
really shameful about myself.
The first time I shot up I
looked at myself with a big
grin.
Something was missing in me
whether it was a self-image
situation, whether it was a
character flaw, stable family,
the suburbs, I had a lot of
advantages, there was some dark
genie inside me that I hesitate
to call a disease that led me to
dope, you know, I didn't have
anyone else who could have
talked me out of what I was
doing, but intervention
wouldn't have worked.
I didn't have a child, I have a
7-year-old daughter now who
I never would have had.
I never would have thought... I
looked in a mirror and I saw
somebody worth saving or that I
wanted to at least try
real hard and save.
You know, anybody can find
themself very easily in this
situation and, you know, I look
back on that and I think about
what I'll tell my
daughter, you know.
You know, that was daddy.
Ain't no doubt about it but I
hope I'll be able to say
that was daddy then.
This is daddy now that I'm
alive and living in hope.
Thank you.
Good.
♪
In Massachusetts the clambake
is a ritual going back
to the Flintstones, before the
pilgrims, today at the long
standing locals only shooting
club, shoots and Veren in German
for the immigrants who started
this ray takes me through the
fascinating and arcane process
of creating an
old-school clambake.
Basically we build a kiln
with hardwood and stone.
We burn it down, remove the wood
and cover it with seaweed and
corn hunks and we put our clams
and lobsters and corn in there
like a pressure cooker.
We've got a pig
hiding in there also.
No, no, no.
We'll pull a tusker out and
you'll see what we have here.
Let's eat.
All right.
First some good chowder and
there really is only one kind of
chowder, new England
clam chowder.
Mm-mm.
That is good.
Steamer clams, lobster,
corn, Potatoes.
Pretty luxurious clambake here.
That was amazing.
Absolutely.
Everybody's attention
for a second.
The awareness task force came
together several months ago.
I don't think we realized how
quickly this could turn
into a cite cyst for us.
Everybody in the room has
been impacted by narcotics in
some way, the opiod task force
is a grassroots response.
Doctor, law enforcement led by
Franklin county sheriff Chris
Donilon, addiction specialist
and addicteds themselves are
coming together to find a
community-based solution to what
is a public health crisis rather
than a criminal justice problem.
A great opportunity to come
here tonight to break bread and
look at the successes that we
have had so far, think what
makes me more proud than
anything else about living in
Franklin county is that we will
not sit back and wait for
anybody else to solve this
problem for us.
We'll be a model for the
commonwealth and nation on how
we save our young people
and save our community.
The city is the place where
all the bad stuff is supposed to
happen, not nice towns
like greenfield.
It isn't the image that people
had 20 years ago, a junkie
in an alley using a needle.
It's not.
It's your kids, your neighbors.
The worst I think is when you
have these young people who
break a leg and they go to the
doctor and get a prescription
for oxy and become
addicted to it.
These are any kid who plays
a high school sport.
Heroin was around, pills were
around but we didn't
have people dying.
Once you've been busted for
heroin, that's a hard
thing to live down.
Got to get rid of that shame
factor to deal with
it address it.
Get support from the community.
I feel like we'll lose a
generation, 18 to 22, the
district attorney, the police
department are all united this.
Task force is home to a
matter of a hundred people.
I lost one daughter to drugs.
You know, whatever it takes.
Let's start by being
honest with ourselves.
As a nation for decades we were
perfectly happy to write off
whole neighborhoods, whole
cities, whole generations
of young men and women.
As long as it was an inner city
problem, an urban problem which
is to say a black people
problem, a brown people problem,
send them to prison into a
system from which
they'll never maybe.
Maybe now that it's come home to
roost and the high school
quarterback, your next-door
neighbor, your son, your
daughter, now that grandma is
likely to be a junkie as anyone
else we'll accept there's never
been a real war on drugs.
War on drugs implies an us
versus them and all over this
part of America, people are
learns there is no them.
There is only us.
And we're going to have to
figure this out together.