I have a block of cheese in my
colon the size of a grapefruit.
Tony, come on.
Don't be grumpy.
Son of a bitch.
Jesus.
Sometimes I don't
understand you.
I'm so hung over; I just want
to crawl under
the bushes and die.
- Seriously?
- No, I hate this.
Are we there yet?
No, the chalet's, maybe like,
I don't know, half hour?
- Okay.
- Ugh.
- It's amazing.
- Worst episode ever.
♪ I took a walk through this ♪
♪ Beautiful world
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good in this ♪
♪ Beautiful world
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
- ♪ La, la
- ♪ Sha la, la, la, la
♪ Sha la, la, la, la
- ♪ Sha la, la, la
- Sha la, la, la, la ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la, la, la
♪
The French Alps,
lovely Italians on one side,
but the terrifying Swiss
on the other.
They're close.
Too close for me.
A man with a neurotic childhood
fear of alpine vistas,
yodeling, even cheese
with holes in it.
♪
But my friend
Eric requires payback.
I have, in recent adventures
with him, been unkind.
He grew up in mountains
like this.
He's an expert skier.
This is like home to him,
so I thought it was only fair
he get a chance at payback.
♪
I am not a graceful skier,
but I am an enthusiastic one,
and that's what you come here
for in winter and early spring.
Some of the best
slopes on Earth.
Also cheese, apparently.
Lots of cheese.
♪
I just take your size.
Yes.
Okay.
Bend your knees,
push on the foot.
They decent?
Yeah, they feel good.
That feels good.
- Good?
- Yeah.
You learned to ski
in what, the Pyrenees, right?
- Yeah.
- I learned to ski
in New Jersey.
Eh, it's the same.
Yes.
Well, that's what I always said.
You thought you were going
to the Moon, or what?
Hey warm feet are important.
Nothing's more demoralizing
than cold, wet feet.
You'll be bitching
in those things; yeah, you'll...
- No, man.
- You'll look... you'll look cool.
That's gonna be...
These are gonna be like sponges.
- You wish me bad luck.
- No, I don't.
I just think you should
have proper footwear, man.
Prior preparation prevents
piss-poor performance.
♪
Ski log, day one.
Conditions are not ideal.
It's thick powder
and zero visibility.
♪
Plus, I haven't skied in years,
so it hurts... bad.
♪
But God bless the French,
they can't go too long,
not even down a mountain,
without eating well.
I gotta tell you,
I'm not impressed
with my performance
on that hill; I was dying.
Today's challenging.
I mean, look.
It... it's about 3 feet
of fresh snow.
The visibility was okay,
barely okay.
A year ago, at this time,
I was a killing machine.
Now, I was like...
I was seeing stars,
I mean, I, I...
No, it was the altitude.
♪
And some extravagant,
fantastic, uh, red wine.
We blow up the budget?
Kill 'em.
- Kill it?
- Kill 'em.
Okay, okay, all done.
Definitely the '66 Latour.
How much is it?
Is it... is it expensive enough?
- Yeah.
- Oh, yeah.
- They're gonna love you.
- We deserve it.
♪
- Oh, it's good.
- Right, this is good, huh?
Well worth the expense
to someone else.
This is the bigger name.
We're gonna have a week
of good food,
good wine, some ski, right?
So, what, what are the
specialite ...of the region?
So, they do the raclettes.
- Cheese.
- You know like, yeah, cheese,
- Right.
- The fondue.
- That's cheese.
- Da dufflets.
- Yep.
I don't know.
- That's not bad; I like cheese.
- Yeah, I like stews.
They make a lot of stews too.
Yeah, of what animals?
Mostly beef.
- Yeah?
- Yeah.
- A lot of cows up here?
I like cows... to eat.
Yeah, to eat, of course.
Don't much like 'em personally.
♪
Where I learned to ski,
we were lucky
to get lukewarm chicken fingers
and a Bud Light at the lodge.
Here, we start with
pan-seared foie gras.
Wow.
- That's fancy, huh?
- All right.
I mean, why don't you eat that
on the ski slope? Seriously.
♪
For the main, a loin of veal,
gently seared and pan-roasted.
Joined by a wild mushroom sauce,
and a pretty little medley
of vegetables.
- Whoa.
- Looking good.
Hoo-hoo.
How is it?
It's really good.
It's also... I wanted you to know
this... humanely raised veal,
free-range, died in its sleep.
I disagree with that,
but I will eat it.
Just trying to make you feel
better about the world.
I'm all over the cheese course
like a one-man army.
Tomme de chevre,
tomme de savoie et piment,
fromage de chevre
et creme de ren.
That's from, like, a cow.
Everybody has blood
on their hands, Eric, everybody.
- I do too.
- Right, we all do.
- The clothes we wear,
the air we breathe.
Everything we do
is built on the backs
of suffering people
and dying animals.
I agree.
We wallow in blood.
♪
Ski log, day two.
Yesterday, Chef Ripert showed
no mercy on the mountain.
Today, conditions
are more to my liking.
A small wager
might have been made.
Loser might have to eat
at Johnny Rockets.
Today it is on.
Ready?
Yeah.
One, two, three.
♪
The title for your biography,
for your bio pic:
"32 Yolks: The Revenge,"
or whatever we're calling it.
"64 Yolks,"
or "For a Few Yolks More."
Well, that'll be the sequel.
"A Fistfull of Yolks."
Okay, that's what we'll call it.
We have to change it
to a more manly title.
- It's... it's...
- "32 Yolks" is...
Now it's becoming your book.
You're changing it; you're...
Welcome to Hollywood, my friend.
The Cremery.
A special place at the bottom
of the mountain.
Croute with morilles,
and cream, lots of cream.
I didn't expect that;
that's really good.
Yeah.
We're eating bread
and mushrooms...
- Right.
- Cheese.
There's no meat in this.
No, there's no meat.
I'm, like, practically
like Gandhi at this point.
♪
I'm not drastic.
I'm not saying, "Don't eat meat,
become a vegan."
I'm saying, "Let's eat less
meat."
You just think it's better
for the planet?
It's good for the planet;
it's good for our bodies.
I'll... I'll stand outside
the Bourdeau Dan.
I'll tell all
your customers that.
"You know, this fish thing,
you should really,
you should eat some vegetables."
♪
Bovine flatulence is a major
source of carbon dioxide.
Yes. It's the biggest
one in the world.
No, not the biggest one
in the world.
- Yes.
- Bovine flatulence?
Yes, bigger than cars,
bigger than anything else.
See, this is why
we should eat meat.
We're saving the planet;
we're gonna kill these things.
♪
We're ripping a hole
in the ozone layer.
Plus, it stinks.
You are a lost... lost case.
What does she want?
She said she hopes you're
very hungry, because...
Uh-oh.
What's coming is serious.
♪
Farcante.
I think that means "cannonball
of goodness" in French,
because it's a big, heavy,
albeit yet thoroughly
delicious loaf of potato,
bacon, dried fruit, and cream
slowly steamed in a bain-marie.
♪
This meal is a foreshadowing
of the kind of light spa food
that will become a regular
feature of our time in the Alps.
- Whoa.
We have to finish that.
It's like a...
It's like a volcano.
Look at this.
You can put the dried
apricots or plums as well.
So, it's a bit sweet and salty.
It's...
It's very good.
It's really good.
♪
You put that on a "Man versus
Food," food wins.
Can Eric Ripert eat
the entire farcante in one hour?
If you can save the world,
could you eat that?
No, if you could save a puppy,
- To save a puppy? Yeah.
- The whole thing.
You'd eat the whole thing
to save a puppy?
Yeah.
Get me a puppy.
♪
Ah, nature,
the rustic charms of the farm,
proximity to one's ingredients,
the smell of fresh grass,
manure, livestock.
I love it.
No, actually, that's Eric.
I didn't mean to be
presumptuous,
but last night after dinner,
I went back to my room,
and I whipped up
a little pâté for us.
Yes, of course.
I thought the croûte came out
pretty well, don't you think?
- Yep.
- I mean, not bad for
a little microwave in my room.
With some Génépi.
Because I know you're a man
of expensive tastes,
I foraged for truffles
this morning.
I rented a truffle-seeking pig
and managed to dig this guy up.
That's pretty nice.
Perhaps you want to do the
honors? The...
- Yeah.
- Wow, look at that knife work.
You should be a chef.
A nice cheese selection
from this very farm.
- Yes, I guess.
- The process that we will be
helping along today.
I'm excited about that
as an experience.
I mean, everything is
an experience today.
So is a colonoscopy, but...
So you ever milked a cow before?
I loved going to the farm
when I was a kid.
- Yeah?
- They, like, they had 20 cows.
In the farming community
in which you grew up,
did kids at school
ever brag about sort of...
I don't know how you describe
this for a family audience...
But inappropriate
contact with...
- No.
- With farm animals?
- Really? Never?
- No.
- So if I made, like,
a grass smoothie and poured
it on your crotch,
I think it would be
pretty funny.
- It wouldn't.
- If no one was watching.
Yeah, no one is watching.
This scene is gone.
This scene doesn't exist.
Don't do that while
I'm milking you, man.
She's like...
Now, the milking thing, I...
I have some concerns.
I'm afraid.
- Are you?
- I'm a little afraid.
I... I think they sense that I,
you know, my Jersey roots
as opposed to, you know,
your country ass, you know?
They know you; they recognize
you as one of theirs.
Hello, Nadine. Huh?
You don't like Tony, huh?
Don't let him do it.
Kick him in the balls.
♪
I give you $1,000 cash
if you can get
some milk out of this cow.
You'll give me a 1,000 bucks?
Okay, now we're
talking, my friend.
Yeah.
Show me how it's done, farm boy.
- Oh, he's gonna show us.
- Okay.
Okay, I can do that.
You see how he does?
I think so. Okay.
- Okay?
- You first.
Okay.
Oh, there you go.
We should be playing,
like, some '70s music, you know.
♪ Un-chicka-un-chicka-un
Okay, save some for me.
Come on, man, that's my $1,000
going in that pail.
- Okay, your turn.
- All right.
Watch how it's done.
Yeah. Jeez, I'm telling you.
- Go ahead.
- Okay. Oh, it's soft.
Hey, what's that called?
That's called $1,000, my friend.
Oh, that's strangely satisfying.
That's my grand.
I feel like a... a champion.
You don't want to do
a goat, huh?
So to speak.
I mean, yes.
I think we learned
something here today.
Yeah. Do it quickly.
♪
Cheese. Don't get me wrong.
I love cheese. I adore it.
But it's day
three of nonstop cheese,
and we haven't even
scratched the surface
of the many wondrous
specialties of the region.
Hotel Du Buet has been
around for many years.
One comes here for the cheese.
In this case,
the iconic raclette,
and the equally iconic fondue.
Hello, can I have
a drink with you?
Please.
Cheers.
Marianne Chanel and her siblings
are the third generation
of her family to run this place.
So this is a fa...
A family business?
- Yes.
- For how many years?
- Soon 130 years.
- 130 years?
So, in the family,
the whole time?
Yes, it's my great granddad.
Great grandfather?
So, you're gonna have
to help us.
I explain.
Finally, raclette.
I've been waiting for this.
I know.
Would you like it direct
on your potatoes?
Please. Oh, it bubbles.
- Yeah.
- I cut with this part.
♪
Oh, man, yeah. That's... whoa.
- Yeah, man, go for it.
- You wanna try?
No, no, go... go for it, big
boy.
All right. Here we go.
Okay.
Uh... is there a future for him
in the restaurant business?
I'm not so sure.
Normal humans do not usually
follow
multiple wads of oozing cheese
melted over potatoes with a
molten pot of more cheese.
So, you excited?
Finally, your fondue?
Yeah.
But we are no ordinary men.
We are Titans. We are Centurions
of dairy products.
- See the fondue?
- Okay, let's do the fondue.
- Do some eights slowly.
- Figure eight.
Eight on the bottom.
You touch the bottom.
But not too... tong,
tong, tong, like this.
Yes, yes, yes.
- Oh, man, that's good.
- That's what I said.
When you do that
to the end of the fondue...
- Right.
- The fondue's perfect.
You know, you should know
he bet me...
He bet me $1,000 today
that I could not milk a cow.
- And you do?
- I did.
- Yeah.
- Victory.
Look, I know what to do
with a cow.
I know what you do is,
you gonna...
You put it in your fridge.
Exactly, right, right.
You are so sweet.
How can you do it?
Can I do what?
I mean, to be surrounded by
so much of this great cheese.
Well, we ate about
a pound of cheese each.
You're gonna have
a big cannonball of crap
lodged up your butt
like a baby head.
The size
of a freaking baby head.
You will understand
the agony of delivery.
We are not leaving this table...
Well, we are, because
there's a bunch of drunk,
horny mountaineers
coming in later.
Oh, we're gonna party
with them, happily.
No, because I believe there
might be yodeling involved.
- My God.
- I'm not worried about it.
I'll be fine.
Oh, whoa, whoa, watch this.
Okay, here goes the egg.
Oh, now we're getting serious.
- Can I try?
- Yup.
- Oh, man, that's good.
- It's different, huh?
- Totally.
- Oh, appreciate it.
♪
- Holy Christ.
- What?
It's flat;
we haven't started yet.
Why do people do this?
You do that to stay in shape,
to enjoy nature.
- This is not a sport.
- Not a sport, man.
- This is a death sentence.
- We came from New York.
Look at the difference.
It's so peaceful.
You can go do this
is Central Park.
Yeah, you can do that
in Central Park.
- But, why would you?
- Ah, for fun.
This is for fun.
We're doing that for fun, Tony.
This is fun
like chlamydia is fun.
We haven't even started
to go up.
Okay, now, that's...
That's doing it exercise.
♪
Oh, hell.
Every chef needs a mentor.
In the life and career
of Eric Ripert,
it was Maurice Guillot
who filled that role,
who took a young,
fresh-faced cook
from the mean streets of Antibes
and turned him into the hardened
professional he is today.
Breakfast.
Bonjour.
- Bonjour.
They said they'd cook lunch,
which sounded like a sweet deal
considering what's on the menu.
Ahh.
Cheers.
Start with heaping spoons full
of the finest osetra caviar.
So, when you were from the east,
on a scale of 1 to 10,
how good are...
- Minus 2.
- Minus 2,
and you only ended up
in the kitchen
because you were
such a shit waiter, right?
Yeah, no, but I wanted
to be in the kitchen.
After graduation,
I was in Paris with my suitcase.
I was 17 years old,
and then I see that guy.
Maybe some asparagus,
upon which one nestles
a poached egg,
a freshly frothed zabaione,
and an obscenely generous pile
of black truffle shavings.
I actually... I like
a little zabaione.
Egg on egg, man.
Nothing beats it.
Ridiculous.
I don't know why people
mistake me for you.
Because they see us
on TV together.
We both have the white hair,
and people can say,
"Oh, I love your restaurant;
it's so good, Le Bernardin.
"Le Bernardin,
I love your restaurant.
It's great, the fish,
it's wonderful."
You know what I always say?
No, I always say, you know,
"Can you believe
all our fish is frozen."
No, he does.
He's not joking.
Steak au poivre with some
fresh morel and new potatoes.
So what was 32 yolks again?
What was the... that's the recipe?
Yeah, for the hollandaise.
For his hollandaise.
32... 32 yolks.
Yeah, to make the
hollandaise for him.
- No, it's an excellent book.
- Thank you, Tony.
My favorite part is
when you're in prison
in the south of France.
They force him to bite the heads
off live chickens
for the amusement
of the other convicts.
- We did...
- That was a good scene,
or was that "Midnight Express?"
I forget.
It was "Midnight Express."
♪
How many years
did you guys work together?
Actually, a long time.
From day one of my career,
to when I left to America.
Very long time.
Why did you go to America and
leave your ancestral home land?
Robichon sent me to America.
I wanted to go to Brazil,
and then he looked at me
and smiled and he said,
"Uh, I can't send you to Brazil.
You're not gonna cook
anything there."
- Right.
- Actually, Robichon helped me
to come to America.
He found me the job.
♪
Yeah, what would you have been
if you'd failed as a...
As an aspiring chef?
What was your fallback position?
I wanted to be a forest ranger.
- Forest ranger?
- Yeah.
Why? You like nature
or something?
- Yeah.
- What was it, the uniform?
You like the uniform?
The shorts... they get shorts,
and a little hat
like Smokey the Bear.
♪
But you're not
an outdoorsman at all.
- What do you mean?
- You don't fish.
No, because I don't
wanna catch fish.
We'll leave that where it is.
You've probably killed more
fish over the telephone than...
A good fisherman.
They are dead already.
No, they kill them for you.
Don't say that.
You're like Scarface.
Don't say that or I give you
a lot of salad.
Oh.
♪
These mountains
are majestic and beautiful.
You can walk them, take pictures
of them.
You can ski down them.
They can also kill you.
♪
So when shit gets bad,
and you find yourself
a tangle of busted bones
and torn flesh,
having slid off
a lonely, high-altitude piece,
it's people like Laurent
Langoisseur
of La Compagnie du Mont-Blanc
who come and save you.
Sonia Popoff works for Peloton
de Gendarmerie
de Haute Montagne.
She's who you call
when things are really bad.
This was Eric's life dream
as a young man, to be a...
- Yeah.
- A park ranger up in the Alps,
or in the mountains; this is
what he wanted to do as a...
- I wanted to be...
- As a young man.
- I wanted to be you.
- Let's face it.
Your career as a chef is coming
to a... coming to an end.
You just turned 52.
Is it too late for him to start?
Oh, that's not a good sign.
I don't know how to say it.
It's, "Sorry, Pops."
I am in better shape
than you to do it.
That's for sure.
Yeah.
- And I don't want to be mean.
- I'm not doing it.
♪
So what's
the most common injury?
So, a lot of knee and shoulders,
dislocated shoulders.
- Head injuries.
- Concussion?
- Concussion.
- Yes.
I mean, I noticed,
you know, there's a bar here.
I mean, do... how stupid
do people get on the mountain?
You would be very surprised.
We see people not trained,
not well-equipped,
following, like, ski tracks
to get them to crevasses,
glaciers, cracks.
Right. So, if he drinks
two bottles of Génépi,
and he goes off piece...
And falls into a crevasse...
Ahh!
Dislocates his shoulder...
Augh!
Breaks his knee...
Ahh!
And...
- Why me?
- Has a concussion...
This is a hypothetical question.
Okay, okay.
So, okay,
hypothermia is setting in.
Your ACL and your meniscus
are both completely shredded,
And your all messed up
from a concussion...
What is the thing I...
I should do?
Should I ski to the bottom
and talk to someone?
- Yeah.
- Like, call my cell phone?
First I'd call
the production company
and tell them we need somebody
else for the rest of the show.
He's such a nice guy.
To answer your question there,
there is something today
we use more and more
on the people's cell phones.
Oh, find my phone.
- Find my corpse.
- Find my phone.
And just ask the people,
"Okay go back to your phone,
"and there's a GPS inside it,
and it tells us
exactly where to find you."
Avalanches happen here
frequently.
Laurent and his rescue squads
are here to prevent them
before they occur if possible,
and if not, to find you,
and dig you out.
Allow us to demonstrate.
We bury our local contact,
Bullet, under the snow.
Search dogs, hopefully,
will find him
before he becomes a corpsicle
and our production insurance
becomes unsustainably expensive.
♪
So, how common are avalanche?
Where are they most
likely to... to happen?
Anywhere but the ski resorts.
Mostly the avalanches that kills
people is not into a ski resort.
It's...
Outside.
Outside the boundaries.
Now, here's a question.
Ugh, great.
So, Eric's come back after
he's recovered
from his injuries,
and he decides
to go mountain climbing.
And he gets drunk again.
Something happened to me,
you're gonna remember,
I'll tell you that.
And he climbs the mountain.
Ahh!
And he gets buried
in this avalanche.
And he's buried in the snow.
What happens then?
Or, do you just say,
"Eh, see you in the summer."
Well, first you have
to find the location,
the whole location, and then we
have a Tran signal locator
like this one, as an example.
Something like this.
- Yes.
- And when you are caught
in the avalanche...
They look for it.
The rest of teams keep a tool
working with the same one,
and then they can find a signal,
and then they start digging.
How long can you live
under the snow? If it's not...
You have three minutes.
Three minutes for...
Three minutes if you can press.
- Right.
- But sometimes, you have
a little place for breathing.
- A little room?
- Yes,
and you can survive
a half an hour, one hour.
So I shouldn't give up too soon.
Yes.
♪
So, why did you choose
such a dangerous
and difficult area of medicine?
I mean, you could have
a nice practice in Paris,
got, you know,
people have headaches.
It's difficult to explain.
♪
Yes, I know it's very dangerous,
but, I think,
"I have to continue;
I have to stop."
I... I continue.
♪
I'm not sure why I do it, but
I know it makes me alive, so...
it's good.
But you like it.
- I do like it.
- Yeah, right?
♪
You don't think about that.
You don't know why,
but you do it.
Mm-hmm.
That's called compassion.
♪
Le France, I love it, and God
knows I love the cheese here,
but a brief respite is needed
from the torrent
of dairy products.
Perhaps, I thought, the short
hop across the border to Italy,
would be a good idea.
I want pasta.
Maison Recettes has a long
and storied history here
in the Aosta Valley.
Our host Jean-Honore Cristie
grew up in the region.
I love it here.
I'm so happy to be in Italy.
I... I feel
a little treacherous,
just denying my own roots,
because I have zero Italian
heritage as far as I know,
zero, but I... I just love
this lifestyle,
this food; it's just great.
- Well, cheers.
- All right.
- Cheers.
- To... to Italy.
Slainte.
♪
After you.
I will definitely have
some of that.
This is even some homemade,
I like it.
Oh, interesting.
And this is a gift from me.
This is chamois that have... this
year.
Uh-huh.
And I have done dried meat
with the leg of the chomois.
♪
Okay, more cheese,
but it's a delicious order
of gnocchi
with beet moot fondue.
This is great.
We're doing prognil again?
We should have a camera
in your colon.
♪
Ravioli with tomato sauce.
Oh, man.
I know you were excited
about it, right?
So you like pasta?
Oh, I love it.
He has been whining for a week.
A creamy polenta
with braised beef.
- Okay.
- Oh, now, that's...
That's exciting.
Carbonada, one of the best you
can find here in most of Italy.
- Which meat is this one?
- Beef.
- Beef?
- Yeah.
You remember our friend,
the cow?
Yes, yesterday. She was cute.
Did you see the connection
between her and I yesterday?
She was...
Yeah, she had her
nose right in your crotch.
So, what is this game
we're gonna play today?
Oh, it's called the feur lane.
- Feur lane?
- Feur lane.
This game is
difficult to describe.
I gather the idea is,
you try to hit
that tiny polished stone
with that stick
as far as you can.
I do not think I can do that.
Oh, man.
Ohhhh...
I can't do that.
He wants us to hit it
as far as he can.
Exactly. It's really simple.
This looks hard.
♪
You have to lick the stone.
Did you see?
They lick the stone
so it sticks to the big stone.
Ooh, this one is good.
Yeah.
Whew.
♪
I'll tell you this,
it's better than golf.
So, you don't love golf?
I hate golf.
- I wanna try.
- Okay.
I wanna try one, yeah,
I wanna do it one time.
So, I, I'll bet you $1,000...
- $1,000?
- $1,000 you can't get it
across the one.
I'm fine; I have nothing to
lose.
- Well, yeah, $1,000.
- No.
♪
Well, you're out, man.
No, three times.
♪
Whoa.
Oh.
Oh, jeez.
♪
No, it's like watching a monkey
try to, like, work a typewriter.
Look, I don't even know
why you would even...
Shh. Silent, please.
Oh, jeez.
♪
Whoa!
Viva Italia!
Congratulations. No, no, man.
No, it was a miracle,
and I'm proud of you.
Congratulations.
♪
I think that's called
a foul ball.
You have to think positive.
How lucky you are to be
in the Alps...
On a beautiful day.
I'm lucky to not actively be
throwing up on myself right now.
You know, you have to enjoy the
little things in life, right?
I do.
I mean, this is
a special moment.
I do.
I will enjoy the minute I
don't have to do this anymore.
Oh, come on, man.
♪
- So here's the plot.
- Yeah.
Okay, it's "64 Yolks: The
Revenge."
- "64"...
- It's about a chef...
- Yeah.
- Named Eric Ripert,
who runs a three-star
Mishnah in New York,
played by Bruce Willis,
but what...
Oh, I'm played by,
okay, I like that. Bruce Willis.
Okay, so Willis, playing you,
goes out of the dining room,
visiting the table,
overhears a conversation.
- And then?
- Car chases, violence,
big fight in the kitchen
at Le Bernardin.
We could shoot it there; I'm
sure it won't interrupt service.
♪
Holy cow.
Oh.
It's unbelievable.
I mean, nothing is more
beautiful than that.
♪
Come in my selfie.
Oh, it's a video; hold on.
Look at him.
Yeah, yeah, you should
do something like that.
- Oh, no, I don't like this.
- Wow, I love it.
Oh, no, no.
Oh, jeez.
No one's ever gone through?
Whoa!
I'm telling you, I'd feel
a lot more comfortable
if you hadn't had
two portions of eggs.
This is amazing.
♪
And when you kill people in
the film, you always have, like,
some little catch phrase
to do with food.
Like, bang, "Check please."
Or, "How'd you like your
dessert?"
You gotta start practicing.
You gotta take your sunglasses
off like David Caruso
and guttle gight.
"Dinner is served."
- I go like that?
- Yeah, you gotta put it over...
Take 'em off; take 'em off.
Okay.
- Dinner...
- I look at them now?
- Is served.
- Yeah.
No, you gotta look... say...
Pretend I'm bleeding...
I'm bleeding out on the ground.
Yeah, okay, okay, okay, fine.
Ahh, okay, okay.
So, you have to put 'em off,
and then on.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Dinner is served.
But you've gotta put
the sunglasses on.
- Oh, okay.
- It's called acting.
That's David Caruso.
Oh, shit, okay.
Jesus.
♪
In a world
where the price of dinner,
could be your life,
one man, one chef
stands alone.
Ben, pickup.
♪
He just wanted to cook...
Ugh!
But they wouldn't let him.
Augh!
Eric Ripert is back
in his own hell-raising...
Ahh!
Bone-crushing...
ass-kicking true story.
Dinner is served.
"32 Yolks to Slaughter."
Not coming soon
to a theater near you.