Beautiful, right?
We can already indulge ourselves
into something special,
such a beautiful day.
Pony ride.
Absolutely.
Now we are coming to your most
beautiful fascination side of
Russian legacy, the
forest of birch.
Ah, what a place.
♪
All hail, the maximum leader.
Now let's dance.
♪
Okay.
Thank you.
Well.
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la la
whatever you think of this
guy, his dead, affectless eyes,
his smooth pulled tight like a
snare drum face, he
ain't going anywhere.
Look at him.
He's the Russian Superman, the
KGB middle manager desk jockey
turned expression of greater
Russia's hopes and dreams.
He lets no opportunity to take
his shirt off pass him by, pose
with a large gun, he's there.
And no matter how transparently
autocratic, vengeful, oblivious
to even a thin veneer of
democracy, Russians love him.
They seem to feel about him like
new yorkers used to
feel about Giuliani.
He may be a son of a [
expletive ] But he's our son
of a [ Expletive ].
It's February 2014, and the
Sochi Olympics are just coming
up when I arrive in Moscow.
It's a different Moscow
every time I come here.
The '80s style go-go capitalist
conspicuous consumption see who
can spend the most money
disco-techno thing that I saw
when I first came here in 2001,
it's still going strong.
In fact, these days, Moscow
has one of the highest
concentrations of
billionaires in the world.
But as never before, its
imperial Russia now, a one-man
rule.
All power emanates, every
decision must consider this guy.
♪
Russia is full of characters
with murky pasts and
shadowy connections.
One of them I' called a friend
for more than a decade.
Tony!
Wow.
Zamir.
Now, my concern is back in the
day, this place was famous for
all of the rooms were bugged.
Not anymore, I'm sorry.
Oh, really?
I'm really sorry about that.
Times change.
My long-time crony tries at
least to be diplomatic
about these things.
I mean, he's got to
live here, right?
He doesn't want problems
with his blintzes.
The forward-thinking Russia,
they removed the
surveillance devices?
Listen, as a born Muscovite,
I'm trying to be a good patron.
I really want you to tell me
frankly a week from now, Zamir,
now I understand why stereotypes
sometimes send a bad
message about Russia.
I have an open mind.
Everything's great.
Russians have
everything they want.
Listen.
Why don't we just taste.
Oh, thank you.
The most gorgeous
women are in Russia.
Welcome to Russia.
I'm trying to be kind of sober.
United we stand.
I prepared the special for you.
Russian tapas.
With small pancakes
like blinis and caviar.
All this cocoon with honey.
This is Baltic sprouts.
Thank you.
I'm hitting the
caviar and the blini.
Oy-yoy-yoy.
Maybe some more vodka.
Thank you.
And your smile makes it
feel like it's water.
What do you think?
What is the perception of Mr.
Putin these days, after
14 years he's in power?
My perception?
You really want to hear it?
I'm not sure, but let's see.
A former midlevel manager in
a large corporation, short, I
think that's very important,
short, who has found himself
master of the universe and like
a lot of short people, if you
tick them off, bad
things happen to you.
He likes to take his
shirt off a lot.
Let's be serious.
He strikes me as a businessman.
He is.
A businessman with an ego.
Okay.
So he's like Donald
Trump but shorter.
I think my friend needs
some kind of booze.
To you, comrade.
Like this, you know.
You can have that one.
I'll get the other two.
I'm serious about your
one week stay in Russia.
I want you to enjoy
every minute of it.
I hope you'll get something new,
positive to learn and
share around the world.
That's my mission.
♪
Okay, Tony, so being part
of the opposition rally.
This is nothing new for me.
Strike against the empire.
I go way back on this.
I marched on the Pentagon
with my dad when I was a kid.
Seriously.
Yep.
So you are well prepared.
It is physical and brutal today.
I don't know.
My day as a dissident
may be over quickly.
There is opposition to Putin
but it's a mixed bag.
If you do see a demonstration
like this one, it is with
permission along a planned
route, carefully managed and the
cops and security tend to
outnumber the demonstrators.
The main topic of this rally
is to support the
political prisoners.
Last may when they came to
protest against Putin's
re-election, which
allegedly was...
The election results were,
shall we say, dubious.
Some of them were arrested
and put in prison and some
of them are still there.
Divide and conquer?
Well, look who showed up today.
Everybody from human rights
activists to ultra right wing
nationalists who think
Putin has been too soft.
Putin is not right
wing enough for them.
No.
He's like a liberal to them.
He doesn't refuse
immigrant workers.
I'm kind of shocked shees
these guys are at the same
demonstration.
Russians are not united
against one political agenda.
It's general unhappiness
with Putin.
That's it.
♪
Bad things seem to happen to
critics of Vladimir Putin.
Journalists, activists, even
powerful oligarchs once
seemingly untouchable are now
fair game if they
displease the leader.
So we were supposed to be dining
at another restaurant this
evening and when they heard that
you would be joining
me, we were uninvited.
Should I be concerned about
having dinner with you?
This is a country of corruption.
If you have business, you are in
a very unsafe situation.
Everybody can press you and
destroy your business.
That's it.
This is a system.
Meet Boris Nemsaw.
He was deputy prime minister
under Yeltsin and today is one
of Putin's most vocal critics.
This restaurant was kind enough
to take us in but the chef is a
Brit so maybe he has
less reason to worry.
First course, gentlemen?
At Yornick restaurant they
are serving their own versions
of Dino-era Russian classics.
A modern riff on borscht,
typically a hearty cabbage broth
with meat, here's a puree with a
more elegant shall we say
deconstructed presentation.
Critics of the government,
critics of Putin, bad things
seem to happen to them.
Yes.
Unfortunately, existing power
represent what I say Russia old
19th century, not of 21st.
Critics of Putin, beware.
Oligarch Kolikofsky accused
Putin of corruption and spent
ten years in prison
and labor camps.
Alexander Litvinenko accused
state security services of
organizing a coup to
put Putin in power.
He was poisoned by a lethal dose
of radioactive polonium and
Viktor Yushenko poisoned,
disfigured and nearly killed
by a toxic dose of dioxin.
I'm not saying official Russian
bodies had anything to do with
it but it's mighty suspicious.
I don't think you need to be a
conspiracy theorist to say
whoever did this very much
wanted everyone to
know who done it.
Everybody understands.
Of course.
Everybody is meant
to understand.
Everybody understands.
Everybody understands
everything in this country.
When you're talking classic
conspiracy theories and
classically Russian style
paranoia, you want some classic
Russian food to
go along with it.
Pelmini, minced meat dumplings
served on a pillow of
cabbage with sour cream.
Mh.
Very good.
Maybe the most extreme and
visible example of how things
seem to work here is
the Sochi Olympics.
If you look at the map of
Russian Federation, it's
difficult to find a sport
without knowing... but Putin
did.
It seems like a pretty obvious
question, if you wanted
to hold a winter Olympics in
Miami, presumably someone would
say isn't it a
little warm there.
This is absolutely
personal Putin project.
They spent more than $50 billion
of dollars, which is the most
expensive games of mankind.
$26,000 a seat for
the curling stadium?
To build?
The road is 30 miles.
Price for that, $9 billion U.S.
This is a road, right?
It's three times expensive than
American program flying to Mars.
And who got many of those
contracts for the roads and
stadiums and infrastructure?
Well, there's these guys.
Putin's childhood friends and
judo partners, the Rottenburg
brothers, whose companies
received contracts worth
upwards of $7 billion.
And Putin's associate of 20
years, Vladimir Yakunin, who
owns the state railroads.
His company received $10
billion worth of contracts.
It's very easy to imagine
what's happened with this money.
Right.
You know who cares in Russia?
Just about no one.
This is a case of
the Binenko case.
A known enemy of Putin stricken
with a bout of
radioactive polonium.
Aren't you concerned?
Me, about myself?
Yeah.
You're a pain in the ass.
Tony, I was born
here 54 years ago.
This is my country.
The Russian people
are in trouble.
Russian court doesn't work.
Russian education
decline every year.
I believe that Russia has
a chance to be free.
Has a chance.
It's difficult but
we must do it.
America, yeah.
All of Russia's
eyes are upon you.
Bring honor to your... you
know what, America, I
will break you.
I will break you.
Forget about it.
I'll bury you.
I'll rip up your visa!
No!
O'er the land of the free.
Just missed it, buddy.
That was pretty close.
I was actually out here all
last night practicing.
I'm kidding.
While Zamir contemplates a
suddenly grimmer future thanks
to me, I head out to Rublevka, a
compound of luxury homes outside
Moscow, to meet
Alexander Levedu.
At one time, Alexander
was doing great.
Former officer of the
intelligence services like
Putin, turned billionaire.
He owned pieces of Russia's most
powerful energy companies,
airlines and banks, and still
publishes one of the only
opposition newspapers
left in Russia.
But running a newspaper that's
been harshly critical of
the ruler has cost him.
He's been stripped of
nearly everything.
It can be a dangerous thing to
do investigative journalism
in this country.
Your own paper, five
journalists, six lost their
lives?
Yeah.
Probably the biggest number
because there was no war in this
country, so in peaceful times,
to lose six journalists
killed is quite a lot.
Six journalists
murdered, one paper.
Presumably for their reporting
on political corruption
or human rights abuse.
Though pointing a finger
directly at the government is
impossible, one can say that the
climate here is such that what
you say can certainly
get you killed.
You have at various stages made
life difficult for yourself.
Business was very good for you,
then you had to have an opinion.
When you interact with the
local bureaucracies and judicial
system, it still leaves a lot to
be desired, let's
put it this way.
Levedev is now a potato farmer.
That's my production.
That's my potato.
The biggest producer in Russia,
true, but his billions
are gone.
He now lives the life
of a mere millionaire.
Let's see how you like this one.
Very good.
Some freshly made potato chips
that Levedev is very proud of.
And his personal chef prepares
Scottish salmon, smoked on
cherry tree sawdust
served with avocado.
Mm.
Very good.
Lately, he is getting
into slow food.
This is cold pressed
cedar tree in Siberia.
Cedar oil?
But he has not slowed down his
profile or kept his mouth shut.
Recently, in a Russian talk
show, he got in an argument over
the financial crisis with
another guest, a heated
argument.
He ended up smacking the guy.
I saw the incident on television
that got you in trouble.
I found it very refreshing,
actually, something that
political discourse
could use more of.
The government took the
opportunity to charge him with
politically motivated
hooliganism, a charge that could
have resulted in a penalty
of five years in prison.
He is instead been
convicted of battery.
He is working off his sentence
painting fences and
shoveling snow.
I mean, sitting on a bench
and expecting to spend the next
five years in prison with two
small kids, it's not always, you
know, very nice, but the guy
said something very bad.
He said those who don't have a
billion go [ Muted ] themselves.
Though his victim did not
register an official complaint,
the message I think was clear.
The charges were pressed by
the Russian state which is funny
because this is a
private accusation.
It's dangerous, very
dangerous, to criticize or
investigate or speculate.
Why?
Why do you care?
Do you really think you
can defeat it, no.
Hopefully, reason will prevail.
♪
It's the KGB.
They're blocking your signal.
I'm sure that they are,
believe it or not.
I'm quite sure you've had
someone on your tail the
entire time you've been here.
What's rock and roll supposed
to be about other than cars
and girls and aggression?
About dissent.
About rebellion, right?
In Russia, where everything is
supposed to be just fine, that
can be a dangerous position.
Travis link is an ex-pat
American that manages
this band, Luna.
Ruben Kazarian is Luna's
guitarist and song writer.
It's very nice, we have
elections, democracy, courts,
but always doesn't
work as it should.
So that prevents right now
in Russia to speak freely.
Formerly nothing but in
reality, a lot of things.
Let's talk about MTV.
Rebel music as I understand it
was an MTV music series whose
fundamental principle was
to celebrate bands who say
difficult things in environments
where there might be
repercussions.
And as I understand it, your
band was chosen for one
of seven episodes.
Correct.
And in fact, one of your
songs was used as the title
track for the series.
So I get a letter from the
producer and essentially it says
because of political pressure,
the Russia episode has been
removed from the
rebel music series.
According to the producer,
MTV Russia pushed back on the
content, she presumes because of
the negative impact it would
have on them and their ability
to do business on a
day-to-day basis in Russia.
MTV's official reason for
removing Luna from the series is
that they simply did not have
enough time to air all
the stories they filmed.
This was a documentary series
about musicians standing up and
risking their lives in some
cases to stand up against
government abuse of power,
government corruption, and yet,
a foreign government was able to
editorially control what
American viewers see
on their TV screens.
That to me is a scandal
of epic proportion.
This entire documentary's gone.
Luna's song is the title track
to the series, but their
episode never happened.
The rest of Russia is very
very different than Moscow.
Here, you drive around it's like
Bentley, Ferrari, Maserati.
You go to buy a pair of shoes,
you pick up a Bentley
on the way out.
You tour a lot in Russia.
What do you see?
We see a lot of problems.
We see the level of
believing is very low.
There is something in music
that unites everybody.
It's something beyond politics.
It's certain energy and this
energy is the same in every
country, in every city.
We have rock music, we
have common people.
We're like you.
♪
I'm going to the hometown
of president Putin.
St. Petersburg.
He was born there,
started his career.
The night train to St.
Petersburg is one of the great
fun things to do in Russia.
Roll on great steel wheels
through the night, through dark
forests of birch and snow.
Out there in the dark, visible
for a second or two at a time,
the real Russia, the one
most Russians live in.
So Tony, time to enjoy life.
The gentle chicken meat.
I need something gentle, Tony.
The seat cushion
and ratatouille.
May I propose a toast?
To gentle chicken meats.
Pro tip.
If the word gentle is used on a
menu, avoid those items and
stick to the classics.
Like blini with caviar and cold
pickled herring and potatoes and
soup of sturnlgen,
olives and lemon.
Is health care free
anymore in this country?
Officially, it is free but if
you want to get operation within
a month, and you can't wait, you
won't get it because
long line of those.
How about education?
Up to the high school,
it's still free.
The quality's not best
as it used to be.
People used to get a lot
of things for free.
Now it's coming to an end.
You asked for capitalism,
you got it, buddy.
According to Reaganomics it's
the trickle-down theory.
That means if I make lots and
lots and lots and lots of money,
money will somehow
trickle down to you.
You know, my masseur, my garage
attendant, my aroma therapist.
They of course will
be making money.
I will be buying more things for
various wives and prostitutes.
In this way I don't exactly
share the wealth but I trickle
it down and if you
don't like your job...
What can you do then?
Cleaning up for my dead
prostitutes, you can leave your
job at Walmart and become
a billionaire like me.
Or you go on a reality show and
become really really rich.
Doing nothing.
It's fantastic.
Tony, I'm convinced.
I think you know what you
are doing in life, man.
♪
Did you put on your jammies?
Uh-huh.
I just want to state for the
record, just because you were in
the top bunk, that's no
indication of any relationship
that we may or may not have.
You and me are very
careful in public.
If we bring up subject like
this, there could be some
different repercussions.
Tolerance never
existed in Russia.
That's why when just recently
people started to come out in
Russia, like lesbians and gays,
they were either fired from
their jobs or were given
like hard time to exist.
What about Tchaikovsky?
They try not to acknowledge
it by saying he was a great
musician, so... he was
a great musician who
liked to have sex
with other men.
That's what people are not
meant to learn in school.
♪
That's the former palace?
You remember what happened
in October of 1917?
Everybody came charging
through, charged up the steps
and looted the palace.
And he had to put on his
female outfit to escape the
revolutionary peasants.
That wouldn't go over
well these days.
Not anymore.
Recently in the run-up to the
Sochi Olympics, attention has
been drawn to a wave of rabidly
homophobic remarks
by public officials.
Images of gay and lesbian
activists being beaten and
harassed in the street, often
with official or
semi-official consent.
And a new law which claims to
forbid promoting homosexual
propaganda to minors but which
could be interpreted any way
the authorities choose.
What's happening here?
What's going on?
Oh, my god.
I don't know what's going on.
Every day, I ask myself what's
going on, what's going on.
Do you have to be afraid?
No.
I have nothing to lose.
So I can be myself.
I'm nobody in social system.
Artist and film maker Xena
Robrek is a brave young woman.
She's openly gay.
Lately, the actual hunting of
gay people has been documented.
Violent skinhead gangs who
contact gay men and women
online, arrange meetings under
false pretenses, then
violently ambush them.
There have been very
few prosecutions.
You can get killed for this.
Our local fixer, Dasha,
helps translate.
She had a situation once
where the skinheads
attacked her on the street.
Not only once.
This new law prohibits
propaganda?
Amongst minors.
Soviet propaganda, you can
go to jail for anything.
It means whatever
they want it to mean.
Yes.
How many gay families we have
with kids, and those people are
in maximum stress right now
because their families
might be hooligans.
We rightly see this
as outrageous.
The Russian public, however,
it's very likely a vote getter.
A cynical pandering to a
powerful and enduring vein of
deep-seated homophobia
that goes way, way back.
What do you think the
source of this hatred is?
It's not about Russian church.
It's about political structure.
It's about power.
We have two Russias.
Okay.
What are they?
Big like big bear.
Not very sophisticated
but instincts country.
Okay.
And the other side is the
country of intelligent
people, thoughtful people.
A lot of these political
leaders, are they using the
issue of gay rights to
appeal to a larger audience?
They try to play with bear.
Because usually what happens
when you play with the bear is
tomorrow or the next day or the
next day, the bear eats you.
Yeah.
Are you hopeful?
It's about responsibility.
We should never give up.
♪
Farm to table, in Russia?
Organic?
Local?
Why, yes.
There are those who are trying.
Sergei is a very popular
musician and leader of
the band Leningrad.
It was banned in Moscow
purportedly for promoting
alcoholism.
Cheers.
This is Sergei's wife, Matilda.
Together they have opened this
restaurant, Kokoko, with the
mission to bring genuinely
local, quality Russian
food to diners.
We opened this restaurant one
year ago which will work only
with local farmers and we
are the first to do it.
In all of Russia.
Yes, in all of Russia.
Traditional combination, rye
bread and Russian fish.
Chef Igor's version of Sushi.
Instead of rice, more
traditional Russian black bread
with sprouts, mackerel, COD
liver and salmon caviar.
Old school, but
looks new school.
When I first came here 2001,
the best restaurant in Moscow
was a nightmare of French,
Japanese ingredients,
recipes from nowhere.
Everyone hated Russia,
wanted to be someone else.
Lightly smoked raw beef
topped with quail egg.
Very interesting combination.
Very nice.
What's the most popular thing?
What do people want?
The most popular is
Italian-Japanese cuisine.
Sounds like a nightmare.
Cheers.
That was good.
Before Putin, before Gorbachev,
Khrushchev, Stalin and
Lenin, there was this.
Imperial Russia.
Mighty palaces spread across the
empire where the very very few
lived in unimaginable luxury.
While their people
worked and starved.
Didn't work out so
well for Paul, did it?
Not really.
They choked the dude
to death, right?
Actually strangled
with a piece of cord.
The czars of previous centuries
were certainly living
the good life.
Money, no object when it came to
personal comfort or
luxurious lodgings.
And today's imperial powers
seem not far behind.
Putin allegedly had a billion
dollar palace built for him.
We couldn't license the actual
smuggled photo but our artist
rendering looks like this.
A Putin spokesman dismissed all
this, telling the "New York
times" we have congress halls
built for the Kremlin but if you
call all of them Putin's palace,
it is nothing but absurd.
Vodka.
Haven't tasted that before.
So what would I be doing on my
outing if I were a czar,
looking for cool ox to press?
Enjoying life.
Picking up some good speed here.
Oh, okay.
Some suggested that Russia
is, after all this time,
coming full circle.
A tiny, tiny minority in
possession of nearly unlimited
power and wealth.
The idea of running up the steps
and disemboweling royals, I can
easily imagine
myself doing that.
It would not take
much convincing.
Wow.
That's a pleasant surprise.
I would hurl them all
into the sea tomorrow.
After the revolution, in a
blood-forced strategy designed
to even things out, the
government seized private
residences, dividing them into
little pieces and portioning
them out to the masses who were
arriving from the countryside to
serve the new industrialized
Soviet union.
I never had any ideas of growing
up in socialist wonderland.
There was a brief period when I
was a hippie and the idea
of living in a commune, not
attractive to me.
I was born in a communal flat
with three other families,
sharing one John, one kitchen.
No way.
They would treat me
when I had no food.
No way.
I share my toilet with no man.
Take the first left, please.
Meet Uri, human rights
activist, professor of
journalism, one of 26 tenants
living in this communal
apartment.
Just in case you
change your mind...
And it's here that I see for
first time a glimpse of my
friends in the years mysterious
past, growing up in a
home just like this one.
This was normal for
you growing up.
Yeah.
I show you how it workings.
So who decided to moved
into these plays?
Those who were in charge of
the specific communal services
assigned X amount to
this plan, to that plan.
You got to choose your
neighbors though?
No.
I got that.
In the present day Russia
there's never been a reason to
create infrastructure to
make people's lives bet per.
Nobody cared about the people
that they should have a
decent toilet or shower.
How is it lately, letter?
Worse.
So he changed the
whole landscape in the country.
First of all he clamped down
on the Democratic right.
The most recent laws bring up
the old Soviet union type of
structure in the country.
So what happens next?
A year before the
Soviet union collapse, you would
never believe in your wildest
dreams it would happen.
Now it's symbolism, it looks
stable, people are
busy, money is made.
But it can't go on like
this for too long.
So Uri predict we could be in a
similar overnight
collapsing situation.
So there is some hope...
You're due for some major
renovations.
♪
Just another crisp morning in St.
Petersburg.
♪
The river, ice fishing paradise.
I wouldn't go out on that,
not for a million
dollars, man, not now.
It's total unstable.
♪
Lessons of history.
Where are we?
It's used to be a place for
those who are a lit the
executed.
Originally built to defend
the swedes, it was overrun
during the revolution.
So the 100-year anniversary
of what is coming up?
Great October socialist
revolution in three years from
now.
So the disparity gap in the
society, very rich and very
poor, that someone might bring
the masses back to palace and
storm it again, like 100
years, nothing changed.
Every day at noon without
fail this D 30 .122 howitzer is
fired to commemorate
the revolution.
Moment of truth.
♪
Come up.
Enemy is destructed.
Congratulations, you are
the hero of Russia now.
Sweet.
You can't take it on
the plane, though.
You understand.
Not even carry on?
Since the filming of this show a
number of things have happened.
Putin's Sochi Olympics
went off as planned.
Russia won many gold medals,
the most of any country in
competition which was
really all that mattered.
A few journalists complained
about the bathrooms, but
that is all but forgotten.
More than $50 billion of
mostly public money gone.
Ukraine rose up and their
pro-Putin president run away.
Russia, in broad daylight has
recently annexed Crimea and is
massing tens of thousands of
troops on the border of Ukraine.
The world has done nothing.
It will do nothing, as
Vladimir well knew.
He wins again.