I've always wanted to get as
far away as possible from
the place that I was born.
Far both geographically
and spiritually.
To leave it behind.
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good ♪
in this beautiful world
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha-la-la-la
♪ sha-la-la-la-la
Tangier, it's Morocco.
But from 1923 through 1956, it
was loosely governed by the
major powers, an
international zone.
For years it seemed
everything was permitted.
Nothing was forbidden.
At the northern tip of Africa, a
short ferry hop from Spain,
Tangier was a magnet for
writers, remittance men,
spies, and artists.
If you were a bad boy of your
time, you liked drugs, the kind
of sex that was frowned upon at
home and an affordable lifestyle
set against an exotic
background, Tangier was for you.
Matisse, Genest,
William Burroughs.
Many have come this way, staying
a while or hanging around.
But no one stayed longer or
became more associated with
Tangier than the novelist
and composer Paul Bowles.
In works like "the sheltering
sky" he created a romantic
vision of Tangier that persists
even today, a dream that's
become almost inseparable in the
minds of many from reality.
I'm here to find
that dream city.
The place Burroughs
referred to as "Interzone."
♪
Tangier, like I said, was a city
of ex-pats... people with pasts,
people who simply didn't like
where they were and craved
somewhere and something else.
The grand socco is the gateway
to the Medina where you could
find the Casbah, which
means fortress by the way.
The port is to the east, and
right in the middle of it all,
the petit socco, called the last
stop, the meeting place, the
switchboard of Tangier.
Reasons for settling in Tangier
diverge, but everyone sooner or
later since the beginning of
memory comes to cafe Tingis.
Jonathan Dawson came to this
city over 20 years ago as a
journalist, and he never left.
He lives a life not too distant
from Burroughs' fantasy.
Cake and tea at 4:00 every day
served by his man servant.
He may not have a gazelle,
but a pet rooster will do.
And every day he makes the
rounds of the cafes, seeing all
the old faces, ending up
sooner or later here.
This is the petit socco?
This is the petit socco.
Yes.
It existed in venetian times,
existed in Roman times, in the
Portuguese times and the English
were here for 22 years and then
the international city
until 1956, now here.
This is a very historic
scare, very historic.
As a writer, I've noticed
everybody who comes here to do
an article does
the same article.
It is so damn boring.
They're all the beat generation
and there are lots of other
stories in Morocco apart from
that, but everyone
likes the beats.
Bill Burroughs, Tennessee
Williams, they were all here,
but that's a small part
of the Moroccan history.
That's a 15-year page.
There was a life before
that and a life after that.
You're here.
Yeah.
It was inevitable.
Let's pretend those
guys never came.
What is this place?
The reality is, you can
read the story and live it.
People do come here and try to
live it, but they
don't stay very long.
They smoke a little dope, go to
a cheap hotel and go
home with bedbugs.
And a great story.
The attitude here is different
than other parts of
Morocco.
I think they have a higher
tolerance of tradition of
bad or outrageous behavior.
They have a high tolerance
of mad people, you know?
But Moroccans essentially
are very tolerant people.
They quite like madness as well.
They kind of celebrate
that a bit.
You know?
How Moroccan is Tangier?
It's a Moroccan city
with a European outlook.
You can stand up on the
boulevard and see Spain and
Gibraltar and see all sorts of
people passing through, but
it is a Moroccan city.
I'm 62 years old.
I didn't know international days
which finished in 1956, but at
that time, I think Europeans may
have outnumbered Moroccans
in the center of this city.
It's not the case now.
There's very few Europeans
actually living here full time.
The notion of living a life
apart, of being somewhere else,
there are those who
like that feeling.
I like that feeling.
Then there are those who may
live apart, may live somewhere
else, but they're not
entirely comfortable.
It's the difference annoys
them or is a burden.
It did, and it frustrates them.
Some people have to leave
home to find their home.
I'm one of those people.
Whereas I didn't feel at home in
the country I was born in at
all, but here I feel okay.
I feel very, very happy here.
There is indeed something
special about this place.
Burroughs described the native
quarter of Tangier as a maze of
sunless twisting streets
filled with blind alleys.
Its smell was particularly
notable to him, including a mix
of hashish, seared
meat, and sewage.
Tangier, before anything else,
is essentially a port city,
with all the things that
traditionally come
with port cities.
It's situated at the choke point
between the Atlantic ocean
and the Mediterranean sea.
The Moroccan coast is a rich
fishing ground, and a lot of
people make their
living from the sea.
Onshore they use a method called
sentul fishing, where weighted
nets basically drag fish
across the bottom of the sea.
Some of that fish, the good
stuff anyway, ends up here.
The saveur de Poisson, or
restaurant populare or Popeye's.
The place has a lot of names,
but locals and ex-pats alike who
have been coming here for years
say it has some of the
best tagine in town.
Mohammed, the owner and head
chef, is from the nearby rif
mountains, and he sources a lot
of his stuff, his produce and
his Greens, from there, and
he's real proud of them.
The back room is dedicated to
sorting and drying various herbs
which he blends into a secret
mix that he claims has all
sorts of healthful and
boner-inspiring benefits.
If every dish I have been told
over the years would make me
strong worked, I would have a
permanent pup tent going on
down there, so I take all
that with a grain of salt.
Hi.
Hello.
His son Hassan
delivers the food.
It all starts with fresh olives,
they're in season now.
And roasted wall nuts.
Some warm, very good bread.
Squishy.
And you get this stuff.
Everybody gets it.
A pulpy puree of figs, raisins,
strawberries and full of
Mohammed's potent herbs and
spices, of course.
All night, 24 clock.
Yeah, yeah, I get it.
It's supposed to
make me more manly.
You know what?
I'm eating.
Let's not talk about
that, okay, sunshine?
What is a tagine, anyway?
It's a traditional Moroccan stew
that can include
vegetables, meat, or ship.
Tonight, baby shark, calamari
and monk fish with fresh
mountain shin spinach cooked in
a classic Clay pot that
gives it its name.
The domed top is supposed to
force the condensation back in
to the dish and keep
it moist and tender.
That's delicious.
I think it's the Greens and the
aromatics and the herbs, I
have no idea what they are.
Never had anything like it.
Tangier version
of farm to table.
Hi.
Wow.
When's that?
Thank you.
And a whole turbot, brushed with
olive oil, salt, and pepper and
some coriander, then grilled
perfectly over the coals.
Cuddled up next to the
fish, tiny shark kabobs.
Cute.
Wow, spectacular.
Good value.
All of this for 20 bucks?
Pretty good job on Mr. Fish.
That will teach you.
[ Speaking foreign language ]
He's freaking me out.
It's like that guy with, you
know, you're tripping
and does this to you?
For dessert, strawberries,
pine nuts and honey.
Like the whole meal, it's
eccentric and delicious.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
I haven't had so much fruits
and nuts since Altaban.
I told Mick, I said, Mick,
this is a bad crowd.
But he's like, man, we
can't disappoint the fans.
Ah, memories.
In Tangier, I lived in one
room in the native quarter.
I have not taken a bath in a
year nor changed my clothes or
removed them except to stick a
needle every hour in the fibrous
gray wooden flesh of
termal addiction.
I never cleaned or
dusted the room.
Amputee everyone pul boampule
objections and garbage
piled up to the ceiling.
Light and water long since
turned off for nonpayment.
I did absolutely nothing.
I could look at the end of
my shoe for eight hours.
I was only roused to action when
the hourglass of junk ran out."
The words of William Seward
Burroughs, one of my heroes.
He came to Tangier in 1953,
shortly after shooting his wife
to death in a drunken
accident in Mexico City.
He was a heroin addict, a
homosexual, and an inspiration
to those protohipsters who
became known as the beats.
Burroughs, however,
was not a beat Nick.
He was a somewhat stuffy,
well-dressed St. Louis son of a
good family gone wrong.
He was also to my mind the
greatest writer of the
whole damn bunch.
On the road, you can have it.
His classic "naked
lunch" was written here.
A nonlinear, dark, dry humored
searingly critical and satirical
and profane masterpiece.
Burroughs was apparently high
for much of the process on
heroin or locally available
prescription opiate.
And the daily staple in
many of these parts.
Hashish, keef and maldune.
Hashish is the concentrated THC
resin of the cannabis plant as
well as varying amounts of its
flowers and leaves that have
been separated from the buds and
compressed into sheet
or brick-like form.
Keif is the part of the plant
containing only the strongest
concentration of
psychoactive ingredients.
Majune is a confection made from
keef, fruits, nuts,
chocolate and honey.
I was, of course, fascinated by
this product since reading about
it and inquired of some local
contacts who shall
necessarily go unnamed.
How was it made?
This is what I wanted to know.
They were kind enough
to demonstrate.
Keef is first chopped into fine
granules and slowly added to
melted butter and chocolate
over a low heat.
You toast it and release the
psychotropic goodies within.
While the binder element is slow
cooking in the pan, a
combination of spices are
blended with ka shoes, almonds,
walnuts, and dried fruit.
This will be the framework to
suspend the THC-laden
goodness in the next step.
The cannabis-laced butter
chocolate is added along with
plenty of honey to bind
together all the ingredients.
Then mix.
Last, you roll the entirety of
the mixture into a ball and
either refrigerate
or dig right in.
Of course, network standards and
practices prohibit me from even
tasting this delicious and
reportedly mind-altering treat.
I'm guessing, anyway.
So until I see Chris, John and
wolf doing bong riffs in "the
situation room," I will, of
course, abide by these rules
because that's the
kind of guy I am.
There's one particular cafe in
the heart of the Kasbah that's
drawn in foreign dignitaries,
rock stars, aristocrats and
artists since it opened
its doors in 1943.
Cafe Baba.
Sweet mint tea in a thick
slow-moving haze of smoke.
It smells like my
dorm room 1972.
Good evening, hello.
This is George Bajalia and
Zeneb, and I should say right
now that I have no direct
knowledge of either George or
Zaneb smoking any illegal
substances nor do I have at the
recollection of me doing
anything untoward in their
presence because that would
be, like, wrong, dude.
George is here on a Fulbright
scholarship and
Zaneb is an artist.
Others in the room, however,
well, don't give me that
innocent look, you young punks.
I know somebody in here
is smoking reefer.
How stoned are people here?
We can ask, just ask.
You're not getting
totally ripped here?
No.
It's a functional
part of daily life.
For a long time, the rest of the
country and the government
didn't really like
Tangier a whole lot.
It was seedy.
There were foreigners
who came here and...
It makes money.
He sees it as a future
economic super power as I
understand it.
He's talk uging condos,
boutique hotels.
That is good for bad?
For Moroccans, it's work, but
of course ex-pats want to keep
Tangier like they
know it before.
I mean, this cafe is very
similar to the way it was, but
there's a TV right there.
Flat screen.
That's why people come here.
They come to watch soccer games.
You can well imagine the
American guy who's lived in
Tangier for 30 years.
He comes in, there's a flat
screen TV on the wall.
He's like... what?
You've ruined the authenticity
and the integrity, but the
Moroccan guy at the next table
is, like, wait a minute,
asshole, you have a
flat screen TV at home.
I want one, too.
What is wrong with that?
There are people here who
probably have never heard of...
If you follow that, there's no
progression, no
progress, no change.
The thing about cafe Baba,
just sitting here, taking in the
atmosphere, you begin to
appreciate the place.
There's something
different happening here.
Contact high, whoa, I'm hungry.
Wait until the Spanish tortilla
dude across the street
opens for business.
This is Abdileh.
He specializes in making one
thing, and he make it is well.
He makes an omelet.
It's like a Spanish tortilla.
But like stonier.
The potatoes are boiled, diced,
mixed with beaten eggs and
cooked in a cast iron skillet.
Oh, yeah.
The eggs.
The egg man.
I am me and we are you and where
is my omelet, dude,
because I am hungry.
One, two, three?
Abdileh is waiting for you
when you come stumbling
out of cafe Baba.
Coincidence or not?
You be the judge.
Ketchup and mayonnaise.
Everything.
Ketchup and mayonnaise?
Sure.
Why not?
Condiment options I will be hard
pressed to turn down at
this precise moment anyway.
A lot of mayonnaise.
Hmm.
Dude, that's awesome.
I'll have 12 more.
♪
Paul Bowles lived in Tangier
for over 50 years, and Sherry
nutting was part of his inner
circle near the end of his life.
She was his friend, record
keeper of sorts, and
photographer.
You arrived when?
I came in the '70s, but
went down to Marrakesh.
In '86, I wrote a letter to Paul
Bowles and said I had to meet
him and take his picture.
He wrote back and
said, come and visit.
Well, I never left.
A lot of people came here to
live that dream or
to live that life.
Has the reality come to resemble
his perception of the reality?
The Tangier I see
is Paul Bowles.
I still see it.
I still feel it.
You can still find the magic.
The market or souk in Tangier
is one of the best in Morocco.
The vendors are still
pretty impressive.
Wander the markets long enough
and you're sure to stumble
across the unexpected.
Hooves?
Sure.
How about a lamb's head?
Here nothing goes to waste.
Charbroiled to crispy burnt
perfection, it's served
on a crusty lunch bread.
Not so adventurous?
The grand socco's indoor market
offers a variety of smoked,
cured and fresh meat.
Smells good in here.
The stuff looks good.
I've heard this
cheese is amazing.
It's good, yeah.
Could I have one?
A Berber favorite, fresh goat
cheese wrapped in palm leaves.
Yeah, they're
beautiful, aren't they?
It's good.
[ Speaking foreign language ]
A little cheese, a little
flat bread, the perfect
Moroccan breakfast to go.
We're headed into the Ja Bala
foothills in the mountain range
about 80 kilometers of Tangier
to a place called Jajouka.
The village is home to the
people of the Al Sharif tribe,
which loosely translated
means the saintly people.
Jajouka is also home to one
of Morocco's better-known
musicians, Bashir attar.
Jazz and rock and roll musicians
have traveled from all over the
world to Jajouka
to meet this guy.
He's part of a lineage of master
musicians all from this
small mountain village.
♪
Famously dubbed as a
4,000-year-old rock band by
William Burroughs, Bashir, his
son, and these musicians
maintain one of the oldest still
living musical
traditions on earth.
♪
We're invited for dinner.
It's family style, of course,
beginning with braywine, like a
kefta pocket, hand formed
envelopes of dough filled with
seasoned beef baked until golden
and then crisped in oil.
I'm good for now well, one more.
Uh-oh, here we go.
The main event,
tajine of chicken.
Welcome, Tony.
Thank you.
Just gorgeous.
First, chopped onions, garlic,
parsley and turmeric are
blended with olive oil.
The bird is generously
coated and stuffed.
Then after simmering in a touch
of olive oil and water, it is
fried until crispy, served with
roasted almonds and olives,
paprika, and ginger.
Nice.
He smells the food.
Like anywhere else in the
Arab world, eating with your
hands, always the right one, is
proper dining etiquette.
This is spinach.
It's wild spinach.
It grows in the mountains?
Yeah.
Chopped mountain spinach
garlic, cilantro, hot and black
peppers finished with
lemon and olive oil.
That's delicious.
I heard you are the greatest
taste for food in
the world, man.
I love good food.
This is good.
Yeah.
After dinner some fruit, some
mint tea, and let
the music begin.
For centuries, the master
musicians of Jajouka have been
the musical choice of the royal
families of Morocco, excused by
the country's rulers from manual
labor to devote themselves
to musical training.
♪
Their powerful style of Sufi
transmusic has inspired many
music seekers, including most
notably perhaps Paul Bowles, who
wrote about them and recorded
them, and spread the word.
Brian Jones was here and
recorded "the pipes of pan at
Jajouka" with these musicians.
The word spread and the master
musicians have ended up being
featured on albums by Annette
Coleman and the rolling stones.
For years, if you were a rock
god, you had to come here, dig
the crazy percussion, strings,
and pipes that took
you to another place.
It's intricate,
hypnotic, beautiful.
If you're in the right frame
of mind, mesmerizing.
Anyone who comes to Tangier
inevitably ends up lost in
the old part of the city.
The Medina is just what
you want it to be.
The ancient world residing just
next to and around the new one.
You can walk around inside the
movie in your head, play the
bogey character you never were,
all against an all too willing,
all too genuine backdrop.
Ordinarily just about the last
thing in the world I would
be interested in doing is
antiquing, but buried in the
network of twisting narrow
streets of the old city is
boutique Majid
owned by this man.
And he's one interesting guy.
Thank you.
Come in.
When he was a little kid back
in the '60s, Majid left his
hometown of fez and came here
where he would earn money
emptying ashtrays at wild
parties being thrown
here by wealthy ex-pats.
He saw what these people would
buy for themselves and how they
would decorate their homes, and
he started to look around for
himself, scoring, then
reselling art and antiques.
Wow.
It became something
of an obsession.
Now his artifacts from Morocco
and north Africa are bought by
collectors all over the world.
Jewelry and old doors.
Wow, these are
incredibly beautiful.
Tell me about that.
Amber, coral, shells.
These used to be currency.
These shells.
How old is this?
Early '20s.
The Amber is millions
of years old.
How much are you selling it for?
By weight.
Quite heavy piece
this one, 429 grams.
So it comes like 42,000
so that's how much in
dollars?
Almost $5,000.
About $5,000.
Almost.
Should we look at another floor?
Oh, yes, follow me.
There's a nice collection
of things from the Sahara.
So you travel a lot?
Not like you.
Oh, this is for pounding...
Yes, this is from the Gon
tribe.
From Mali.
How much will this
sell for do you think?
Around $300.
Really?
For this?
That's very reasonable.
I'll be buying that.
That's going to
be an old friend.
Also memory.
Also memory of Tangier as well.
Majid suggests lunch at
Andalus, a locals only place
nearby.
As a Moroccan, so many people
come with a romantic notion of a
Tangier they read
about in books.
Do people have a
realistic expectation?
Are they looking for Morocco or
are they looking
for this phantasm?
It is a phantasm.
It is.
When you get here, you know
Morocco, you feel that you are
in Morocco but you are not.
There's a lot of Mediterranean
attached to this town.
Also the history, people hear
story about Tangier that it
was... when I first came in the
'60s, everybody said
that you came late.
Right.
Now I'm saying the same
thing as the young now.
They come and they
saw wow, I say...
What was better
about those days?
Well, for me at that time I
was young, and it was the boom
of hippies, and it
was a destination.
You know, cafe Baba, meet Bob
Dylan, and the parties
was going on.
I miss these kind of parties.
People fly from everywhere to
the party, and they make
the whole town move.
Blue and white party, white and
gold party, hat party,
you know, it's amazing.
You see people coming in with
amazing hats, like a cage with a
bird, extravagant
hats, you know.
They put so much energy and time
into the parties, you know?
Look at... now, that looks good.
Tomatoes brushed with local
olive oil, garlic and coriander.
Liver kabobs, beef liver to be
exact, grilled over charcoal.
That looks very nice.
For fish, a bit of swordfish and
and some orange roughy.
That is just beautiful.
How do you like the tomato?
The swordfish is amazing.
So how else have things changed?
You saw how many tourists
there was today?
They were in a hurry.
If they come to the shop,
even try to avoid your eye
contact.
They afraid if you get my eye
contact, I'm going
to rip you off or...
Or make you buy something
that they don't want?
I don't know.
Do they buy?
They don't even say hello.
They don't buy?
Of course.
We call them penguin.
They have short hands that
don't get into the pockets.
I'm just kidding.
When Tangier was Interzone
back in the day, it seemed to
some I'm sure as if the ex-pats
outnumbered the locals.
That was never true, but you
certainly could live a life
apart, make your own world
within the existing one.
Reinvent yourself and live
entirely within a universe
of your own creation.
Far from the grand socco is
a 14-acre estate owned by
Christopher Gibbs, a well-known
dealer of antiques
and longtime ex-pat.
Today, he's having
a garden party.
Who's coming?
Jonathan you know.
Maggie Dean is from Scotland.
She's been living here
for more than a decade.
GP, a Frenchman who has a
hind in a lot of businesses.
Including a cafe in the Kasbah.
Years living here, unknown.
An American, she's been here
forever, led many lives, I
gather, and occasionally
translates books from
magrabbi to English.
And the dashing and mysterious
baron, an artist from Chile who
has been living and working in
the Kasbah since a hasty exit
from Puerto Rico for reasons
never fully explained.
On the menu, bastilla, a meat or
often pigeon pie, as traditional
Moroccan as it gets.
Today made by Gibbs' full-time
cooks, jamilla and Fatima.
It's chicken slow-cooked, pulled
or shredded and folded
into an egg mixture.
Cooked in a reduced
stock from the boil.
This is layered with blanched
almonds, powdered
sugar, and cinnamon.
The whole lot is wrapped
in a crepe-like dough.
After baking to a golden
crispiness, the final touch is a
dusting of even more
cinnamon and sugar.
It's got a sweet savory thing
going on, and it's quite tasty.
If you get nervous when you
go in a room and you touch the
light switch and the lights
don't come on, you shouldn't
be in this country.
I came here first in 1958.
When it was quite different.
Everyone wore native dress, but
Islam still the throbbing
motor of life here.
I have a very tender feelings
from Morocco and the
friendliness and the courtesy of
the people and its children.
It's bonjour.
[ Speaking foreign language ]
I always feel welcomed here.
I never consider it's mine.
It's theirs and they've allowed
me to feel here in a nice way.
I feel recognition.
They know who I am.
There is a side by side
aspect to life here
that's very unusual.
Very unusual here.
It's mostly you can do whatever
you want if you do it
with good manners.
It is a station of the cross
for, you know, bad
boys of culture.
I mean, Rambo.
Iggy pop.
The stones.
Burroughs writes and came
here to be a writer.
He was a junkie before
he was a writer.
As so many of us were.
A place to think of yourself
as a writer you would come here
and somehow working within
a romantic tradition.
Yes.
Burroughs said right up
front, writer to me lounged
around in a smoking jacket or a
caftan and smoking littered
with sleeping boys.
Yes.
Or girls.
To what extent did that world
exist and to what extent was
that world created by the people
that showed up with
that expectation?
Since Bill departed, yep,
dear, wonderful, marvelous man,
he's gone, it's tame now.
It is tame.
Well, he was... genteel now.
He was the very
opposite of genteel.
He was an outlaw
of every society.
My husband knew him very well
and he was saying that I cured
him of being a drug addict.
I said how?
He said, I turned him
into an alcoholic.
Who smokes hashish
at this table?
Please raise your hand.
Is the camera on?
Put your hand up, Bianca.
♪
It's my last night in
Tangier and I'm headed out.
Thank you, yes.
Most cities in the Islamic
world, getting a beer
can be difficult.
Not here.
As long as you're outside the
Medina, nearly anything goes.
Tangier reverts to
its libertine past.
Here, western influences
become very apparent.
♪
Any night of the week is a good
night for young Moroccons
to take to the streets.
He's from a generation of
Moroccans far removed
from the Burroughser era.
He's invited me out
for a casual snack.
Tuna, eggs and a
healthy wad of Mayo.
French fries within
the sandwich.
This is delicious.
By the way.
The bread here is very good.
You work in magazine journalist?
Yes.
I'm not a journalist but I own
an urban magazine here in
Tangier to inform Moroccans we
are living in a place
that's pretty special.
It is not a place for Burroughs
or Paul Bowles or other
people came to Tangier.
The city has something which
makes it different
from other cities.
What about young artists,
young writers, young musicians?
Do they come here expecting this
romantic Paul Bowles
wonderland of the '50s?
Some were.
Some weren't.
Too bohemian.
Too bohemian?
Yeah.
They thought that coming
and being an artist...
Is going to be enough?
Is going to be enough.
Today it is not enough.
Most of them pack their bags.
Right.
Today we have so many
investments going on here in
Tangier thanks to our king.
Investors are here.
Tourists are attracted.
But the most important part of
it is we should keep the old
parts of the city intact.
The Kasbah, the Medina.
That's what's hard to do because
when you have a European
purchasing power coming over
here to Tangier... they
come like we come.
We embrace it.
Other people want to come.
And then we throw up.
We'll, will Tangier's
unique character survive?
I hope so.
I really hope so.
Tangier is Morocco.
Always was Morocco.
And recently the country's
leadership seems to have
embraced it.
In all its ill reputed glory.
The days of predatory poets in
search of literary inspiration
and young flesh are
probably over for good.
Hippies can just as easily get
their bong rips in
Portland or Peoria.
But the good stuff, the real
good stuff, the sounds and
smells and the look of Tangier,
what you see and hear when you
lean out the window and take it
all in, that's here to stay.