My grandparents teach that
there are some people who have
been in Madagascar before.
They were very little people and
they live in forests and they
respect their environment.
But then comes many people from
other countries, from Africa,
from Asia, from
Spain, from France.
Many of us don't
know the history.
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ Sha, la, la, la, la, la,
♪ sha, la, la, la, la, la
♪ sha, la, la, la, la, la,
♪ sha, la, la, la, la,
♪
Market.
Over the years I've let a lot
of extraordinary landscapes
recede into a blur
outside my windows.
I've looked, maybe seen,
maybe noticed, then gone.
We all carry different
experiences inside us.
We see things
differently, don't we?
Madagascar, exotic unspoiled
paradise or microcosm
for the end of times.
Antananarivo, Tana for short,
Madagascar's crowded
chaotic capital city.
How are you doing, man?
Base camp.
That's quite a rain.
I don't know.
I'm not sure if I can be
in front of the camera.
Just ignore them.
I'm so used to
controlling everything.
Director of the film's pie,
the wrestler, black swan, and
sort of appropriate to
our location "Noah."
He asked me if he could go
along on a trip with us.
I said where do you want to go.
Madagascar, I knew
almost nothing about it.
I knew it was an animated film
I've seen a lot of
times in my car.
It is one of the more extreme
places that you hear about but
you know you'll never go to
unless something
weirdly summons you.
We're on an island in the
Indian ocean with this amazing
ethnic mix, an
incredible landscape.
What does it mean when an
ecosystem goes out of balance?
What is the blowback?
Here, you can see the blowback.
All of a sudden you don't have
soil anymore and you can't
grow anything anymore.
There we go.
An important question.
You are a vegetarian.
Yes.
And it just sort of happened
with the release of "Noah."
In scripture he was a
vegetarian as was Adam and Eve.
Humans weren't given permission
to eat animals until
after the flood.
So we'll see who is doing
better after the end of days.
Little social experiment here.
Madagascar was settled best
we can tell around 700 A.D.
by people from what is know
Indonesia, later Africans.
In 1895 the French took it,
killed off a substantial number
of people in the process, and as
they do, left behind beautiful
buildings and the French
language.
When independence came in 1960,
it was sudden and
ill prepared for.
Continuing political
incompetence has left most of
Madagascar's 22 million people
living on less than $2 a day.
Do you know this place?
Yes.
Monday, Saturday, before going
out, before going tonight club.
First meal in country and
I suggested this place.
I thought it would be perfect
with Aaron being a
vegetarian and all.
This is what you call being
passive aggressive, I think.
So what's good here?
Pork.
Pork, my favorite vegetable.
Just the head of the pork.
It sounds good.
I'm not going to have it.
I'm going to go just
with vegetables.
You don't want to taste it?
I'm not going to taste
pig head, not today.
Always take it with beans.
Rossi the famous musician
here is out of a period out
of favor with the previous
government back home and
elected to parliament.
The leaves are from
that's excellent.
These days what are the big
issues that are not
being taken care of.
Not enough education.
We are very rich.
We have oil, but our political
leaders most of the
time are crook.
How much does the environmental
issues matter to
the people or is it
just about survival?
They don't care.
The international community,
they've paid a lot of money
to protect the forest.
You protect the monkey.
You don't protect the people.
I eat the monkey.
If I'm hungry, I eat them.
They don't care about the world
is going more and more war.
Climate change.
Okay.
You are going to die, yes?
You're going to die.
That's life.
For them, just normal.
A lot of people feel that the
future should be ecotourism,
essentially working in hotels
and restaurants for tourists.
Yeah.
That's kind of a return
to colonialism, isn't it?
Exactly.
♪
Tell me what you think of this.
I'm looking forward to this.
It's a very famous dish, goose.
Goose and shredded meat.
Very cool.
There's always someplace where
the flame is kept burning,
history kept alive
however faintly.
This is the stuffing.
These days in Madagascar's
capital city it's left to
Mariette.
The epitome of the cooking is
the way Mariette cooks it.
♪
♪ You are, you are like
a sweet perfect bloom ♪
During the colonial period
Mariette was a frequent
colonial ambassador.
Harry Bellefonte.
The go-to chef for visiting
presidents and royalty.
The success story her mansion
high atop Oatville, the former
neighborhood of choice for
aristocrats and colonizers
alike.
Though semi-retired, Mariette
continues to entertain
guests from time to time.
So this is broth with
chicken and ginger.
These dishes marry cue seen
with the techniques of the
classical French.
Wow, look at this.
It is one of the side dishes.
It's like a salad.
String beans.
We don't eat meat at every meal.
Most would eat rice broth with
vegetables and that's it.
I'd do fine.
Yeah, absolutely.
This is a country that is very
rich in natural resources.
Madagascar we have a lot of
things that a lot of people
want.
For example, the trafficking of
rosewood, prospecting for oil
and gas, and don't leave
anything for the
rest of the country.
This is an island paradise.
And it is disappearing
very, very quickly.
A lot of our forests
are being burned down.
Ecotourism will save the day.
The local people will be
cleaning rooms, cooking, and
performing traditional
ethnic dances.
Yeah, absolutely.
To me, this is not
an ideal option.
What's an ideal option, though?
♪
Heading south from Tana, it's
a very different country out
there where rice is the
difference between
life and death.
Between the traditional slash
and burn agriculture that's
existed here since this island
was first settled and the
imperative of charcoal as heat
source, 90% of the forests and
jungles that cover
Madagascar are gone.
Anything?
Not yet.
They're very elusive.
They're very difficult to see.
Thanks largely to the work of
Dr. Patricia Wright, over 4,000
hectors of forest have been set
aside for a national park.
Her recently completed research
station is a state-of-the-art
complex that reminds one of
that... what was it
Jurassic merch.
The greater bamboo lemur
previously thought extinct.
There's only 500 of these in
the world in the whole wild.
Slash and burn agriculture.
Look at it.
Beautiful.
It's so nice.
He's taking a leak right now.
Hopefully that's not an
editorial statement.
Look.
This is the kind of bamboo
chute that the lemurs loved.
It's full of protein and
it's full of cyanide.
The cyanide not a
problem for them.
They can tolerate all
kinds of cyanide.
The cyanide comes straight
through in the poop.
Do they know how they get
it through their system?
We're working on that.
What is the dew on
the outside of it?
Just dew?
Careful.
Don't touch.
How is your finger feeling?
It felt sharp, but a fuzziness.
It's just like
fiberglass actually.
Leave tiny little cuts.
Am I going to die?
Probably.
Are you serious?
Can it go through the skin
now that I've touched it?
No, you have to eat it.
Hopes of a "black swan 2"
were dashed today when
one right above you.
Has the film "Madagascar"
been good for the
lemur business?
I think the cartoon woke up
the world and that there is a
place called Madagascar although
a lot of people don't
think it really exists.
How hard is it to
maintain the forests?
It's incredibly hard.
We've been working with the
villagers around the park and I
think they understand the value
of these extraordinary lemurs
the economic value of tourist is
.tremendous for this country
The boundaries of the park
protect what they can of
Madagascar's rapidly diminishing
rain forest, but it's not all
about lemurs and rare species of
unspoiled beautiful places.
These are the Tenalla people.
These are the people
of the forest.
This is the fifth time they've
had to change the location of
the village because they do
slash and burn agriculture.
This ceremony today is a
ceremony to celebrate the fact
that 17 people from the village
are going to donate their
land to conservation.
It won't be cut down.
♪
Before the Tenalla land can
officially become a part of the
park, the gods or the ancestors
must be appeased and that often
means that something must die.
I have to go when
this is happening.
Wow.
For someone with as dark a
world view judging from his
films anyway, he seems unusually
uncomfortable with the bleeding
realities of local custom
preferring instead to trip the
light fantastic in the
rain forest idle.
♪
When the forest
means fuel, food?
What we've had to do, of
course, is make their lives
better in exchange.
Health projects, education
projects, tourism.
Many of the people
work as tour guides.
They work in the hotels.
They have work.
They didn't have any work when
they got here, but also the
benefits of researchers.
We hire 85 people full-time.
The director of the national
park, where's your village that
you lived in when you
were a little girl?
That's on one side of the park.
The ancestors presumably
okay with the land transfer.
It's time to party.
Dr. Wright worked hard to
establish the park with the
stated aim of protecting the
absolutely unique flora and
fauna here and reducing human
pressures on the area.
This, however, is the face of
human pressure, just
so we're clear.
Okay.
Take care, guys.
♪
We're right on the
edge of the park.
Right on the edge, literally, is
where they built the power lines
and where they're
slashing and burning.
We were trying for landscapes
like this in "Noah."
Sort of a postapocalyptic
wasteland thing going on, right?
Look, all the original fauna and
flora in New York City and
Chicago and Detroit are gone.
We don't feel too
guilty about that.
That's the argument of all
these developing
countries, you did it.
Didn't they teach us in the
third grade that two wrongs
don't make a right?
♪
What were they welding on?
Oil pan.
Most of Madagascar's French
built rail network has crumbled
into nothingness, but
this train still runs.
Look how it's painted.
It's first class.
Yeah, yeah.
We ride in style.
How old is this train?
Wow, it works.
Oil pan worked.
I hope that's not a pitying
look I see on some of their
faces.
They're all looking on.
It's like... it's 162
kilometers to the
one time major port town.
It's both the greatest thing
ever, meaning a fantastically
scenic emersion that most
visitors never get to see and
at times punishing crawl.
For the majority of the 17
station stops along the line,
this train provides the only
connection to the outside world.
People hop off and on, load and
unload fruit, leechees, bananas.
Quite a few foreigners
on board watch.
There are invevendors selling
food and drink, which is a
necessity since the supposed
eight-hour trip is
said to approach 18.
All right.
So we got a shaker.
We got an umbrella, champagne.
You let the train pour for you.
Right.
This is the leechee.
That smells good.
Darren woke early and made
the leechee puree for
festive cocktails.
Wait, wait, wait.
Oh, yes.
It's not bad.
It's not bad at all.
Okay.
It's a nice summery drink.
The leechee makes it.
The leechee makes it, yes.
What do we call it?
The golden lemur.
♪
Flashes of everyday life, the
struggle to live, to eat, viewed
from a moving train, then gone.
Different areas of Madagascar
are burning everywhere
you can see.
After seven hours or so...
We're coming into a town.
The imperatives of food,
any food, become ever more
urgent.
This is it.
This is the stop.
I am starving.
I am so with you.
Look, this kid is wearing
a banana like a yamka.
The train of treats we were
told would be here, it
is what suboptimal.
Little did I know there
would be a feeding frenzy.
There's no papaya salad.
Everything's gone.
Here are some bananas.
Yeah, a few of those.
Yeah, merci.
We get what we can.
It's hard to complain about the
lack of food options
when you look around.
Lots of kids.
Want some?
Yeah, it's hard.
This is nice.
This is the way to travel.
Until a palm leaf
comes flying at you.
Watch it, watch it, watch it.
♪
This is what it's like to
wake up at the end of the world.
Beyond here to the east nothing
but thousands of miles
of Indian ocean.
♪
Morning, and fishermen
return with their catch.
Have you felt how wobbly
that boat was coming over?
Yes.
Imagine going out and fishing.
It was a major port back in
the day, a major transportation
hub, but now it's a
sleepy beach town.
That's a disturbingly
large spider.
I would be happy if I saw
that coming across my pillow.
Dude, it's a chicken or rooster.
I tell you that lobster
is smelling good.
No, they're disgusting.
They're like giant insects.
What do they eat?
Corpses.
Dead things.
You are such a Debbie downer.
You were born here.
And your parents are from here.
How far out do they go out?
50 miles.
He goes out 50 miles
in a little canoe?
Yes.
Every day, every day.
Awesome.
This is typical dish.
Green leaves, egg,
plants, some spices.
We bought a lot of food.
This sort of spread is not an
everyday meal in these parts.
There's your veggie platter.
There you go, man.
Now we have a piece of a shark.
He says smaller fish.
Smaller fish?
Yes and the quantity smaller.
That's a papaya salad.
It's one of those days where
the artifice of making
television threatens to move
dangerously into cruelty.
What are you guys
eating over here?
Who gets to eat and when
becomes a pressing concern to
the two of us?
Can we get the kids eating?
Can we hand out the food?
In a local culture like this,
first ladies serve the
and then the kids.
They will eat later.
Right.
I got you.
It's like a caste system.
It's not like our system but
it's a system and it becomes
clear that, yes,
everybody will eat.
There we go.
Come to daddy.
That's good, dude.
You picked a bad time
to become a vegetarian.
You really did.
Not bad.
The food is amazing.
There's some really good
cooks at work here today.
It's really amazing.
And then the music
starts and the dancing.
♪
And as so often happens the
Nat so spontaneous made-for-TV
party becomes a real party.
♪
And we all for a little while
anyway forget about where we
came from an where we
might be tomorrow.
Hallelujah.
Praise the lord!
You are blessed today.
Amen.
Hallelujah.
The book of revelations say
what if ever we do god
can see and he take not.
I will destroy the city because
all of the people are sinners.
Amen.
Hallelujah.
The camera is a liar.
It shows everything.
It shows nothing.
It reveals only what we want.
Often what we see is seen only
from a window, moving
past and then gone.
One window, my window.
If you had been here, chances
are you would have seen
things differently.
Whoa!
I lived it now.
Looking back, if you were
editing this show, how
would you tell this story?
This is it.
This is the food stop.
I'm starving.
I am so with you.
That is quite a scene.
Lots of kids.
Want that?
You always want a simple answer
to everything to make it
all make sense, and it seems to,
I don't know, it's just
constantly surprising.
What can you see
everywhere with you go?
In the office, in the market?
People are sinning, making sin.
As a kid I always wondered if
I was good enough to get on
the ark so I always sort of
empathize with the people
who didn't make it.
God, make out of the animals,
come inside the big sheep and
all of the people and
make the families saved.
It is all on ship.
God decides to destroy creation.
Ten generations after he created
everything, so it must
have hurt tremendously.
God will use us.
He brought the ark.
He will send us, too.
Alleluia!
Alleluia.
Pray for yourself.
Pray for your family.
Pray!
God will save Madagascar.