I didn't even think about it.
About death.
But shooting at those things,
anybody in the camera was shot.
Immediately.
By a Russian soldier.
At that time, I didn't
think about that.
But I found that I had
to think about it.
You were alive and holding a
camera at a very important
time in history.
You had to think, I'm doing
something important.
It's very easy to make
pictures, but pictures mean
something, what's in it.
That's a totally
different story.
♪ I took through this beautiful
world, felt the cool
rain on my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ Sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la la la la
You know these images.
You grew up with them.
They're burned into your brain.
Their iconic sequences.
Framed and lit and scene through
the lens in ways that
changed filmmaking forever.
All made by the same man.
So, who made these
beautiful things?
Where did he come from?
It didn't begin in Hollywood.
It began here, in the
streets of Budapest.
What about his life, his past,
his upbringing led him again and
again to look through a piece of
glass and make
images like these.
But first, some context.
And schnitzel.
Did I mention schnitzel?
It's beautiful here.
They say that, of course,
that Budapest is beautiful.
But it is, in fact, almost
ludicrously beautiful.
A riot of gorgeous architectural
styles, palaces, grand public
spaces, former mansions of
various princelings, the remains
of a long-gone
empire, still here.
Still here.
If there was such a thing as
building porn, it would be this.
Just looking out the window as
you drive or trolley by,
you think, I want that.
Who lives there?
Who lived there?
What's it like inside?
And where did they go?
From high up Gellard hill, you
get a sense of the
layout of the city.
Divided, split by the Danube
river, Buda on one side,
Pest on the other.
Hungary divided in two.
Literally a
crossroads of worlds.
Which is which?
If you look down,
you're in buda.
If you look up, you're in Pest.
According to the myth I was
brought up, if you are in buda,
you're in Europe and the
other side is Asia.
This is the border of the
Roman empire, originally.
This big river.
Why didn't they cross?
The other side is flat, it's
hard to defend and there were
all these tribes that were
vicious and not as civilized as
the Romans believed they were.
They've all been here, the
settles, the Romans, the
mongols, the ottoman Turks.
All had their way or tried.
All left their Mark to
one extent or another.
♪
Then mid-19th century, the
curious, seemingly improbable
Austro-Hungarian empire.
This is when the city came into
its open, fueled by untold
wealth, accumulated power, and
ambition.
Architecturally,
intellectually, a great city.
One of the world's greatest.
And that was a time
when Budapest was a really
progressive Metropolis.
The first subway in the
continent of Europe was in
Budapest.
Parliament had like a very
sophisticated air-conditioning
system.
So people wanted to come, they
wanted to live here,
wanted to start a career.
Wanted to build places like
this, because it was a good
investment.
The New York cafe is one of
the last remnants of a society
where artists and writers were
valued citizens, regardless
of financial means.
When this cafe was built,
there were more than 500
cafes in this neighborhood.
And this was the biggest and
nicest cafe in the
world at the time.
Never to be closed.
Here, like in most cafes at
that time, a few cents or a few
bucks could buy you space all
day long, sipping your coffee,
thinking great thoughts.
Nobody would hassle you.
It was a petri dish
of creativity.
No hipster neck beard barista
would make you feel bad about
not speaking any dough.
Waiters were speaking
several languages and you read
literature and they invited the
writer, occasionally, if he
didn't have money, because they
appreciated their literature.
Where are we now
compared to there?
Don't try that now, of course.
Today's new-York cafe patrons
spend both their time and money
on things like goose
liver tegrine.
Foie gras is all over Hungary.
And it's good.
Real good.
Peter's going for the soup.
If you looked like a writer,
they would bring you paper and
ink, bring you a dictionary.
Also, most people didn't have
telephones at home and you
could be called here.
Why do I want to
attract writers?
It's like, I need more jazz
musicians on my register.
It was a different time.
It was not simply
about the money.
So it was about identity.
Yeah.
We want to be the place
that attracts the best and the
brightest.
Yeah.
Even if they don't have money.
Those days will never return.
Yeah, those days
will never return.
Lovely, thank you.
For the main courses, Peter
gets the filet of perch.
I'm going for the pork throttle
stew, mostly because I like
the sound of throttle.
That is beautiful.
That makes me very happy.
If I were to ask most
Hungarians, when were the good
old days?
You would have the answer.
Of course, it's not all
foie gras and fine wines.
There are other pleasures,
just as awesome.
Maybe, maybe even more awesome.
Like this.
Plesharda.
A smokey, chilly working class
joint run for the last 25
years and beloved by locals.
A long time coming.
A golden brown pancake
happied with chicken livers,
covered, nay, drowned with a
rich, deeply satisfying
sauce of bone marrow.
I've got to tell
you, this is great.
Some of you have noticed and
complained that I don't really
describe food
anymore, on the show.
This is a deliberate strategy
on my part, actually.
It's really a lot
like writing porn.
After you've used the same
adjectives over and over, look
at it, it's chicken liver, bone
marrow, a delicious pancake.
Is this going to make your life
better at all if I describe
exactly how while smacking my
lips and annoying you?
No.
It's good.
Venison stew, delicious.
And then this.
This.
Good... holy... really?
Good lord!
This I need a photo of.
Put a human hand next to it.
That's just truly terrifying.
Who eats that?
Behold the massiveness, the
surf board-sized fried to order
in a pan to only the highest
standards schnitzel of justice.
Ride that, baby,
all the way home.
Yeah.
Oh, that's good.
Extra pork flavor.
Hints of day-old friar.
I could surf this thing
back to my hotel.
I kid you not.
This is a testament
to a great culture.
Also gout.
But who's counting?
Do I get a T-shirt
if I finish this?
Or my picture on the wall?
We are, all of us, perhaps,
called to serve a higher
purpose.
Put here on earth to do
god's mysterious will.
Daniel Matta is here for this.
To spread the gospel of meat.
Hungarian meat-related wisdom in
all its delicious,
delicious variety.
Like St. Francis of Assisi, he
wanders the earth,
doing good works.
In this case, highlighting the
ancient arts of butchery,
sausage making, and the
preparation of many of the
Lord's creatures.
As he, himself, would no doubt
like to see them prepared.
What have you heard
about Budapest butchers?
Not much.
We have about seven
butchers in Budapest.
Seven?
You can find us on a small
dorn with roasted meats.
It's very.
In five minutes, you can find
a butcher where you
can eat something.
And on this particular
corner, one of Daniel's
favorites.
So, you are not a butcher.
You're not... no, no.
What is your... what do you the?
I am an economist.
I understand it, you go from
butcher shop from butcher
shop, investigating butchers.
Why do you do that?
Because I like it.
And I thought, I'm
not alone with this.
So we should make a fan club.
And it started to
rise on Facebook.
Nearly 10,000 likes.
It's so unusual that
there are so many.
Because in France, Germany,
in the states, the old school
butchers who know how to do
all of these things, they're
disappearing.
Their kids aren't doing it.
It's not so easy to be
a butcher now in Hungary.
But with this catering function
doing prepared foods.
They try to save themselves.
Yes, there are many boutique
cuts of meat available, as one
would expect from a master
butcher.
But then there's this.
A field of dreams.
A landscape of braised and fried
and cured delights that seem,
under glass, to go on forever.
A good Hungarian butcher shop,
they should be able to cut
meat, cure meat, make sausage,
and cook preparations as well.
Yeah.
Look at that.
There he goes.
So beautiful.
There's no comparison
with a supermark.
Plus, you can ask him,
what's good today.
Today... oh, look,
what great timing.
They're making one
of my favorites.
Blood sausage.
You have to say in
English, because I can't.
Paprika.
Oregano.
Thyme.
Marjoram.
All spice.
Here comes the rice.
Here comes the blood.
Beautiful, so good.
Salt.
And the sugar.
I don't understand why.
It makes flavors pop.
Beautiful.
Seasoned and right
into the tube.
Stand by for big jokes.
All right.
So what do we have here?
Oh, that looks good.
Some nice pickles.
Braced red cabbage.
Over there, from the mighty
shanks of some mythical
creature, perhaps, slow braced
until the meat is
falling off the bone.
And let there be blood,
delicious, delicious blood, in
tube form, served, still
steaming, nay, heaving,
engorged, as you will, with
goodness, to squirt across your
plate as you press against it
with the side of your fork.
So delicious.
So how often do you do?
Two or three times a week.
What distinguishes a good
butcher from an okay butcher?
They're doing
good business here.
That is true.
Yeah?
I can't tell you which
is my favorite butcher.
All of them are different.
Right.
Do you ever just going
out for like a salad?
No.
I kid, I kid.
There is another long
tradition of artistry here in
Budapest.
We grew up with their works.
Visual artists,
photographers, filmmakers.
Where did they all go?
Well, world war I happened
and with it, the end of the
Austro-Hungarian empire.
Budapest and all Europe
changed forever.
A decades-long wave
of emigration began.
A stunning number of the world's
great photographers fled their
native Hungary and
took up new lives.
Eventually, this
man joined them.
I've been shooting photos since
I remember I was living.
I was 5 or 6 years old when I
was taking pictures with my
father's Kodak camera.
The right moment, you
have to capture.
And that's the difficult
part the exact moment.
Hungarians, there is
this need to excel.
My father was not
really an artist.
He was a soccer player.
A very good one.
He said, son, whatever you do,
you have to be the best at it.
First, not second, you
have to be first.
Otherwise it's not worth it.
Vilomo Zigma.
Legendary cinematographer.
If you don't know his
name, you know his work.
The Oscar-winning
"close encounters."
"The deer hunter."
His evolutionary work on
"McCabe and Mrs. Miller."
"The long good-bye."
"Deliverance."
He created a whole new palette,
took crazy risks, changed film
language in ways people
still try to imitate.
And he's making our camera crew
very nervous, I can tell you.
You taught yourself to shoot.
Basically, I always tried to
use my father's Kodak camera.
It's a kidney disease.
I was in bed for a month and an
uncle of mine gave me a book
about a great photographer.
And I started to take
just amateur pictures.
One thing that hasn't changed
through the years is the
Hungarian affection for taking
the waters, marinading in
thermal baths, a tradition going
back to the Romans, continued by
the ottomans, and something that
survived right through
two wars and communism.
And they do it in style.
Who came here?
Back in those days?
Was this reserved for anyone who
wanted to could come here?
Well, you know, money wise,
everyone before did
basically what was cheap.
Right.
In hungry, we have so many spas.
There are many bathhouse spas.
Baroque, elaborately wedding
cakes, built atop mineral rich
hot Springs gurgling
from the earth.
None more storied
than the Geller.
You arrived in
Budapest around age 21.
What was the city like then?
It was always beautiful.
There were ruins after the war.
Half of the city was
still in ruins.
When you first moved here,
you go to film school, what was
your average day like
other than your studies?
What did you do for
fun back then?
What were your options?
Our options were zero.
Imagine from little help
from the government.
Very little money.
Enough to have breakfast and
lunch or breakfast and dinner.
You had to skip lunch
for a pair of socks.
So we were very, very poor.
But I must say that under this
whole thing, the happiest part
of my life was when I fell
in love, immediately.
In fact, some of Vilmos' most
powerful and world-changing
footage occurred around this
time, before leaving Hungary, as
a film student during the
outbreak of revolution.
But we'll get to that later.
In many ways, Viloms Zigma's
career as one of the great
photographers in
cinematography begins here.
Here he was raised by his
father, who worked many jobs to
make ends meet.
Weekends in warmer months all
over Hungary, wherever there's a
river and fish, places like this
are thronging with families.
And here along the Tisa
river is no exception.
Here Vilmos and his dad would
come and eat the local
specialty of soup.
How old were you when you
first came to this place?
I must have been
about 7 years old.
You know, my father
was really great.
Those days, years, actually, he
didn't have much time, but
occasionally, he wants to take
me away, away from work.
He loved this place, actually.
He loved this,
especially this fish.
That's murky and good-looking
and need some bread
for this, for sure.
Pike from the river simmered
low and slow in a rich fish
stock with healthy amount of
onions and the near you pick we
to us but always good paprika.
That's good.
On the summer, in the side.
Then go swimming in the river.
It was a great place.
Used to be a great
place for fun.
And you know at night, we
used to come here at night, when
the gypsies were playing music.
And I loved that, actually.
I always loved gypsy music.
They had a very happy childhood.
Good times until, until the war
got in and then stopped all
that happiness, you know?
There was just hard times.
Were you fully aware of how
bad, how grave things were?
Near the end of the war, the
Germans came in and then
started to bomb us.
And they started to take Jews,
actually, to work in camps.
That started to be
very, very ugly.
For people of your
generation, who grew up, these
were incredibly insecure times.
Psychologically, what do you
think that teaches you
as far as a world view?
Do you become more adaptable?
Do you become more suspicious?
Do you become more cynical?
It's about survival, actually.
We want to survive as Siberians,
to preserve identity as
hung Hungarians.
So that's what we did.
And survived.
We saw a lot as a young boy,
as he would later, as an adult.
In 1944, German tanks
rolled into Hungary.
His country was now in the
hands of a foreign power.
It made me thinking
back to my school years.
I almost said those were the
happiest years of my life.
Being under a regime,
terrible things happened.
We were stuck.
Being in the film school was
like an island of the craziness.
I grew up in New Jersey.
My family was sentimental about
beautiful pictures,
a beautiful script.
We saw every film you ever shot
and talked about them
at the dinner table.
These were important.
This has got to look pretty
close to the way it did
in the old day, right?
Oh, yeah.
Doesn't change much.
Through it all for Vilmos
was this place, however.
A very special place for a boy
growing up during wartime.
The moviehouse where he
saw his first films.
What memorable films did
you see in this theater?
My probably best experience
in my life, I was in Hungary,
see chaplain's "the dictator."
Democracy is fragrant.
Liberty stunk.
Liberty is odious.
Freedom of speech is objectable.
Chaplain did such a
great job, you know.
Some films, of course,
resonated more than others.
The power of the visual image
intensified by what was going
on outside that dark room.
Fills could be inspiring, but
they could be dangerous.
It was so magical, to go to a
film, especially a dangerous
one, one that was just the
subject matter and the content
was different and to see that
just, oh, my god, what do I do
with my life now
after seeing this?
This theater, by the way,
is now named in his honor.
When you look at footage you
took during the revolution,
you're not in those pictures,
but do you see yourself?
Do you remember
what it felt like?
I remember that I was
actually scared to death.
Shooting those, going
through there, should be.
I found I had to photograph it.
Things were going from one side
to the other side of the Danube.
There were tanks
coming across this?
Well, yes, actually.
It was a pretty cool,
cold day, too.
Yeah.
It was bad weather.
It was pretty much, you know,
you could see what was
happening in Budapest.
After the war, a cold war.
Hungary now found itself firmly
in the grip of the Soviet union.
Germans had been replaced
by Russian comisars.
Vilmos was now at film school
along with his best friend,
Laszlo.
Then in 1956, something
amazing happened.
Hated emblems of red tyranny
went down as hub guerin patriots
for ten glorious days sent
armored Russians which pitted
rifles against tanks.
The statue of Stalin used
to be under the first night,
actually, when the revolution
started, the people wanted
to take the statue down.
It took about a couple of hours,
actually, to get Mr.
Stalin's legs off.
And naturally, the next day,
people took pieces home as a
souvenir.
To date, this was something
that had never been done.
The Hungarians took
to the streets.
A revolution.
That's when Vilmos and Laszlo
and some pals snuck 35
millimeter cameras and film out
of their school's equipment
room, and at great risk to
themselves, joined their
countrymen in the streets,
documenting the revolt
and the aftermath.
These images are from some
of that historic footage.
It seemed for ten glorious days,
that freedom had finally come.
Encouraged by the west and
by CIA radio broadcasts in
particular, the Hungarians
believed that help was on its
way.
That this was it.
They dug in and fought.
Hoping to hold out
until help arrived.
On November 4th, a desperate
plea went out over the air
waves.
This is Hungary calling.
For the sake of
god, help Hungary.
The Russians had been beaten
back for a time, but now they
doubled down with a vengeance,
pouring tanks and troops and
heavy armor back into Budapest
and brutally and all too
effectively put down
the resistance.
Help never came.
This is a place where a
lot of things happened.
Used to be the headquarters.
I never shot this before, so
this is about the first time I'm
going to get this building shot.
So this was the internal
secret police, so if someone
came at night with a Van and he
were taken away, you ended
up being interrogated here?
Yes.
Secret police
headquarters in 1956.
The site of a firefight between
snipers on the roof, and
their fellow citizens below.
Then the people got into the
building, went up there, hunted
them down and killed them,
actually, basically.
And hanged them ton the streets.
Hung them here.
Hung them on the street.
It's hard to find a tree which
they hung those people up there.
Had you see people killed
before the revolution?
Though.
Very tragic moment.
The building is abandoned.
The door, as it turns
out, wide open.
Oh, wow.
Oh, look at that.
It still feels sad.
A little haunted, yeah?
Those were vicious
times, you know.
People's life was not really
important to these
people, they were cruel.
And you have people, some of
them have been to Siberia.
They killed so many people after
that time, unfortunately.
And they went through the film.
People were in trouble,
many were killed.
How long did you stick around?
Almost three weeks.
And that's when we realized that
nothing is going to change.
You left Hungary with
a lot of cans of film?
As much as you could carry.
We have just enough money
to get to America ♪
The sound track to old Budapest.
The ubiquitous gypsy violin.
Found at one time in every
cafe or restaurant.
♪
It's a hard life, that
of a professional musician.
As true a statement in
Budapest as anywhere.
These guys are Budapest bar, an
eclectic troupe of extraordinary
musicians united by their
dedication to that uniquely
Hungarian crossroads of
gypsy and classical music.
♪
So, what does a band do
when the hour's late and some
sustenance and drink
are required?
It's back to the manager
flat and his wife, Andrea.
And they play more music.
Do you play gypsy music?
No hesitation.
He says it's very rare that
anybody who's not a gypsy
can play gypsy music.
In gypsy music, the whole
lifestyle, the whole experience
is in and kids start learning
it when they are 2 or 3.
At the time you are 8, you
have bore these ingredients
in your blood.
♪
Marguite, a household
name, also a fantastic cook.
Extraordinary singing talent
does not seclude her from
preparing whole perch roasted in
bacon, stuffed cabbage filled
with goose meat and slow cooked.
And of course, the
inevitable goulash.
The iconic dish you see
everywhere, but rarely as good
as this.
♪
Thank you.
Should I put a little
sour cream on there?
Yes.
Beautiful.
She says it's her
own special recipe.
Luxurious.
If you're a musician and living
in buoyed test right now,
this is a good time
to be a musician?
Never.
It's not... it's
not a good time.
Depend on the view.
It's very bad for the gypsy
musicians generally
speaking because it's dead.
It's completely... apart from
things like Budapest, gypsy
music is extinct.
It's heartbreak, is sadness
an important part of this music?
I mean, Hungary is a country
that has experimented
a lot of heartbreak.
So it is a lot of heartbreaks.
It's a lot of
difficulties, and...
And... and there is another
saying that the violin is
crying, that the gypsy violin is
crying and there is another one
that even if we have joy
we cry, the Hungarian.
♪
Tonight, Vilmos has invited
me to the home of his longtime
friend and college in
the film business.
He met Richie on set of a movie
more than 20 years ago, and they
have been friends and
partners ever since.
Cheers.
In Hungary it's... I'll never
learn to pronounce that.
Richie's wife Maria, daughter
Judith, Vilmos' wife Susan,
friends and family reunite for
the best of simple pleasures.
We start with a rich carroway
and onion and paprika soup
finished with homemade croutons
and there's a deeply rich and
deeply warming beef stew with
pork sausage for good sausage
and cooked for hours and, of
course, heavy on the paprika,
traditional cucumber salad.
To accompany the soup,
boiled dumplings.
Our style in photography
was not realist.
It's poetic realist.
That's what we always thought
about that certain photography,
emphasizing basically the beauty
of the things but also I make it
more beautiful than it is.
Why is Hungary so
strong on photography?
I think they are very strong
in mathematics which was in
the early days connected to
photography.
Phil tells me about his
education in math.
It was totally different.
Very good school.
That's what I said, the
schools in Hungary were very,
very good.
Not an answer to me.
You've made some of the most
beautiful images we made in
the modern world and you keep
telling me I was good in school.
I was good in math.
What would you like to hear?
I was touched by
god, I don't know.
I don't know.
If you're regularly creating the
sublime, I'm looking for a
metaphysical answer, I don't know.
You learn this.
You learn to be an artist.
So if I would ask
you how was dinner?
So deeply delicious.
Thank you.
Oh, really good,
really good, wow.
Oh, thank you.
What a great meal.
Thank you.
Do we emerge fully formed
with a god-given eye?
For pictures, images
that can move people?
Or are we the end result of all
the things we've seen, all the
things we've done, the places
we've been, the places, the
people we've had to leave
behind, all that's happened in
your life?
Is it those things that bring
the light or the the darkness
to the blank screen?
And what about the faces of
those we capture in our magic
lenses for a minute or
a second or an hour?
Afterwards should we think about
them and where
they might be now?