One of our roles here has
always been to take away excess
money from people who don't know
what to do with it, who can't
think of a better idea about
how to spend their money.
In the old days, you would
throw it on a table.
Put that in the context of
throwing away a bottle of
seven-up in a club.
We're slightly more
honest about it.
You're talking crass
commercialism in the very best
sense of the word.
This is it.
Is it the cultural
center of the country?
We may not want to think
it is, but is it?
I don't know.
It's that place where they
all leave and come here.
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha la la la
♪ sha la la la la la
♪ sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la la
♪
I can go to the desert, but
I am not going to get
there by accident.
But that's part of the whole
experience of the desert is
that, you know, it ain't
friendly.
It ain't nice.
It ain't good, you know?
You're out here, you know, a
half a mile, it doesn't matter
if you're half a mile out
or you're 20 miles out.
There's no reason to
walk a mile further.
You're already in
infinite desolation.
Sin city was true, it was real.
Part of moving out here was you
were never going to see
your family again.
That was it.
I'm moving to Vegas and you
ain't coming to see me and
I ain't coming to see you.
That's the character
of the city.
It really was, you know,
the pit of America.
It wasn't that somebody came out
here because I'm going
to make a million bucks.
It was I'm going to come out
here and I'm going to survive
and you all ain't going to
bug me anymore back home.
In Vegas, there's
winners and losers.
And god knows I've been both.
In a place like this where you
can lose your shirt on the
unlucky turn of a card,
you need a friend.
And for my sins, I got Roland.
Currently evading prosecution in
just about every jurisdiction
from his hometown, Cleveland, to
Grand Forks, wanted for bail
jumping, usory, misuse of
livestock, assault, grand theft
auto, also the respected author
of such food related classics as
the French lottery cookbook and
soul of a chef, he washed up in
Vegas at just the right time.
Vegas was always the
most unlikely of dreams.
The longest of long shots in
the middle of the desert.
A real but imaginary space that
keeps expanding, creeping ever
larger across the wasteland.
Back in the '40s, the
'50s it was a small town.
100,000 became 300,000 became
500,000, then a
million, then two.
But it doesn't matter if it
was five years ago or 50.
The town has always
ended like this.
An abrupt cut in the desert
racks on the horizon.
But there are comfortable
dark places, too.
Where a man can have a drink
meet like-minded sophisticatos
of the open west.
Places like this.
♪
It's the good stuff.
That's Jameson black.
Huntridge tavern, where those
who have to live it, see it, the
things that men do day after
day, night after night, in a
town where people are encouraged
to do their worst, where they
can drink the stain away.
This is the side
of Vegas I like.
This side.
Yeah, because people
here are really cynical.
Really.
They have a dim world view.
Even more dim than me.
That's hard.
You know what this
whole show's about?
You know there's a theme.
No.
This is about people who
live here, you know.
When all the meatheads come
and go, they're still here.
These people have seen every
variety of horrifying
human behavior.
The old business model was come
to Vegas and behave
really, really badly.
I think it's encouraged
people to be their worst.
They're expected to do that.
Kind of makes my skin crawl.
Really?
Not here.
Here, I like it.
I'm comfortable here.
Is this an easy town to make
a living or a hard
town to make a living?
Depends what you do.
25 years behind the
bar, you see some...
If you were born and
bred here... I am.
She's third generation.
Third generation.
Are you an optimist
or a pessimist?
You think basically the
human race are good people?
I would say roughly
half of them.
Half are going.
There are probably more
knuckleheads per square foot in
the Vegas strip than
anywhere in America.
I'm not hanging with
those people, man.
There will be a few high end
meals during our adventure here.
We will be sampling
the other side.
But there's a price.
There is always a
price with you.
♪
There are places in Vegas
where the available rooms are
not listed on any websites.
Places reserved for the whales,
the high rollers, the $10
million a night gamblers who
arrive by private plane.
♪
Bobby flay probably lives
like this all the time.
Yeah.
It could have been
dark, couldn't it.
Very dark here.
I honestly never thought it
would have come to this.
Well, it was Duncan
Frey’s 14 years ago.
You made some steps up.
You make me feel better about
all of this luxury
looking back at that.
Yeah.
You deserve this.
You're right.
Entering my golden years era.
They don't show this in
the Viagra commercials.
They show them on the beach with
a tennis racket but they're
never sitting here.
Go out and kill
some young people.
To victory.
Victory in our time.
You always try to comfort
yourself in situations like this
thinking oh, I'm sure people are
really, really wealthy, they're
probably really miserable.
They don't know the sort of ups
and downs, the happiness, the
contrast, the passion
that I have.
We don't know, do we?
Right.
Like maybe every day
is like wonderful.
Thank you.
Mm.
Delicious.
Perfect.
The villa at Caesar's palace.
A little pad they give you if
your credit line runs
into the eight figures.
How did I get it?
I told the casino that wolf
blitzer was coming, that he
was expected any minute.
I suggested that wolf might
be hungry and they sent up
geesavoir.
Fortunately he doesn't watch a
lot of television and I plan to
live large until they figure
out wolf ain't coming.
I'll deal with the
fallout later.
But for now, we live.
This dish, everything
is in layers.
In the bottom of the glass you
will find caviar vinaigrette,
topped with puree of
French string bean.
Then finishing the dish
with caviar sauvignon.
Oh, beautiful.
Look at that.
It's rare that I say it's
too beautiful to eat.
I was just thinking that.
Oh, speaking of
fantastically luxurious...
This is a specialty.
Oh, man.
That's truffle.
Mm.
This is a combination of
pheasant, rabbit, seared foir
gras and cabbage.
That is beautiful.
You feel guilty
eating this well?
I do.
You do?
I'm feeling guilty now
but it will pass.
I will follow you.
Wow.
You ever even seen
anything like this?
I haven't seen anything
like this anywhere.
Yeah, me either.
The thing is, you can see the
main pool in front
of the window here.
You can see the hoi paloi.
I was thinking of inviting
them up to our crib for a party.
Don't you do that.
No.
Don't they deserve a good time?
I don't know.
Maybe not.
Not going to happen.
We're getting back to guilt.
Do you feel enlightened and
inspired by this meal?
What are you asking?
What are you getting at here?
You're trying to
get at something.
Trying to make
myself feel better.
I'm trying to prove that I'm
down with the people, man.
I'm still cool.
This guilt keeps coming back.
You keep bringing up the guilt.
You're right.
I feel guilty.
What are you doing here if
you feel so guilty about it?
I don't.
I feel guilty about
not feeling guilty.
That's more to the point.
Now you're being
honest with yourself.
Right.
It's so easy to say I came
out here because it's
a lot of opportunity.
Well, that's really great.
If you're not here for that,
why else are you here?
It's the good old wreck
your life scenario.
That's always pretty popular.
You can change your mind about
wrecking your life,
now what do I do.
There's a lot less
self-reflection about why people
are here than there is
about most other places.
What a lost opportunity that is.
Sinatra and the mob are gone
but there remains still a
certain sentimental attachment
to the way things used to be.
There were rules then, a way
that things were done, and when
they weren't done, there was
always the desert and
a hole in the ground.
Also, there were lounges and rub
joints and places where a man
could get a proper plate of
Italian American
meatballs and spaghets.
Thankfully there are
still such places.
Places like this, the bootleger.
It's a family operation.
Mama Maria's family has been
running it for 41 years.
You got your veal parm,
fetucchini and shrimp.
And believe me, you want it.
Good evening, ladies
and gentlemen.
Welcome to the bootlegger.
Thank you very much.
This is Charlie Schafer,
my esteemed father.
My name is Laura Schafer and we
are your entertainment
for the evening.
♪ I've got the blues
I feel so lonely ♪
♪ I would give the
world if I could only
make him understand oh, that
surely would be grand ♪
the bootlegger has the
reputation for being a locals
joint and it is but there's a
lot of out of towners too,
sentimental fools like me who
did if they don't miss Sinatra,
they miss Dean and Keely Smith.
When I was 19, I got my first
show on the strip and it was a
small casino which is not there
anymore now, it's been imploded
for something newer,
bigger and better.
♪ Baby won't you
please come home ♪
what I do, anyway, it's part
jazz, part nostalgia, but
obviously I do it with a heavy
dose of nostalgia because I'm
recreating the whole look, not
just singing the old songs.
Which is what makes
it fun for me.
♪ To call your name when you
left you broke my heart ♪
pick one, Dean Martin
or frank Sinatra.
You get to see one of them live
in a small room like this.
Frank Sinatra.
Going with Dino.
I like Dino as a person
better because I never heard
anybody say anything
bad about him.
Whereas Sinatra, you would
have a hard time hearing
something good.
There does seem to be a
sound track to old Vegas.
A sound track.
Yeah.
Does that help?
Who, me?
Or other entertainers?
An affection for the classics.
An expectation that while I'm
here, I should hear some
standards.
I don't know if there's a
certain place that people stay
who are sentimental about Las
Vegas because there are very few
hotels left that were
there in the old days.
They have all been imploded.
They recreated ancient Rome
sort of and the Amalfi
coast and Paris.
You would think somebody would
want to recreate Vegas.
I would go there.
I would work there.
♪ Every hour every day
you will hear me say
oh, baby won't you
please come on home
baby won't you
please come home ♪
Thank you very much.
♪
You used to be able to go see
Louie Prima 3:00 A.M., have
breakfast and then go out and
watch the atomic bomb
explode in the distance.
That sounds like a good time.
That's the time I would
like to live in.
Was it better before?
Is it better now?
Is it different?
It's better to
talk about before.
People loved having their mob
stories and there's that
weird romance of bad people.
Yeah.
I don't think it
actually was better.
I think it was really
good if you were Sinatra.
Penn Gillett, another cog in
the entertainment machine though
at a somewhat more
elevated level.
Of the live acts left in Vegas,
his might be the biggest draw.
I suggested this place because
rock off the strip is where
every chef I know who knows
this town said I should go.
The Japanese modern Izikaia,
known as one of the best places
to eat in Vegas,
casual but pricey.
Pricey because the ingredients,
many from around the world.
There is sea urchin
from Santa Barbara.
Okay, that's not
too far, but good.
The tuna is from Spain
where it's best.
The fresh river crab from Japan.
That was good, right?
Yeah.
Delicious.
I didn't know oysters
came that big.
Oh, yeah.
Sashimi, juicy deep
fried chicken.
And one of my favorites, fish
collar, where all the best,
tastiest, moistest, meatiest
bits hide their favors.
Penn has been living here and
performing here for
over 20 years.
He knows.
The thing about magic is, you
cannot see it electronically.
Many people come to Vegas are
people that see one or two live
shows a year and if you see one
or two live shows, you might as
well see something that
you can only see live.
Right.
You can never, ever see a
magician anywhere but live.
These days for better or
worse, live acts, live
performers, are being squeezed
out in favor of EDF,
electronic dance music.
It's a deejay's world and where
once they used to say cocaine
was god's way of telling you had
too much money,
now maybe EDM is.
We get invited to all the
openings of the new clubs but I
simply don't understand it.
I'm embarrassed that I
don't understand it.
Are we just old?
I think that might be it.
I don't know.
You want to spin it the latter,
I'm afraid it might
be the former.
Used to be a whole spectrum
of entertainers who existed
almost entirely in Vegas.
Danny Ganz was huge here.
Wayne Newton.
They were gods.
But what's the big
money draw now?
This.
Come, ye lords and princelings.
Here my clarion call.
Anointed thyself with gel
and heavenly body spray.
Maketh the sign of the devil
horns with thine hands.
Let there be high-fiving and the
hugging of many bros, for this
is the kingdom and the power.
Now frolic and
maketh it to rain.
Power.
It's crazy.
Press a button and
people respond.
They do, man.
Wednesday night at the marquee.
Deejay Jason Lima
works for the house.
Tonight at marquee and in other
clubs like it around Vegas,
somewhere between 8,000 and
10,000 people are going to stop
by and drop a whole
boatload of cash.
It's not just coming in here
and ordering a bottle and
sitting there drinking it.
You get a full-on
group experience.
The new money, the new Vegas,
where the take at the big
nightclubs is outpacing the take
from gambling and slots.
Where everybody for the right
price and with enough sparkles
and the right mix
can be a winner.
After you finish work, how long
does it take for your
adrenaline to level off?
At least an hour.
What are your dreams like now?
I'm not going to lie.
Sometimes I close my eyes and
I still see the strobes.
Ears are ringing.
Still got like flash
of the strobe lights.
Las Vegas is an adult playland.
And that's what we intend to be.
If people want to see Mickey
mouse, they can go 175
miles down the road.
If they want to see bugsy Siegel
under a rock, they stay here.
Is there a Mr. Vegas like
Elvis or Wayne Newton or
bugsy Siegel used to be?
If there is, it would
probably be this guy.
Former mayor Oscar Goodman.
A man who knows allegedly and to
the best of my knowledge where
all the bodies are buried, some
of them equally allegedly by
some of his former clients.
We meet over drinks at Oscar's,
the steakhouse that bears his
name and boasts beef,
booze and braudz.
Broads.
Who was nice and who was
less fun to have...
The truth of the matter is,
all my clients were nice to me
because I kept them
out of prison.
Did alleged mob guys
know how to eat?
My mother used to say
two things, she said.
She was the greatest lady.
She said Oscar's clients don't
hurt anybody, they
just kill each other.
And she also said Oscar's
clients take us to the best
restaurants.
They knew where to go.
Yeah.
And were always treated right.
They were always treated
like kings and queens.
Did the feds hold
it against you?
You were just doing your job.
They didn't see it that way.
They thought I was
a consigliere.
In order to murder somebody,
they had to get my permission.
That's how stupid
these people were.
These were gentlemen not
unknown to mayor Goodman.
A lot of people tell you
there's a better place when
the mob was running it.
In many ways, that's true.
There were rules
then that mattered.
You know the old saying, what
happens in Vegas stays in Vegas.
Back when the mob ran things,
there was a certain urgency
to that suggestion.
Talking about with prince
Harry, that's a perfect example.
Here's a guy who was
here having a good time.
In the old Vegas, that
would never have happened.
There would never have
been a disclosure.
In today's modern age it was all
over the world in moments.
Moments.
Yes.
It says something about the
town that his honor served
three terms as mayor.
He's unabashed booster,
entrepreneur, drinker of hard
liquor and gambler and he was
never shy about admitting it.
It's unique.
It's its own hothouse
environment.
Vegas is unique.
But I'll tell you one thing, you
go to the airport,
everybody is smiling.
They can't wait to lose their
money and afterwards
they're smiling.
It's a special place where
people can take their basest
instincts and just let it fly.
I think that's good.
I have no problem
with that at all.
When you come to
Vegas, you see this.
The lights and smoke and
mirrors, the casino floors.
But who manages the machine?
Where did they come from?
Beneath the floors, behind
the walls, above the winking
surveillance camera lenses, a
whole other world manned by
thousands and thousands of
waiters, maintenance people,
repairmen, chefs,
engineers, plumbers.
Three shifts a day they slip in
and out of the casinos almost
unseen through their own
entrances but it's these people
who have seen it all, seen
everything, night after night.
Kenny has been working here
since Caesar's opened
in August of 1966.
He's dealt cards to everybody.
I've dealt to Diana Ross,
Harry Belafonte, Sinatra.
Sinatra was not supposed to
be particularly
amiable at the table.
Sinatra was class.
Really?
He was class.
He was a gentleman.
But those were the good days.
But it's nice now, too.
Would you describe yourself
as a degenerate gambler?
I'm trying to move past that.
We have a 2-year-old at home.
But I'll always have that
gambling gear, no doubt about
it.
Eric and Erica are
professional gamblers, poker
players, to be precise.
It's routine for them to sit
down to a game with a bankroll
of half a million dollars.
Tonight, slightly
smaller stakes.
Hey, how do you like my chances?
Good.
That's a trained answer.
Instead of actual poker, we
are set up with a dumbed down
for the camera version
of Texas hold 'em.
You play against the house.
The odds, to say the least,
are stacked against you.
Oh, here's a winner.
Here's a winner.
Two pair.
He's cutting up over there.
See how easy it is?
You got this game down.
Uh-oh.
Those are famous last words.
All right.
Let's put out a hundred
dollars, see what happens.
All right.
Now we have a pair of 7s.
I want to bet.
Okay.
I have trips.
That's going to be
pretty hard to beat.
You're a dead man, Benny.
I'm a dead man.
I'll bet again.
Okay.
Two pair.
Pair of deuces.
Pair of 10s.
Oh, no.
Pair of kings.
Benny!
Goodness, Benny.
Huh?
You got a full house.
This is unbelievable.
Is there a cooler
standing behind us?
All right.
That works for me.
Thank you very much.
This is what we call a learning
experience in my case.
That was fun.
We got away with our shirts.
Let's not do it again.
Let's never do it again.
It's easy to find people
that will help you but
somebody's got to be the one to
create the mess in
the first place.
Where's our metaphor here?
Untangle this.
This is going to be so much fun.
Anthony Bondi is an artist
and a born and bred
Las Vegas native.
After many adventures and I'm
guessing some misadventures as
well, he chose to live here.
To what degree am I complicit
in the worst of our city by
making art that
glorifies the city?
I don't profit directly from
what those people do but of
course, I do, because I live in
the city and as that money
rolls all around us.
But how do we live with it?
It's not why and where the
people come from who do the
grotesque things people do here.
It's how do we live
here complicit in it.
That's the big issue to be
self-reflective about the place
or you have to go and stay high
all the time because
of the shame.
You know, which is another
popular way to deal
with living here.
Is Vegas a friendly town?
Yeah, because that's our job.
But I mean to itself.
You're a local.
No.
Not a bit.
This town has never had any
respect for the people who
just happened to live here.
In the old day, we were
co-conspirators in those days.
We weren't citizens.
The new authority, the new power
is exactly as anonymous
as the old power.
No poll number, no access.
Though it's been for some
years an art community in Vegas,
you know, like art that makes
your life, all our lives,
better and makes us think.
Granted, Vegas is a town
designed to make you not think,
just separate you from your
money in as pleasurable
a way as possible.
So pleasurable that even after
you limp out of town leaking
from your... with nothing in
your pockets, you want to
come back and do it again.
Reflection, not so good.
As a resident, what are the
general rules of survival?
Don't cry about being broke.
If I'm broke, it's because I
threw away my money and too bad
for me because I
didn't get lucky.
Don't complain
about being broke.
Okay.
What's another one?
Well, smile.
That is absolutely
local characteristic.
This is a service industry town.
One of our roles here has
always been to take away excess
money from people who don't know
what to do with it and who can't
think of a better idea about
how to spend their money.
We'll always take it.
Is that worse than before?
The wrong is there are people
with that kind of income who
could put it to so many
thrilling uses and can think of
nothing so crass and boring than
to wave the money in the
air and throw it away.
How loathesome but within those
of us who live here
is that challenge.
This has always been.
Here we are.
You are sitting in the best
Thai restaurant in Vegas by far.
One of the best Thai
restaurants in America.
Jet has been here before.
An L.A. guy, he came out here to
do four years as executive chef
at encore, a Wynn
casino on the strip.
He's a reigning authority on
Thai food but really, everybody
who loves Thai food
knows about this place.
What you should order here
should only be northern.
You go to the back of the menu,
it's northern specialties.
You come here and eat chicken
with cashew nuts, I'm going
to punch you in the face.
Right.
Sipend is the owner and chef.
Now get this.
And it's important.
You don't do pad Thai here.
You do what they are uniquely
superb at which is specifically
the food of northern Thailand.
♪
Oh, yeah, yeah, of
course, love it.
Chili dip.
It's really more of like a
composed room temperature salad.
This is a puffed crispy rice
salad with preserved pork
sausage.
That's good.
Jackfruit salad.
This is a pork curry braised
down with garlic and ginger.
This pork is amazing.
Isn't that great?
And that's northern love.
Right.
Very important dish.
Oh, that looks really pretty.
This is the food
my grandma made.
That's perfection, man.
What I love about Vegas Asian
food is on one street you have
the best Cantonese food, you
drive down the street and
get the best Thai food.
How did that happen?
Gambling.
But I mean, were there high
rollers who would come into
town... a dude
with a $10 million
credit line that wins will go
eat a $10 Chinese meal because
it's the closest thing
he has to home food.
I'm going to eat Asian food,
come back and drop $5 million
more and then go home.
This is what avant gard cooking
is. People think that we want
to do things in a way
because we want to be cool.
No.
We do it because really, we
believe we are increasing the
value of the product
we are working with.
We are giving you the essence.
Tonight, tucked away in the
back of another of Jose's
restaurants, behind the guys
making paieia over a flame in
the center of a
crowded dining room.
Quiet, serene, a kind of magic.
This is granted a far cry from
the $1 shrimp cocktail and the
all you can eat buffets groaning
under the weight of
a thousand carbs.
Ham and bean soup with
black and roasted garlic.
The world's best,
like from Spain.
Nitro almond cup, a frozen shell
made from a puree of almonds,
filled with almond milk espuma
and finished with caviar.
You know, chef, this meal
is working very well.
My palate is open, I'm
intrigued, I'm only growing more
hungry and excited.
The desired effect
is taking hold.
If you were a famous chef and
you are lured as so many are to
rivers of green promised by
Vegas, it's nice if you can
get yourself a playroom.
Gentlemen, this is foam.
He doesn't say air.
Water is not water anymore.
Water has a body, belongs.
The truffle egg, truffles
formed into an egg shape with an
actual yolk suspended
in the center.
I think we will be feeding
our kichickens truffles.
Served with onion puree, and
finished with more
shaved white truffle.
This is crispy chicken skin.
Sliding this off
right into my face.
This is your portion and
Brian is going to come finish it
with a Clementine sauce for you.
Gentlemen, this is
your next course.
Awesome.
It's a secret cut.
You know the work that goes
into creating a dish like this?
They say the chef was not there.
Then look at the food critics
saying it's almost like
a lack of respect.
Who do you think
these people are?
Where do you think
they come from?
Everyone one of those amazing
sous chefs we have, they are as
good, if not better, than the
guys that have the big name
on top with neon letter.
There is not an acre of
preserved Mojave desert in the
city limbs of Las Vegas.
Why would you preserve this?
This desolation
is not nurturing.
We can't be here unless there's
a lot of technology
supporting our presence.
And so there's a sense of
the city versus nature.
This is not our friend.
You would think looking at
the vast lake, the canals, the
fountains of Vegas in the middle
of a desert, the flush of
100,000 toilets and the casinos
and what they bring would
constitute an obscene
waste of water.
And indeed water is at a
desperate premium as water
levels decrease at
an alarming rate.
But it isn't the casinos
that are the culprits.
In fact, Vegas casinos are a
model of water efficiency
and conservation.
Main culprit?
All-American lawn.
A little square of green.
Robert Kern is water police.
He patrols the Vegas streets
looking for evidence
of water violations.
Saw some water in the
gutter on both sides.
This is not their day.
We're in an area where there
shouldn't be any water,
yet there's water here.
That's what we do, we drive
around looking for something
like that, to give them
a little education.
Hey, you're not supposed
to water today.
So you don't wrestle them to
the ground, cuff
them and drag them?
No, we do not.
Although we have a fee.
How much?
$80.
Then it doubles.
It.
It seems a losing battle
to keep your grass green.
Most everyone came from the
east coast and everything
was lush and green.
That's what Vegas
was 20 years ago.
The city assigns watering
days to control useage, and also
encourages a landscaping style
focused on drought-resistant
plants and efficient irrigation.
And if you don't get with the
program, there's a hole out
there in the desert for you.
Okay, not really.
You get a notice pinned to
your door or something.
But some people want the lawn?
Got to have it.
They can have it, just don't
water on the wrong days.
How critical is it?
Very.
I mean, there's no snow on the
western sierras, so we don't get
any continued flow into the
Colorado dumping into lake mead.
Unless something drastically
changes in the near future.
But got to stay positive.
For the first 30, 40 year,
you just couldn't conceive
of what was ahead.
What we had, whatever was the
newest thing that was happening
was so spectacular and wonderful
and oh, my gosh, we reached a
new eastern edge, a western
edge, a northern edge.
The odds are slim to zero that
we're going to extend it to
yet an even further horizon.
It was unconceivable.
So there's the thing.
The desert exceeds our ambition.
In Vegas, nothing is permanent.
It constantly eats itself, tears
down, builds up, expands
according to no known or
easily understood plan.
An organic thing responding to
the dark dreams of the
American sub conscious.
Come frolic, live like Caesar,
or make money off those who do.
Drop a few moist bills
in a gas station slot.
See the full spectrum of human
folly and commit some
follies of your own.