My great fear is a
fear of failing.
And that's Hawaiian because I
was born that way because
that's expectation.
You're Hawaiian, you're
going to be less.
going to feel more.
It's old.
It's in you.
It's part of your identity.
But when I navigate a voyage, I
know when the storm comes, it's
going to take you to the bone.
And if the storm keeps coming,
you've got to stand up.
That's just what
you've got to do.
It's this zone where you learn
to make fear your best friend.
You hold it really close to you
and you open up the door to
believing that you can make it.
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ Sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la la
♪ sha la la la la
Hawaii is America.
As American as anything
could possibly be.
Yet also never shed what was
there before in the layers and
layers that have come since.
It's a wonderful tricky
conflicted mutant in lack of a
better word you'd have
to call paradise.
No man's paradise.
Paradises don't exist.
Paradise is kind
of in your head.
Wait a minute.
You look at your window here.
You look at those hills, those
mountains, all that
green, that blue sky.
The clear sea.
It sure looks like
paradise to me.
This guy knows.
He's been everywhere.
He's Paul Theru.
He's a legendary travel writer.
Of the all the places he's been,
all the places he's seen, he
chose Hawaii to live and he's
lived here for 25 years.
Does it matter
that it's America?
It's the big thing
that it's America.
It has elements of
the third world.
The nicest elements of the third
world which is the
self-respect, the pride.
Things that don't work at all.
And then it's USA.
Where we are now.
There's PTA meetings here.
They get together and watch the
super bowl and it's the most
main street USA you will find.
Town is a neighborhood spot in
the district and as Hawaii is
the only state in the union that
allows fishermen to sell to
restaurants, the pan-roasted
mahi-mahi is pretty damn good.
It's not a particularly
welcoming or friendly part of
the world.
Contrary to the sort
of the aloha myth.
No, that's right.
But no island is.
Nantucket isn't.
The island of Hawaii isn't.
An island that, want
foreigners there?
Sicily.
Did anyone come to an island
with a good intention?
No, never in this new world.
Best case in the world,
bring syphilis.
Pretty much.
At the very least.
Yes.
Captain cook put his sailors
ashore just to look
northwest of here.
The first.
Hawaii killed its first tourist.
Philippines killed their first
tourist but people on the
islands born on the islands.
View anyone who comes
ashore with suspicion.
What defines a Hawaiian?
Maybe should go back in our
imaginations to could have been
2,000 years ago.
The Tahitians had this voyage
way before any other culture
was exploring the deep seas.
Somehow, someplace in the south
pacific, single most
isolated in the planet.
Fast forward to captain cook and
get a glimpse, very
productive people.
They're industrious, healthy.
For the arts.
That was a large population,
more than half of what we have
in Hawaii today.
Fully sustainable, because
there was no other choice.
So over time, the native
Hawaiian population goes to
22,000.
It's the same story.
Introduced, the inability to
deal with it, people die.
1926, public school system would
outlaw language and the practice
of culture in public schools.
So extinctions well paid.
Between captain cook's
arrival in 1778 and today,
disease wiped out most
of the population.
Missionaries came.
A booming sugar and pineapple
plantation industry.
Influx of immigrants in Okinawa,
China, and the Philippines,
the overthrow.
And the U.S. takeover of
the Hawaiian government.
World war ii.
And finally, statehood.
The geographical realities of
being thousands of miles from,
well, anywhere else, has
given Hawaii to some degree,
protection from the forces that
eradicated so many other south
pacific cultures entirely.
In fact, they've arguably been
holding back the inevitable
better than just about anyone.
What Hawaii looks like today
depends which island you're
standing on and to some extent,
the reputation of the locals.
The Hawaiian islands
are not a monolith.
Islands, that's plural and we're
talking eight very different
islands with very different
identities.
It's been over a century since
the waves of immigrants began
and things got all mixed up
in the best possible way.
There's layers.
And a simple question like, who
is Hawaiian gets you
all kinds of answers.
The neighborhood of Kalihi is
far from what most know and most
specific kind the last 40 years.
It's the blue collar town.
They all come here.
Breakfast, lunch.
Every day.
I'm joined by two local chefs,
Mark Maguchi of mission,
known by some as the gooch.
Second generation
Japanese and Andrew.
He's first generation Vietnamese
American or would that be
Vietnamese Hawaiian?
As you'll see, it
gets complicated.
I actually cooked on the east
coast for three years and people
would always be like,
are you from Hawaii?
You're Hawaiian?
I said, no.
Japanese.
But Hawaiian?
No, I realized like, here in
Hawaii, we identify ourselves
ethnically versus
geographically.
No way we would call
ourselves Hawaiians.
We would get our asses
kicked by a Hawaiian.
Who is Hawaiian?
A native of the land.
In your blood.
You come from a lineage of
native Hawaiian people.
What's here?
I feel like Hawaiian
in a sense, you know.
It's my place.
But culturally, that's
a different story.
You say you're not Hawaiian.
No.
What's your feeling about
so you're Hawaiian.
I'm born and raised,
going to die 808.
Aka mob, mainly Japanese
husband, and daughter, who I
guess would be Japanese,
Okinawan/Hawaiian and
son-in-law, Robert, who
is of course, Mexican.
That's pretty.
Ooh, look at that.
That looks good.
Now we are talking.
That's awesome.
I just caught local food.
When I look at this
table, it's just Hawaii.
Got Portuguese, Japanese.
Okinawa Okinawan, world war ii.
I don't know.
Korea?
Korean, Japanese, Hawaiian.
Awesomeness.
The food is bone deep Hawaiian
stuff, which is to say
delicious mash-up, okay.
Take taco rice.
It's a dish created in Okinawa
to approximate Tex-Mex
appropriated by younger
generations of Okinawan and
Japanese found its
way back to Hawaii.
Got that?
Identify, my best friends
were native Hawaiian.
Helped me to realize the
pride of being from Hawaii,
understanding the
Hawaiian culture.
Living it.
Possibly Japanese.
There's still a
movement to sovereign.
There's strong movement.
So if fighting broke out,
which side are you on?
You don't have to
think about that.
I would joke about it.
If like, me and Hawaii.
I am back and uncle Sam and were
like, no, native Hawaiian only,
I'm like, everybody needs to
cook.
I'm a cook.
I have worth!
This is Ninoa Thompson.
In 1976 with similarly heroic
Hawaiians, he did a difficult
important thing.
Before 1972, it was generally
assumed even insisted upon
that Hawaii had been settled
originally by some random
savages who maybe drifted over
accidentally from south America.
Couldn't have been ancient
Polynesians across thousands of
miles of open water.
No dreams.
No hope.
Can't see.
They were set out to prove
that's what did happen.
There were those in the
community that loved this,
prayed for it.
It was powerful.
It changed everything.
The hokulaia.
A kind of craft believed to have
been used in those times
and only using primitive
contemporaneous navigational
tools sailed to Tahiti and back.
The trip that helped spark a
Hawaiian renaissance, a rebirth
of pride and interest in
traditional Hawaiian culture and
identity.
The success was monumental.
Changed the view of ancestors as
extraordinarily skilled
and so we come from them.
Thomas is a water man
who continues to sail.
Native Hawaii, his roots go
back in the valley 200 years.
My grandfather was born here.
So I grew up.
Spent many years learning
techniques from a master.
Now the small
Micronesian island.
He was put to be trained and
learning the wind and the water
and the zone, he was sailing.
The canoe make me sick, my
grandfather threw me into the
ocean to go inside the wave.
When I go inside the
wave, I become the wave.
When I become the
wave, now I navigate.
I approached him.
Said to me, too old?
You want someone to
know everything.
Send his son.
He said I'll teach you enough to
find the island you seek, but
I can't teach you the magic.
Why do you think it was
important to do such a thing?
The same story you'll see
everywhere in terms of the
indigenous people.
My father's mother, nearly pure
Hawaiian, chooses not to teach
her children language or
culture or genealogy.
Where do you come?
Who's your family?
What's your name, and that could
have been 100 generations.
What the voyage did was a
reconnection back to feeling
wholesome about who you are,
because knowing where you come
from and who are your ancestors.
This this wasn't.
It was symbolic.
A bumper sticker,
t-shirt emerged.
I'm proud to be Hawaiian.
1987, first language.
Mandatory in schools.
Has to be taught.
Private schools won't have
attendance if you don't teach
Hawaiian.
Now Hawaiian identity
into everything.
It has to be recognized
in everything.
That is powerful.
What I mentioned to people, is
in Ooahu, that I was going
Moliki, a lot were surprised.
They said the Malachi dudes were
mean, unfriendly, tough as iron
and quick to get pissed off.
As it turned out, that
was not my experience.
We like to brag that we
don't have traffic lights.
We only have traffic.
Nice.
Walter Naki is a skilled
fisherman and today, we head out
for some octopus.
It's not the friendly island.
Supposed to be the most
unfriendly island.
Traditionally, we're
here very freely.
Now, unfreely is where you
go try to come and fix it.
That's when it
becomes unfriendly.
We had a lot still in tact.
Still?
Yes.
But there is always other
people that want to come.
Unsurprisingly, fishing rights
is an issue around here.
Don't come over here sport
fishing the wrong place if you
know what's good for you.
So this is the area.
Okay, ready?
Let's go.
We are here, man.
Culture.
We keep the feeling there, make
them feel, not going
to take no more.
Come right up, stick them.
Final step, stun the struggling
creature with a sharp
blow from the mallet or if you
want to go old school, fight
them right in the bray.
In my case, it took repeated
crunching for the
chicklet sized organ.
This one died eventually, likely
by exhaustion as anything
else, I suspected.
Hawaiian renaissance.
This is what really
set things off.
Beginning in 1941 continuing
into the '70s and beyond, the
U.S. Navy been using the
beautiful neighborhood island of
Kaloa as a bombing range.
People have never been happy
about it but emboldened by times
and recent events, a group of
young activists decided
to take a stand.
In 1976, there were a number of
attempted occupations of the
island in protest
of the bombing.
None more successful
than Walter.
He and fellow activist, Richard
Sawyer, sat on the island
and refused to leave.
Back over there.
Managing to evade pursuers just
over a month before finally
being arrested in jail.
The first here.
They emerged, of course, heroes.
And these protests went on to
inspire many others to
enjoy the movement.
Still alive when they happen.
I want to see.
And em body the independent
spirit and desire for Hawaiian
sovereignty that today
resonates across generations.
Welcome to supposedly the most
unwelcoming place in Hawaii.
♪
My name is Hanuhanu.
Nice to meet you.
Please come inside.
Aloha.
This is a shared community
space with a sacred history.
Hano Hano is the caretaker of
the fish pond and here is the
famous Walter Ritty.
Everyone knows how valuable
this is because we can see what
happened to the
rest of the island.
Essentially an old
school fish farm.
800 years old.
Modernizing one old idea and
an ancient idea simple as
feeding your community.
This, the island you're on, this
place could feed over a million
people back in the day.
You hear the word again
and again on Molki.
I know.
Means land and translates
to that which feeds you.
Springs, mountains, rivers.
Fresh water from the
fast moving oceans met.
Early, sustainable
clean fish farms.
Something in modern times, we're
still struggling to figure out.
People think about us.
The true story, we have a place
of abundance and trying to
protect it.
Trying to protect all of these
things we've been trying to
protect for the last 30 years
and it's getting harder and
harder.
Every single one of these
Hawaiians over here, get enough
evidence that the state of
Hawaii, the department of
natural resources have
done a terrible job.
We're not even
looking for blame.
We're looking for an
agreement for today.
Right.
We all are going to be pono.
We're all going to be
righteous and good.
Our planet is in such bad shape
that being environmental,
being green is trending.
That's how Hawaiians
have always been.
Who gets to be Hawaiian?
Is it the question,
who is Hawaiian?
You can be Hawaiian.
Come on.
Don't now.
I have to be born here.
This is a different story.
I can give you the
best explanation.
You cannot be our blood.
You cannot be kanapa.
Hawaii is our nationality.
It matters so much, if you love
this place and you don't want to
develop it, destroy, abuse
it, we're on the same team.
If you, in this place as a
money-making vehicle for
yourself, we enemies.
Right, and it doesn't matter
what race, religion, what sex.
If you love this place and the
way we love it and our ancestors
loved it, oh, we can be more
than friends but we can be
family.
I'm going to aloha you.
Beautifully put.
Wow.
That's it.
Right on, bro.
Slow roasted pig,
grilled kala fish.
Cooked.
And of course, octopus.
Known as squid luau.
Fresh poi.
You've got to have it fresh.
Believe me.
Makes all the difference
in the world.
Fresh water snails called I
believe hihi vine harvested from
streams way up in the mountains.
Up in the mountain.
Squid.
That's octopus?
Oh.>up in the mountain.
Squid.
That's octopus?
Oh.>up in the mountain.
Squid.
That's octopus?
Oh. Up in the mountain.
Squid.
That's octopus?
Oh.
I recognize you.
♪
When somebody steals this, it's
easy for us to say, you're
stealing our stuff.
Right?
But all of this stuff is
dependent on what healthy
environment and Eco-system is.
Let me ask you just because
I'm a bit of a dick.
I have to ask.
All right.
So we have like 12 more beers.
And I pull out some nice suvi.
I would eat them.
Look, I would eat them.
That doesn't mean it's
what I feed my children.
Our culture made everything
we did the best of the best.
Hawaiians are the only one
that turned into poi.
We're doing the best.
Introduce Christianity to us,
we're going to do the best.
Our Christianity is
better than yours.
I love it.
So disappointed, no way live up
to your reputation, mean,
inward looking, hostile.
Admit it.
It's a calculated strategy.
It is.
And the message, if you're
watching this show, I hope your
heart is swelling
with admiration.
The bottom line,
don't come here.
Yeah!
The ocean is all around
for thousands of miles.
A humbling feeling knowing at
all times the ground upon which
you live and breathe is but a
tiny speck in the
middle of all this.
So in Hawaii, the water, man,
is an important distinct.
It expresses the shared
consensus you're able to handle
yourself in the ocean no
matter what it throws at you.
It implies you're capable
of almost mythical things.
The ability to live in the
water, handle many moves above
or below the surface.
Meet uncle Ross.
A canoe-surfing legend and
generally accepting ambassador
of the aloha spirit.
He's offered to share the truly
ancient Hawaiian space found
only on the face of
a crashing wave.
Surfing, a life connected to
the ocean, just spending time
with family and friends on the
beach, some of the
cornerstones of Hawaiian life.
This is decent.
Tony, that's Kiola.
How are you?
Kiave.
Megan.
Hello.
Those are my two daughters.
This is my wife, Felicia.
Hi, how are you?
Come say hi.
Milton.
This is Milton.
How does everybody
know each other here?
We live on an island.
Everybody knows everybody.
Why do I even ask?
I think I met uncle
Ross through the water.
Surfing, we became like family.
He's like my dad.
My ohana.
Each and every weekend, Ross
can be found here with his
ohana, extended
family and friends.
Beautiful day.
Even when it's storming,
it's nice on the beach.
Yeah.
And we'll stay here until
that thing goes down.
Hits the horizon.
When the sun hits the horizon,
it's time to go home.
Maui is an island as beautiful
as it gets and sure,
it's got share of
portion-controlled cruise line
entertainments, doled out
and digestible bites and
complementary Mai Tais but a
beloved institution like tasty
crust.
Local a place as
you're likely to find.
Daniel Akitahito will explain.
This is a situation I
can order for you.
I think we'll hook you up
with the local flavor.
Okay, I trust.
Raised on the big island,
he's a journalist.
First Hawaiian editor of a major
surf publication and founder of
the local contrast magazine.
Local culture is very much so
trying to point a finger at
anybody coming going,
hey, you don't belong.
Therein kind of lies a little
conflict we have of being a
modern day Hawaiian.
And I still think that's
something we forget about these
days is how educated and how
accepting our ancestors were.
It was always built on
incluesivity, aloha.
Aloha is giving without
expecting anything in return.
You've got a Hawaiian
culture part of
populated the islands and the
local part of the plantation
lifestyle.
The Japanese, the Chinese, the
Koreans, Filipinos, Portuguese.
All can be explained
what's on your plate.
This is a prime example.
Behold.
The most identifiable and
essential feature of the plate
lunch is this.
A big scoop or two of white
rice and potato Mac salad.
There is nothing more Hawaiian
with protein or this hamburger
steak, like Patty drowned in
dark sinister
stinky shiny gravy.
Or voodoo nori with sesame seed.
That looks beautiful.
That's going to work.
All right.
Sit this right on
top of the rice.
Yep.
Get some of that
salad on there too.
Get the gravey on.
They're fundamentally local.
This food, the most delicious,
let's be honest, delicious.
This is not healthy eating.
We're kind of paying the price
for it right now in the
health of the state.
Which is terrible.
As I take a bite of a hamburger.
As I said, just so good.
If you really want to do Hawaii
right, you've got to get
that.
That's a power that Hawaii has
is that if you show aloha and
you give without asking, the Ina
is going to recognize it and
shower its blessings upon you.
So you think traditional
Hawaiian culture and lifestyle
has a chance against
the modern world?
I think so.
The beautiful part about my
ancestors is they realized there
was a limited number of
resources where they lived, so
they observed nature to the best
possible they could to figure
out what were the cycles and how
do we preserve this resource?
Hawaiian culture can teach the
whole world something that it
needs to know, that we
all live on an island.
And we are all part of
the same community.
Let's all show aloha to the Ina
and everybody else as well.
An extraordinary man
lives in this house.
Chef Gordon.
Long time resident on Maui.
Legendary talent manager.
Maybe you know some of the
people whose careers he's looked
after.
Alice Cooper.
Blondie.
Pink Floyd.
He was years ahead of
the chef explosion.
Shepherding emeril
through his career.
Great chefs like Roger.
Close to holiness
the Dalai lama.
Basically done everything with
everybody in every place.
I first got here 40 years ago.
I put one foot on the island and
I knew I was living here
the rest of my life.
Do you ever look out there
and it's wallpaper?
I say it out loud.
First words in the morning.
Thank you, thank you,
thank you, thank you.
Every day.
Chef is famously one of the
most generous and enthusiastic
of hosts, a more stand-up loyal
guy you could barely imagine
and no wonder they call the
documentary based on his
life "super Mitch."
That's how he's known
around the world.
Here, he's known that guy
who throws great parties.
Prep starts early.
With chef's friend, Julio, a
Maui-born and bred rancher with
help from Sheldon.
Middle of the night, in a
traditional emu is done filled
with lava rocks.
The fire allowed to burn down to
coals before the pig wrapped in
combination of banana leaves
and tea leaves is dropped in.
Okay, you guys ready
for the unveiling?
Hold on.
12 hours later, you dig it up
and well, it's party time.
What you've been saying is
you've been drinking steadily
since 5:00 this morning.
I didn't say, it didn't
come out of my mouth.
Behold.
The magnificence.
It's a very important
part of your childhood.
Dun dun.
Wow.
Look at that.
You just lift the
bones out by hand.
Yep.
Ready?
Just dump them in into a bucket.
Awesome.
Wow.
That's pretty much the
way I want to end up.
Pour me into a pot.
There's lots to do and
everyone pitches in to help.
It's an extended, all day affair
of prepping, chopping,
dicing, slicing, mixing.
Of course there is some
sampling along the way.
Like this wild pig sausage that
someone was nice enough
to stop by with.
Sheldon works up a
potato-Mac salad.
One more type.
Hit me one more time.
Julio carves up unicorn fish
he caught earlier in the day.
A couple of fresh red snappers
are stuffed before being
thrown in the oven.
There is Po I pounded
fresh out back.
Somewhere, somewhere pig's foot
soup is happily bubbling away.
Why do I want to do this?
There is chili pepper water used
for dipping or taken as a shot
for boner medicine or whatever.
Oh, yeah.
There is also spam noodles.
There is no party without spam.
By dinner time the beerks wine
and festive beverages have
been flowing for hours.
Moods have been adjusted in
a completely natural way
indigenous to the
islands, of course.
How about Julio and the pig?
Oh, man.
I have cooked a lot of things.
I ain't never seen one poured.
Into a pot neatly.
It's what I love.
This is what we
do on the island.
This is what it's about.
Always bring the
family, the kids.
You rarely ever see a party
where there aren't kids.
Ohana means the... family.
Extended family.
Like you are now ohana
to everybody here.
So we can borrow money from you.
As happens, I have come to
find out things end up in the
most natural kind of happens
why, songs and dancing.
♪
This is Willie K. And that's
his daughter Lisette.
It's pretty damn captivating.
♪
It's getting near
the ender for me.
I look over at sheep and see a
happy man surrounded by friends,
his family really... his ohana.
To be Hawaiian to me, there
needs to be a sense of
connection to a place.
Some sense of
responsibility for it.
It's about being honest to a
place, honest to what you love
and honest to what you value is
a road that's constantly trying
to be more and more informer
presidented.
I don't know sometimes
how to be fully honest.
I don't know enough.
What I love about the
oceans, that's my path way.
I go on the oceans to
seek that sense of truth.
They said I can see
whales, like close up.
I had reasons for optimism.
All week I had been staring out
to see watching lump back whales
spouting and frolicking
out of the ocean.
Are things compared to other
parts of the word, are
conservation of efforts as far
as marine mammal miss if general
but whales this
particular going well?
That's the one thing
on the planet that is.
They are talking about taking
humpbacks off the endangered
species list.
It's good to hear they have
recovered but it may make it
ease stairway the add to
the whaling list again.
It's mating season in Hawaii
for nearly 10,000 humpback
whales that migrate from
southeast Alaska each year.
Dr. Joe Mobli of the university
of Hawaii dedicated his career
to studying these whales.
I guess the song is supposed
to be the most complex display
in the an ma kingdom.
When you are close you can feel
it through your whole body.
180 db, really loud.
Wow.
They don't mind us
at all, do they?
♪
Oh, we got it.
Amazing.
That was incredible.
Unbelievable.