This house came to be built by Dr.
Blake.
My grandfather came to be
nominated to the council of
state which used to be a
part of British India.
It was another time, one
that few still remember.
The India before partition, when
these rooms, this house, was
part of the seat of power.
I had the privilege of being
born in this house upstairs.
This was the maharajah's bed.
His chambers are present.
We went up to my grandfather's
room to wish him
good morning and we would
all come down to breakfast.
The walls tell a story.
Many stories.
There used to be a
lot of animosity.
There were two very divided
classes in India so there was a
lot of tension between the
ruled and the rulers.
But that was a different
time, you know.
Now I think back and it's
more like a fairy tale.
♪
Day one in northern India
near the Pakistan border.
This is the Indian
Punjab’s largest city.
Population, about a million.
This is a part of India I have
never seen, a place I have
always been curious about, home
to some pretty
legendary cuisine.
They have a saying, the best
food isn't cooked
in people's homes.
You find it on the streets.
♪
Punjabis are known for their
adventurous spirit as brave
warriors who spread throughout
the world, bringing
great food with them.
♪
In fact, much of the good stuff
we refer to simply as Indian
food comes from here.
The Punjab of the early 20th
century saw some of the most
violent resistance
to British rule.
And when the British finally
cashed out in 1947, they carved
off a huge piece,
what is now Pakistan.
And it remains a potential
flashpoint for conflict.
But that's easy to forget when
you first smell the food.
There we go.
Dhaba meaning side of the
road food stall and there are
countless dhabas to choose from
in this town but this
one is legendary.
See Tony eat vegetables.
And like it.
To eat around this part of
the world, Punjab in particular,
get used to eating a
lot of vegetables.
India is one of the few places
on earth where even for
me, that's not a burden.
What's that?
I'll take that.
Right here, my good man.
Mm.
That's good.
In the Punjab, meat or no
meat, you are almost guaranteed
a free for all of intense
colors, flavors and spices.
Unlike some of the joyless
vegetarian restaurants in my sad
experience, vegetables here are
actually spicy, all taste
different, different textures.
And served with
extraordinarily good bread.
It's got this multi-tiered
crispy on the outside,
chewy in the middle.
It's a whole different
experience.
If this was what vegetarianism
meant in most of the places that
practice it in the west, I would
be at least half as much less of
a... about the subject.
If you made bread this good,
I might eat in your restaurant.
Mm.
Around here, one of the first
things you notice that's
different from the rest of
India, turbans everywhere.
The symbol of self-respect,
bravery and spirituality
for Sikh men.
This is the home, the spiritual
center of the Sikh faith, the
world's largest and maybe
most misunderstood religion.
In the heart stands the majestic
golden temple, the Sikh
equivalent of the Vatican.
Sikhs are fundamentally against
any caste system, believers in
religious tolerance, but they
are just as fundamentally
war-like when it comes to
defending their principles
and what they see as their
territory.
Welcome to golden temple.
Thank you.
Today is one of the most
auspicious days of the Sikh
calendar.
Pilgrims from all over the world
come to worship, walk the
perimeter and bathe
in the holy pool.
All are welcome of any faith or
caste to remove their shoes,
wash their feet, cover their
heads and take part
in a simple meal.
This is a free vegetarian meal
served to many thousands of
visitors from every walk of
life every day of the year.
They serve 16 hours a day?
16 hour a day.
For how many years?
Continuously?
300 years.
Everyone doing the cooking,
the serving, the washing of
thousands and thousands of metal
plates and utensils,
are volunteers.
The sound is extraordinary.
We have a feeling that
everyone should serve to other
people free of cost.
Walking me through it
all Tod Tod today.
For a religion so concerned with
tolerance, where does the
tradition come from?
Powerful people,
hard-working people.
Every Sikh you have seen, when
we get baptized, you must
protect yourself, you must
protect others and you must
protect your country so
that makes us what we are.
Morning.
The smoke from countless burning
fields covers the
city in a thick haze.
The ancient art evolved from
Indian wrestling techniques that
date back to the
fifth century B.C.
Ready, start!
Training is rigid.
This is not just a sport,
but a way of life.
Wrestlers live and train
together and have strict rules
of diet and personal conduct.
No smoking, no drinking,
no contact with women.
I took high school wrestling so
that I could get
out of gym class.
I was a dirty, dirty fighter.
It's an all too natural segue
between the aggressive posturing
of opposing bodies and this.
The entire border between India
and Pakistan has
only one crossing.
Here.
Every sunset the border is
officially closed with this
bit of national theater.
Wearing nearly duplicate
uniforms, the Indian military
and Pakistani rangers partake in
a game of theatrical contempt.
Clearly it's a popular show.
So where are we?
We are right next to Pakistan.
India and Pakistan were once
one country, ripped apart in one
of the hastiest, ill-considered
partitions imaginable.
Beyond there, no more fence?
No more fences.
So once you get past there,
you can go straight into
Pakistan if you want?
The problem is, the thing is,
India is trying to stop people
from coming in, infiltrators,
drug dealers, terrorists.
He is working on a
documentary about the
India/Pakistan border.
No one wants to go to Pakistan.
No one wants to?
In their right mind,
to go into Pakistan.
That's a fairly
decisive statement.
So they put up the fence but the
fence is on the Indian side.
Yeah.
It's 115 meters from the border.
So beyond that fence,
still Indian farmland.
Yes.
So people who live over
here can farm over there.
Farm over there.
The Punjab is a fertile region
in an otherwise very dry
country.
This is India's bread basket.
With over a billion people
currently residing in India,
every inch of fertile Punjabi
soil has great value.
These are people who own land
over there, then they put the
fence, suddenly your
life became difficult.
Exactly.
They can only grow some kind of
crops and they can't farm more
than eight hours in a day.
How long does it take
to get back and forth?
The border security force
manage these gates so they have
times when they can
enter and come out.
How much farther can we go
before they start to get
worried?
I think [ Inaudible ].
When India and Pakistan were
separated, the attempt was
to try to draw a line across
religious lines.
Exactly.
Drained by the colossal task
of fighting two world wars, in
1947 Great Britain decided to
end their nearly 200 year rule
over India in an attempt to
prevent an inevitable civil war
between Hindus, Muslims and
Sikhs, the British commissioner
drew up a new border.
He was given two months.
Two months to create a
new country, basically.
People died because
of the displaced men.
Unofficially they say
two million people.
In one of the largest
exchanges of populations in
history, many millions of
people fled their homes.
Almost immediately, religious
violence broke out
on a mass scale.
This is exactly what the
partition had been intended to
avoid.
Do people here still have
families over there?
They do.
When the line was drawn, there
were religious
split into halves.
There are some houses where you
enter from India and
exit from Pakistan.
Really.
Wow.
This part of Punjab and that
part of Punjab were once the
same so the cultures
are very similar.
It's a popular
metaphor for India.
Pakistan is twins
separated at birth.
We were never twins.
It was one country.
You could say dismembered.
If you cut a body in two, they
are not going to become twins.
Right.
It's sad, you know?
You can see them.
They are doing the same
work as you are doing.
They dress the same.
They look the same.
But you can't talk to them.
It is an ongoing struggle, an
enduring cause of paranoia,
visible all across the region.
Two nations with atomic arsenals
who have shown if nothing else,
a terrifying willingness
to use them.
From the horrific 2006 train
bombings to the militant attacks
in Mumbai, the threat of
terrorism along this
border is a daily concern.
♪
Want something good?
Really, really good?
Something local, regional,
iconically wonderful?
You can't say you've had the
whole experience until you've
had a little cocha in your life.
This is the iconic
dish of Punjab.
Yes.
It's a perfect little flavor
bomb of wheat dough pressed
against the side of a very, very
hot Clay oven, slathered with
butter and served with a spicy
chickpea curry on the side.
Did I mention the butter?
How is it?
Delicious.
Everyone seems to be an
expert on the dish, including
this lady.
This is our radish.
Very, very, very good.
Generally speaking, Punjabis are
famous for being
a warrior class.
Taller, bigger.
Yes.
They're big.
Still maybe not fighters
so much but still eaters.
Oh, yeah.
Big-time.
Yes.
The religion doesn't matter.
Food is religion here.
Checking off my list of
things to do in the Punjab, I
got to score some
animal protein.
It's time.
I've been going all Morrisey for
two days now and
frankly, that's enough.
I need chicken.
We are nowhere here.
Where am I?
It's very famous for chicken.
When we are talking must-haves,
tandori chicken is
just that.
I have some lemon in this.
You will enjoy it.
Oh, man, it's delicious.
This type of
establishment, dhaba?
This is the most
successful business here.
Anyone who open a dhaba
tomorrow, it will be like this.
But if you're going to have
chicken it better be good.
Yeah.
Would you like to
have something else?
There's ground mutton?
Mutton ball, dough.
And the special
ingredient, magic hands.
Believe me when I tell
you, this is good.
So good that people snap it up
the second it comes
out of the Tandora.
Hey, that's mine.
Mm.
Is it good?
Sensational.
Wow.
People do love their food.
I love eating.
The movies and television in
this country is fantastic.
I don't even understand
why... what's going on.
Everybody dances and sings.
I don't get it.
♪
Would you like to
have something else?
No, this is good.
Oh, yeah.
Wow.
Mm, that's good.
Thank you.
No, nothing, thank you.
Delicious.
So good.
Leaving the fertile plains
of the Punjab behind, I'm headed
out towards the Himalayas.
In getting there, at least the
way I'm going, hasn't changed
much in the last hundred years.
All aboard.
This is going to be
suboptimal seating.
I don't think this reclines.
Thank god they have relaxed
attitudes towards
prescription drugs.
Before you enter the gateway to
the Himalayas, you
better self-medicate.
Meanwhile, I have been like 24
hours without a bite of food.
I arrive, it's like oh,
there's sneaks on the way.
Great.
Get a bag of peanuts.
Truth be told, I'm an angry
bitter man when I board.
I'm guessing there ain't a P.F.
Chang on the way.
So little.
The universal tourist.
You go on the king Kong ride.
While my stomach growls, I
become the kind of traveler
I warn against, gripy,
self-absorbed, immune to my
surroundings.
But as my brightly colored
little train heads up into the
hills from Kalka station, known
as the gateway to the Himalayas,
my world view starts to improve.
The naturally bright colors of
India start to pleasurably
saturate my brain.
The view of the windows,
ridiculously deep valleys,
hundred-year-old Bridges,
it's, well, breath-taking.
My fellow passengers, too,
are irresistibly chargming.
The school kids cheer in unison
every time we pass through
one of the tunnels.
Hip hip hooray!
I had pretty much forgotten
about my hunger until the
whistle stopped.
Two of these.
This place is named for a
colonel, the British engineer
tasked with building the line.
The station and the adjacent
tunnel bearing his name are
rumored to be haunted.
It's delicious.
Already behind schedule and
plagued by cost overruns,
Barog screwed up.
When he realized the two ends of
this tunnel didn't meet in
the middle, he shot himself.
It's the kind of personal
accountability I would like
to see more of, frankly.
Or is that just me?
All my snarkiness fades as one
can't help but reflect on what
it took to dig, drag, blast and
tunnel one's way up this
route back in the day.
Back in the beginning, making
the trip required a somewhat
uncomfortable three-day trek up
the mountain by foot or horse or
hand-carried pelanguin.
The stats are impressive.
The climb of around 5,000 feet,
over 100 tunnels, more than 800
Bridges, an engineering feat, a
job that when you consider
the time, defies imagining.
In the building of this
railroad, many died.
Many, many died.
When you look at that
painting, when you stand out
front of the garden and look out
at the view, can you
picture the way it was?
I have been to many places
where it reminded me of what
it's like to be when the British
came and settled there.
I have ventured to such places.
Fond memories of British rule,
maybe not what you would
expect to hear.
But Reggie's family
was different.
Indian royalty with
palaces, the 1% of the 1%.
So life for Reggie as a young
boy was relative to the millions
and millions of others
his age, enchanted.
Shimla is from a time before
partition, when nearly the
entire ruling class of British
India would move to hill
stations in the hotter months.
Shimla was once known as the
queen of all hill stations.
Here, the colonials created
England in miniature.
Complete with Tudor
architecture, Rose gardens,
afternoon tea.
My grandfather
entertained hugely.
Garden parties, fancy dress
balls, elephant hunts.
The remnants of British
rule can still be seen.
And felt.
This is particularly
true of one house.
Chapsley.
My family was very fortunate
that they were able to buy this
house, because it
was a famous house.
The house was purchased by
Reggie's grandfather,
the last maharajah.
The Brits really left
beautiful buildings.
From a distance, it looks
much the same as it must have
when the maharajah slept here.
Check out the tub.
Locked in a constant battle
against time and nature, barbed
wire does little to keep
Shimla's ever encroaching
monkey population at bay.
Stripped of their wealth and
their kingdoms, the one-time
royals all across India have had
to either sell their estates or
like Reggie, turn them into
hotels and guest houses
in order to hold on.
Ring a buzzer and a
servant appears.
They bring you hot water bottles
at night, put them
under the covers.
Butlers keep popping
in, build a nice fire.
A great facet of my childhood
was how my grandfather
entertained.
His table came to be known as
perhaps the most famous in
northern India because he
was a conoisseur of food.
Tonight, dinner at Chapslee,
an elaborate Anglo-Indian
menu from Reggie's childhood.
I will put on my apron first.
My fellow guests, two
of Reggie's friends.
A historian on the subject
of Shimla and the barrister.
So much history here.
While I take a dim view of
colonialization, it's very hard
to resist the charms
of a house like this.
That's quite
understandable, actually.
You've got 100 years of very,
very intense history funneled
into a very small place.
This house used to house
the secretary of state.
This is eggs Florentine.
Oh, that's good.
This was a small town.
Small town with a very,
very big government.
It has the distinction of
surprisingly, it was the capital
of Burma during the war days.
You have this tiny little
village up on the hill connected
to the rest of the world by a
narrow mountain path and a rule,
approximately a fifth of the
human race for eight
months every year.
In today's context it would
almost seem bizarre.
Mulligitawny soup.
A classic example of what we
think of as Indian food in
the west but not at all.
This was originally a soup made
by Indian chefs to accommodate
British tastes, is that correct?
It was something what you
would call halfway between a
soup and a broth.
Basically, meat cooked
in its own fat.
It's a misnomer.
This meat is not
actually mutton.
Here, back before the rail
line, it would be
a difficult trip.
Yes.
But once they were up and
running, there were many
servants to look after
your every need.
You had a fireplace, a
hearth in every room.
And people on the regular
payroll whose only job was to
Is this man would go on the
ground and the common
folk would get real.
Normally they would not supposed
to look in the direction.
It was bad manners.
Right.
It wasn't easy for the
people who built it.
It was India that paid the bill
for all this grandeur
for all this show.
They did it at our expense
and with our money.
At the end of the meal,
there's coffee, Brandy and
cigars in the sitting radio.
As one does, or once did.
Did you enjoy your time?
Very much so.
A lot of his are in this house.
And one can be forgiven for
briefly forgetting what it took
to build this lost kingdom.
And how much the world
has changed around it.
The monkey temple is
overrun by its namesakes.
Twisting up further into the
Himalayas, I find myself at a
place known as the
land of the gods.
Nearly every village credited
with having its own deity.
Getting there, you might well
have an opportunity to
meet one of those deities.
As you tear around narrow
guardrail free mountain roads,
overlooking terrifying dropoffs.
I can do heights.
I've done a number of jumping
out of the planes a
number of times.
But looking over precipices
like that one, ew.
If my knees could vomit
with terror, they would be.
They would be vomiting
with terror right now.
They should have little
underwear stops on this road
where you can get a fresh pair.
Every couple of miles it's
like oh, that was scary.
Overloaded buses, water trucks
with brake pads, aggressive
truck drivers come whaling
around the corner at anytime.
And they do.
About every two minutes.
Squeeze your cheeks tight
and close your eyes.
The remote locations of these
isolated mountain villages have
kept old traditions alive.
Villa village fairs serve as an
opportunity for families who
live very far apart to get
together, play game, eat and
participate in religious rites
honoring local deities.
Quite a ride getting here.
Yeah.
How did you enjoy that road?
White knuckles.
Meet Hashim.
He runs motorcycle tours
through these parts.
You're traveling almost 1,000
kilometers on the trip.
So vegetable curry?
Yogurt based curry, quite
typical in these parts.
Vegetables again?
Surprisingly, not a problem.
That's good, huh?
This is one of the few places in
the world I could eat vegetarian
every day and still be happy.
Most of the people in this
community are farmers?
Farmers.
Agricultural?
Yeah.
What are they growing?
A lot of corn, potatoes, peas.
And weed.
People grow marijuana?
Yes, loads.
For export or personal use?
Everything.
A mix of everything.
So you think you want to
go check out the fair?
Yeah, let's take a walk through
town, see what's going
on.
Families come together
and socialize.
People are busy in their farms.
They're not going to walk down
and socialize with people.
But this, you know, because it's
Autumn, everyone is done
with all the agriculture.
Now they're just baring
down for winter.
A lot of romance in the air.
I've been to Mumbai, this is
a part of India that's
different than any other part.
It's fascinating and beautiful.
Oh, yeah.
Sweet.
♪
Whoa, it's moving.
End of the road.