Pity the salary man.
Tokyo's willing cog in an
enormous machine requiring
long hours, low pay, total
dedication.
And sometimes, what's called
koroshi, death by overwork.
Here in a society of tight
spaces, the pressure is on to
keep up appearances, to do
what's expected, to not let the
interior life become exterior.
But at night, things
are different.
♪
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la la
What do you need to
know about Tokyo?
Deep, deep waters.
The first time I came here, it
was like it was a
transformative experience.
It was powerful and
violent experience.
It was as if it was just like
taking acid for the first time.
Meaning what do I do now?
I see the whole world
in a different way.
I often compare the experience,
going to Tokyo the first time,
to what Eric Clapton and Pete
Townsend must have gone through,
the reigning guitar gods of
England, what they must have
gone through the week that
Jimi Hendrix came to town.
You hear about it,
you go see it.
A whole window opens up
into a whole new thing.
And you think what
does this mean?
What do I have left to say?
What do I do now?
Welcome to Tokyo.
You are not invited.
This is the other Tokyo.
12-hour flight and I'm baked.
No sleep.
Might as well... must... go out.
The district near my hotel has
the advantage of being where the
subterranean life, the repressed
Japanese male and some female,
too, comes out to play.
Joining me is Japanese film
producer and production
manager Maso Sokubel.
Always a good sign when
protective chains protect
entertainers from the
soon to be entertained.
Prepare yourself for the
greatest show in the
history of entertainment.
♪
No.
No, it can't be over.
Not yet.
No!
But yet... yet it is.
With a series of chaste high
fives with the
hard-working performers.
Okay, I've got to tell you.
I've seen Jimi Hendrix.
Have you?
I've seen Janis Joplin.
I've seen David
bowie, diamond dogs.
I've seen moon for the
misforgotten, considered one of
the greatest productions ever.
This was the greatest show
I've ever seen in my life.
It had it all!
It was the greatest show in the
history of entertainment.
I don't understand it.
I'm completely confused.
There's like 100 people
working on that show.
Millions of dollars worth
of robots and technology.
How do they make money?
One thing for sure about this
area, part of our business is
unspoken, but governed by the...
The fraternal organization
prominent in the entertainment
and financial services sector,
as they say, who is said
to supervise things here.
Arcades, gambling, adult
entertainment, porn shops and
sex clubs, along with
other ancillary services.
But how much actual boning is
going on in the sex district?
Generally speaking, it's more a
field of dreams than
the actual act of sex.
Hostess caves, where a lonely
overworked salary man can find
the attention of cute seemingly
adoring girls who find their
every uttering fascinating.
So now hostess bar... I just
want somebody to tell
me I'm fantastic.
Oh, you're so interesting.
Your job is interesting.
You are a very sexy man.
I don't care what
your wife says.
I think you're
really interesting?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Penetration, maybe by a q-tip
in the ear, followed by a
personal love spell in this case
to make your tea taste better.
What is this place?
What's happening here?
Are these boys?
Young boys... not for man,
but for middle-aged ladies who
are bored with the
regular housewife.
Wait a minute.
You've got a million guys
wandering around, and they've
got a bunch of bored middle-aged
housewives coming in here.
Spending quite a lot of money.
Why don't they go to the same
club and actually have sex?
People don't like getting
rejected, so they sort of
pay for their pleasure.
And they make you feel welcome.
Maybe you can feel like hmm, I'm
not that bad, after talking
to those girls or boys.
That's the saddest
thing I've ever heard.
Well... that's
heartbreaking, dude.
Is the business dreams?
It is more for the dream of
doing so, which is
never going to happen.
Really?
All of this... it is a very
enticing... I mean,
look at this.
She looks like she
really likes me.
She's got her tongue tucked up
the corner of her mouth.
That's a boy.
Oh.
Whatever.
Golden gong.
My favorite place
to drink in Tokyo.
Hundreds of microsized bars,
each differ from the other
with their own micro crowd.
I love it here.
I've never been here.
Maybe I have.
This place is one of Maso's
favorite, bar albatross.
Strong drinks, the definition
of a hole in the wall.
Now, do people come here right
from work, drink all night
and then go back to work?
[ Speaking Japanese ]
Oh, sorry man.
Would a sorry man
bring his wife here?
So look, in America, the
bartender is like a priest...
So you come and talk to them?
I can tell them all
of my problems.
And I could behave very badly
and he will never talk, ever.
This is the contract.
Absolute confidentiality.
Do I have that kind of
arrangement here now?
[ Speaking Japanese ]
So I have this implied
guarantee of total security.
Yep.
So if I came here with some
dinosaur-riding ho in a
bikini... what?
[ Laughter ]
You don't have to ask.
Oh, man.
This is a great country.
Every chef I know
wants to die here.
Because the food is awesome.
And because we... I think all of
us understand that we don't
understand anything about Japan.
And I totally don't
understand the porn here.
Why is it okay... you can't...
Somebody with a penis but you
can with an octopus tentacle.
In Japan, there's a very old,
very deep, and very rich
tradition of martial arts.
Many styles, many schools.
The Yurakura gym
focuses on boxing.
And this man, Kenji, is a
legend, having trained fighters
using a simple and effective
philosophy that has some real
application to our story.
There it is pasted on the
wall behind the ring.
One, speed.
Two, timing.
Three, distance.
The same idea applies to the
convention-shunning Sushi
techniques of New York City
legend Naomichi Yasuda.
Until recently, the chef partner
of one of the very best, if not
the best Sushi
restaurant in new York.
The Sushi Yasuda.
A short while ago, under very
mysterious and completely
misreported circumstances, he
left the Manhattan restaurant
which still bears his name.
And at age 52 moved to Tokyo
to start all over again.
I was determined to track him
down and see what the
hell he was doing.
These days, this great man is
running a 14-seat
Sushi bar in Tokyo.
His wife Naomi is
his only helper.
Welcome to the place.
Thank you for coming.
Why did you do
such a hard thing?
This city, Tokyo, this is
kind of the maker of the Sushi.
So I just want to be the
Sushi chef in Tokyo.
Yasuda is a friend, and my
master in the sense that he's
taught me pretty much everything
I know about Sushi
over the years.
He's a very, very interesting
and complex man who
constantly surprises.
This is the most
expensive wasabi.
So I wait, wait, wait.
Finally, then I ball this.
It's very French of you.
So many things separate Yasuda
from other Japanese
Sushi masters.
The most noticeable
is his hands.
They're huge.
Look at the knuckles.
Enormous from years of pounding
cement walls during repeated
daily practice in karate.
He first trained and
competed in Tokyo.
When he came to New York,
he continued to practice.
Often in underground,
bare-knuckle matches, you fight
until someone gets
beaten to the ground.
This style Yasuda practiced was
about beating your opponent as
quickly and as
aggressively as possible.
Speed.
Every second is important.
The rice is getting cold, the
seaweed is getting soggy, fish,
less than perfect temperature.
Look at his posture.
A fighter's stance.
Distance, knowing the
perfect spot to be.
Moving in and out as needed.
Never out of position.
Timing.
Reacting to his customer's pace
of eating, their ever-changing
desires, always ready
for the next move.
Most people who don't
understand Sushi will go to a
Sushi bar and say oh, I had
the best Sushi last night.
The fish was so fresh.
It was right out of the ocean.
The freshest fish,
there is no taste.
Just chewing, just hard.
And people think
freshest should be good.
But it wasn't.
Yasuda's menu changes constantly
with what he finds in
the market.
Like thousands of other Sushi
chefs, he heads every day to
Tsukiji, Tokyo's central fish
market, where the world's best
seafood arrives every day.
But unlike most others at his
level who arrive at 4:00 A.M. to
get what they perceive as the
best and freshest,
Yasuda arrives later.
He does not buy the ridiculously
expensive otoro, the fatty belly
meat of the blue fin tuna that
people have been known to pay
hundreds of dollars a pound for.
Instead, he buys tuna from the
heads, using his knife skills to
go for qualities that most
others miss, removing every bit
of sinew from what would
otherwise be a difficult
piece of meat.
In total, it's, well, perfect.
And he cures the results.
Actually cures it.
Breaking down its molecular
structure in a desirable way by
freezing it quickly in a medical
grade blast freezer where it
will stay for a week or longer
in minus 82 degrees Celsius.
He pioneered this technique
years ago in New York, where if
you bothered to ask, he would
have proudly told you that the
absolutely unbelievably sublime
piece of perfect Sushi you
were eating was frozen.
Delicious.
Thank you very much.
Which is more important,
the rice or the fish?
Rice.
More important?
What percentage?
About 90%.
Wow.
Fish is the second ingredient.
The main ingredient is rice.
So my Sushi is rice.
Yasuda, he still trains,
though his fighting days are
over.
He says he was tired
of hurting people.
He brings me to try and show me
how his Sushi technique and
karate are one in the same.
Yuki Kamio, the master.
Nice.
People ask me, what's the
point between the
karate and the Sushi?
But this movement
is so much good
for when I make my Sushi.
Because of the stance.
The stance is more upper.
So this karate
stance is more deep.
So stand in front of the cutting
board, a deep stance
and movement.
Deep stance and body and
watch, through the right.
Move this, move this.
Watch this and watch this.
This is the key.
So this karate is
my Sushi stance.
Now, in an official tournament,
two-minute rounds.
Two-minute round.
And the result you are
looking for is points?
Points, or knockdown.
But two minutes fight.
One minutes fight.
That's most hardest.
It's underground.
You can just work on their legs
for five, seven minutes
to slow them down.
Then you go in.
Yes.
And not compromise.
Just do it.
Whatever happen, no excuse.
See the result good or not.
If it's bad, try again.
Don't give up.
Right.
This is my Sushi.
Perfect.
Those who buy into the
notion of Japanese women as shy,
giggling, subservient victims of
convention would be
confused by Tomika.
People, as everywhere, if you
look deeper, can surprise you.
Her day job is doing this.
And I gather from what she tells
me that she gets plenty of work.
♪
Another complicated layer of
businesses where
representing businesses.
A place where someone can have
many beers and many sakes.
And salty, savory, delicious
snacks that go brilliantly
with alcohol.
Please.
Tomika brings me to one of
them, Daitoro, to meet some
friends.
Kusaia, followed by secures of
beef intestine and chicken.
This place is known for its
motsunabe, intestine
stew with mizo.
This is Naga, invited
along to translate.
Naga also teaches
pole dancing for men.
Then there's this man, one
of the best known and most
respected practitioners, the art
of ropes of beautiful knots, of
for what lack of a better
word, we call bondage.
So how big is the
sadomasochistic community?
How many people are
active participants?
100,000 people.
A lot?
A lot.
This is... translation, to buy.
It makes things more confusing,
for what sure as hell
looks pretty disturbing.
Tomika, who spends most of her
time ripping, burning, and
generally abusing men,
enthusiastically reverses roles
in her longtime relationship.
It looks like a very
delicate procedure.
Does it hurt?
Or does it feel good?
This pain change
to the excesses.
She said when she was tied
up, no need to think.
Just leave it.
She loved it.
Performance art, craft,
fetish, or compulsion.
It's an old and shockingly
omnipresent feature of Japanese
popular fantasy culture.
Magazines, movies,
even comic books.
The intricate restraint of a
willing victim is...
Well, it's there.
Not far from the surface.
What percentage of Japanese men
are interested in either tying
up women or subjugating?
[ Speaking Japanese ]
All of them?
Then the question is how many
Japanese men like to be tied up?
All of them.
So in your experience, all
Japanese men like to tie women
up, but in your experience, all
Japanese men like to be tied up.
Who's more... sexually,
Americans or Japanese?
[ Speaking Japanese ]
She says you need to be tied up.
A little late for me.
In America, where I come
from, we are told at a certain
age to put aside
childish things.
The action figures, dolls,
features of our imaginations, to
arm ourselves with brutal
realities of the real world,
real combat, real sex.
In Japan, increasing
numbers of people don't.
They continue to live a life
inside four walls, inside their
mind, the life we call the
computer geek, the nerd, as
avatars.
There's a name for it, a whole
subculture of what's
called otaku.
Once a derisive term, now a
proud identifier of the geek,
one who has turned his back on
the real world and finds
satisfaction elsewhere.
Manga, or comic books, hold a
different place in the cultural
landscape here and
address different needs.
There's yowi, otherwise known as
boys love manga, extremely
popular with teenage girls.
Stories change, but the core
themes are sexually ambiguous
boys getting very
friendly with each other.
What legions of young girls and
soccer moms find compelling in
the thousands of these titles,
something of a mystery to
outsiders looking in,
but there they are.
Whole sections of manga book
shops dedicated to basically one
direction type boy band figures
having sex with each other.
Yaui isn't generally
explicit, though it can be.
Some of the most popular
manga are, however, lurid,
over-the-top illustrated stories
of incredible violence, rape,
murder, and sexual fetishes.
Toshiyo is a manga creator like
few others, the father of what
could only be described
as tentacle porn.
His 1986 manga was about
half-human, half-bestial space
invaders in search of
an evil supreme being.
It contained unbelievably
graphic, lurid, violent, and one
would argue offensive images of
sex acts involving not
sexual organs, but other
protruberances.
It became a huge hit and has
been imitated wildly both in
other manga and other
live action films.
A whole genre of lurid, but
extraordinarily well-drawn
madness.
Toshiyo tries to explain.
This girl seems like
a high school girl.
Basically, it's forbidden.
Notice, by the way, the
distinguished owner and her
complete lack of shock or
offense at the graphic, frankly
horrifying images of rape,
violation, and murder spread
casually across the
table for all to see.
Japanese manga, ones that
everyone reads on the subway
home even, well,
they're different.
The big breakthrough was you
couldn't draw penises, you
couldn't draw specifically
orifices.
You couldn't actually show
humans penetrating each other.
In Japan.
Right.
It was a big no-no at that time.
So I invented tentacles to
be evasive about the law.
Also demons.
Demons.
That's fantastic.
Whether you meant to at the
time, you absolutely changed
the world of manga.
You created an entire spectrum
of pornography that
didn't exist before.
If you go to YouTube now,
there's tentacle manga.
Tentacle and demon manga.
There is tentacle
and demon anime.
A lot.
That looks good.
For dinner, there's fresh bonito
seared quickly over flame,
arranged in bite-sized pieces,
garnished with fresh greens,
sprouts and ponzu.
He comes here commonly for the
favorite of sumo wrestlers as
part of a weight gain diet.
Basically it's a hot pod
of meat and vegetables.
Chicken, pork, beef, fish bowls
keep getting fed into the pot.
Usually alongside
much beer and rice.
So, appealing to the human
desires of a manga-buying
audience, men want filthier,
dirtier, more violent?
In Japan, you can't
be rude in public.
But you need to just, you know,
I can say that
letting off steam.
So for me, the manga
is one way to do that.
What do women want?
Generally speaking, what
do women want in manga?
Yaui.
Boys.
Because they don't have enough
experience to do
that with real men.
But nobody's going to the
fish market and asking
for live octopus.
Probably not.
The pop music scene in Tokyo
is not that different than ours.
With an accent, though, on
pretty boy bands, pop
idols, tween stars.
Generic, industry-created
crap, for the most part.
Like I said, not so
different than us.
Picture an army
of Miley Cyruses.
Going against the grain
are a few lone heroes.
Two self-released albums and
no hint of a record deal.
Damn suits.
What do they know?
Lead singer Yu.
Sweet, shy, lyi Lilith fair?
No.
♪
So how big an audience in Japan
for thrash metal, death
metal, hardcore?
We had Ozzy Osbourne this
year for the first time in
Japan.
I feel like people are seeing
the heavy metal scene
as a new movement.
And the audiences?
Good audiences here?
They are kind of polite.
Really?
Yeah.
Very quiet.
Just watching us.
And when we finish playing,
they suddenly clap.
Really?
When I look at popular music,
the stuff that's selling
millions of records in America,
it makes me angry, actually.
Sometimes we are angry.
If I see nickel back, I
want to kill myself.
I want to kill them, and
then I want to kill myself.
And then I want to kill
everybody who listens to them.
Okay?
What's so funny?
It's true.
I mean, what band do you hate?
A band that I would know.
Who's the worst
band in the world?
The worst popular
Who?
Oh, my chemical romance.
Yes.
Hate them.
That's a good one.
♪
Can you make a living?
No.
Not at all.
Not at all?
We all have part-time jobs.
You all have jobs.
What do we are 22
to 25 years old.
It's the hunting job season.
So there's pressure on you.
Yeah.
We all went to university.
The expectation, the pressure
is okay get a real job.
Yeah.
Put aside this record
dream and get a real job.
In a perfect world would you
like to play metal every night?
Yeah.
If I could keep doing this.
Can you?
These guys look like lifers.
♪
Tokyo may well be the most
amazing food city in the world.
With a nearly unimaginable
variety of places stacked one on
top of the other, tucked away on
every level of densely
packed city streets.
At Lawsons, you can dig into
their unnaturally fluffy,
insanely delicious addictive
egg salad sandwiches.
I love them.
Layer after layer after
layer of awesome.
Proud eateries serving
who knows what.
But it all smells delicious
and looks enticing.
In the tiny almost
micro-neighborhood of
Nakamaguro, Tokyo, all is quiet.
Right here in the middle of this
pinball machine
of a city, green.
He loves this place.
A low key joint to enjoy family
meals and meet friends.
I so much appreciate I see
you and all of the
people from the U.S.
Well, we miss you.
I miss New York City.
I'll tell you something
really terrible.
Every relationship I've ever had
with a woman, at some point very
early on I bring them
to yasura in New York.
I would watch how they eat.
If they talk too much, if they
didn't understand how to eat
Sushi, if they did not eat the
huni, we will never
have a relationship.
That's it.
That's the end.
They don't serve
high end Sushi here.
It's almost like
hipster tempura.
This is known as kushiagei.
Things dipped in
batter and fried.
Orders up shrimp and basil,
octopus, and quail eggs.
And an egg batter pancake
filled with many things.
For us it's squid brushed
with Worcestershire sauce.
That's awesome.
I've been coming here many
times, but this is the
first time to eat this.
Love this dish.
You lived in New York, what?
14 years?
18 years?
27 years.
27 years in New York.
That changes a person.
Very much.
You're a new yorker now.
Yes.
What was the hardest thing to
get used to when you
first came here?
Culture.
The culture.
The culture is so much different
in the U.S. and here.
And so interesting always.
I never, ever get bored.
I never get bored and I
always learn new things in
Manhattan.
But there's 15, 20 different
Manhattans in Tokyo to me.
From my perspective these are
completely different cities.
Even building to building.
Nightclub for men, nightclub for
girls, nightclub for rock
and rollers, hair salon.
All up.
15 different businesses
in one building.
One building.
I could spend the next five
years just doing shows
on this one building.
What is weird?
What is strange?
What do those things
even mean, anyway?
Sure a lot of what you've seen
looks different from
maybe the mainstream.
It's certainly different from
the way we like to portray
ourselves, see ourselves, at
least our daytime selves.
But roughly 50% of all movies
rented in American hotel
rooms are adult films.
The American important industry
catering to exactly the kind of
dark urges we've been talking
about but even nastier is a $12
billion a year industry that
dwarves the Hollywood product.
Our own obsessions arguably are
at least as crazy, violent,
and lurid as Japan's.
And we tend to actually carry
out our violent fantasies
more frequently.
Maybe with that fetishism, that
attention to detail comes some
kind of excellence
in other fields.
Maybe there's a line
from there to here.
So who's crazy now?
♪