So we begin at the end.
After a wild week in Seoul,
there was, I believe,
something called... involved.
There were many strange and
delightful things to eat.
Things might have spun
slightly out of control.
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha la la la sha la la la sha
♪ la la la la sha la la la la
♪ la ♪
the biggest difference between
Korean fried chicken and
American fried chicken... I
feel like chicken tonight.
Next, we'll be performing a
medially from flavor town.
Who is everybody here?
Come to me, come to me.
Powerful in a small girly way.
Whoops.
Oh, yeah.
You shouldn't be surprised I'm
in a happy place right now.
Maybe the best way to tell
this story is to
start at the end.
Like a dog returning to its own
vomit, I keep flashing
back to was it last night.
The night before, I smell fried
chicken on my clothes
so perhaps... hello.
We meet again.
Am I glowing with health and
pink, freshly scrubbed?
You look like a better
version of yourself.
Why is that?
Because I've lost about
eight pounds of dead skin.
Koreans like the idea
of optimal cleanness.
We like to be the
most clean possible.
I'm okay frankly
with soap and water.
I like beer.
Let me see if I can pour
this properly for you.
There you go.
Do you know about this?
No.
The Koreans have many
eating traditions.
If you have a very big
production or big event, you
celebrate that in a proper way.
What are we celebrating?
We're celebrating the
end of this Korea show.
This is important.
This is the most important
thing you've ever done.
There's nothing
involved with salt.
I don't have to rub that
into my raw, thick skin.
I'm a broken man.
I seem beneath the shame and
a headache to be missing a few
layers of skin, as if I've
been rubbed somehow raw.
I believe in clean, really,
but this is beyond clean.
This is sanded,
stripped, filleted.
The beer is not helping.
Well, maybe it is.
I think I've had enough.
The gleeful embrace of mixing
whiskey, rice wine,
beer, and oys
oysters, it seems
to tempt the fates.
Ooh.
Yes.
Let me ask you one
more question.
Uh-huh.
What do you think about
Han now after your trip?
I'm brimming with Han.
I mean I could never actually
have a Han because
I'm not that Korean.
This is a genetic
over cellular thing.
I understand.
But it's something I feel
I can really relate to.
I'm definitely a revenge is a
dish best served
cold kind of guy.
You eat a lot of chicken.
You didn't eat all day, did you?
No, I did not love
myself this morning.
But you felt better
after your scrub down?
It was like punish the evil.
♪
This social contract, the
confusion hierarchy of age
before everything, fades away.
We are no longer Mr. Ha, Mr.
Park, Mr. No, and Mr. Tony.
We move as one, a band of bros
through the night, the
world our oyster.
♪
I feel like a boy band.
Johnny cash.
Johnny cash?
Yeah.
Thank god there was no karaoke.
All roads lead to here.
No escape, just embrace.
I'm acutely aware of my role as
big brother, my new friends
looking at me to set an example.
All right, guys.
Let's party.
Nice to meet you.
So correct me if I'm wrong here.
It is dried squid, m&ms,
and mixing your alcohols?
Yeah.
It seemed like a good
idea back at the office.
Next we'll be performing a
medley from "mama Mia."
We got a low score.
We only got 44.
Mouse?
Mouse fish.
Tony?
You got to go somewhere else.
Squid treats and m&ms?
Sure.
Makes perfect sense.
In fact, there were oysters
somewhere along the route.
A tale that becomes increasingly
worrying with our
alcohol intake.
Oysters, awesome.
Nice.
Competitive drinking
and shellfish.
Have you ever played in
Korean drinking games?
No.
Well, they have a lot of them.
It keeps the energy up and keeps
everyone kind of drinking.
Stop two.
All right.
We're going to play a
little game first.
Tony, we're going to let
you start the festivities.
You have to use a chop stick,
hit everything forward,
it's going to splash up.
What?
A strike or a push?
A push.
There's a lot of games.
We're not going to go through
them all because it would take
forever and we'd be
really, really drunk.
But this game is called
the bottle cap game.
We're going to pass this around
in a circle and you're going to
flick it as hard as you can.
No one wins or loses.
We all get drunk.
Very good.
That is brotastic.
Okay, this is chop sticking.
Don't play this game
with engineers.
Oh, don't hurt the man.
He's been hitting
those oysters hard.
See you in flavor town.
One, two, and three.
It's pretty good.
That's good.
We got to go somewhere else.
Yeah, we're going.
Let's hit the street, guys.
The idea that only an hour
earlier we sat like
gentlemen and had barbecue.
A rapidly fading memory.
Tony, how many bottles
can you drink?
We'll see.
Yes, I remember now.
Somewhere near the start of the
evening, the moment little
brother grabbed the reins of our
soon to be careening chariot
unfettered by good sense and the
reality of work tomorrow.
Eat the egg, eat the egg
before it gets cooked too much.
That's good.
It's good.
You like the marinated
one, right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
This is being Korea, beer is
a must as is apparently soju.
What seems to define Korea as I
know it is it anticipates
the future very, very well.
This is a country that's famous
for looking forward,
looking into the future.
Where does one go to see Korea's
past, and are these guys
sentimental about it at all?
Younger brother?
All right, younger brother.
My mission for purposes of
television is to ingraciousuate
myself with a total group of
strangers, insinuate myself into
their lives and insert myself
into an expression combining the
concepts of company and meal.
In Korean culture, this
would be a regular thing.
A one night corporate
retreat, if you will.
Which is how I ended up at my
appointment with the fates, a
barbecue joint popular
with the salary man.
How did I end up here?
Mr. Noh.
Tony.
I think they like me.
Do you drink soju?
I do.
This is Anthony Bourdain, CNN.
Good night.
Notice the totally blissed
out happy look an my face.
Observe the bowl with nothing
left but fiery remnants.
Behold the magnificence
that is this dish.
Enough, enough.
That's good.
Geez.
Oh, man.
That's going to go
straight to my hips.
Yes.
Okay, okay.
Thank you.
This is a magical dish.
So most people are not
sentimental about their time in
the military.
Why do this?
Everybody serves in
the military, right?
It's mandatory in Korea.
Very happy.
You want the recipe about this?
I got the recipe now.
It's everything mama warned
you about, and it's got it all,
baby, and when the music is
over, your life will have
changed forever.
One, two, three.
Okay.
Yes.
Yeah.
Dating back to famine years of
the Korean war, scrounging from
American military bases, it is a
classic example of necessity
feeding the mother of
deliciousness.
Hot dogs, baked beans, spam, and
noodles put together
with kimchee.
It became an enduring and
deeply loved classic.
Like I used to say to my first
girlfriend, how could something
so wrong be so right.
You got that right.
No, no, no.
Wow!
No.
I tell you.
I'm sorry about that.
Sorry, man.
Regrettable incident.
Looks healthy.
Look at this thing.
Look at the color alone.
In go the noodles.
Wow.
Yeah, baby.
Come to me, come to me, my love.
Yes.
Little spam in there.
Good job, chef.
Good chefs.
Yes, yes, yes.
Thank you.
My pleasure.
Any time.
In a society reeling from
conflict and deprivation,
largely without meat and fresh
ingredients, this was
the gift of the G.I.
The Korean war lasted from 1950
to 1953, but in many
ways it never ended.
The country is split in half and
in a constant state of alert.
120 miles to the north, a crazy
dictator with an army, a bad
haircut, and a nuclear arsenal.
This we know.
But the war divided a country
and divided families.
Altered forever the
Korean character.
The chef's early experience
working the mess hall during his
mandatory military service led
directly to super stardom.
He beams his cooking show live
in more than 50,000 homes today
via something called
the Internet.
And he's not the only one.
There's competition.
Lots of it.
Broadcast eating, it's kind of a
phenomena in Korea, which is how
I wound up in a tent on
the outskirts of Seoul.
Right here?
All right.
Classic indigenous ingredients.
No spam.
Excellent.
Yes.
All right.
It's a slaughterfest.
I've gotten killed like 12
times already today, so I think
I'm going to hang it up.
All right, I'm ready
for some food.
In Korea, the food delivery
system is really good.
Really good.
A whole bunch of food
you can just order.
Order food while you're playing?
Yeah.
PC bomb sounds like a male
porn store, but this
one has a lounge.
Here in Seoul, given that
there's an entire strata of
professional gamers, more
sustainable food is, from
time to time, required.
No problem.
Anything you want right
to your console.
Real-life, does it
have any attraction?
Real life?
You know nongaming world.
People love it.
Professional gamers, people love
the professional gamers.
They get a lot of fame for that.
Right.
Oh, man.
This is too much.
You got to get the
sauce with the noodle.
Yep.
It's a black noodle.
It should be all black.
Tasty.
Good?
That'll work.
Some of the games you can
play while still eating.
One handed?
Basically, you eat a little
bit and then play the game, eat
a little bit, then
play the game.
The only game I've ever really
gotten serious about and
lived with a year... I spent a
lot of time and it
was GTA vice city.
In my opinion, it is a
little bit violent for me.
That's my personal opinion.
Look, there was a lot of
bleeding out in this game.
That's true.
Over the mountain and through
the woods to grandmother's house
we go, blowing some shit up on
the way and was it right
click, left click?
Okay.
I'm looking for the little
guys with the red over them.
Yeah.
That doesn't look good.
Oh, geez.
I'm respawning.
Yeah, respawning.
You could target.
You can pull long distance or
short distance depending
on where your target is.
I'm just learning
how to move here.
Oh, poor little red riding hood.
She's not good.
If I'm shooting
something, it's me.
Oh, no.
Little red riding hood,
you're bleeding out again.
Oops.
Didn't make it.
I don't see any bad guys.
Are these friends?
Oops.
Back in the old days before
time itself, spending 17 hours a
day at places like this was
frowned upon by family.
Now gaming has become a
respected and often lucrative
profession in Korea.
Simon has pretty much retired
from gaming, per Se.
Instead he makes a living
advising rising stars in the
industry.
You do this for a living?
Yeah.
How many hours a day?
The professional gamers, they
spend all day playing this game.
They wake up, play
a game, practice.
Have lunch, practice again, have
dinner, and go to sleep.
Today the game is one of
those multiplayer kill fests
where mighty avatar post
a range of abilities.
There we go.
This is all about love.
Really cute.
Little girl.
That's me?
Oh, geez.
Can we choose another
avatar maybe?
Something more killy?
I don't know if I'm going to
strike fear into my enemies.
Little girl comes around the
corner having a big
fireball on your head.
I'll try to keep up with
you for a few minutes.
Press W to go forward and
press right and left clicked
together.
Right key on the mouse.
Forward is W.
Yeah.
E shift and left together.
Shift and then...
Left together, yeah.
Then space, right click, left
shift with left click together.
Brutal.
How long did it take you to
figure out how to move
around in this world?
About ten minutes.
Ten minutes, yeah.
Okay, me and Simon are going
up against these kids and I'm
expecting to pistol whip some
bitches unless time has
once again passed me by.
The life of a professional video
gamer is a concept that's
not easy for me to grasp.
These young nerd
lingers are famous.
They have TV shows where they
compete and are making
actual cash money.
They have sponsors
and super fans.
They probably even get
laid off this shit?
And that explains how little red
riding hood ended up bleeding
out on the cold,
hard, virtual floor.
Should we start the game?
Sure.
Okay, where's our opponents?
I'm going to fire your ass.
Don't say anything
about Wayne Newton.
He's the man.
He's early 90s west coast.
I'm a west coast guy.
I'm not entirely convinced
that Korean food is healthy.
Have you always been a food guy?
I'm very happy here.
Last one?
Yeah.
Is this drinks that goes with
food or is this food
that goes with drinks?
The culture is you have to
have something that goes
well with that drink.
We should probably be
drinking that, right?
Yes.
Have you had soju before?
How often can you come to
a place like this a week?
Would you come every day?
Sure.
I like to recommend
the soup of death.
It's a soup, but the main
ingredient in that is silk
worms.
That okay?
Yeah, sure.
Oh.
Nice?
Oh, yeah.
Eating bugs, that
is so last network.
How do you like the soup?
The soup is awesome.
I'm going to go home and
have Benisans tonight.
Get the [ Muted ] out of my
soup and make me a sweater.
Even Koreans don't eat this
all the time, but I guess this
country makes you feel like if
you can't eat this,
then you're not Korean.
What were you born?
In New York.
Yes.
And were there until
until roughly 21.
I grew up on the streets
and new York city.
It was automatically
you're a chink.
I'm Korean and I'm
proud to be Korean.
Mark is what's called a
Korean who has lived abroad.
More and more people are, like
Mark, moving back home for
the ever more numerous
opportunities.
When I came here, it
just felt right for me.
I'm here.
These are my peoples.
This has what I've been missing.
I was considered an
outsider in my own country.
I had like this thing going on
because I was like am I not
Korean enough if I don't do
this, if I don't drink this, if
I don't eat this, but there was
a sense of I want to learn this
if that makes me
feel more Korean.
Nice.
Is this so hard to walk in and
eat delicious food and get
hammered in the street?
Being Korean is pretty awesome.
Last one.
Yeah.
Nighttime in Seoul and
everywhere you go it seems, food
and drink.
This is what they call kind of
like a pub, if pubs could
operate in the street.
You can have drinks, and well, I
guess you could
call it, pub food.
We're about to go eat
some really, really good.
Welcome to Seoul.
Let's do this.
My new friend Mark helped
popularize western style
hip hop in Korea.
An event that led me to
eating silk worms in a tent.
So where are we?
Do I have the position correct?
Are you complaining
about your hours?
Number one selling liquor
in the whole world.
Prostitutes so many times.
Get many my mouth
and stay there.
She's already dead.
Come on.
I'm getting this weird
sense of deja vu.
Haven't we been in a fish market
in Seoul at some point?
Maybe a slight... what should
we toast to this time?
To a triumphant return to Korea?
There's something I've been
craving since I got off the
plane.
The snacks that accompany
your meal in Korea.
This is one of the most
exciting things about Korean
food.
Doesn't that make you
want to drink more soju?
Is that a hint or something?
I know the formality of it all.
The appetizers, yes, I
remember these guys.
Bringing back memories.
Here we go.
So this is spicy stew.
I need it to burn.
It has everything under
the sun seafood wise.
You can find crab,
all kinds of fish.
Fishermen stews all
over the world.
Exactly.
This bowl for me, that's the
perfect example of
Koreans in general.
We love being together in a
space, huddled around a
bubbling pot of something.
This is good.
You are failing your duties
as a young assistant.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
We don't have to drink
it immediately, do we?
Face planting.
Koreans, they just want each
other to drink as
much as possible.
Peer pressure drinking
is kind of a big deal.
May I have another glass please?
Korean drinking etiquette 101.
You never pour your own drink.
Younger pours for the older
and you never drink alone.
How come all the Korean
guys are so tormented?
They're carrying around
an unseen weight.
Every single Korean person is
born with this thing called Han,
which is a deep
sorrow and anger.
It has nothing to do with your
upbringing.
Han, my favorite Korean word.
Generally speaking, it is a
mixture of endurance, yearning,
sorrow, regret, bitterness,
spite, hatred, and to bide your
time until revenge can
at last be exacted.
Revenge is a very, very sweet
tasting thing for Koreans
because there's been so much
wrong that's happened to us.
What about little Timmy
master who is made fun
of you in second grade?
Is there vengeance
coming their way?
I want them to actually
love Korean food now.
Doesn't sound anywhere close
to personal suffering.
Well, that's my personal story.
I would think electric
nipple clamps.
They slowly bled the
reason that Koreans are
able to just not wallow in that
is because of this other
emotion called Chung.
It is a deep fondness that you
have for your other Koreans, and
people all focus on Haun and I
know, like, Haun, yes,
yes, yes, it exists.
No one is denying that.
We all have it.
But Chung, no one talks about
that and it's equally strong.
Okay.
I believe you.
I don't think you believe
me about this Chung thing.
No, I believe you.
Like I like the
whole idea of Han.
I totally get that as an engine.
I like that.
I like that dark side.
The fact that this word exists
is sort of awesome because a
negative emotion has been
converted into a number of
very, very, very positive
developments.
Absolutely.
Koreans are, you know, this
amazing group of people that
don't curse and eat amazing
food, and we like to
drink and have fun.
Oh, stop sucking up.
So, to the Han.
We need to make a serious toast.
We're you a nuclear and amazing.
That describes me.
I'm not drinking this.
No, you don't have to drink it.
My relentlessly cheerful
friend and colleague Nari.
She loves Korea and all things
Korea and wants nothing more
than to make everybody love
it as much as she does.
That's why she brought me here
to the Garak fish market where
you find the kinds of
casual joints that I love.
I will have, let me
see, perhaps the fish.
I want some enchana and spicy
stuff and we'll start
off by drinking.
Yes.
I'm getting a weird
sense of deja vu.
Like haven't we been at
a fish market in Seoul.
Walk down memory Lane.
At some previous life.
The past, the
present, the future.
In Korea they all
bleed together.
If you're there for the whole
ride, one explains the other.
Drop in in the middle, and
it makes no sense at all.
Korean culture, as far as I can
tell, is defined by the drive to
succeed, a churning engine
fueled by decades of Han, a
remarkable ability and
remarkable willingness to
anticipate the future.
It reaches back across time
and binding millennials and
generations long since passed.
Last time I was here I was
working for another channel, the
bacon channel, the competitive
eating channel, what was
that old show called?
It was so long ago.
Back then I was dragged around
in Nari's powerful
wake, as I recall.
That was nearly a decade ago.
Things have changed since then.
I've changed and I'm guessing
Nari's changed, and Korea,
Korea has certainly changed.
The Korean war ended more than
half a century ago, but in
some ways it's still going.
The north and south have been on
perpetual war
footing ever since.
It's a psychological
and physical scar.
Korea is literally split in
half, but that's not
what this show is about.
There aren't many comparisons to
South Korea's stratospheric
rise over the last decade.
One of the poorest countries as
recently as '60s, today it
claims one of the world's
fastest growing economies.
The government has been
extremely shrewd and forward
thinking about selling the world
all things Korean, underwriting,
encouraging, financing and
supporting the export of
intangibles, things like music,
movies, TV show, food, the whole
Korean sensibility, and the
world is responding, learning to
love what Koreans
have always loved.
The heart of Korea is Seoul,
capital city, a bustling
Metropolis.
Futuristic in look
and character.
Population 25 million.
Look at that.
They have a selfie stick.
Everybody is taking
pictures of their food.
They feel right at home.
In October 2014 I
went back to Korea.
This is what I saw.
This makes me so happy.
The kimchi, make room
for the noodles.
Oh, that's good.
Should be no surprise that
I'm in a happy place now.
Oh, yeah.
First night back.
Back to the market.
Unrecognizable and
invariably and inevitably
delicious food.
Good to be back, man,
good to be back.
♪