For a long time,
we were forgotten about.
We were the joke
of the country, you know?
And now I think we're the ones
kind of having the last laugh.
It's a magical, beautiful
place to live,
and we're surrounded
by amazing things.
♪
To be able to go outside
and, you know,
go out and jig a fish
or shoot a moose
or, you know, go out
and pick some berries
and to be able to bring that
to the table
and create a sense of place
for people...
When they look out the window,
they know
they're in Newfoundland.
♪
And it's just about, again,
celebrating
all the wonderful things
that we have.
And I think we're... we got
a lot to celebrate, you know?
♪ I took a walk
through this beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good
in this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪
♪ Sha la la la la
♪ Sha la la la la la
♪ Sha la la la la la la
This is the shed.
This is what every
Newfoundlander...
You know, this is
their hangout spot, is the shed,
oddly enough.
It's like an escape.
It's like a doghouse.
How do I say "Newfoundland"?
I got to get this right.
Understand, Newfoundland.
Everyone says that,
but that's not helping me.
I'm gonna get my balls busted
so bad.
Think of it like "New Fun Land."
New Fun Land.
- Newfoundland.
- Yeah.
- There you go.
Not "New Found Land."
- Newfoundland.
- Yeah.
Newfoundland,
a rocky island
off the east coast of Canada
extending into
the North Atlantic.
They might not be from here,
but chefs, restaurateurs,
noted raconteurs
Fred Morin and Dave McMillan
were excited to explore
this wild and beautiful rock
with me.
♪
It's a part of Canada
all its own,
with its own distinctive
history and culture.
So as entertaining as my
Quebecoise friends might be,
I thought it wise to recruit
some natives:
chef Jeremy Charles
and his partner, Jeremy Bonia.
It's an all-dude affair.
♪
What's on the menu today?
- Codfish.
Yeah.
Or rather just fish.
- Just fish.
- They're both fish.
We say, you know, fish is cod
in Newfoundland, you know?
When you talk about fish,
people just assume it's codfish.
♪
Living off the ocean is insane.
It's unbelievable
when you get out here
and see
and you're in the elements.
It makes you really respect
people who work on the water.
You know what I mean?
Like, guys used to row out here.
- Yeah.
- And, like, you know,
you just realize what it takes
to get it to the restaurant.
It's not easy, right?
Respect the fish and chips
a little bit more, right?
Respect the fish and chips, man.
For over 500 years,
the icy waters
off Newfoundland's coast
overflowed with a seemingly
endless bounty of cod.
Fishermen from all over...
As far away as England,
Portugal, and Spain...
Came here
to pull them from the sea.
They built entire food cultures
around the delicate,
white-fleshed fish.
And for most of its history,
cod defined the culture here.
Cod was king.
Ottawa is about to announce
a moratorium on northern cod.
Small independents,
big company trawlers,
all will have to pull their nets
and dock their boats.
But in 1992,
after years of overfishing,
the Canadian government
shut the industry down.
Six generations down the line,
passed down,
and he's done nothing but...
The moratorium wiped out
the main source of income
for the province
and ended a way of life.
And though
it's been loosened some,
the moratorium
is still in effect today.
What was the spirit
of the people in '92?
Think about it; think about
your number one industry.
No one could fish.
- Culture...
- Nothing, zero.
It went from going out
to jig a fish with your family
or whenever you wanted
to absolutely nothing.
So it just, like, tore the heart
and soul out of people.
What did people change cod for?
Tilapia?
Can I ask this, though?
Was it warranted,
the closing down of the fishery?
- Yeah.
- It was.
Thing was, I mean, a lot of
the in-shore small guys
were talking about it for years,
talking about,
"We can't keep this up."
Like, the factory trawlers
and the fisheries
were just getting bigger
and bigger,
and it's like, how do you put
a factory trawler
that's just dragging the seas...
Everything in the ocean.
From multiple countries,
including our own,
for years and years
and not have an effect?
It was very dark times.
- But better now.
- Yes.
- Getting better.
- Yeah.
From what we've seen...
And I've talked to fishermen
in the bays and stuff...
Cod's coming back.
- Cod is king still.
- Cod is still king.
What's your water dam?
140.
Okay, that's perfect.
Let's give her a shot.
Let's start with two lines
and then see how much of
a mess we've got with tide.
- I got a nibble.
- There you go.
Lift that.
Lift that rod.
Oh, there you go, Fred.
Nice one.
Wow.
Next one is a moose.
- No.
- Okay, it's on.
- No, you got a big fish.
- Go, go, go.
There you go.
Oh, it's a nice-sized one.
1 down, 14 to go, was it?
Yeah, go ahead. You guys
are drifting more east.
Oh, yeah, fish on.
There we go.
I can see him there now.
♪
- All right.
- Just keep him in the water.
All right.
Perfect.
Well done yourself.
- Thank you, sir.
- There you go.
- Oh, that's a nice size.
- Yeah, that's... there you go.
Wow.
That's why
these things went extinct;
they bite like crazy.
Here you go.
Well, I think that's
the most successful
fishing scene I've had
in many, many years.
All right.
♪
We're surrounded by water,
and we're not really
a seafood-eating place.
♪
We live in this fish culture.
It's been fishing here
for hundreds of years.
And the fish was always
not accessible to people here.
It was something
that was always for export.
Right.
And so the fishery
is changing a little bit.
I think as well, it was always
just a single-species fishery,
and now that's diversifying.
- By necessity.
- Yeah, absolutely.
And that's really important,
'cause we live on this island
where food security is an issue.
Dale Jarvis works for
the Intangible Cultural
Heritage development office
for the province
of Newfoundland and Labrador,
helping communities safeguard
what they can
of traditional culture.
What's changed as far as...
the way that... I'm going to try
to pronounce it correctly...
Newfendlers...
Newfoundlanders.
Newfoundlanders see themselves?
I mean, something seems
to be happening here
as far as people here beginning
to value their own products,
their own traditional food ways.
Yeah.
That's a big change,
and it's something that
Jeremy Charles, for instance,
has been doing
very, very, very successfully.
How important is that?
I think the one thing
that has kept people here
in the wake
of the fisheries collapse...
Like the fish moratorium
in 1992,
so many people left.
And what really
has kept people here
is that sense of tradition.
I think sometimes
there's this idea
that tradition is static,
and that isn't necessarily true.
Tradition is always
kind of changing
in response to the environment.
And people choose the things
that they're passionate about,
and they find a way
to make that work.
And I think Newfoundlanders
have always had that tradition
of making do
and making things work
in the situation where they are.
Here at
the family-owned-and-operated
Charles Landing,
the specialty is fish and chips.
♪
How's everything taste today?
Really good, thank you.
- Thank you very much.
- Glad to hear.
Homemade fries,
always a good thing.
How Canadian is Newfoundland?
You know, we have this
kind of complex relationship
here in Newfoundland
with the rest of Canada.
You know, we're a very old
British colony here,
but we've only really been
part of Canada since 1949.
And I think for a long time,
on the mainland of Canada,
there was kind of this
stereotype of Newfoundlanders
as being, you know,
poor and uneducated,
kind of that goofy Newfy
stereotype kind of stuff
that happened.
And over the past 10, 20 years,
there's been a real shift
in how the rest of Canada
perceives Newfoundland
but I think also
as how Newfoundlanders
perceive themselves.
And people, I think,
are starting to say,
"Hey, we don't have
to just import food
from, you know,
the United States or Canada."
You know, the stuff
that we have here,
the ingredients
that we have here
are actually pretty special.
You could actually shoot a bird
and serve it in a restaurant.
If you do that in Montreal,
you get arrested.
You can shoot rabbits
and serve them in restaurants.
Yeah, we have the benefit
of that here, yeah.
This is an enormous
and unique advantage.
♪
Back at the shed,
a classic fish and brewis.
A hearty sailor's stew
of cod and hardtack.
- Sweet.
- Look at that.
- Whoa.
- What's this?
- Scrunchions.
Scrunchions?
Salted pork fat.
They're crisp.
- Oh, God.
- Isn't that ridiculous?
Oh, I need to sit around
in, like,
some shit-stained underwear.
Sit there in front
of a television
and eat those all day long.
Ahhhhh!
You'll have to change,
then, before jujitsu,
those same underwear.
- As one must.
- Yes.
Well, look at that.
It's beautiful.
Are you searching for the parts?
Yeah, just kind of get
a bit of everything.
Garnished with scrunchions?
- Soigné.
- Yeah.
It's pretty much the dish,
you know?
- Thank you.
- Damn, this is delicious.
Oh, good?
You like it?
- Yeah.
- Excellent.
Oh, so good.
My grandmother would be
happy it's good.
♪
Hunting is very much
part of the culture here.
Traditionally, you hunted
to eat, to stay warm,
to survive.
And there is no game more prized
than the moose.
Just over 300 miles from
the capital of St. John's,
about a seven-hour drive
through some beautiful,
if rugged and wild, country,
is Buchans.
From what we are told,
it's prime moose hunting.
♪
A beautiful lake,
rustic cabins
where a few friends
can hunt and forage
and perhaps, in between
combing the wilds
in search of the elusive moose,
throw together
a simple wilderness meal
around the campfire.
♪
Nothing fancy.
Just the bare essentials.
We're drinking Sacrament from
Prince Edward County, Ontario.
Hinterland winery.
And we're also drinking
a wine from here,
the Maritimes, Nova Scotia.
It's a Benjamin Bridge
Metered Classic rosé.
Roughing it in usual style.
Cheers, gentlemen.
Are we fessing up
to having a successful hunt?
- Cheers.
- Welcome to Newfoundland, boys.
If this is failure, I want more.
♪
Thankfully, fully aware
of my jinx-like effect
on on-camera hunting scenes,
the boys have stocked our larder
with many delicious things,
so we're covered.
Whoa.
Cotechina?
Finocchiona.
Fino... what?
What did you call me?
Finocchio.
Wow, that's awesome.
Yeah.
You often eat in the rain?
Like I said,
you're in Newfoundland.
It was Miami, like,
five minutes ago.
You don't come here
for the weather.
Literally five minutes ago,
it was, like, sunglasses.
And that's...
That's Newfoundland.
Four seasons in one day.
How many times
have you been here?
I've never been here.
- No.
- No, never.
Whoa, whoa.
Wait a minute.
This is your first time...
Our first time in Newfoundland.
We've tried to come
on a couple of occasions,
but no, we've never been here.
Proud Canadians.
This is not
one of the destinations
that a Canadian ends up in.
And yet you decided to open
a fine-dining restaurant
that, by definition, is seasonal
and requires at least
a significant part
of your clientele
to get on a plane
and make the kind of commitment
that these
clearly have not made.
And this is them!
Yeah, I mean, we just plan
to do what we love to do
and cook good food and
celebrate Newfoundland product.
And where do these oysters
hail from?
- These are Beau Soleil oysters.
- Beau Soleil, yeah.
Named after the early
Manson family killer?
Was there a Beausoleil
in the Manson family?
Bobby Beausoleil.
In fact, the entire
Manson family's killings
were designed to draw suspicion
away from Bobby Beausoleil.
I was always a fan
of Squeaky Fromme.
They just let Leslie
Van Houten out of the joint.
Correct.
And I hear she likes camping.
♪
Fred and Dave
do not travel light.
♪
Previously acquired stunt moose,
the legs slow-roasted
over an open fire,
the ribs of the same beast
braised on the coals,
and natural gravy simmers away.
A cured ham bought from
our generous friend
Marc Tampica in Montreal.
♪
But first, cans.
Oh, my good God.
Look at that thing.
It's a jellied foie gras.
Look at this thing.
Jesus.
This is the proof
of our low self-esteem.
A tureen of wild hare
drizzled with sauce.
What... what... what...
Another tureen of pheasant,
wild duck, and guinea hen
loaded with pleasing hunks
of foie gras.
Oh, look at that.
A wild boar tureen.
- Do you have boars here?
- No.
- Hogzillas?
That's another thing...
"Hogzilla"?
I think it would be
an amazing legacy
for Joe Beef to introduce
a foreign species
to Newfoundland.
I think that's awesome.
Like, that's the kind of shit
people don't do anymore.
Mmm.
Wow.
So you're mixing canned
and fresh truffle.
Yeah, because we can,
the same reason
the dog eats his ass.
'Cause he can.
After a humiliation in the wild
as severe as ours,
as sporting gentlemen,
it is required
that we discharge our weapons.
Yeah!
Repeatedly.
In this case,
at nonliving things.
All right, pull.
Got a fish.
Okay, pull.
What are the symptoms
of lead poisoning?
Uh, inability to hit a skeet?
Pull.
It's a bad place
for hippies to go camp
on the other side.
Yeah.
Pull.
Is that the stuff you learn
in West Virginistan?
Our main course arrives
as the temperature drops.
Moose shoulder and ribs,
neck braised in red wine,
wild mushrooms,
and grilled Scotch lovage
for the essential
vegetable component.
And roast chestnuts, bacon,
and pearl onions.
Whoa. Look at that.
It's gorgeous.
We didn't shoot a moose,
but we're gonna taste a moose.
That's good.
Wow.
Yeah, that's.
- Who's that?
- Thank you.
Wow, it's good.
Moose meat, best meat.
Number one meat in the world.
No better meat than the moose.
That's for sure.
♪
- Wow.
- Yeah.
This is amazing.
♪
I think that it's a treat
and it's...
I've said for years that
moose meat is the best meat,
the champagne
of animal proteins.
You're right.
It is something special.
Don't even mind the rain
anymore.
Look at that.
Like, what is that?
It's amazing.
It's a gray jay.
He'll just hop in your hand.
- Would he?
- He might.
Put something in your hand,
and he'll get it.
Look, he's on the camera.
I want... I really want
to do this.
He's gone?
Oh, he's on...
Oh, he's on Tony's head.
Animals love me.
I told you.
I'm like St. Francis of Assisi.
Oh, look, they really are
hitting the ham.
Oh, this could get ugly
really quickly.
Next thing you know, they're
pecking our eyeballs out
and tunneling up our asses.
63 feet.
Okay.
We're ready to go.
Thank you, sir.
What are we drinking?
A little Benjamin Bridge
out of Nova Scotia.
- Cheers.
- Gentlemen, cheers.
To the queen.
No, I hate the aristocracy, man.
They don't have long.
Raymonds in St. John's
is probably
the best-known, most celebrated
restaurant in Newfoundland.
It's gotten the region
national, even international
attention
with its hyper-localized,
wildly creative menus.
Wow, this is exciting.
Whoa. Wow.
Seafood tower.
Yes!
Razor clams, snow crab,
mussels, capelin, whelk,
and sea urchin.
Oh, look at that.
Little plump sacs of goodness.
Oh, God, that's good.
Boquerones, I'm very
excited about as well.
Whelks is my game.
- Really?
- Oh, love 'em.
The boquerones
are quite remarkable.
This is really good.
I'm gonna pass the tuna around.
I like the little berries.
It's funny; there's no oysters
on this or clams, which is...
- Right.
- Refreshing.
I don't think
I've ever seen that.
No.
It's only local.
Here you go.
Today we're just gonna do
just a scallop crudo.
Basically raw scallops
just with a salt, fresh herbs,
and a few simple garnishes.
It doesn't need much.
It is what it is, you know?
Speaks for itself.
Ready?
For me, the ocean,
the definition of the ocean,
when I think of the ocean,
I think of New England,
the northern part of France.
You know, magnificent,
steel gray, intimidating.
♪
It's the coldest [...] water.
Iceland?
Here?
- Sterile.
- Northern Europe?
- Northern Atlantic.
- Right.
- It's where it's all about.
- Yeah.
Or for me, it was always
where it's all about.
There's no draggers, no nothing.
You know, friends of mine
who gear up
and who are crazy enough
to jump in the Atlantic Ocean
and go to the bottom,
they emerge with these baskets
of beautiful scallops.
All right, let's get started.
Look at them.
The nerves are still in it.
See it there?
Fresh scallop.
Just want to keep it
pretty simple, you know?
They're delicious.
You can't get
much fresher than that.
No, I would say.
I myself, I take it on myself
to turn it into
nasturtium tacos.
Tacos of scallop.
I love nasturtiums.
Wow.
- We're eating Newfoundland.
- Yeah.
We're so fortunate here
in Newfoundland and Labrador
to be able to serve wild game...
Moose, rabbits, partridge,
grouse.
It's a really big part,
big staple
of our menu, obviously.
It's the reason why
the restaurant's
pretty much open, you know?
Nowhere else in the country
you can do that.
Heart of caribou tartar
with Adler and chanterelle.
I'm enjoying this meal.
Yeah, man, it's...
Very, very, very much.
This is really, really good.
Jeremy Charles, in my opinion,
honestly, I would say
easily top chef in Canada,
most likely, you know?
As a model of bravery,
determination, courage, pride.
And not a false note.
We've not had anything
that's not from this island.
What we got here
is the cod sound.
It's the swim bladder
of the codfish.
Just goes right up the middle
of the fish.
We've been toying around
with this for a long time.
This is almost like
boot leather, you know?
It's really, really tough.
So we'll salt it overnight.
Then we'll soak it,
and then we'll dehydrate it.
And this is the part
of you're left with.
It's almost like a chicharrón
type of texture, you know?
But my grandmother,
she'd probably just
render up pork fat scrunchions,
and they just fry these off,
you know?
So what we'll do then is,
we'll drop that in the oil.
And it's gonna puff up,
become this beautiful chip.
Charred whelk with [indistinct]
And crispy cod sounds.
What was this?
Sound, floating bladder.
Bladder.
Yeah, I like that.
Mmm, good.
Bladder.
- It's what?
- Fried bladder.
Smell it, though.
It's good.
It's delicious.
The onslaught of food continues.
Cod fillet
with cod liver [indistinct],
partridge profiteroles,
and this, the classic
Newfoundland staple,
Jiggs dinner,
reinvented into a pasta dish.
It's beautiful.
Oh, it's good.
Mmm.
- It's spectacular.
- Yeah.
I'll go so far as saying
it's the best pasta
I've ever eaten.
Wow.
The pasta itself
is extraordinary.
Even the detail
in this room is amazing.
Even the carpets, if you notice.
No!
We have a pair for you.
No way.
That's super creepy.
I'm alarmed.
As you step away
from the urinal,
are you shaking the last
couple of drops...
- Yes.
- On my face every time?
Wow, I don't know what to say.
I'm stunned.
Last but not least,
it's chanterelle ice cream.
- Oh, it's good.
- Mmm.
Ooh.
It tastes like
farmer's daughter.
That musty funk, you know,
in the hayloft?
That was spectacular
ice cream, though, for real.
I'm, like... I'm mad at you for
not having made this already.
No, no, no.
You're the king
of soft-serve flavors,
but you've not done
chanterelle ice cream?
Fred, I'm kind of pissed.
Tons of it.
You just never pay attention.
It's kind of dirty
in a good way.
I mean, a really good way.
♪
I hope they don't find
that 8-ball.
♪
How long is the flight?
Just about 45 minutes.
45 minutes?
That's enough to see, you know,
all the good films
that Michael Bay ever made.
I'm going to France.
Not like Francophone Canada
but France.
Really.
A little bit of actual France
sitting about 45 minutes
offshore.
The islands
of Saint Pierre and Miquelon,
France's last foothold
in North America.
French cars, French food,
pay in Euros,
and French attitude.
♪
We have a French way of life
here, really.
We eat French.
I think we think French also.
Almost.
Our hosts on this otherwise
male-centric brocation
are Maite and her friend Hilary.
People around here
don't eat out much.
Instead, most cook at home,
often with friends.
This is sea urchin paté.
- Yes!
- What?
Paté d'oursin,
a sea urchin paté.
Plump sacs of roe
fresh off the beach
formed into a loaf
and cooked with bread, garlic,
and onions.
And utterly delicious.
- Look at that.
- This is a try.
Wow, it's pretty.
Look at that.
Wow, it's sensational.
- You like it?
- Mmm, fantastic.
- Good.
- Wow, that's good.
You know, this is a kind
of dish for real we should do.
That's a very good idea.
Urchins,
transform it all at once
when it's at the peak
of freshness,
make a solid paté,
and serve it slice by slice
like foie gras, you know?
My mind's already racing.
Urchin sausages.
Steal this recipe, dude.
This is good.
Well, we'll have to call it
Paté Maite.
Well, my goodness.
What an honor.
I don't have copyrights on that,
because it's local.
- Classic.
- Really traditional food here.
It is that you've had this
all your life?
- Yes.
- Wow.
♪
Stuffed squid over rice.
Oh!
This is family style.
- Nice!
- Wowee.
Wow, look at that.
♪
Wow.
Thank you.
♪
Mmm.
Do you want some rice with it?
Wow.
You know, traditional
and family meal.
Yeah.
You're an amazing cook.
- Thank you.
- This is really great.
Maybe you're gonna have to
open a small, little restaurant.
Did you ever think of that?
Well, I'm planning
to open a pastry shop.
- Really?
- Yeah.
You bake as well?
♪
Braised halibut...
Simple and perfect.
- Halibut.
- Wow, look at that.
♪
Are these are potatoes
from here?
From France.
Oh, no.
We would like to.
Le Charlotte?
La belle de Fontenay?
Your knowledge of tubers
is dazzling.
Fred has an incredible amount
of pedantic knowledge
about several subjects.
Oh, wow.
This is great.
♪
At this point, there's only
one thing missing.
Oh, wow.
Wow!
- No way.
- Local cheese.
Glorious cheese.
And this is...
This is a tart, creme de mon.
- With urchins.
- No.
With baked apples
and blackberries from here.
Fantastic.
♪
You have to open
a little [inaudible]
Or something like that.
You have so much talent
in cooking and sourcing
and talking about it.
Don't stick to the pastry shop.
That's my gut feeling.
I want to talk to you
about financials as well.
I want to talk to you about how,
when you say "tea shop,"
there's no money in it.
You have to sell wine.
Make a small wine bar.
A wine bar is a license
to print money.
Wow.
Thank you, guys.
Thank you so much.
I'm so happy with this cheese.
The meal in general,
all of it was fantastic.
I'm so happy.
This is what I needed.
This is really a throwback.
This is the sort of meal
you have a hard time finding
in France now.
- Yeah.
- Correct me if I'm wrong.
You really have a hard time
finding a true, proud
French regional meal.
It's incredibly difficult.
I am, above all things,
a man of the people,
a regular Joe,
a man as moved by a simple
slab of Mom's meatloaf
as I am of lark's tongues
in aspic
studded with truffles
and moistened with the tears
of baby unicorn.
Big R's provides the local
version of comfort food
that all of us...
Chefs and regulars...
Want and need.
Now, correct me if I'm wrong.
The indigenous specialties
would be the Jiggs dinner.
Yeah.
And we got to get
the Funyuns, the bunions.
The scrunchions.
Scrunchions?
The truncheons, the...
You think they can whip up
some beets and goat cheese
for me?
♪
Fried baloney.
And don't sneer.
It's awesome.
♪
And you got to have
some fried clam strips...
For Dave, anyway.
Liver and onions for Fred.
♪
Pan-fried cods tongues.
They call it a Jiggs dinner,
perhaps the ultimate
Newfoundland classic,
like a pot-au-feu or
a New England boiled dinner...
Basically boiled salt beef,
cabbage, turnips, potatoes,
and peas pudding
topped with gravy...
Preferably, lots of gravy.
♪
Oh, this is magnificent.
This is something you'd have
at your grandmother's house.
Really?
It's basically pot-au-feu.
It's beautiful.
And one gravies this
without apologies.
Yeah, no apologies.
♪
Oh, that's good.
Yeah.
I love this gravy.
Give the boys the recipe
for the Joe Beef Swiss chard.
Oh, it's amazing.
A lot of Swiss chard
in the restaurant.
And the gardens as well.
And for years
and years and years,
we used to serve it
to customers,
and they never liked it.
Wow.
So what we started doing is,
we split the stems
from the greens.
We'll take the stems.
We'll blanch them, like,
in the Presto oven.
Then we'll juice them.
Mmm!
I'm happy.
We'll take the juice, reduce it.
Then we'll char lightly
the leaves.
- Clam strip.
- Thank you kindly.
We'll chop them, season it,
and we'll combine both
with a bit of butter.
Swap you a little bit of
baloney for a clam strip.
You okay with that?
I'm going in.
Sometimes we put the peppers
and smoke in the smoker.
All right.
Cheers.
We'll bake it in the oven
with parmesan cheese
and breadcrumb,
and then we'll toss it
in the garbage.
Immediately.
♪
You know what I like to do
on a sausage-fest-themed show
like this one?
I like to get liquored up
and throw axes at a target,
hoping, of course,
they don't bounce off
and sink into my groin
or somebody else's groin.
I hate when that happens.
Have you done this before?
I've thrown axes.
I throw axes.
Yeah, I had a throwing ax board
in the back of Joe Beef
until I realized
it wasn't really safe.
♪
Try not to cut your own ear off?
You want to draw back
nice and slow over your head.
Lean right in.
When your arm is straight out
and it's parallel
with the ground...
- That's when you release.
- That's it.
Is there a William Tell
kind of story in Newfoundland
with a cod over the head
and a father that threw the ax?
Not yet.
Do it proud.
Go, Fred.
Watch your head, there.
All right, so far,
we kind of suck.
This is not encouraging.
Try the double hand, yeah.
Oh, that was close.
You know what I'm gonna do?
I'm gonna put my ax to good use
and cut a little bit
of that Muenster cheese.
Now you're talking.
Let's have a little pork
and stinky cheese.
We'll become Thor,
the thunder god.
Mmm.
Oh, here we go.
I'm gonna try again.
I will get this right.
We're going back to drinking
after this;
I can tell you right now.
Something I excel at.
- Oh, yes.
- Oh!
Wow.
Now I'm making
my David tattoo even bigger.
I'm gonna concentrate.
I'm gonna think of someone
I really, really,
really, really, really hate.
- Yes!
- Oh!
Oh, [...].
Oh, [...] you.
You look like a serial killer.
Well, he killed a two-pack.
Hear ye, hear ye, hear ye!
Yeah!
Let's bring the Royal Order
of Screeches to order.
One final bit of business
remains
in this enchanted land
called Newfoundland:
an ancient and solemn ritual
reserved for newcomers,
an official welcome,
an initiation,
a way of saying,
"You are welcome.
You are maybe now one of us."
Oh, there's fire involved.
It's always fun
when there's fire involved.
I feel much better about this.
Today I will be screeched in.
I do need you to take
a small piece
of Newfoundland steak.
- Is it organic?
- Yes, of course, yes.
Do not worry about it
if you're vegetarian;
there's not much meat in it.
Thank you kindly.
And David and Tony.
And David.
- Thank you very much.
- You're welcome.
♪
In 1497, there was a man
by the name of John Cabot.
John Cabot sailed the Atlantic
on his boat, the "Matthew,"
all the way
from Bristol, England,
to Bonavista Bay.
And when he arrived,
he saw lots of activity
in our water.
Now, he didn't know
what was going on,
but he dropped his bucket down
to fill it up with water,
and when it came up
to the top of the boat,
it was filled right to the rim
with codfish.
Now, word got out fast
how plentiful the fish were
in our waters
that they traveled from all over
to settled here
and to catch the fish,
sell the fish,
trade the fish
all around the world
as a means of survival.
And one place in particular
that we traded with
was with Jamaica,
'cause in Jamaica,
they make rum,
and we loved rum.
We loved it so much
that we would actually get
on that wharf,
and we'd kiss the fish good-bye,
knowing that it was coming back
to us in the way of rum.
So in keeping with that time
and honored tradition,
I do have a little buddy
for you to meet.
It's a Gremlin.
This is a real Newfoundland
codfish.
Given the chance, this fish
could have grown up
to the height of 6 feet tall
and weighed as much
as 130 pounds.
This fish won't grow
any more than this,
because it's dead.
I do need you all to pucker up
and give this fish
a little kiss.
Excellent.
Fred, there we go.
On the lips?
You're best
to go first and last.
And by Jesus, keep
that tongue in your mouth.
Did you name your fish Valtrex?
I will now.
You were just in a strip club,
though, right?
Were you... were you...
Where did you put that mouth?
Tony, you can't catch it twice.
Oh, here, me darling.
Oh, my God, Vince.
Come on, love.
Lick up.
This is like an aphrodisiac
for you two.
Okay!
And we can't have a drink
without having a toast,
so please wait till
everybody gets their shot,
and we'll do it together.
Okay.
So here's to health
and your company
and one for the lasses.
Let's drink and be merry
all out of our glasses.
Let's drink and be merry,
bad thoughts to refrain,
for we may or may not
ever all be here again.
Up to the lips.
Over the gums.
Look out, gullet.
Here she comes.
Flush her back.
Okay, now I now declare you all
honorary Newfoundlanders.
Awesome.
There we go.
♪ Oh, well, I's the b'y
that builds the boat ♪
♪ And I's the b'y
that sails her ♪
that catches the fish ♪
♪ And brings it home to Liza
♪ Hip yer partner,
Sally Thibault ♪
♪ Hip yer partner, Sally Brown
♪ Fogo, Twillingate,
Moreton's Harbour ♪
♪ All around the circle
♪ I took Liza to a dance
as fast as she could travel ♪
♪ Every step that she did take
was up to her knees in gravel ♪
♪ Hip yer partner,
Sally Thibault ♪
Sally Brown ♪
♪ Fogo, Twillingate,
Moreton's Harbour ♪
♪ All around the circle
♪ I don't want
your maggoty fish ♪
♪ They're no good for winter
♪ But I can buy as good as that
way down in Bonavista ♪
♪ Hip yer partner,
Sally Thibault ♪
Sally Brown ♪
♪ Fogo, Twillingate,
Moreton's Harbour ♪
♪ All around the circle