This is the story of one
man, one chef, and a city.
Also it's about France and
a lot of other chefs.
And a culinary tradition that
grew up to change the
world of gastronomy.
It's about a family tree, about
the trunk from which
many branches grew.
It's about food, lots
of food, great food.
Some of the greatest
food on earth.
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la la
What is it exactly
about this place?
Over the past century, the
system here, the tradition,
whatever it is that took hold
here, churned out a tremendous
number of the world's
most important chefs.
Chappell, bocuse and most
importantly, influenced
nearly all the rest of them.
Why Lyon?
Why is this such a
gastronomic capital?
Why all of these great chefs?
Because Lyon is really
positioned between the
north and the south.
Right.
You're locked in between
burgundy and Rome.
Lyon is the second largest
city in France, situated in the
southeast of the country midway
between the alps in the east and
the Mediterranean to the south.
This was also a bottleneck
when cars began the mode of
transportation.
Goes right to the heart of
the idea of driving the
destination on the way
to... completely.
Out of that system came chefs
like this guy, Daniel Boulud.
Like prince or Madonna, he
needs really only one name.
In New York or anywhere in
the chef world, Daniel.
The name of his three star
restaurant in Manhattan, one of
many in an empire that stretches
from London to Singapore.
He came from here, a farm
outside the city of Lyon,
through the city's great
kitchens into New York,
then his flagship.
When did you start
working with food?
14 years old, 1969.
I started as an
apprentice in Lyon.
He started as so many French
cooks of his time did,
at the very bottom.
As a 14-year-old apprentice
in the restaurant.
What was your first
job in the kitchen?
They used to call me the
beaver, because I was just
washing every single day.
They make you clean the
vegetable, they make you carry
all the boxes from the market.
14.
You can't do that
anymore, can you?
I don't think you can make
him work 12 hours a day and pay
him maybe a buck a month.
Ah, the good old days.
Why Lyon?
Why here?
Look at the fundamentals, the
things that Lyonaisese
think of as birthrights.
The right to eat delicious cured
pork in unimaginably
delicious forms.
The art of chocolatery,
they can't live without it.
Pate, sausages, it's an art
that's revered here
and widely enjoyed.
Few names garner more
represent from aficionados of
pig.
20 ton just inside this room.
They are going mad
with the prediction.
In a relentlessly cold room,
pork shoulder, belly and fat
back are fed in batches
through a vertical chopper.
The sprinkling of
seasoning and spices.
Removed in large balls of finely
but not too finely chopped leek.
You do not want to get your hand
caught in one of these things.
Then mixed to smooth
perfection with a dough hook.
Lot of work.
Spread out and layered for
consistent seasoning, formed
into shapes and smacked
to remove air bubbles.
Make sure the meat
gets really tight.
Into the sausage machine and
piped into organic casings.
Trust me, it ain't easy.
Very light touch.
Let's see now.
Come on.
Let's see this.
That's how you get pregnant.
It's all in the meat.
Yeah.
Just release at the end.
It's a serious workplace but
with production nearly done,
this being France and all, it's
time for a snack and some wine.
Doing what I'm good at.
Eating.
This is so good.
Another of Lyon's most famous
sausages is made primarily from
pig's head with pork belly, pork
shoulder, Brandy, nutmeg and
allspice mixed in for flavor.
Man, it's good.
We're going to eat
with my father.
Oh, yeah?
He knows he does
really good work.
Huh?
He knows how good his stuff is.
Cheers.
Nice... it's a
beautiful day in Lyon.
Yeah.
In Lyon, a city that believes
absolutely in the power of food,
one name is everywhere.
The name that brought honor,
attention and millions of
visitors to the city.
Though there have been many chef
heroes in the annals of
gastronomy, in Lyon and even
cross France, one name
stands above all others.
Murals, Bridges, markets, casual
brasserie, the name of
missour Paul is everywhere.
One of his most enduring
institutions is this.
One of the nation's
great culinary schools.
Now, just to give you an idea of
the standards here, the kind of
traditional dishes, baseline old
school fundamentals you're
expected to master before you
move on at becoming a creative
genius all your own,
meet these guys.
Matthew, Joseph and the
institute's top dog, Alain.
Chefs at M.O.S., all.
Otherwise known as mos.
Otherwise pay your
flight home, private.
Master chefs.
Every four years, they
have this competition.
The master craftsmen of France.
There's about 30 discipline
of craftsmen where you can
acquire the M.O.F.
See that red, white and
blue around their necks?
That means they made it through
the rigorous competition where
only a handful survive.
Certified by the highest in the
land as being at the very top of
the top of their professions.
M.O.F. Challenges often include
ultra old school classics not
unlike the one we're
making today.
Poulair Au visse.
The rolls Royce of chickens.
It's then tied, slipped inside a
pig's bladder and
steamed until tender.
The idea is to concentrate
the flavor of the truffle
inside the bladder.
The dish they choose, it's
always in reference to
a chef of the past.
And this was a dish
they were doing.
The at times brutal world of
the kitchen looks much of the
time like a boys' club but
where did they come from?
If we track back a bit to where
it all began for Lyon and for
many of the chefs whose names we
now know and look up to,
it all goes back to here.
La mer brass Erie, the
godmother, the original master.
Teacher, chef, force.
Two restaurants with
three Michelin stars.
An achievement no one, male or
female, had attained and for
many years, Lyon's
most famous chef.
Her influence runs right through
every kitchen that's come since
and her graduates carry on her
recipes and her traditions.
This was one of
hers, a signature.
For the next hour, you
keep putting it like this.
The most miserable thing is
when the bladder explodes.
That's never a good thing
when a bladder explodes.
As the chicken proves, the
bladder is really tough to
expand.
You have to talk
to your bladder.
I do all the time, believe me.
Please hold up, please hold up.
Not here, people are looking.
Wait until you get
in between cars.
A rather luxurious sauce of
more, much more black truffle
and generous amounts of
foie gras and triple cream.
Perfect.
Nice milkshake.
Slightly pink around the legs
but cooked through, the flesh
perfumed by the generous
slices of truffle.
Who gets to eat like this?
We do.
How is it?
Divine.
You see the perfect
balance in the sauce.
If I was a chicken, that's the
way I would like to end up.
Even if I weren't a chicken,
I would like to go like this.
Die surrounded by truffles and
foie gras and fine wine.
Merci. Merci.
The roaring of a
powerful engine.
The screech of rubber
and off we go.
Kings of the road
in our Citroen.
Two horse power classic.
No power steering, huh?
You're kidding.
It's like a toy car.
We're going back in time a bit,
to the area where Daniel
grew up, where life was very
different from New York.
Were you the misfit of the
family, rebellious or...
I was quite rebellious.
My parents were talking to me
about the idea of
taking over the farm.
As the oldest son, that would
have been the logical thing.
Right.
The farmer's life
was not for you.
No.
He grew up in a
true farm family.
You milk the cows,
tended the animals.
Daniel claims he never even saw
processed food until
he was a teenager.
A brief respite by the side
of the road and some passersby
are apparently less appreciative
of fine automobiles than we are.
A short consultation with an
automotive professional and we
are back on the road, back
in this case to school.
This was Daniel's old elementary
school in a nearby town.
I'm automatically taken back to
memories of my own school days.
The smell of caustic pine
cleaner, chalkboards and fear.
The cruel ministrations of
tiny-eyed lunch ladies slopping
canloads of prison chow
into steam tables.
Tuna noodle surprise that haunt
my sense memories still.
Pumpkin soup today with
onion, nutmeg and chicken stock.
Basic good pumpkin soup.
This is Marie, head chef,
cook, host and server for 320
hungry and very discriminating
French schoolchildren
ages 3 to 12.
On the menu, prefix today,
pumpkin soup, home made
cous-cous and a sauce supreme.
This is a very sophisticated
meal for children.
I was a little...
In school, frankly.
Like a lot of other students, I
want pizza, pizza, pizza, are
the children here
open to variety?
We want to make sure they
always get a little challenge by
how the food looks and the smell
and also, the taste after.
I think she has a
very strict budget.
In the USA, greatest country
in the world, no doubt, we spend
an average of $2.75 per student
for public school lunch.
Compare and contrast.
$1.50.
Did you eat this well
when you were here?
Absolutely.
Bon jour.
The kids attack their food
like hungry trenchmen, wiping
out three servings in the
time it takes me to eat one.
I guess they like it.
It's good.
This is good.
I don't think my chef in
new York would do better.
These kids eat fast.
Look how fast this kid eats.
Turn your head, he'll dish your
food right out of your plate.
Push up your tray just like
in prison, move it along.
Move it along.
They come to you and serve you.
Most important thing that we see
here is the love Mary give to
the food she make and
to the kids she serves.
I think it has a lot to do with
the reaction they have to food.
Dessert is homemade fromage
blanc, cheese with chocolate
and orange segments.
What do you want to
be when you grow up?
Fireman.
Generate machine gun.
He wants to make...
Generate machine gun, yeah.
Okay.
Keep an eye on that one.
All right.
For a dope fiend, feeding the
monkey means finding and
sticking with heroin.
For one poor guy, it's this.
French food, in particular,
lyonaise food.
The cautionary tale of bill
Buford, literary lion with a
perfectly good job as fiction
editor at "new yorker" magazine,
at the undignified age of 53, he
pretty much pulled up stakes,
put his whole past life on hold
and defected to France
to learn how to cook.
What happened to you?
You used to have a good job, you
hung out a couple nights with
battagli and next thing you know
you're living in
France and cooking.
I discovered a whole world
that the rest of the world
didn't seem to know about, just
a very compressed and tense
lifelong learned expertise
and knowledge of food.
It's not the food network and
it's not glossy magazines and
it's not something you get
from reading a recipe book.
It's something you get
by just going deep.
I was afraid of France because I
didn't find when I took on the
subject of French food, I would
have to go really deep.
I went and thought we would have
to stay for six months and
we stayed for five years.
We meet at a uniquely lyonaise
institution, a casual
laid-back kind of pub/bistro
with a limited old school menu
and always, always an
unpreten shouse vibe.
People come here to unwind,
relax and eat with abandon.
So you say outright recently in
one of your published works that
Lyon is better than Paris.
Lyon is beautiful, well-eating
city and everybody
here knows they have a really
good life and they don't give a
flying fig if anybody
else knows about it.
They don't actually
want visitors.
If you were to pick one
iconic dish to represent, it
would have to be
the canel broche.
Not particularly fabulous river
fish, pike, folded into a light
dough until fluffy and airy but
still rich, adrift in a rich
creamy, almost bisque-like sauce
made with crayfish,
creme fresh and Brandy.
It's kind of a nice mix
of France and Italy.
What a treat to eat
together in Lyon.
If you're really gonna
understand a place, love it the
way it deserves to be loved,
maybe you have to live there.
Bill Buford did just that
and made Lyon his home.
Today he's taking me somewhere
only someone from the home team
could be expected to know about.
It's a beautiful day.
The sky is blue, we're feeling
the seasons changing and we're
about to go into a dark room,
and you eat a very lyonaise menu
and drink a vast
quantity of wine.
What sinister bodies
will be in there?
Only kind of people who would
do this kind of thing on a
bright pretty day, its's
a very male tradition.
You work hard, you drink harder.
Uh-oh.
Don't be afraid.
The mysterious, fabulous,
goofy, wonderful bro-fests are
basically eating and drinking
societies that go back over a
century, when the silk workers
of Lyon would finish their night
shifts early in the morning.
Hungry and looking to get, shall
we say, completely hammered,
they would take over, stuff
their faces like heroes, blow
off the proverbial steam in
decidedly French fashion, which
is to say no freakin' guytallion
nachos or mozzerella
sticks for these guys.
All of them have
special memberships?
There must be 50 of those
that I know about.
You are invited to be a member
and remain a member the
rest of your life.
The food is invariably
deliciously dinosauric and heavy
always glorious classics, the
slow, slowly stewed neck and
shoulder pieces of veal with
mushrooms served over rice,
hunks of bread and
wine, and lots of it.
It works, and for 50 years.
Do women have their
own organizations?
Yes.
There are.
So somewhere on the other side
of town, there are a lot of
women sitting around drinking
wine, eating and
complaining about the men.
Uh-oh.
Then there will
be, yes, singing.
And no doubt the telling of
lusty jokes followed by
serious official business.
Alongside and some say above
the names of the other culinary
giants in and around Lyon
is the name trois gros.
It sparked a dynasty of culinary
excellence that continues today
with Pierre's son Michel
and his son, Cesar.
My dream always was to
put it on my resume.
Bon jour.
Many have called Maison trois
gros the best restaurant
in the world.
In the '60s, the brothers were
early, important and fundamental
innovators of what came to be
known as nouvelle cuisine.
Behold, one of their
breakout classics.
One of the truly game-changing,
timeless, most influential
dishes in history.
It seems now maybe a simple
thing, but it absolutely turned
the world upside down when it
debuted on the menu in 1962.
When you have a dish this
legendary, this iconic,
there's no escaping it.
The rolling stones will always
have to play jumping Jack flash.
If you Google foie gras,
you will see this thing.
Forget everything you
have been given.
Before this, fish was
generally overcooked.
It was served alongside
elaborate garnishes, starches,
vegetables.
This simple, elegant, almost
Japanese ode to flavor changed
the way we cook fish in
restaurants today.
And how we make sauces,
what our plates look like.
I remember seeing a picture
of this as a young man.
I'm getting goosebumps
seeing this.
Thrilling.
Perfect.
It's beautiful.
The moment you put
the fish in the pan.
It's very important.
All right.
From now, to you in the
dining room in one minute.
One minute is the time.
Perfect.
Because it's cooking
all the way.
Mm.
Perfect.
It's a perfect dish.
It's really one of the great
ideas of the 20th century.
Fashionable.
Sexy.
When in Lyon, one can't help
but a see line from there, from
the rustic dishes of the farm to
here, the classics of the
great tables of Europe.
All roads lead here.
A major trunk of the tree that
goes back to karem and beyond.
Monseur Paul Bocuse.
The brigade.
The way it is done and has
always been done since a
military style hierarchy was
instituted into the kitchen.
When the only acceptable
response to any question or
any command is oui, chef.
This is the special forces,
the S.a.S., of cooking.
And these cooks live to avoid,
under any circumstances,
disappointing their comrades,
the hierarchy or monseur Paul.
Daniel worked here and so have
many, many who have gone on to
run their own
celebrated kitchens.
In the '70s as a young wanna-be
cook, I managed to lay hands on
a French copy of the classic
cookbook, La Cuisine Du Marche
and I struggled to translate the
descriptions of dishes so
fantastic I was quite sure I
never, ever in my life
would cook, much less eat.
If you could please say how
honored and grateful
I am to be here.
This is a dream come true.
Over the years, how many great
chefs have come through this
restaurant and on to
open great restaurants?
There is a child somewhere
around the world because
everybody goes around the world.
But he is and was
part of the system.
He came up with his own cruel
and terrifying masters and
their faces are here.
The towering and intimidating
figure behind la pyramid.
Owl out of his
kitchens same such
figures as Francois Biese,
George Perrier and many more.
This was all the gang of
the nouvelle cuisine.
The '60s in New York.
Every great chef I have ever
met has nightmares of they're
still a young man, they're back
in a kitchen and a chef
is yelling at him.
Who were his masters?
A woman.
Really?
La mer brassier at the ripe old
age of 20, he worked
as an apprentice.
She was such a screamer.
You would fall on your butt, she
was screaming so hard.
She was the first up in the
morning and the last
one to go to bed.
She would go to the market with
three cook in the back of the
truck and she would put the case
of green beans or something and
the cook will be sitting down
making the beans,
not to waste time.
Truly a terrifying figure.
Truffle soup Elyssee.
I can't tell you how many hours
I stared at photos of this dish,
how pathetically I
tried to replicate it.
Never did I think I would get to
try it, much less like this.
Sea bass with a tomato bernaise
sauce baked in a
meticulously crafted crust.
This is a great moment.
The fish is filled with a
delicate lobster mousse and
tarragon and wrapped
carefully in pastry.
Notice the careful and
tableside carving and service.
He has been making the
same thing for 50 years.
Paul has an amazing
respect for classic.
The peasant classic.
Tony, get closer.
You are totally sending me
every one of those
pictures, by the way.
Wow.
Look at that.
This style of dish goes back
long before cameras
but it's perfect.
Is there a more perfect
assortment of colors and
textures.
This one is a somewhat
more luxurious version.
Beef flanks, oxtail, veal
flanks, chicken, marrow bones,
beef ribs, leeks, carrots,
turnips, fennel and parsnips,
served with its own
deeply rich broth.
Think it's enough
for the two of us?
And then, this.
As if the chef had been
listening to my deepest, darkest
secret yearnings, an almost
completely disappeared,
incredibly difficult
preparation of wild hare.
The animal is first slowly
cooked, then coated by a sauce
of its own minced heart, liver
and lungs that has been
thickened with its own blood.
After more than six hours of
preparation, the hare is served
as the chef prefers, whole on
the bone, the rich glorious
sauce finished with truffles
and chartr chartreuse.
Absolutely the lost
ark of the covenant.
Everything great about cooking
is encapsulated in this
dish.
We continue all over the
world to make cuisine for
many generation to come.
Forever.
I will never eat like
this again in my life.
Chef, merci.
The meal of my life.
Today I was treated to the
greatest hits of a glorious
and fabled career.
For the first and probably the
last time, I sat next to the
great man himself and Daniel and
I were served a menu that chefs
will look back on in a hundred
years and smile at appreciably,
sentimentally, respectfully.
So me and Daniel were going
hunting and over lunch, we
mentioned that fact to Paul, who
immediately insisted, insisted
that if we wanted to go duck
hunting, we should come by his
crib, and so we find ourselves
in the morning mist of Le dawn,
a rural area about a
half hour outside Lyon.
Sure enough, in spite of his 88
years, and the fact that he's
been less than well, 9:00 A.M.
On the nose, there he is,
sitting on top of his beloved
John Deere with his
faithful dog ready to go.
Nice fresh morning.
That dog is happy.
The great chef loves this
place, and you can see why.
♪
Monsuer Paul can't safely
hunt but is happy to chase
around flushing birds for us.
Beautiful.
Yeah, it is beautiful.
I could do this all day.
That was about as good
as we're going to get.
If you look long enough,
you start hallucinating.
You start hallucinating ducks
where there aren't any.
You see that one falling?
Okay, not a moment to waste.
Quickly, a second shot.
Okay.
You got it?
Yeah.
Right there.
Between me and Daniel and the
dog, we managed to
actually bag a few ducks.
Good job.
Very good.
Easy shot.
Then it's back to the lodge,
clearly Paul's happy place,
where we meet up with some
hunting buddies of
the great chef.
You did a good job, no?
Success.
Yeah.
It's fantastic.
Is this the hunting lodge,
the weekend getaway,
hang out with the guys?
That's where he comes
every day, almost.
Look at the picture behind.
You see?
For tonight's meal, we pluck
and roast some woodcocks
over an open fire.
Cook up some well-aged
duck and pheasant.
They make mashed potato here.
There a head in there somewhere?
Yes, of course.
That's happiness right there.
I am a man of simple needs.
And I notice... we can
spend the whole week
and we'll be hunting, we'll be
cooking, eating, drinking, and
talking and that's beautiful.
It is for me a dream to spend
this time with a legend.
But I'm thrilled that Beaucoup
himself seems delighted.
In Lyonnes, he's the great chef,
a public figure, a
hero, an institution.
Always treated with the
greatest deference.
Here it appear he's free to
enjoy the simple things with
friends, local farmers who talk
to him like anybody else.
It's a pretty damn
magical thing to see.
Daniel might be a 3
star Michelin chef but
like so many of his
predecessors, he's basically a
farm boy.
He grew up milking cows and
doing farm work here on
his family's spread.
There is as it turns out,
something of a restaurant
tradition to build on.
The house on his farm was once a
cafe as well, operated first by
his grandparents and
great grandparents.
The famous cafe Boulou was not
the first place to
keep that name.
That kept it for 80 years,
100 year, then they closed it.
Meeting hi dad, one seems to
understand the roots
of his perfectionism.
His mom, dad, wife Katherine and
Danielle collaborate
with some debate.
On a super old school
farmhouse classic.
The sort of things good times,
bad times, a family could make
with stuff always readily
available on the farm.
Check this out.
It's a hollowed out pumpkin
layered with toasted chunkses of
stale bread, nutmeg, grated
cheese, mushrooms, fresh cream
from the cows and the
meat of the pumpkin.
And a layer of bacon also.
Oh, man, it's heavy.
Are you concerned the pumpkin
is go I think to try to get out?
His dad can be a bit of a
mcgooi mcelhi McGyver.
You don't waste stuff and
he's a bit of an inventor.
An old washing machine
turned still.
To seal it so there's
no air coming in.
Leftover grape solids usually
used to be make liquor,
today a different use.
If we can get it out of here.
Why did you put so
much cement on it?
We'll be using this delightfully
funky stuff to flavor the steam
that cooks the vegetables
from inside the still.
Then we come back in an hour.
At Dutinsk we settle for dinner.
Look at that.
Ion credible.
Wow.
The pumpkin is amazing.
We also have that great sausage.
Oh, look at that.
Cabbage and potatoes, all
steamed in the still.
The flavor you get from the
fermented grape, awesome.
Good.
So good.
As you know Danielle can't
really help himself.
He's popping up and down,
serving everybody, making sure
everything is just right.
Sitting here with his family in
the house he grew up in, you can
see where it all comes from.
Their son is now a gigantic
international success.
When he was a young man at 14
sneezing in the field, did
they ever anticipate this?
We do.
They all reflect the
region hopefully.
But in the best case,
they're interdependent.
They come from each other.
In fact, who cooks in
the great restaurants?
Farm boys basically.
That's who always cooked.
My deepest thanks to your
mother an your father.
Thank you.
Merci.
Next time my father will
make you drive the tractor.