In the early 1960s,
three idealistic
young CIA officers
arrived in Laos,
a sleepy, mountainous country
of barely over 2 million people,
mostly rice farmers.
Their mission:
stop the spread of Communism,
recruit and train
hill tribe warriors
to fight a shadow war
against the North Vietnamese
and the Pathet Lao.
The war in Laos was secret.
The Russians knew about it.
The Chinese knew,
the Vietnamese.
The Laotians certainly knew.
The only people who didn't
was the American public
and Congress.
♪ I took a walk through this ♪
♪ Beautiful world
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good in this ♪
♪ Beautiful world
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ La, la
♪ Sha la, la, la, la
♪ Sha la, la, la
♪ Sha la, la, la, la, la
♪
Though never actually at war
with Laos,
at the same time
we were fighting
in neighboring Vietnam,
the United States flew more
than half a million missions
over this tiny
Southeast Asian nation,
dropping more bombs here
than on Germany and Japan in
all of World War II combined...
This only a part
of the largest covert
military operation in history,
a conflict that became known
as the Secret War.
There were three
intelligence officers,
key players in this secret war,
who, depending
on who you talk to,
were either greatly loved
or greatly feared and despised.
Anthony Poshepny,
also known as Tony Poe,
had an extensive
paramilitary background
as a former Marine
and CIA officer.
Bill Lair, a Texan
and World War II vet,
was an influential
CIA case officer.
Vint Lawrence was recruited
right out of Princeton
even though he was
an art history major.
They succeeded at first
in impeding the flow
of Communist North Vietnamese
arms and troops
on the Ho Chi Minh Trail.
But by the end,
they were arming even children.
What happened here...
Presumably in the cause
of freedom,
of democratic Western values...
Resonates still.
An estimated 30%
of the bombs dropped on Laos
failed to detonate.
These and other UXOs
remain in the ground
and continue to take lives
and limbs.
♪
When you get off the plane...
Yes.
What's the first sort of
recognizable smell
that registers?
Wood smoking, grilling.
♪
The river as well.
You know, it's just, like,
the Mekong...
Diesel or whatever
the fuel is here.
A little bit of that.
Yeah, yeah.
♪
From the first time I heard
of Laos, I was hooked
and filled with a desire
to see the place,
once a storybook kingdom
of misty mountains and opium,
at one time a protectorate
of France,
a mysterious landlocked nation
bordered by China,
Thailand, Cambodia,
and, as fate would have it,
Vietnam.
♪
See, the best
restaurant view ever.
All these women butchers.
♪
Chef James Syhabout
earned his Michelin star
in San Francisco.
This is the first thing I eat.
Get off a plane,
I just want to go find
some khao piak sen.
He learned to cook
from his mother
and never looked back...
until recently.
It's crispy pork, sliced pork.
- Blood cake?
- Blood cake in it.
- Meat broth.
- Meat broth, yeah.
Oh, it's, like, steaming hot.
James' family, like many,
fled the fighting in Laos
or the Communist takeover
that followed it.
Mmm.
Nowadays, things are
looking up a bit,
and some, like James,
are returning.
Oh, yeah, this is,
like, so homey.
Takes you to a place.
Takes me to a place.
What's it like being back, man?
I mean, it's only
your second time,
but what's it like?
Oh, man, it's like home
more and more.
I totally get it
when my mom says,
"I want to go back home."
That's a common thing.
Refugees live in the States
for a couple years.
Once their children have
their own careers and families,
they come back.
My mom's doing that now,
rice farming again.
She said, "I want to move back
to have a more relaxed life,"
but, like, it's hard work.
But she's happy?
She's happy, super happy.
She looks a lot younger now.
After she moved back.
Less stress, I guess.
Yeah, yeah.
♪
This village, we call Long Ian.
- Rice farming?
- Yes.
They're doing rice and also
growing some vegetable.
Northern Laos...
Enchantingly beautiful,
sparsely populated
by remote mountain villages,
for centuries home to
ethnic minority hill tribes
like the Hmong.
This is where the CIA
recruited, trained, and armed
over 100,000 fighters.
Before that,
how did you get up and down?
Walk?
In these same mountains
but on the other side
of the conflict,
there were people like Mr. Li,
now in his 80s,
who fought for
the Communist Pathet Lao.
He is Hmong,
and during the Secret War,
he fought other Hmong.
♪
Ah, fantastic.
Wow.
Mmm.
- This is chicken.
- Chicken.
And this is chicken also
but with blood
and some inner heart.
Every Hmong family
will know this.
Beautiful.
Mmm.
He was here when the French
were here, yes?
How was he injured?
In the end,
when the last choppers
hurriedly left Vietnam,
Laos and many Lao
who fought with us
were left behind too.
What had been a kingdom
was now a Communist regime.
Yeah, the bad guys won.
A few who'd been
most directly associated
with the American effort,
unwilling to face
rehabilitation camps or worse,
never surrendered
and are, all these years later,
hiding in hills like these.
Hmong were killing Hmong
bitterly for many years.
If the same people
who were trying to kill him
and who he was trying to kill
came back now,
how would he feel about that?
♪
Luang Prabang,
Laos' ancient capital,
is a sleepy city of
ornate palaces and temples.
♪ Get up in the morning
They enthusiastically observe
Boun Ork Phansa here,
a big party marking the end
of Buddhist Lent.
The whole thing culminates
in a few days
with a fire lantern festival,
the symbolic casting away
of your sins.
Hey!
♪
Oh!
But this morning, the Lao
are watching and drinking
as others pull at oars
and race to the finish line.
♪
Boat festival?
Yeah, boat festival here.
Today is the girls racing.
Each boat will be women
from the same village.
Yeah, one boat is one village.
For weeks, racing teams
have been practicing
on the Mekong River,
each team sponsored
by a local Buddhist monastery.
♪ 'Cause it's true
♪
Eat, drink, enjoy view,
enjoy boat.
How old is this tradition?
It's a long time ago,
many generation.
We start maybe on sixth century.
♪
♪ If you want to figure
it out, take my advice ♪
♪ You gotta think,
you gotta think ♪
♪ You gotta think
for yourself, a'ight? ♪
Uh-oh, what are we doing?
Lao lao?
Yes, lao lao.
We doing some lao lao.
So made by the sticky rice,
so it tastes good.
That one quite strong.
Ooh!
Boy, this is close.
Both of you born here?
Yeah, I'm the older sister,
and she's younger sister.
How has the country changed
since you were little kids?
The country change a lot.
We open the tourism scene,
so it's good
for the local economy.
And local people,
they can earn money
from the visitor and tourist.
President Obama was just here
a few months ago.
Few months ago.
Yeah, he offer a lot of help
for education and for the...
Unexploded ordnance removal.
I think $90 million.
That's...
- That's a lot.
- It's a lot of money?
Help a lot.
This one the local snack.
Oh, chicken feet.
Good.
And buffalo tendon.
Oh, nice, good.
Yeah, I'll try that.
Squid?
Dry squid.
God, I love this.
This is delicious.
When we eat and we enjoy food,
in Lao, we say,
"Sep lai."
- Sep lai.
♪
- Your hotel.
- My hotel.
How long has it been open?
Well, it's been about 20 years.
I'm having lunch
at the Ban Lao Hotel.
During the Secret War,
it was the offices
for USAID,
America's foreign aid mission.
The building was also a cover
for CIA headquarters.
Can we say...
USA or CIA.
I don't know.
Well, this is
what I want to ask.
Generally speaking,
back in the '60s and '70s,
USAID and CIA had a lot of,
let's say, overlap.
♪
Mama Von, who I met here
on my last trip,
is making lunch,
an elaborate spread of dishes
whose recipes are left over
from imperial times.
So what do we have here?
This is lon song,
a fish from Mekong.
We cook with shallots
and garlic and chili
and coconut milk and pork.
♪
Crab?
River crab?
River crab, yeah.
♪
- Mmm.
- See?
It's good.
It's only in Luang Prabang.
- You can eat the shell.
- Yes.
Mmm.
And fish with pork, grill.
Or in banana leaves.
Mm, and the ginger sauce.
We eat the pork skin.
Pork skin.
And we have to have sticky rice.
Yeah, sticky rice.
Okay, bon appétit.
Food like this...
This is an imperial dish,
a royal dish...
Have these disappeared,
these recipes?
Or are they still here?
They're still here,
but, you know,
sometimes they do it not the way
that not supposed to do it.
They change ingredient a lot.
My grandma teach me
how to do this.
You were born here, yes?
In Luang Prabang?
In Luang Prabang, yup.
And, Michel, you...
- I was born in Vientiane.
- In Vientiane.
And you lived here
all your life? No.
- In France.
At the age of 11,
I went to France to study.
I came back in 1971.
Oh, difficult times, 1971,
very difficult.
Yeah, it was still the war.
Mama Von's longtime friend
Michel
was a journalist,
though what that means
in a Communist one-part state
like Laos
is necessarily different
than what you and I
might define it as.
When I was in Paris,
I studied ethnology.
When I came here, they said,
"Ethnology can wait.
What we need is journalists."
That's why you get your job.
That's how I became
a journalist.
American involvement here
remains a particularly painful
and even taboo subject
with the Lao government.
Obama,
the United States president,
just came here to visit.
What do you think it means
for Lao?
Well, I think
one important thing
is the UXO,
unexploded ordnances,
Right.
American B-52s, they came
on bombing missions in Laos
every day, every day, every day.
And after bombing,
they had to cross Mekong back
and land,
but they are not allowed to land
with bombs on board.
So if they have bombs left,
they would drop them at random.
That's why we have so, so many
in so many provinces.
What do you think
it means, though,
that the president came here?
Look, this is a small country,
only 7 million people.
- Yes.
- Yeah.
Not a lot of mineral resources.
- No, not really.
- No oil.
If you were a cynical person...
I'm not.
Well...
Why do you think he came?
Well, you have China.
You have Russia.
You have...
You think that maybe we think
we need a friend
in the neighborhood.
I think everybody needs friends.
♪
So you were born
in a refugee camp.
- Yes.
- Moved to the States what age?
Two.
I don't really remember much.
My dad never once talked
about the Secret War.
He didn't really explain why
we had to come to the States.
It was just like,
"We're here. Enjoy it."
♪
Almsgiving is a daily ritual,
but this is special.
People always sit down
along the street...
Right.
Wait for the monk coming,
and give sticky rice.
Most people,
they give sticky rice.
Boun Ork Phansa means the end
of months
of isolated meditation.
Monks celebrate
with a once-a-year
Halloween-like bonanza
where, in addition
to the usual sticky rice,
all manner of treats
are offered.
♪
I was a novice.
Come from my home village
to live in the temple
in Luang Prabang.
I finished a monk.
The orange robes, the whole bit.
Mm-hmm.
Now, do most young men
go to the temple to...
To get education, yes.
It's the only way you get,
like, public education,
is to become a novice.
- Yes.
- Ah.
So everybody.
Everybody, yeah.
That's where you learn English.
Yeah.
- And you speak French too?
- No.
Chef James' friend Mr. C
lives with his extended family
on the outskirts
of Luang Prabang.
♪
Looks awesome.
So what have we got here?
Aw lahm is
an incarnate Lao dish.
Wood ear mushrooms, dill.
The key ingredient
is the pepper wood,
these wooden blocks,
which has, like,
a white pepper, star anise...
That infuses the fish.
You don't eat it.
It's like an umami.
Very herbaceous, peppery,
really rich.
Unlike anything I've ever had.
We have two types of lahm.
One's raw. One's cooked.
So it's cooked buffalo,
raw buffalo.
- Buffalo.
- Man, it's really good.
This was kind of improvised.
Leuat paeng.
"Leuat paeng" translates
to "fixed blood."
So it's buffalo blood.
It's a really tricky way
to prepare the dish,
'cause you want
the blood to set,
so the way you do
is dilute the blood with water.
And just pour it over herbs,
and that's it.
Lao panna cotta.
Mmm, this is
really, really good.
You know, the balance
is so beautiful.
This meal kind of represents,
like, a Lao table.
You always got to have a soup.
You always got to have
some kind of lahm, a stew,
some kind of muddled salad,
sticky rice, of course,
and a dip.
- And Beerlao.
Yeah, let's get that.
Let's get that.
Your parents left Laos in what?
- '81.
And, you know, we migrated
to a community
of other Laotians.
And it was pretty much
a community like this.
We all shared water.
Scratching out a living.
I mean, if you were Laotian
and you wanted
to make money back then,
you were cooking Thai food.
Exactly. My mom worked
in Thai restaurants, and...
What does your mom think
of your Lao cooking?
She's just pretty impressed,
surprisingly.
The first thing she does
when she walks
through my kitchen is,
she goes to the waste bin,
and she goes looks in the trash
and goes...
"Why you throwing this out?"
Yeah, yeah.
You know, it's, like,
cilantro stems.
So how many years
were you a novice?
Three years.
- Three years?
- Yes.
Well, what's the minimum?
Ah, minimum seven days.
- Wow. That's easy.
- Easy.
I don't have time.
What's life like at the temple?
Sleep on the floor?
You sleep in a bed?
Normally, we sleep in the floor,
and later I sleep on bed.
- One meal a day.
- Two.
- Breakfast and lunch.
- Yes.
And you get a snack
from the almsgiving.
Yes, snack and drink:
coffee, Ovaltine.
Coffee and Ovaltine,
did you say?
- Ovaltine.
He got it.
Here's a cup.
- Ovaltine.
- For you.
Cheers.
♪
The American experience
in this part of the world
is something that everyone
wants to pretend
never happened.
More bombs dropped here
than all of World War II.
This is the gold medal of Laos.
It's, they say,
one ton per person.
And if they continue to clean
the country at that reason,
more 600 years to clean it.
Come on, 'kay.
Come on. Come on. Come on.
Oh, no,
this is the strong stuff.
Good for you.
Hello.
One, two, three.
Très bien.
♪
Motorbike... the only way
to see this part of the world.
The thick, unmoving air.
The smell.
Past rice paddies,
water buffaloes.
What feels like another century.
♪
Laos is the kind of place
that can easily
capture your heart
and not let you go.
This is what you do, right?
I mean, if you're thinking
of a place
to open a bar or restaurant,
you're gonna put it
by the river.
- Yes.
- Nice breeze, nice view.
And you see the Lao people.
They come here
during the afternoon.
They have a drink.
It's nice.
- Perfect.
More than a few people
came here for vacation
and never went home, like Ben.
So how long have you been
in Laos?
In Laos?
Oh, around 15 years.
I haven't been back to France
for a long time.
When you first came here,
what was it like?
It was just open.
You know, it was
beginning of 2000.
What do you mean by "just open"?
Before, it was very difficult
to travel, you know.
If you have a permit
to travel in Luang Prabang,
you can only visit
Luang Prabang.
If you want to go
another province,
you need to have
a special permit to change.
And I had a friend,
and my friend say,
"No, let's go to Laos.
"It's more protected,
more natural,
more authentic."
I said, "Okay.
Why not?"
The first time I arrived
in Luang Prabang,
I was feeling like Indiana Jones
discovering a beautiful city.
And the point is,
I fell in love,
and I couldn't go back.
What's your typical day here?
Like, if you're not working,
on a good day, you know.
On a good day, you have a party.
You have a party.
Beerlao, friends,
that's what for.
Again, there is
nothing special to do.
It's just the way of life.
♪
- Look.
- Yeah, training.
♪
So how has it changed
over the years?
I mean, you go to Saigon
or Hanoi...
Money, money, money coming in.
Foreign ownership of everything.
Is... that's not happening here?
Yes, I can see there is
the next generation now.
Now when you go to the markets
and you say,
"Where is it from?"
they say,
"Thailand, Vietnam, China."
And to find local foods
is difficult.
But if you talk to old people,
they will say, "Boh penh nyang."
"We are like the bamboo.
We are not trees.
"So when there is too much wind,
we bend, and we get up,
and boh penh nyang."
I was a monk for a little bit
more than one month.
In fact, I "signed"
for three weeks.
After three weeks, I wanted
to stay a little bit.
They push a lot
the way to not suffer,
to learn how to disconnect
the important things in life.
That's why the people,
they drink a lot.
They like to enjoy, to share.
If you don't share,
you are poor.
The more you give,
the more you are rich.
You have money a lot.
You lose your money tomorrow.
Some people would be upset.
And you go up and going down.
It's never a good feeling.
Boh penh nyang.
I just say look at the river.
It's go up. It's go down.
But always in the same way.
And at the end is the end.
Boh penh nyang.
♪
Let us assume the best
of the intelligence officers
who served here,
of the pilots and bombardiers
who ran missions over Laos...
Watch your step.
That they were doing
their duty as they saw it,
that they believed they were
serving the interests
of their country.
So this is a banana plantation?
Yes, banana and lemongrass.
That still leaves us
with the unarguable fact
that generations later,
UXOs, or unexploded ordnances,
remain a huge problem.
What's here?
Cluster bomb, mostly?
Or bombies?
Yes, yes.
Organizations like UXO Lao
are tasked
with cleaning up the mess.
You go with a metal detector,
dig them out by hand,
no machines,
detonate them.
The technology we use nowadays
is the same as 20 years ago.
Right.
Wow.
That's a big bang.
Yeah.
Laos is the mostly heavily
bombed country per capita
in the history of the world.
Yeah.
80 million is the number
of cluster bombs
that did not detonate.
Since the war in Vietnam ended
and we left our Secret War here
behind,
20,000 people, many of whom
were not even alive
during the conflicts,
have been killed or maimed.
Now, most of the people
who are blown up, who are they?
Mostly farmers?
Nowadays, the picture's
a little bit changed
to the children right now,
because the children,
is look like tennis ball,
is good for playing,
for the children to pick up
as a toy.
So far, only half
of 1% of the country
has been cleared.
80 million cluster bombs
are still left in the country.
Right.
20 years, what we did
is 1.4 million.
- In 20 years.
- 20 years.
- So that's a lot left.
- That's a lot.
And many people are asking me
how many years it will...
I have no answers.
- Saam!
- Three.
- Song!
- Two.
- Neung.
- One.
♪
So this is bamboo soup.
This bamboo is very fresh,
because they just get it
from the forest up here.
Normally, the bamboo is still
a bit bitter.
Mm-hmm.
- But he has to boil it.
- A long time.
And then he will take off
the water.
Ah, will change the water.
He'll change the water
and cook it again
with chicken or duck.
- Right, some flavor.
- Yes.
So what year was he born?
How old is the gentleman?
1960, so born at the beginning
of the war here.
Yeah.
While these days, the effects
of the Secret War
are receiving more attention,
much of how we got here
remains off limits.
The CIA and their relationship
with Hmong,
in part because there are
to this day
insurgents deep in the jungle,
is a sensitive subject
with the Lao government.
Where did the American
doctors come from?
Uh...
So, actually, it's...
I think this is not...
This is not a question, I think.
Okay.
In a Communist, one-party state
like Laos,
it can be dangerous
to talk politics.
You tell me whether we can
talk about this or not,
whether it's
a comfortable subject or not.
But here on one hand,
we have Americans dropping bombs
that blow this,
at the time, child up.
Yeah.
And then there are
American doctors
to put him back together.
Given that, is he angry?
I mean, all of the bombing,
all of the suffering,
all of the death...
What did he think
it was all for?
♪