♪ I took a walk through this ♪
♪ Beautiful world
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good in this ♪
♪ Beautiful world
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
- ♪ La, la
- ♪ Sha la, la, la, la
♪ Sha la, la, la, la
- ♪ Sha la, la, la
- Sha la, la, la, la ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la, la, la
♪
Everything old is new again.
Maybe not.
I come close
sometimes to believing
that nothing actually
ever changes.
♪
Back in the beginning,
fresh out of the kitchen,
when I first went out
in the world
trying to figure out
how to make television,
I came to Northern Portugal.
Little did I know
what I would find.
Up until then,
for 30 years spent
working in kitchens,
meat had come
wrapped in plastic.
I'd order it in boxes.
I had never seen an animal die
because I was making dinner.
Ooh.
♪
Hi.
How are you guys doing?
Oh, man, they can be so cruel.
All right, ciao.
Oh, man. Oof.
I had to call the crisis center.
♪
Portugal, sandwiched between
Spain and the Atlantic Ocean,
and tiny as countries go,
has had an outsized impact
on the world.
During the Age of Discovery,
the Portuguese went to sea
in great numbers,
and gained fame as navigators,
ship builders, and explorers.
They conquered
a large part of the world,
their empire stretching
from Brazil,
to Africa, to the East Indies.
The city of Oporto
is a reflection
and a creation of that
relationship with the sea.
A lot has changed
since I was last here.
Or has it?
♪
When I decided to return
to take another look
at this place,
I, of course, reached out
to Jose de Meirelles,
my old boss and
first entre to Portugal.
How you doing, man?
- You look good.
- You good?
- Yeah, nice to see you.
- It's been a long, long time.
Jose is from the area
around Oporto,
and this time,
just like back then,
he said "Come, see
my country, meet my family."
We'll do a pig feast."
16 years later.
I came here in 2001,
one of the first times
I've ever been on television,
and here we are again.
There are only so many beautiful
places left in the world.
Oporto is one of them.
It's gorgeous.
Has it changed too much?
Eh, yes, especially
in the big cities.
Especially Oporto,
it change a lot.
It was never too rich town.
Now it's packed with tourists.
So that's... is that
good news or bad news?
- Yeah, it's good news.
- Good news.
I mean, it's good
for the economy,
and especially it came up
during the big financial
crisis and all that.
So it was a great job
for the city.
I mean, it looks even prettier
than it looked last time.
They seem to have fixed up
a lot of buildings.
So what are we eating here?
It's the specialty?
Oh, actually we're gonna
start with [indistinct].
That's small sardines.
♪
You eat everything. The bones.
You eat the whole thing.
You can eat a thousand of them,
and the plate is empty
so that's a good thing.
Nobody can tell you
how many you eat.
You ready for the tripes?
- Yes.
- Absolutely, let's go.
- Tripeiros, right?
- Tripas.
We are known as the tripas,
that's tripe people.
Why?
Right.
The people from Oporto gave
them all the meat they had.
- So they...
- All they're left with...
Just with the tripes.
It's cheap food for the sailors.
It would last a long time.
And it usually is on Thursday.
That's the day with the tripes,
because being
a Catholic country,
on Friday, they skip the meat.
♪
A meal here is, generally
speaking anyway, not light.
The Portuguese like pork.
They like it a lot.
So sausage, bacon.
- Sausage, pig's ear.
- Cured pig's ear.
What do you do
when left with nothing
but guts and hooves
and odd bits?
You have the tripes here,
some beans.
Figure out how to transform that
into delicious,
delicious things, of course.
♪
Oh, wow, look at that.
Oh, that's fantastic.
- It smells delicious.
- Perfect. Yes, it does.
So I put a little rice on
the side there to mop it up?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
♪
Mmm.
That is good.
♪
Mmm.
I mean, it's sort of incredible
the story of the wines here.
I hear that because the soil
is so tough with flint
and stones also,
the vines have to dig
up to 30 meters down.
But it's a lot.
I think it gives the wine
a special character.
♪
Northern Portugal's Douro Valley
is where Port comes from.
♪
If it's not from here,
it's not Port.
It's just fortified wine.
♪
I don't usually do wine scenes.
No matter how good the wine,
on camera
it's just colored liquid
going into a glass.
Wine nerds usually bore me.
Don't talk about
your damn wine, drink it.
♪
But I absolutely love
cheese served
with a glass of Port wine,
and that's what most people,
including my new friend Andre,
that's what they do around here.
I'm not a dessert guy,
but a nice blue cheese
with a glass of port,
for me, is, like,
the perfect thing
to end a meal with.
Unlike wine,
cheese porn is easy.
Just like shooting actual porn.
Start with an establishing
shot, move in for a close...
Oh, yeah, there we go.
...cut away to a reaction.
Mmm.
Money.
Works every time.
Oh, that's disturbing.
I mean, it's delicious.
What kind of cheeses
are we looking at here?
These two over here,
they're goat cheese.
They're aged ones.
Then all the other
are sheep milk.
This is worldly known
Queijo Serra,
so the buttery one.
This is what we call
a Queijo Azeitao.
It's strong,
intense to your palate.
Oh, I like this guy already.
Any cheese that are, like,
you need a spoon pretty much.
Oh, then smell it.
For me, the worse the smell,
the better the flavor.
- Mmm.
- Huh? Like it?
Smells like dirty feet.
Tastes like heaven.
This is a 30-year-old Port.
♪
- Oh, that's delicious.
- Yeah.
Put a little bit of that
and then some pumpkin jam
on top.
Mmm. If I put on my Speedo
and dive into this thing,
please stop me before
I completely face plant.
Oh, no, no, no.
I love Portuguese gastronomy.
The heart and soul of it,
its simplicity.
Look, that's the thing
that makes me fall in love
with it every single day.
Cheese is one of those things,
it's always magic to me
because it goes
into the cave one way
and then you go in
and you pull it out,
and, I don't believe in God,
but somehow
it went in like that,
and it came back like this.
Relying on time to cut his way
through it and to change this.
Change the texture,
even the smell,
and we have nothing to do with
that other than enjoying it.
♪
Portugal has got
a lot of coastline
and a lot of history
with the sea.
It's a close relationship,
one that's imprinted deep
within the national character.
The songs.
The poetry.
The state of mind.
I love this word, saudade.
♪
Saudade means missing
something. Nostalgic.
♪
A word with no direct
translation to English.
It connotes longing,
being away from something,
and yearning to get back.
The Portuguese went out
of the country
for years at sea,
and he does not know
when he's gonna get back
to his family.
♪
During the cold gray months,
it's lamprey season.
Oh, hell yeah.
So I'm here
at just the right time.
What do you call
this dish in Portuguese?
This is the lamprey eel?
Yeah, the lamprey bordelaise.
Awesome.
Lamprey are butt ugly
damn creatures,
but delicious when cooked right,
and my man Pedro
knows how to cook it right.
Very traditional.
Cooked in its own blood.
Yeah, it's bordelaise style.
When it's bordelaise,
it means it has the blood.
Mmm, it's good.
Fantastic.
Saudad is going back to a moment
where you're happy.
It doesn't matter
if it was through food,
through sex, through wherever.
You're making me sad
already thinking about this.
No, but that's not sad.
- I'm getting depressed.
- Come on.
Yes, thinking about happy times
that I can't have right now.
But there's a hope in the future
that that's going to happen
because that's also part of...
- Yeah, no.
- Yeah, I see it like that.
If you don't see it,
that's your problem.
The Portuguese were
the original navigators.
Yeah.
It was about the sea.
About fishing, exploration.
Ah, question.
I went to the fish market.
I met these women
who sell fish there,
and they were saying terrible,
terrible things to me.
They were saying, "Hey,
pin dick, get over... you know",
how do you satisfy your wife
with that tiny little penis?"
My God, I've never
in my life heard women,
anybody speak like this.
This is what I'm gonna get?
Yeah, nasty approaches
about your penis
and your height, yeah.
♪
I'm Tony, hi.
- I'm Sophia.
- Sophia.
I'm Shanna.
Nice to meet you.
- Hi. Good to meet you both.
- How are you?
Those of you who know me
even a little bit
are familiar
with my unholy attraction
to the mutant hot dog.
Is it actually called
a hot dog here or is it...
- No, here we call it cachorro.
- Cachorro.
Toasted bread.
Fresh sausage.
Fresh pork sausage.
And a cheese and a spicy sauce.
And spicy sauce.
♪
And cut in a very specific way.
Wow, look at...
Fast knife work.
Nah.
He's asking if you want
some fork and knife.
No, we can eat it with the...
No, we don't do that, right?
♪
Mmm. This is delicious.
This is very healthy too.
Yeah, it's a light dinner.
Yeah, I'm not so sure
about that.
No, no, no, yeah, it is.
- They're busy.
- Yeah, they're always busy.
- Yeah, always busy.
- It's a small place.
And you can see it's just
Portuguese, just locals.
How many places
like this in town?
Nowadays, not many.
- Now, you guys own a tavern?
- Yes.
How's employment
in Portugal now?
There's a lot
of unemployment here.
No, I was gonna ask,
do you get a lot
of people with degrees,
you know, higher degrees
who are opening restaurants?
Yes. She has the degree
in psychology.
I have the degree in sociology.
And everyone who is working
with us they have the degree.
- Yeah, or they are finishing.
- Or they are finishing.
I might have to have another.
That was good.
♪
This city seems to have
been preserved carefully
and with respect for the past.
I don't see a lot
of high rise buildings
breaking up the skyline.
We are still very authentic.
We don't sell out very easily.
I mean, I was
in a relatively poor
neighborhood
a couple of nights ago
just walking around,
and somebody said,
"You know, you could buy
that apartment building
right there for $50,000."
I said, "Okay, good deal."
"But you can't touch
the exterior."
Yeah, no.
This is the fishing
and port area of Oporto, yes?
And it's called Matosinhos.
The fishing boats just arrived,
and the market is just
two streets away from here.
♪
- Okay.
- Oh, my God.
Seafood tower, bitches.
All right then.
Okay, not a tower precisely,
but a whole heap of incredible
creatures from the sea.
♪
Coastal shrimp.
Local oysters
and crab.
Sea urchin.
Langoustine.
Gooseneck barnacles.
This I'm very excited by.
- Yeah.
- So dangerous to get these.
Yeah, it's not
the thing that you get
from the hulls of the boats,
but from rocks.
And you've got to get it
in between waves.
- Mm-hmm.
- Quickly. Whelks?
- Caramujos.
Oh, there we go.
Mmm. Insane.
One thing that I don't like
with food is sauce.
Yeah, I don't need it.
This is all perfect.
What do they do to it?
They steamed it, some of it.
- Yeah.
- The rest is raw.
It's not like this
is fancy cooking.
♪
Mmm.
This crab is...
It's like a Rubik's cube.
I'm trying to figure
my way into here.
Okay, I found it.
♪
This is the thing that
gets you back to your roots.
You have to use your hands.
You don't have to be polite.
Yeah.
♪
Mmm, these little shrimp.
The brains are really good too.
♪
Oh, look at that.
Sea urchin, fat sacks of roe
buried deep inside
these prickly exteriors.
When I was a kid, I went
with my father to get these,
and it was nasty,
but also very good.
Mmm.
It's funny, a lot of things
that you see here
were used as fertilizer.
In the years before
independence in Massachusetts,
Lobster was seen as a pest.
The only people
who used them regularly
was the prison system.
The prisoners rioted because
they said this is cruel
and unusual punishment having
to eat lobster every day.
"No, I don't want that.
It's lobster."
♪
Nobody knows who first
salt-baked a fish.
Maybe it was Jesus.
- Ohhh.
- Oh, wow.
Scale and gut your fish,
in this case a sea bass,
insert lemon and onion,
then pack it in salt and bake.
♪
Light the whole thing
on fire tableside,
then break open.
The salt acts like
a protective crust,
sealing in all
the moisture and flavor.
Now, that looks beautiful.
That's perfect food.
Mmm.
Clams cooked Portuguese style.
- Yeah.
- So tender and sweet
and delicious.
Why do you think Portuguese food
has not had a higher profile
internationally?
Well, for me it's
real easy to say this,
it's basically...
It's your fault.
- Our fault?
- It's the Americans' fault.
Yeah.
Why?
The American culture
embraced Spain.
It embraced Italy.
It embraced France.
It didn't embrace Portugal
because... I don't know.
If we have a civil war
so popular like the Spanish had,
and Hemmingway came
to Portugal instead of Spain,
we would be a different country.
You know, you think of Italy,
you think of romance.
- No, but we are romantic.
- I know. These people...
We are the most romantic
country in the world.
After you have a couple
of meals in Porto,
you're going to feel saudade
in your heart and soul.
Man, good meal.
Oh, what, there's more clams?
Right over here, my friend.
♪
Contrary to what some might say,
I do not enjoy seeing
the death of any living thing.
I do not promote animal cruelty.
♪
- Yeah, ready to go?
- Yep.
Kill the pig, kill the pig,
kill the pig.
But I think people should
know where meat comes from,
and knowing, they should
feel free to decide
what they want to do from there.
- It's the least you could do.
- Yeah, exactly, so...
Here, right here
on Jose's family farm,
is where I saw
my first animal die.
A pig too.
This, after years and decades
of being a chef, serving meat,
ordering up my death
over the phone
at a comfortable distance.
Up close, it was not
so comfortable.
I think he's starting
to get the bad news.
I guess on the DNA, they know
that's gonna happen and...
They know it's coming.
- Really they know it's coming.
- Yeah, well the pigs are smart.
And sometimes
they manage to run away.
To do the job right,
professionals are brought in,
and they do it
like this because,
how shall I put it,
they need the heart
to keep pumping the blood
into the pail
for sausage and soup,
and many delicious things.
We all come to this in the end,
whether struggling for air
in our beds,
bleeding out on cold concrete,
a last mighty dump like Elvis,
or this.
Oh, yeah, it's a firecracker.
That's the start of
any festivities in Portugal,
is the firecracker.
Really?
As befitting tradition
and the way things are done,
this is a once in a year event.
For two days, extended family,
friends and neighbors
gather to cook,
cure and eat a pig.
Time for a haircut?
Yeah, haircut.
- Old-school.
- Yeah.
♪
They finish up
with the blowtorch.
- As one must.
- Yeah.
It's like rappers.
Yeah, yeah,
that's it, that's it.
Free style.
Up.
Up. There you go.
So now they gonna finish up
and take all the guts out...
Take all the guts out,
and that is lunch.
Lunch time.
In Portugal, we used to say
that if we want
to know our body,
you have to kill a pig because
it's absolutely the same.
All the organs are placed
on the same disposition.
I see a liver there
and the heart,
and you have
the tongue there too.
That's all in a package,
all the good stuff.
Look, it's a lung.
♪
He's good.
Yeah, he really knows
what he's doing.
I would say a surgeon,
but he's faster than a surgeon.
♪
Guts removed, the liver
and heart are used today.
Cooked immediately.
Oh, this is the best, the heart.
- It's like a tender sirloin.
- Oh, it's so good.
It's so good, yeah.
The intestines washed
and reserved for sausage casing.
Mmm. Looks nice.
The rest is left to hang
until tomorrow,
when we shall feast again.
- Ah, it's like chicharron.
- Chicharron.
Oh, wow.
Yeah, yeah.
Oh.
That's kind of perfect.
Mmm.
That's good.
Not all of the countries
eat all of the meat
off of the pork.
And here, we eat everything.
- They don't waste anything.
- Anything.
♪
Fado, the national music
of Portugal.
Songs of longing, heartbreak,
saudade set to music.
♪
Anthony, in Portugal
everybody thinks
that they sing Fado.
We, the Portuguese,
think that the Fado
is not the perfection,
the ability, the fine-tuning.
It's emotion, so everybody's
allowed to sing.
Yeah.
That's why Jose is
telling that I sing Fado.
I see.
Normally the guys who sing
Fado are very happy guys.
They are very...
But when they begin to sing,
they turn into sad guys.
I don't know why.
Well, you said
the Portuguese are bipolar.
Yes, yes they are.
They are.
So ready to eat, I see, huh?
Big enough table?
The home of Jose's
ancestors for centuries.
Much of their original estate
still in family hands.
Very exciting.
Jose's mother Maria
is in charge today.
She's preparing a feast of
rustic Portuguese soul food.
They boil the bones out,
then they finish with the
blood, so... blood and bread.
- Blood and bread.
- Yeah.
Mmm.
Beautiful.
♪
It's so good.
The main event, cozido,
a glorious stew of seemingly
every last part of the pig.
I'm gonna give you
some of the pernil,
that is the smoked meat.
Spare ribs.
Nothing goes to waste
around here.
The blood sausage.
Cabbage.
- Oh, what's that?
- That's the butelo.
It's the pig's bladder
that's stuffed with pork belly,
the spare ribs, and then smoked.
Wow, look at that.
♪
Extraordinary.
And one little thing,
you don't feel that guilty
when you eating this
because it's only just boiled.
Not fried. Not...
Oh, I don't feel guilty.
Oh, it's fantastic.
Oh, it's superb.
Wonderful.
Thank you.
♪
So, Jose,
what's left of the pig?
A couple of hams
and not much else.
Well, the everything
is on salt right now.
So the shoulders
and the legs are in salt?
They're on salt.
They're gonna be in salt
for about three months,
and then they're going
to be smoked
and they are a prosciutto.
And they are fantastic.
So you spoke about
Fado and sadness,
but, you know,
after a few drinks,
everybody gets very happy,
you know?
Good.
Means, "With wine, happiness."
- Yeah!
- Cheers.
- Yeah.
- Happiness, happiness.
Thank you.
♪
Cheers.
Now it's time
for the francesinha,
which translates
as little French girl?
Yeah, yeah.
But I understand
she's not so little.
- No, it's not.
- No.
It's your first time,
francesinha?
- It is.
- Really?
You have this look
on your face like...
You look worried.
- Good luck.
- It's gonna be okay, right?
Oh, here we go.
- Oh, thank you.
- What do we got?
Good Lord, look at that thing.
Is there a vegetable in there?
- Only meat.
- Oh, my God.
It weighs, like, a ton.
♪
So it's bread, ham...
Mm-hmm.
Steak...
Sausage, and a bit of...
- Linguica.
- Yeah, linguica.
♪
And then the sauce
has many things like beer,
Port wine, spicy, tomato.
- Cheese.
- A lot of cheese. A lot.
Wow.
What a construction.
Meat, cheese, fat and bread?
It's the immortal combination.
Yeah, it's the ultimate solution
for a hangover or too much pork.
♪
That is delicious.
Oh, that's good.
It's really, really good.
Are there a lot
of places making this?
- Mmm.
- A lot.
- Yeah.
- Everyone does.
And this is a Oporto
thing specifically?
- Yes.
- Yeah.
What's the relative rate
per capita of heart-related
disease in this country?
I'm just curious.
It depends on how many
francesinha you had.
Oh, right.
♪
Oh-oh, oh-oh.
How are you doing?
No, I don't know. Today?
You guys need any fish?
Thank you.
♪
Everything old is new again,
maybe not.
I come close sometimes
to believing
that nothing
actually ever changes,
that we are trapped
in our destiny,
hurtling or limping
or being dragged
towards the inevitable.
That saudade refers
not to a long-lost place,
but a long-lost time
when we were all
young and innocent.
Saudade can help
you value things.
Be grateful for just a sunset.
Enjoy that. Smile.
- Enjoy it now.
- Yes.
Because tomorrow we die.
Yeah, you never know.
♪