♪ I took a walk
through this ♪
♪ Beautiful world
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good
in this ♪
♪ Beautiful world
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
- ♪ La, la
- ♪ Sha la, la, la, la
♪ Sha la, la, la, la
- ♪ Sha la, la, la
- Sha la, la, la, la ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la, la, la
♪
I've been here before,
this coastline,
this city.
I was looking
for something then,
but instead I found this.
♪
Uruguay,
the tiny, underappreciated
South American country
tucked between
Argentina and Brazil.
Only 3 million people live here,
half of them in the
capital city of Montevideo.
I love this city.
I love this country.
I mean, there's a vibe here
that just...
It's unlike any other
place on the continent.
It's the opposite of New York
in a lot of ways.
Like, people aren't
pushy here, you know?
In New York,
everybody's, like, sort of
hungry and pushing and moving.
Here it's extremely laid back.
The only competition is soccer.
Well-
- That's the only time
that you get competitive,
and it gets extreme.
Ignacio Mattos is the chef/owner
of three very successful
restaurants in New York City,
Estela,
Cafe Altro Paradiso,
and Flora Bar.
He's been a New Yorker
for the past 12 years,
but he comes from here.
Uruguay is a pretty chill
and relaxed place
where you just can
disconnect from everything.
For me, it's a melting pot.
It's mostly Spanish
and Italian immigrant food.
Bar Arocena in Montevideo's
Carrasco neighborhood
specializes
in Uruguay's unofficial
national sandwich,
the legendary Chivito,
24 hours a day,
seven days a week, since 1923.
A prince, a king,
a Gargantua among sandwiches,
this terror-inspiring
heap of protein
is built out of
steak, ham, bacon, cheese,
hard-boiled egg,
mayo, and garnishes.
That's, like,
a perfect sandwich.
Now, last time I was here,
I have to admit that
after about six days
I would've killed somebody
for a vegetable.
I mean, I didn't see a single...
You're gonna feel
like that very soon.
♪
"Nacho," as he's called
by nearly everyone,
started his career
at the age of 17
with a master of fire
and burning wood,
Argentinean chef
Francis Mallmann,
and stayed with him for ten
years before moving to the U.S.
Working for Francis Mallmann,
I felt at home.
They were just a bunch
of outsiders
that they found a place
where they belonged,
you know, finding this new
culture and, like, new flavors.
♪
- How often do you come?
- Every two years.
And how long do you spend here?
I usually spend a week.
- Why so little?
- We live in New York.
You know what I'm talking about.
- Yeah, I do.
- I mean, I love it here,
but it's... you know,
you have to commit to it here.
But, you know,
you were born here.
You spent your childhood here.
Do you feel the way I feel
about this place?
It... it is special, right?
I-I think it's special.
But I'm so far
detached from it...
Right.
...but I can go back to that,
and I can just connect.
Well, we'll see.
Over the next few days,
we'll see if you can
just slide right back in.
Oh, we will.
There's no other way out.
There's no way around it.
You have to.
♪
Things to know about Uruguay.
It's progressive.
Weed is legal.
Abortions are easily accessible.
Gay marriage,
universal healthcare,
free education
including college,
and democracy is no joke here.
96% of eligible Uruguayans
voted in the last election.
Compare that to barely 60%
here in the U.S.
There's something really
special about this place.
You like it?
It's really one of
my favorite countries.
It's really...
Amazing.
Many Uruguayans could say that
it is the worst place of the...
Well, a lot of it...
That's weird.
Some of the Uruguayans
I've spoken to
are very ambivalent...
Yeah.
- About your country.
- "I like it, but you know..."
And this I don't
really understand.
I meet Carina Novarese,
a journalist and editor
with the newspaper
"El Observador"
at Escaramuza
Cafe and Bookstore.
I think this thing
that Uruguayan has
that is kind of pessimistic
and is always...
Sometimes complains too much
about what we have
comes from before.
1930s, '40s, and
after the Second World War,
this was one of the Americas
as they used to call us.
There are few reminders of
colonial days in Montevideo,
but plenty of evidence
that this is the chief city
of a dynamic
and progressive country.
It was a pretty cool society.
Healthcare was free,
cradle-to-grave.
Uh, education free.
Also a very big medium class.
That is very important
for Uruguay.
- Right.
- That began to change
after the '60s and '70s.
One could say that
the prospect of
socialist, or God forbid,
communist movements
in Latin America in the '60s
was an area
of great concern for the U.S.
and its more
authoritarian-leaning
allies in the region.
So the emergence of the radical
National Liberation Movement,
known as the Tupamaros, was
cause for alarm at the CIA.
A lot of things happened
in the '60s
in the context of Latin America.
A lot of students, young people,
were very active in politics.
There weren't the low classes,
as you could say.
They weren't the poor people
who were doing this.
These are middle-class kids
and highly radicalized.
Yeah.
At the beginning, I think,
they really thought
they could change the system.
With covert and overt
support by our country,
a state of emergency
was declared,
and a right-wing dictatorship
grabbed hold of
the instruments of power
launching a period of
repression that
lasted from 1973 until 1985.
Supported and often
guided by CIA officers
trained in
what we call these days
"enhanced
interrogation methods,"
some of the most brutal bastards
in the ugliest
military juntas on Earth
crushed minds and bodies
in cells across Latin America.
What kind of people were
finding themselves swept up?
- Especially teachers.
- Teachers?
- Professors from university.
- Troublesome intellectuals.
Sometimes lawyers or...
Something like 3% to 5%
of the entire population,
uh, had gone through
the prison system.
I mean, we're not talking
about incarceration.
We're talking about...
No, no, no, no.
They were tortured and then
kept inside a prison system
that was specifically designed
to pretty much destroy them.
In the mid 1980s, the people
of Uruguay had had enough.
Massive demonstrations
and strikes finally
forced the government
to hold elections,
and the military
was swept from power.
We're now a democratic country
since 1984.
- And how's it going?
- I think it's going well.
We have troubles.
We are in Latin America.
We'd like to believe that
we are a European country.
We are not.
- But are you optimistic?
- I am.
I am.
I don't see, like,
a huge crisis coming.
But also when they came,
you never realized before too.
♪
When people think of this
often overlooked little country,
if they think of it at all,
they tend to think of it
patronizingly as
Argentina's little brother.
Not so.
And that attitude
pushes people here
to think of themselves
in many ways
as existentially in opposition
to their
bigger, louder neighbor.
Where were you born?
Are you from Montevideo?
No, no, I'm from Argentina.
Is it a big difference
culturally,
Argentina and Uruguay?
Here, if you're
a little bit courageous,
then you made it, you know?
It's a scene here.
Like, to be flashy,
it... it's a scene.
To be successful, it's not
something that is one scene.
You got to do it quietly.
There's a saying,
"[speaking Spanish]."
It means "Stay in
the small thing," you know?
Right..
It's something that defines...
Right.
Uruguay in a way.
Lucia Soria is the
chef and owner of Jacinto
in Montevideo's old city.
She worked with Nacho
back in the Mallmann years.
What was it like for a woman
working in the restaurant
industry in the early 2000s?
I was very lucky
because Francis, he had, like,
this army of women... no?
Around him.
You were surrounded by women
from the beginning?
Yes. Yes.
Is that an unusual situation
in Uruguay do you think?
- I mean...
- I'm not asking you, man.
You're... you're a man.
I'm asking...
Oh, I sound like a woman.
The food here takes its cues
from Spain and Italy.
Homemade gnocchi
with mushrooms and pumpkin.
Prawns with avocado,
apple, and wasabi.
Beef tartare with quail egg.
So when you were first
planning the menu for this place
and thinking about the
concept...
- Yeah.
- What inspired you?
I wanted to have, like,
a small restaurant,
but that you could have
a very nice everything,
but small, you know?
You want fish?
Very nice and a little
vegetables, you know?
Right.
This is the most vegetables
I've ever seen in this country
all in one time.
We're all driven people
at this table.
Yeah.
You know, you went
all the way to New York.
You have how many restaurants
in New York now?
Just the one? Two?
Three.
- Three.
- Nice number, man.
- You're not lazy.
- No.
- It's just a little dump.
You could have seven.
I'm gonna guess
you're like this too.
We're all driven people,
so where is your happy place?
Well, I got married
on Saturday, and...
- This past Saturday?
- Yes.
That was the day that
I felt happy all day.
But it's good because you cannot
have happiness all the time, no?
Happiness is a thing that...
No, no.
Happiness all the time
is fascism.
- No. It doesn't exist, man.
- It's oppressive.
It's oppressive.
You're not doing anything.
But if you have
a few moments a week,
will you just go,
"Oh, shit. I'm happy"?
- Yeah.
- It sneaks up on you.
♪
Which is more satisfying,
eating a good meal...
Yeah.
Or cooking a good meal
for somebody
you really care about?
I think eating.
I... I actually enjoy both,
but I don't want
to hear anything.
I don't want you to talk to me.
I just want to see
your expression, like,
seeing you're connecting
without having to
have a dialogue about it.
I'm not sure.
Cooking for customers,
that's a different experience.
Making an omelet for someone...
Mm.
The morning after.
Just stay in.
Yeah.
It's really the best.
The guy that I marry,
I was with him
for the first time.
And I cooked three eggs,
two asparagus,
and five cherry tomatoes
with my heart.
And we had this small
but very beautiful
breakfast, brunch, lunch.
It's the best thing ever.
You're gonna make me cry.
- You know?
- You're gonna make me cry.
There's some basic urge
that made
all of us at this table
want to cook.
- Yeah.
- There is a desire to
say something you can't say,
to nurture.
So basic, and it's so
beautiful that it's so basic.
♪
Hablan por la Espalda
got together in 1996
when they were all
just teenagers.
They were considered pioneers
of the DIY
hardcore movement here.
Two decades on,
they're still one of
the country's
most popular bands.
And they recently opened
for Iggy Pop.
♪
Right, so what does everybody
do here? What do you do?
- I'm psychologist.
- You're a psychologist?
This will come in useful later.
Musician and a...
I'm a writer too.
- Writer and, uh, restaurateur.
- Yeah.
I work in post production.
- Post production?
- Yeah.
That could be... actually this
is a very useful table.
Fermin, the lead
singer and songwriter,
grew up with Nacho.
Tuca and Valentin play guitar.
What do people like
to listen to in Uruguay?
It's a very musical country,
I think.
You know Candombe?
Yeah.
Okay, that's our, like,
our native rhythm.
And the folklore from here,
it used to be called...
"protest music..."
Protest music.
So it was, like,
late '60s, early '70s,
was the most popular music.
But then came the dictatorship.
Right, so no more of that.
And everybody
had to leave the country.
Yeah, dictatorships are usually,
like, usually bad for music.
Yeah.
They're good for
the underground music scene,
but not so good for the...
Not for the popular music.
Do you want to smoke?
Yeah, sure.
- I brought some.
- Excellent. Good idea.
I... I am permitted
to smoke weed on camera now.
- Yeah. You are in Uruguay.
- I am observing local custom.
♪
Proceed to smoke weed.
It's cool.
Everybody's doing it.
Somebody call
the elfin Jeff Sessions.
He'll shit himself.
How long
has weed been legal here?
- One year.
- A year?
- One year, yeah.
- A year? Awesome.
But here, like, you could
smoke in the street...
- Always.
- For always.
Do you have dispensaries?
Do you have stores
that you can go through?
Yes, that's the problem
here now.
The pharmacies cannot sell
because the...
- The international banks...
- Right.
Don't want to accept drug money.
So if I were to open
a marijuana hydroponic farm...
You can have your club.
All right, when...
When we starting this?
I don't know, man.
Let me smoke another joint.
There, you got it.
♪
What to do next?
Pizza and beers, yo,
at Bar Las Flores.
So, uh, here's
an interesting question.
What is the national
pathology of Uruguay?
- It is the envy from...
- Envy?
Yes, Uruguayan very envy.
You always envy, like...
I cannot envy a very
big guitarist, guitar player.
I cannot envy Paco de Lucia.
I will envy
this kind of guitarist
that plays almost like me,
just a little better.
- Just a little better.
Yeah.
The envy is between brothers.
Right.
Is this a destructive envy?
Do Uruguayans want
other Uruguayans to succeed?
- As long as they're far enough.
- Yeah.
Not my neighbor.
Not in my neighborhood.
This is an honest man.
I really like you.
I love this Uruguayan.
He's in Mexico. He's great.
I feel like
I'm talking to myself.
♪
The pizza here is
a bizarro stoner hybrid
topped with
thin chickpea flatbread.
Why?
I don't know.
Makes sense though.
The one on top of there
is a fainá.
You should put fainá
on top of the pizza.
Really?
♪
We call this pizza
no cheese now.
- Yeah.
- He's a vegan, so he's...
Really?
I don't know
if I can work with you.
22 years, I'm vegan.
- Vegan?
- Yes, in Uruguay.
Wow, that is
a revolutionary position.
They used to be vegan too.
- Yeah.
- You are such an asshole.
He used to be
very vegan militant.
So what did you eat?
- Pizza.
- Yeah, but no cheese?
- Yeah.
And this is on health grounds,
or you hate to herd animals?
I don't know.
Okay, if you had to kill
Fred Durst or a cow?
- Oh...
- Or a cow.
Fred. Fred.
Look, this one.
Iggy Pop or a cow?
I like Iggy Pop,
but I will have to kill him.
- No?
- No!
No.
Oh, no.
- I just saw him live.
- You're a monster.
You are not my therapist.
♪
All right, meat.
I want meat.
And this is the place.
You want meat?
Yes.
Yes, I do.
This must be the place.
His friends say
Marcello Quiben looks German,
hence the name of his
small neighborhood restaurant
"Parisa el Aleman."
The beating heart of the place
is, of course, the Parisa,
a grill where
dripping meats of many kinds
are slowly cooked
over glowing wood coals.
Why is this an Uruguayan thing? Why here?
I mean, I know
you're a cattle country.
I think the first settlers,
when they came in,
they realized there was nothing
else but raising cattle.
- Right.
- And they let it grow wild.
- Uh-huh.
- And they over-populated.
And, you know, gauchos,
they would roam the land,
and they would kill it on
the spot and actually cook it...
- Right there.
- ...right there on the spot.
And actually, like, a lot of
times with the skin on.
Really?
Morcilla, or blood sausage.
Oh, now this is what
it's all about for me now.
Every great culture does this.
It's moist.
I love it.
Right when you kill it,
it's pretty amazing.
Look, when they kill me,
that's the way I want to go.
You know,
keep the heart beating,
pump the blood into the bucket,
let the village women
come and make sausage.
Then chorizo.
Then steak... gotta have that.
In this case, rib eye.
You should spend more time
in this country.
I don't know.
I've been gone for 17, 18 years.
Yeah.
It feels kind of like the same.
That's the magic
about this place.
It's like, it feels like
traveling into the past.
I don't see Starbucks
on every corner.
I don't see McDonald's.
It's sort of unspoiled, right?
This is pretty awesome.
I mean, am I missing something?
Is there something that
really sucks about this country
that I don't... I've not seen?
I think this... it's a society
that's, like, very patriarchal.
Ah.
And it has a lot of colonial
tradition that overshadows...
Yeah, but compared to what?
Compared to who?
Who's doing really great
in that department?
Denmark?
It's, like, the happiest
country on Earth.
I hate happy.
I mean, you want to be
surrounded by happy people?
Do you notice how melancholic
this place is and nostalgic?
It's like
you walk on the street,
and you just, like, feel it.
Yeah.
It's, like,
the melancholy, it's...
I like that.
♪
Nacho Mattos grew up
about 45 minutes
north of the capital
in Santa Lucia,
a small town of 16,000 people
surrounded by farmland
and cattle and sheep ranches.
I think as a child, it was
an incredible place to grow up.
You know, I like escaping and
going fishing on the river,
and that's pretty safe,
you know?
Like, the doors
were always open.
But I didn't feel like
I fit in at all.
And I needed to find a place
and a way to express myself.
We were raised as very liberal,
but at the same time,
it's conservative.
As a teenager, it was kind of
like everything the same.
It's just, you didn't
feel that interesting.
And yeah,
it wasn't fun as a teenager.
♪
His family own a dairy farm
just outside of town.
Nacho's mother, Gloria,
runs the farm
along with his brother, Leandro.
Nacho's sister, Rocio,
lives in Montevideo
but comes home often
for family meals like this.
What's the name of this town?
You grew up here? This house?
- Santa Lucia. Yeah.
- You grew up in this house?
Yes.
For the most part, yeah.
It's beautiful. Why
would you ever leave this place?
It's fantastic.
He never liked this place.
- No?
- No, never.
I felt like he had, like,
anger of being
on such a small town.
He always had, like,
been on the front.
I couldn't fit in here,
so I get out of the house,
and I actually call her
and say that I wanted
to go to culinary school.
"This is what I want to do.
I need support,
and I pay you back."
And one year goes, and
I drop it to work for Francis.
I... I love that you went
from being a vegan to
working with Francis Mallmann...
Yeah, yeah.
...who's, like, you know,
the Satan of vegans.
What was at the dinner table
when you grew up?
Mom wasn't that... it wasn't
that skillful in the kitchen.
- Oh, that's cold, man.
- I know, but it is true.
She was the one in charge.
So you grew up eating
a lot of Italian food?
Yes.
Nacho's grandmother,
Ercilia, was born here,
the child of Italian immigrants.
I grew up around my grandmother,
like, constantly cooking.
And that was her form
of affection
and a way of, like,
showing that she cared
and she love you.
♪
Her tucco, her version
of Sunday gravy,
is made from porchetta,
cured pork ribs,
and hunks of beef
simmered for hours.
There's also matambre,
a local specialty
of rolled stuffed beef
served alongside Russian salad.
So when did you start cooking?
I think... I think it was,
like, my mom get divorced,
and I realized
that she needed help,
and I start cooking
as a way of support.
- Mm-hmm.
- Then I decide to become vegan,
and she was like...
She threw the towel.
And I was like... and
and she stopped cooking for us.
So I start taking the
initiative, and I start cooking.
Well, you had to because
you were the only vegan
in all of Uruguay.
♪
How often does he come back?
- Two years?
- It's been two years?
- Mm-hmm.
- I like it. I like it.
I like it in a different way.
I like it far away.
If he would find
the thing to do here,
like, he would be happy,
but the things he wants to do
are not here.
♪
Si?
Yeah, it's good.
- It's so comforting.
- Yeah.
This makes me happy.
♪
Fishing from kayaks
is... is amazing.
First of all,
it's easy, really easy.
You don't need
any motor or nothing.
It's just bring the kayak
to the shore
and paddle in.
♪
A couple of hours east
of Montevideo, the coast,
and the seaside towns
of high-gloss,
big money, Punta del Este,
and the slightly more
laid back Jose Ignacio,
once a sleepy fishing village,
and now a Hamptonian
vacation hotspot
for the money class
from all over the world.
♪
Cantina del Vigia, thankfully,
is open in the off season.
Diego Robino is a film producer
and occasional fisherman,
and Clo Dimet
is a chef and owner of
a posada in Jose Ignacio.
So what town is this?
Where am I?
- This is Maldonado.
- Maldonado.
And this is, like, the capital
of all these fancy beach towns,
but this is where
the working class people live.
It's the city where
most people live all the year.
Cantina's chef/owner
is Federico Desseno.
Like Nacho, another
Francis Mallmann veteran.
Diego brought some fish
he caught today.
We got empanadas with corn
and shredded slow-cooked beef.
Ooh, nice.
Love it.
Oh, I'm liking
this meal already.
There's goat cheese
and spinach croquettes.
- Mmm.
- Nice.
- Look at the catch.
- Oh, look at that.
- This is the catch of the day.
- Beautiful.
♪
So today Diego went
on one of the roughest day
in the ocean
to get fish somehow.
We're talking about,
like, hard work.
I mean, the kitchen is hard,
but like, fishermen...
No, the fact that you are
alone in the middle of the ocean
with all this
destruction around you...
That's why we play soccer.
There are
two wood-fired ovens producing
this thing, provoleta,
a beautiful slab of cheese
which puffs up and
inflates in the heat.
Wow.
Whoa, and this is the cheese?
The history...
This is the cheese.
Normally if you're doing
a grill with friends,
this is the only thing
you will get that is not meat.
Whole-roasted suckling
wild boar.
♪
Wow, that's spectacular.
And whole-roasted fish.
♪
- Whoa.
- Fish.
- Wow.
And milanesa.
Here in Uruguay,
not veal as in Italy,
but a pounded, breaded,
and fried hunk of beef
covered in tomato sauce, ham,
and melted mozzarella cheese.
Oh, more cheese.
All right.
Milanesa.
This is milanesa napolitana.
- Right.
- And it's a typical dish.
And the people here
eat a lot of milanesa.
- We grew up with this.
- All the people.
Holy moley.
Yeah, you know this is
good cold, too, right?
First thing in the morning?
Cold?
It's great.
See, you have an instinctive
sense in this country
of what people need.
♪
How much you loving Uruguay?
You still loving it,
or you change your mind?
I love it.
It's beautiful, so laid back.
You haven't changed that...
Your mind a little bit?
No.
Feel tense about anything,
I smoke a little weed.
I feel better.
Yeah?
I'm getting hungry actually.
Yeah, what's
on the menu tonight?
Got some quinoa?
Maybe some quinoa.
I don't think
it exists, quinoa, here.
You might see it
in some health store.
Yeah.
I don't even know what it is.
I don't know that
I've ever had it.
It's like, I used to
really like kale,
I used to love kale, but now I
don't want to eat it because...
You'd become pretty annoying.
They're making, like,
smoothies out of the shit.
Are we doing steak?
If we can do steak,
that's what you eat...
That's... that's what we have.
Yeah.
Yeah, I was thinking
just off the top of my head.
"What do I want tonight?
Uh...
How about meat?
Yeah, yeah, meat."
I know where to go.
I've actually never been.
This friend told me about it.
But the funny thing,
it's a drive-thru.
Drive-thru steak?
I know.
Like, I'm... surprised as you are.
Cocktails? Do we get
cocktails in the drive-thru?
I doubt it, but I'm sure
we can get some beer.
- All right, steak it is.
- Let's do it.
♪
Diego wants you to know that
his other car is a Ferrari.
♪
Hey, what's up, man?
Hey, so far it's working.
I think they use this
in the desert.
Yeah, they're pretty common
here, right, like, on the beach?
Not good for winter.
No.
♪
Las Nenas for drive-thru steak.
A beer or...
- Cerveza.
- Yeah, beer.
Okay, gracias.
♪
Gracias.
Do we have, uh,
knives and forks somewhere?
Inside of each box.
They're there.
Oh, okay.
You need potatoes.
Yeah, I got potatoes in there.
Yeah, this could be a challenge.
Hey, the meat's good.
You should bring your own
cutlery, you know, next time.
Yeah.
♪
La Caracola is a party space
on a strip of sand
about ten minutes
outside of Jose Ignacio.
The ocean on one side,
a lagoon on the other.
During the high season,
it's a regular hangout
for over-the-top asados.
Today Nacho is supervising
a meal for a bunch of friends.
Hey, guys.
What's going on in here?
Hey. How's it going?
- Very good.
- So this is Martin.
- Hey, how are you?
- How are you?
Martin Pittaluga is
the co-owner of La Huella,
a restaurant in town
that also serves
as the mother ship
for this place.
- Right?
- Man, what a spot.
- I mean, you look at this...
- The weather is good?
The weather is difficult,
but it's beautiful.
You'll stay the whole day.
You know, you arrive at 2:00,
and you leave at 9:00.
Nice.
So, jefe, what's cooking?
♪
So it's one of the spots
in the fire oven.
Wow. Look at that,
a whole fish baked in salt?
Yes.
♪
Some whole rib eye slabs.
Rib eyes. Wow.
Some suckling pig.
It's not some snack.
That's no snack, man.
That's a meal right there. Wow.
You want to help
in the kitchen, or...
- The carving, yeah, man.
- All right.
Everybody's here.
Fermin, the guys from the
band, Lucia, Federico, Diego,
and it's time to eat.
Oh, yeah.
Come on, it's perfect, right?
Right.
So how long has
this place been here?
Like, about 12 years.
It started as, like,
a shack or a house or a...
It used to be a little house
on the beach with a bar.
You're not allowed
to build here anymore, so
I bought all this land, and
that's the only thing we can do.
♪
- Man, the food is delicious.
- Yeah.
Look at us out here
on a sandbar, middle of nowhere,
eating like gods.
But this is what
I love about Uruguay, no?
Then you suddenly...
You take a drive,
even, like,
one hour and a half...
And you're someplace different.
And you're in a different world.
Good to see. I mean,
this is really exciting here.
I love it here.
Every day he asks,
"Are you sure?"
Every day. Every day.
Hold on. Hold on.
- Do you really love it, Tony?
- Every day.
- Do you Really? Really?
- Shut up, I asked you once.
He says this...
He says this every day.
Every day.
♪