Some time ago, something
crawled or slithered or grew
like a fungus.
Something that started small,
got bigger, lurched like a swamp
thing out of the mud and moist
earth and humid
nights of the delta.
Then it took over the world.
So next time some smartass
horrified by our ham-fisted
foreign policy wonders what good
is America, well, you can always
pipe up that the blues, rock and
roll, R & B, and soul all
came out of this place.
One state, Mississippi.
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la la
♪
Right now we're in the
middle of downtown Jackson.
Parrish street.
A lot of history.
What did it used to be
like back in the day?
The street was
packed with folks.
Folks all over.
They had their own restaurants,
grocery stores, joints, I mean,
everything happened here that
happened in Jackson for the
African-American community.
The state capital of Jackson,
Mississippi, located along
interstate highway 55, just
outside what's known as
the Mississippi delta.
It's the kind of place that
makes you wonder why did
they make it the capital.
Until you grab hold of what
used to be around here.
Farris street used to be the hub
of African-American
life in this city.
Its black commercial cultural
center, when Dr. King came
to town he came here.
Everybody did.
Medger Evers had a
house upstairs here.
Musicians like Tommy Johnson,
Sonny boy Williamson, too, and
Elmore James all played here and
the likes of Duke Ellington, cab
Callaway, count Basie and Louie
Armstrong took the stage at
places like the crystal palace
ballroom and the Alamo
on Farris street.
What happened?
Where did it all go?
What killed it was immigration.
Once we were able to break out
of our indigenous black owned
businesses, the businesses died.
Great for the black race but
terrible for the black business.
In fact, the only reason you're
coming here right now is you
have two churches, two funeral
homes and the big apple inn.
You will either die, worship or
come to my place to eat.
That's the only... or all three.
Not in that order.
How you doing today?
Back when things were
hopping, Geno Lee's great
grandfather moved to Mississippi
from Mexico City, started a
family with an African-American
woman in Jackson.
He sold hot tamales out of a
steel drum on the corner.
In 1939, he moved the
operation inside, right here.
Now, the last restaurant
on the street.
Lurking inside, waiting for us,
is John T. Edge, who leads the
Southern food ways alliance.
Mr. Edge, how you doing?
Who makes a point, a mission,
out of knowing and teaching as
much as he can about the real
culinary traditions of the
south, and doing what he can to
keep them alive and unmolested.
Look at that.
Awesome.
It's like a cream sandwich.
What you go for here are smokes,
smoked sausage sandwiches and
these magnificent beauties, pig
ear sandwiches called ears, both
pretty much served with the same
garnish of slaw, mustard,
home-made hot sauce on a soft
bun.
As I understand it, originally
this is one of those nobody
wants these things,
they're dirt cheap.
Exactly right.
In fact, by dirt cheap, the ears
were actually free when my great
grandfather started getting the
pig ears, the butcher was giving
them to him because he would
just throw them away.
So everything we love about
pig, the texture, the mix of
fatty and lean, all
that, all that's good.
Mm.
Man.
That is hard to beat.
Isn't it good?
Um-hum.
It's a good sandwich.
Of course, some hot tamales
which at this point in history
are about as Mississippi
as they are Mexican.
Like the blues, they came out of
Mississippi in the early 20th
century as Mexican migrant
workers came in to replace
African-Americans, who were
headed to work in the great
factories and stockyards
of Chicago and Detroit.
Sitting down here, eating
tamales, we can sketch a
history of Mississippi.
That's kind of what I'm most
interested in doing, helping
southerners understand that
their foods are as African as
they are western European.
And hopefully... if not largely,
you know, music and all the
other cultural expressions
of the south.
I think food is a sneaky way of
getting at some of the serious
stuff we've been talking about.
I told you before, I didn't know
what a cool job or what a cool
restaurant I had until
you showed it to me.
I'm just making a living.
Just like a lot of folks
around Mississippi.
We're not trying
to make history.
We're not trying to
increase tourism.
All we're doing is
doing what we do.
There is a discomfort level
about exploring Southern food
race or particularly Mississippi
food race when you're talking
about high end traditional
Southern cooking, you're talking
plantation slavery cooking
because that's where these
recipes came from.
So to revel in that, you don't
want to tumble into nostalgia.
The potential for awkwardness
and offense is enormous.
I want to be careful.
I'm not saying that's what
I want the south to be.
I'm saying that's what people
come to the south looking for.
Right.
They come to the south looking
for the past preserved
but the reality is
something different.
I want it to
progress and change.
I want to document the change
along the way and
celebrate that change.
The burden of race is upon
us and we must shake it.
That can make us better.
I'm a Yankee, so for me, it's
kind of shocking
to see this flag.
It means a lot of things
to a lot of people.
First and foremost meaning I'm
not a Yankee and I don't
much care what you think.
There's no doubt that much of
Mississippi history is ugly,
from slavery which was pretty
much the backbone, the
foundation of industry here from
the get-go, to Jim crow,
lynchings to church burnings.
14-year-old Emmett till, killed
for talking sass to a
white lady in 1955.
The assassination of
Medgar Evers in 1963.
The murders of civil rights
workers James Cheney, Michael
Schweren and Michael
Goodman in 1964.
They had to send in 30,000
federal agents, national
guardsmen and military police
to enforce a law allowing a
black man to attend college.
A notion that was, shall we say,
less than popular here.
To be honest, that was about all
I had for an image of the
state of Mississippi.
That was all I knew.
And it hadn't occurred
to me to look further.
But I have traveled the world
since then, and I have visited
and learned to love many places
not my own, cultures and beliefs
very different from the upper
east side of Manhattan.
Why can't I love Mississippi?
♪
Infamous is a proud son and
resident of Mississippi, a youth
mentor in Jackson's church and
public school systems, owner of
a marketing agency
and hip-hop artist.
This town, it feels empty.
Where is everybody?
I think one thing is a lot of
people think that you have to
leave Mississippi to be able to
do something great, but I think
a lot of it is there is so much
bubbling in the undercurrent
that it sometimes isn't seen and
I think it takes an artist, it
usually takes something that's
blank and creates something
that's awesome to be able to see
the potential in a place, in a
canvas, so to speak, that
has been vacated by others.
So wired cafe, one of the
number of places where something
is going on, where artists,
entrepreneurs, work shop shops,
performance spaces, set up
something good in formerly
abandoned and neglected
parts of town.
♪
This is a deeply, deeply
conservative state, to say the
least.
Right.
This is a tough question
because I have my own opinion.
Is it more racist than New York?
So I think there are some
deeply ingrained problems in
Mississippi that are connected
to a very ugly past that we
share with some other
Southern states.
However, I think as far as when
we talk about racism expressed
through a classes lens, I think
Mississippi and New
York are on par.
No doubt.
Pie infamous is originally
from Clarksdale in the delta and
went to ole miss but he's
neither left nor lost faith.
He feels an obligation to
empower, uplift, educate, to
contribute.
One of the important tasks of
musicians is being able to
really speak truthfully about
what's going on without
fear of reprisal.
It allows the audience to then
say you know what, you're right.
Now that you've put it to a nice
melody or a nice beat or you say
it in that way and hopefully
then that engages them more
and allows them to move.
I don't think any movement in
the world has not had
a sound track, right?
Regardless of what it is.
So that's our job.
♪
Depending on what metrics
you're using, the Mississippi is
somewhere between the tenth and
the fourth largest
river in the world.
One thing for sure, it's big.
And it's freaking strong.
Also, you really got to put your
back into it if you're crazy
enough to want to paddle a canoe
around in its
fast-moving waters.
What's the source
of the Mississippi?
Well, anywhere a raindrop
falls in 44% of America.
If you follow the volume of
water, two-thirds comes down the
Ohio river, but most people will
say a lake in Minnesota.
John Rutski is I guess what
you would call a river rat.
He started the Quawpaw canoe
company, a custom outfit that
leads guided expeditions on the
Mississippi river and
its tributaries.
As a central part of his
operations, he trains local kids
from Mississippi and across the
river in neighboring Arkansas
under an apprentice program,
teaching skills like hand
carving canoes, outdoor survival
and the ins and outs of guiding
and the history of the river.
Most of these kids come from
pretty distressed neighborhoods
and the hope, the intent, is
that once trained up, they
will stay with the company.
Nice paddling, Tony.
You got it down.
Thank you.
I'll be feeling that tomorrow.
Buck island.
Most of the island could be
under 45 to 50 feet of flowing
river water from April to June
with the spring ice
melt and rainstorms.
We do a lot of cooking out here.
Multi-purpose and
indestructible?
Um-hum.
The next step in this thing is
here are the Greens and we
should stuff as many Greens
as we can into that.
This right here?
Yeah.
All right.
So how does your program work?
Around what age are they
generally when they first start?
Teenagers.
As soon as they can
hold a paddle.
The only thing we ask is
interest and commitment.
What does that mean, commitment?
We had respect of yourself,
getting good sleep, eating good
food, especially before
we go on a trip.
Second one is respect of other
people, other paddlers and
of course, the clients.
And the third thing is
taking care of the river.
You know, they have been told by
their parents don't get
on the Mississippi river.
Maybe they don't even
know how to swim.
You know, for a young man or
woman, overcoming a feeling like
that of getting in the canoe and
then to have people come and
appreciate what you're doing is
life-changing experience.
Within that is this incredible
and beautiful spirit that
is intact in the delta.
Sweet potatoes, Greens,
into the Dutch ovens.
Throw on the corn,
we're getting close.
Finally on the wet logs on top
of glowing coals lay some
steaks, pork loin and pork
tenderloin right on there.
Just keep an eye on them.
We have full spectrum steaks.
Potato's perfect.
Corn on the cob.
Yeah.
Hunk of bread.
Living large on the Mississippi.
And yes, there is too
much food for two people.
And yes, that is a whole
hell of a lot of meat.
And I know it would be awful to
waste all that extra
but don't worry.
Because these gentlemen
are tired and hungry.
Welcome, gentlemen.
Come on.
Corn on the cob here, Greens.
Have a little more of this.
Oh, looking good.
I don't want to say I'm
good, but I'm good.
All right.
More, sir?
You got it?
Who needs steak?
I feel all crocodile Dundee.
Beautiful.
So all that paddling, how bad am
I going to hurt tomorrow?
I don't like the sound of that.
That hesitation,
not a good sign.
Those tenderloins are nice.
Good stuff.
Man, we have mastered
the wild today.
♪
The Mississippi delta is a
big sponge that stretches
between the Yazoo and
the Mississippi.
It's what's called an alluvial
flood plain of about 7,000
square miles or almost 4.5
million acres.
This area used to
look very different.
Massive wild old wood
forests and swamps.
After the passage of the
cheerful-sounding native removal
act of 1830, the delta became
open for settlement by any white
people crazy enough, Hardy
enough, determined enough or
just plain mean and greedy
enough, to come here.
♪
There's no way to make up for
our bad racial past but you
know, the sense of community
that keeps people here is
evidenced in this place.
Julia Reed is Greenville born
and raised, daughter of a
political family, a writer,
author and as delta as it gets.
How long you been
in Mississippi?
22 years.
I came in 1992.
John currant is is a
celebrated chef who left new
Orleans to come to Mississippi
and open first one, then many
more restaurants and businesses
in the town of Oxford.
Stay busy.
This is doze's place
in Greenville.
So good to meet you.
Florence is in charge of the
salad bowl and this is
senior's sister-in-law.
When did y'all open up, 1930?
'41.
Close enough.
Like a lot of folks around
here, Dominic Big Doe Cigna got
his start selling
hot tamales to go.
In the beginning, the place
catered to the black community
but after word got out how good
the food was, white people
started coming which led to a
kind of weird accommodation to
the segregation of the day.
Blacks came in the front, white
people snuck in the back.
The menu expanded
with the clientele.
What human qualities are unique
or marked in the
native of Mississippi?
I cannot address Mississippi
because like I said, the
delta's a whole other planet.
Okay.
Better question, then.
How does the life-long delta
resident differ from...
You have to be a little crazy
to want to come in the first
place because it was
like the swamp, buddy.
It was under water.
You had to be crazy to come and
you had to have enough money to
make it work, so it took
some sort of gamblers.
That spirit still
infuses the place.
It's a little reckless, it's
sophisticated because they
all come from elsewhere.
You know, you go from the delta
to the hills, we are totally
snobbish up here even when we
didn't have a right to be.
Where you just came from,
Jackson, are you kidding me?
You would have to be paid
money to go to Jackson from
Greenville.
They feel the same way
down there about you guys?
They don't get us because
they ain't got no sense of
humor.
So what about the food?
Has this place changed
at all in... no.
It's been 20 years since I
was here last and literally
exactly the same.
Not much in the way of
capital improvements or time
motion study.
The system such as it
is is, well, crazy.
Eat right here in the kitchen
and the division of labor, the
flow of work, well, I gave up
trying to figure it out five
minutes in and just figured I'll
get loaded and eat all
this delicious food.
The salad thing is famous.
Hand-tossed in the same
wooden bowl for decades.
The hot tamales, same
as they ever was.
Those tamales are just
incredible because they're made
with the steak drippings and
stuff you're getting
ready to see.
Oh, really.
It greatly enhances the flavor.
Oh, my god.
I could eat them
until I was sick.
Fries done in cast iron
pan on the stovetop.
The famous shrimp.
Steaks on an old roll-out
broiler, drippings
all over the top.
And you know, you're not going
to get skinny or healthy
eating the hot tamales, fried
shrimp and steak at Doe's.
No question about it.
Oh, that's good.
I'm happy.
That's good.
You're right about the shrimp.
They are delicious.
The shrimp?
Oh, yeah.
Is there a dessert I
should be saving room for?
Are you kidding me?
There is no dessert.
It's pretty damn bare
bones, my friend.
If you ask for one, they
will give you a lollypop.
♪
This is exactly what you
expect in Mississippi, right?
Yeah.
It's supposed to look like this.
I moved here from Georgia and
the thing that struck me when I
moved here, driving through the
delta the first time, was
just how empty it was.
Like it's like everybody left.
The great migration.
Three factors.
Automation, the invention of
mechanical means to pick cotton,
the call of better-paying jobs
in the industries of the
north, and of course, freedom.
People think about the
blues as a lament.
A lot of blues songs are about
freedom, about getting the
hell out of Mississippi.
And there were a lot of reasons
to get the hell out of
Mississippi.
For a long time.
Now there's a return migration.
There's that whole period late
'60s, early '70s, where kids are
bugging out of brown university
to come sit at the foot of an
aging blues man in Mississippi.
There's a cyclical
pattern to that.
Now you see people kind of doing
the same thing with food, like
there's a whole generation that
wants to come down here and sit
at the foot of an aged cook.
State senator Willie Simmons
has been an elected official of
the Mississippi
delta for 20 years.
He's been running this place,
senator's place, for 11.
What's the difference between
soul food and Southern,
traditional Southern food?
It depends on the culture and
what neighborhood you were in.
If you were in the black
neighborhood, it became soul.
We probably put a little bit
more of the throwaway in our
cooking, the pig feet, the pig
tail, the neck bones and
all of that's fatty.
Now you're making me hungry.
So Greens... collard Greens.
Have some of that, for sure.
Is that fried okra there?
I'll have a little of that.
Might need more than one
plate at this rate.
Let me get some Mac and cheese.
What's that, Lima beans?
The red bean.
Oh, man, that looks
kind of good, too.
Yeah, little bit of that.
Neck bones floating
around somewhere?
Okay.
Yeah, I'll have some of those.
Little rice and gravy
on there, yeah.
Thanks.
And oh, a piece of
fried chicken there.
If you got a thigh,
that would be great.
Okra's perfect.
Yeah, it is.
Man, that's good.
Now here in the south, if you
want to, you can throw
your fork away and...
I'll be working on that.
We forgive you and don't
hold it against you.
Could eat this okra
all day long, man.
It's good.
I don't know what you
think about those Greens.
They're nice.
That's tasty.
This is the way people get the
credit for Southern
cooking as we know it.
I do.
You think the right
people get the credit?
People know.
People know who's behind this
food, whether it's called soul
food or whether it's
called country cooking.
How is the detail, the mindset
of the delta, different
than the rest of the state?
Nobody else can compare with us.
They have no one who can sit on
top of you and tell you they
represent dockery plantation
where the blues were born.
There's no one else that can
tell you his district is the
home of B.B. King, where
Jared Butler was born.
Or the staples singers.
When we talk about the heritage
and the culture and what comes
out of the delta, that's all
within this district
that I represent.
So Mississippi delta
has that pride.
46 miles southeast is
greenwood, a town with a lot of
history, most of it of
the not good variety.
Known unfortunately as much for
Tom Brady's infamous speech
after brown versus the board of
education as anything else,
fairly or not, it's
hard to get past that.
During all the years of cruelty
and struggle from 1933 on,
through it all, and until today,
this place, Lusco's, was
a beloved institution.
Once a grocery store it turned
restaurant to the moneyed class,
served them in discreet quarters
in the pack where one could
enjoy an alcoholic beverage in
what was then a dry state.
Still going after all
these years, unchanged.
Why?
This place is like a rel
quarter of indiscretions past,
you know?
But maybe to really tell the
story of this place, you have to
start with a story of its most
famous employee, Booker Wright.
He had been working at Lusco's
as a waiter since he
was 14 years old.
I'll be glad to tell you what
they're going to serve tonight.
In 1965, NBC news came to
town, making a documentary on
race relations.
Booker's entertaining recitation
of the menu at Lusco's was
famous around town so they asked
him to do his usual
routine for the camera.
But at the end of his usual
litany is where he dropped the
truth bomb that
nobody was ready for.
Right here.
You have to smile.
If you don't, what's
wrong with you?
The meaner the man be,
the more you smile.
Although you're
crying on the inside.
You don't look for no tips.
Yes, sir, thank you.
What did you say?
Thank you, sir.
That's what you have to go
through here but
remember, keep smiling.
Telling the truth was still
risky business in 1966
Mississippi and Booker Wright
was not rewarded for his candor.
It was not a good
experience for him.
It did not make him a star.
Not within the white community
but even though black
power was first chanted here,
that was less important to the
black community here than what
Booker said on the NBC news.
Yeah.
The private dining rooms
at Lusco's is still here.
The menu, much the same.
Steaks, fish.
The famous broiled shrimp.
The Lusco special salad with the
house Italian vinaigrette
dressing and a healthy dose
of anchovie, onion rings.
Salad makes me happy.
Me, too.
Mostly anchovies make me happy.
Yeah, yeah, love those.
Catfish for Mr. Edge, the
famous pompano for me.
It's kind of the Mark of
being a great restaurant in the
delta if you have pompano.
Big damn fish.
No way I'm finishing this.
Sitting here, the booth, the
curtains, the whole ring bell
for service thing, it
seems lost in time.
We got a long ugly history
but that's one of the things I
love about this place, you can't
deny the burden of the past.
It gets on your shoulder.
It's right there.
America chooses to deny its
problems in many ways.
It declares itself a
post-racial society.
Oxford, Mississippi is a
lovely, eccentric island, a
magnet for writers, thinkers and
oddballs, drawn perhaps by its
rich literary tradition as the
home of one of our greatest
authors, William Faulkner.
Faulkner was a Mississippi
native, a former postman, an
outdoorsman and eventual winner
of the Nobel prize in literature
and two Pulitzer
prizes for fiction.
He never graduated high school.
This was his house, Roanoke.
Faulkner wrote such American
classics as the sound and the
fury, as I lay dying, light in
August and many of his works
took place in a fictional
county, a place very much like
this place, in Mississippi.
This is where Faulkner started
his writing career, in
this room here.
For the past ten years, bill
Griffith has been curator
at Faulkner’s estate.
After he won the Nobel prize,
on the wall here is an outline
of one of his novels.
That was his greatest book.
Faulkner thought that
was his masterpiece.
Jack Pendarvis is the author
of your body is changing, the
mysterious secret of the
valuable treasure and awesome as
well as a staff writer for the
game-changing animated
series adventure time.
All works of which
I am a huge fan.
He wrote right on the wall?
He wrote on it.
It's his man-cave.
It's his version.
He said houses in Mississippi
who have a family business have
one room dedicated to the family
business and this family's
business is writing.
From as early as 1919 through
the early '60s, Faulkner wrote
extensively about the
post-civil war south.
He was the first author to do
so, at a time when most writers
were writing about anything but.
He always said that he wrote
about a south torn between
itself, torn between the old
ways, the old traditional
ways and modern.
He said he would break
the code and he did.
But?
He did.
Yet he had those hobbies and
interests that were definitely
of a gentry class
and gentry nature.
His portrait.
Great example.
And his writing habit.
That's a great example.
You do get to a certain level
of success and all of a sudden,
this seems like a good idea and
it's never a good
idea at that age.
At any age.
Exactly.
Was he politically
active at all?
He was a middle of
the road democrat.
That's what he said.
He said you have to bring
black education up with white
education and since the state of
Mississippi will not invest in
black education it's up
to its citizens to do so.
He said that segregation wasn't
about being right or wrong.
He said any sane, sober
southerner knows that it's
wrong.
It's about wanting
to change or not.
But people don't want
to give up power.
Fear is still alive and
well in Mississippi.
I think racism is one of those
great things in the world that
you'll never solve and that's
why Faulkner wrote about it.
Writers as I know from looking
in my own dark heart,
are generally terrible people.
Put ten of them together and
it's like putting your head
in a bag full of snakes.
I meet a bunch of them above
city grocery, John currant's
place on the square.
There's the brilliant author Tom
Franklin and his wife, the
poet Beth Ann Fennely.
Grisham writers in residence,
Megan Abbott, Pendarvis, a
senior writer for ESPN,
novelist, Ace Atkins.
Poet, Derek Harell is
originally from Milwaukee.
Crime novelist Billy
Boyle from Brooklyn.
Downstairs, currant's restaurant
city grocery cranks out
many delicious things.
The man known as big bad chef,
aka Johnny snack, is sending
some of those goodies upstairs
as there's nothing professional
writers like more
than free food.
Usually you put five writers
in a room, it's an ugly hell
broth of envy, hatred...
We all hate Tommy.
That goes without saying.
I hate me worst of all.
The writers are really
supportive of each other.
For writers to argue would be
like arguing over
a piece of dirt.
What are we fighting about?
The stakes are so low, why would
you be a jerk about it?
If Mississippi were a country
and there were a national hero,
dead or alive, by consensus,
state-wide, who would
the statue be of?
Elvis.
Really?
It wouldn't even be him.
It should be B.B. King.
Yeah.
But it would be Elvis.
It would be Elvis.
Mississippi I you know, the
joke is that it's not a state,
it's a club, that it's so small
that everybody knows everybody.
In the middle of Mississippi,
Oxford is an oasis of thought
and literature and feeling.
The velvet ditch.
Why the velvet ditch?
It's pretty freaking
comfortable.
You don't care much
about getting out.
Right?
Am I right?
No one here seems too
bitter about that.
It's a place that needs help
but it's a really great place.
We're never leaving.
Is there a distinctive
barbecue style in the state of
Mississippi?
No.
Not that we can really
discern at all.
And it's part of the reason
that we wanted to do this.
We got our hands on this place
and sort of been puzzled for
years of what Mississippi
barbecue is all about.
The more I dug into it, the
less and less I could find.
So what we wanted to do is sort
of take a look at barbecue that
surrounds us and see if we could
sort of Frankenstein barbecue.
Isn't really any fixed idea
of Mississippi barbecue and
other than this place, Lamar
lounge, John currant's not for
profit bar/restaurant, there's
no other pit-smoked barbecue
in the entire state.
A 175 pound pig will
feed many mouths.
About 250 people eat here a day.
This is a not for
profit establishment?
Yeah.
Is that right?
Yeah, it sure is.
What sort of communist
socialist are you up to?
What's going on?
This is the state
of Mississippi.
Just a feel-good type of guy.
Me, too.
I've been here only a week and
my sentences are starting to
change already, because there's
not just a physical rhythm to
the speech, but the way I'm
organizing my thoughts is
starting to change.
Some of the Oxford writers from
last night managed to make it
out of bed, heads pounding no
doubt, filled with the shame and
self-loathing surely
familiar for writers.
But like such greats of the past
as Malcolm Lowery, F. Scott
Fitzgerald, they too have
learned that more alcohol first
thing will often make you
feel better about the world.
Particularly if accompanied
by freshly baked cornbread,
biscuits, pulled pork off that
whole hog, sweet jerk
chicken and brisket.
Hell, I feel better already.
The Mississippi I perceived
is not the Mississippi
I had in my head.
I was surprised how
sold I was off the bat.
If you want to write,
come to Oxford.
You think that's true?
Apparently, yes.
Like that line you can't throw
a rock without hitting a
writer.
Do me a favor, throw it hard.
It's easy to look at
Mississippi and go that just
happens down there
so we're good.
Our hands are clean.
It's a totally
misperceived place.
When I came, I fell in
love with the place.
I never thought that I would.
There's something to it but you
can't put your finger
on what it is.
What it is can be found in
the dark spaces across the
tracks and on the
other side of town.
Good evening, ladies
and gentlemen.
Welcome to the lounge
right by the cemetery.
♪
What is a juke joint?
You heard reference to them,
no doubt, but what is it?
I guess the first thing you've
got to know is it's
pronounced juk joint.
And this one is a real good one.
Scholars suggested juk came from
enslaved Africans and it meant
wicked or disorderly, to
dance, or a place of shelter.
Juke joints started in the
plantation community rooms
during slavery times.
They went on to become the
small, private African-American
bars, clubs and lounges.
First in rural areas, then in
towns and cities where workers
could dance, drink, party and
gamble as respite from the hard
labor of sharecropping, tenant
farming, house service
and segregation.
They were often condemned by
church leaders as
houses of the devil.
William runs this place, as he
has since 1963, and
he makes the rules.
How long has this
been in business?
How did you get
into this business?
Something I like to do.
Everybody come in and enjoy
themselves, no problem.
Please explain this policy.
No hats backwards and
no .pants hanging down.
If you don't like the
rules, don't come.
No rap music.
Give me a headache.
I love blues.
Good R&B?
That's right.
But no rap?
If Kanye West wants to rent out
the place you'll rent it to him?
I'll rent it to him.
Thank you, sir.
I love your place and
thank you for having us.
Got to come back again.
I surely will.
I'll find somebody to
get naked with you.
Uh-oh.
Okay, you can kick it back off.
Thursday night is family
night at Po monkeys.
Mostly locals, mixed bag.
The music is classic
R&B and predisco soul.
Attitude, loose.
Just familiarize with those
rules and there won't be a
problem.
In the cities of the north
where I come from, in some ways
we've been able to buy
ourselves free from our past.
New arrivals pour in with no
member of the ugly
parts of our history.
We can afford the
luxury of the new.
We can live in comfortable
bubbles, our apartments
high in the sky.
In many way, more separate
than at anytime in history.
But for Mississippi, the
past is right there to see.
Still present, and coming to
terms with it, not through
abstract discussion, but the
daily business of life.