Miami sneaks up on you.
Or do we change and find
ourselves sneaking up, washing
up, ending up in Miami?
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha, la, la, la, la, la,
♪ sha, la, la, la, la,
Miami, it's a big place.
Bigger and more multifaceted
than it's given credit for.
Miami, where you at?
We tend over the years to
focus on Miami's... how shall
I put this... party zone.
♪
It's the kind of place we say
that could never be
me and then it is.
It's a temptation that's
almost irresistible.
The seductions of flash, of palm
trees, balmy nights, television
shows made real, but across the
causeway a few miles down the
way there are other
worlds, older ones.
I think it's safe
to say better ones.
♪
Way out west 20 miles from the
airport tucked in yet another
strip mall is this place and you
go there because, well, you need
coffee and because Cuba,
respect, and because Michelle
Bernstein is there.
It was a long time getting here.
You need a car in Miami, and
yes, this is like
the heart of Miami.
Michelle is one of my Miami's
most iconic influential
chefs, born and bred her.
When people say where did
you grow up, you say...
Miami.
This is out west.
You can't get much
further west than this.
What's beyond here?
Swampland.
This restaurant, we would
actually come here for the
seafood and it would be elegant.
Well, you have the waiters in
the little bolero
type jacket things.
Or a bow tie and there's
still some places in Miami
that still have that.
This is how you drink
coffee in Miami.
What do they call this?
It's a big cup with little cups.
It is basically like the
coffee version, the caffeine
version of a one-hitter.
I'd have one of those.
At the next place,
I'd have another.
I grew up on the colada.
We all give our babies coffee.
They put their finger in it to
taste it and they all
grow up loving coffee.
This is a nonjudgmental
land, Miami.
It is.
You can pretty much get
away with almost anything.
It's good coffee.
I'm so glad you like it
because a lot of people don't
like it.
Really?
Well, because they
think it is too sweet.
You're thinking, yes, a
cubano sandwich, but you'd be
wrong.
This is not a cubano sandwich.
Close, a cousin.
Ham, Swiss cheese, pickles, a
little mustard and like a cubano
it is pressed until
it is soft inside.
You see how juicy that is?
You know what pisses me off?
People try to improve on this.
How is it?
Is it yummy?
It's good.
A lot of thought is given to the
structure of the sandwich.
It is all about the layers.
Yeah.
This is the perfect
breakfast, right?
It's good, yeah.
I always go for the salty.
Never the sweet.
I don't care about sweet things.
If I have to give up one
course of the meal, dessert.
Cheese over dessert any day.
Yes.
I'd rather have steak over
dessert, but maybe that's
because my mother
is from Argentina.
♪
This is my world
away from the world.
To me, it's my little
king's domain.
There's one place I
keep coming back to.
It's a place where if you look
deep enough, ask the right
questions, you can get a whole
history of Miami from one man.
This man, Matt Klein.
You're going to have to
remember you're speaking to
100-year-old man.
I know.
You look good.
Raise your voice a little bit.
If I look that good when
I'm 60, I'll be happy.
You know what the amazing
thing about being 100 is?
Last year I was 99.
Nobody cared.
He turned 100 years
old this year.
Yes, 100.
He's still here.
The cigarette smoke and dark
dank atmosphere pretty good for
a guy that's seen it all.
That's 73 years ago.
Matt Klein came from new
York's lower east side by way of
the battle of Normandy.
I came here pause I was
wounded and the warm weather
was much better for me.
But there was a lot of G.I.S
during the war here, right?
They saw a world that
they didn't believe.
During world war ii, Miami
saw a massive influx
of military personnel.
Hotels, which had seen a sharp
drop in business, made a deal
with the government to house
troops in empty resorts.
Parents came down, sons came
down, they opened businesses
here, and they were basically
Jewish at the time and
that's how it started.
By the fall of 1942, more
than 78,000 troops were living
in more than 300 hotels
in Miami and Miami beach.
How long have you been
running the deuce?
I took over in 1964.
Half of my life I've spent here.
Miami beach has turned over at
least six times since
I've been here.
All I need is "Miami vice."
This was their favorite bar.
It makes sense too.
Still, it was very flattering.
The same as how flattering
it is to have you here.
I love this place.
I mean I love it.
It's my favorite bar in Miami.
To many more.
The dreamers, the visionaries,
crooks, and con men
who built Miami envision many
different kinds of paradise.
A new Jerusalem in the
infinitely expanding real
estate, just fill in where
there's water and you've got
property.
Or as in coral gables,
a new Venice.
Gone Doe last to ferry the new
seekers to their
palatzos in the sun.
The dream was as
expandable as the space.
Where there was water, there was
now magically Terra
sort a firma.
And in the 80s where there was
decline, a vacuum, suddenly
there was a new and vibrant
economy one that raised all
boats, shiny cars, swanky
nightclubs, and a new reputation
for murder and criminality
to go with it.
Cocaine.
Say what you will, cocaine
altered the skyline of Miami
forever.
It made, for better or
worse, Miami sexy again.
Going back to the very
beginning, was Miami always a
criminal enterprise?
But I mean that in a good way.
Outlaw culturism a very deep
part of American culture.
We don't produce or manufacture
anything but oranges
or handguns.
We sell sunshine.
The only jobs we have are in
hospitality or in restaurants.
Real estate.
It is all to sell the
dream to the next people.
In 1981 the FBI called Miami
the most violent city in
America.
The drug industry brought in an
estimated to 7 to $12 billion a
year and that was of 1981 Miami.
That is a lot of trickle down.
One of the most successful
documentaries in the history of
film is "cocaine cowboys"
that tells that story.
So things were in decline.
Cocaine sort of saved the city?
We'd say so.
Am I going to get
in trouble for it?
Yes.
You had a murder rate.
25% of those bodies had
automatic weapons bullets.
We talk about the uncomfortable
reality of where a
lot of the modern Miami came
from over something you just
have to hit hard in
Miami when in season.
Stone crabs.
Federal reserve branch in
Miami had a $5 billion cash
surplus.
Mostly 50s and 100 dollar bills
all of which had trace
elements of cocaine on them.
And the guys in cocaine
trafficking got out and are now
big medicare fraudsters.
We're whispering because
they're probably here.
So where's the money now?
How's business in general in
Miami and where is that
business coming from?
Remarkably the rebound from
the great recession, the people
thought it would take a decade
and it seemed to happen
almost overnight.
We're in the middle
of another huge boom.
Who is buying?
Wealthy foreigners.
A lot of capital Russians.
If it is money looted from
another country, do we care?
The question is how
long will it last?
There's history and there's
the more immediate
needs of the present.
I need food presently and
perhaps some fine bourbon and
when I need good food in a city
not my own, more and more these
days I call somebody if they
weren't good at enough things
already has become something of
an expert on food
around the world.
Every time I check Instagram
you're eating with one
of my culinary heros.
I'm here.
You've been to
this place before?
I live at this place.
Really?
Yeah.
Yard bird quickly became
a Miami favorite.
The old joke was James brown
was the hardest working
man in show business.
You make him look lazy.
Producer, a teacher.
Yep.
A D.J.
Technically, I have
16 jobs right now.
Devilled eggs with fresh dill
and trout roll will be so over
next year, but right
now I want more.
Fried beans with pork belly.
This is the perfect thing for a
guy looking to squeeze into a
size 28 Speedo tomorrow
and hit the beach.
What makes the Miami sound
different from the Detroit
sound, the Philadelphia sound,
the New York sound, whatever?
You can't say Philadelphia
has strings in their arrangement
whereas records had
organ in there.
What's called 77 Elvis pancakes?
Chocolate chip pancakes, bourbon
maple syrup, banana compote.
Yard bird's signature fried
chicken comes with spiced
watermelon and cheddar
cheese waffles.
They brine the chicken
17 hours to be exact.
Tender inside and perfectly
crispy on the outside.
To me, I like waffles and I
like chicken, but I don't
understand waffles and
chicken together.
You still don't understand?
I understand people deeply
love them and I do like waffles
and I do like fried chicken.
Put them on separate
plates and I'm okay.
You don't want your
food integrated?
Shrimp and grits, a
Southern classic.
I was reading your book.
Is it Curtis Mayfield you
have bad associations with?
Whenever I hear Curtis
Mayfield, just as a kid, that
particular structure
always frightened me.
Even now?
I'm angry that that
band ever existed.
I hate that old englishy, old,
bar minstrel, stand on one
leg mother [ Muted ] shit.
You never know when you play
music were they molested by a
rodeo clown to that song and
Jethro Tull is my
version of that.
Who got here first?
Who other than say some early
native American
tribes and Spaniards?
Caribbean blacks, Bahamian.
Henry Morrison flagger, the
tycoon largely credited with big
the father of modern Florida.
His dream was the Florida east
coast railroad, which would run
from Jacksonville to key west
connecting the ports of Miami to
the rail system of the rest of
the United States, creating
along its route new towns,
new cities, new places where
America's rising middle class
could frolic and play.
As more and more whites moved
in, segregation took hold and
much of the community was forced
into the black neighborhoods
like Overtown.
If you're looking for old Miami,
original Miami, you're looking
to an extent for black Miami.
♪
These days Liberty city is
mostly ignored by developers,
but back in the day it was
the epicenter of the black
community.
A lot has happened since then.
Pancakes, smoked
sausage, boiled eggs.
What do you usually get?
The fishy grits.
Your parents were
Jamaican and Bahamian.
Yes.
Today I'm having fish and
grits at milk restaurant with
this guy, Luther Campbell.
A lot of good cooking
tradition in the family.
Oh, yeah.
One night we'd have
peas and rice.
The other night we'd
have rice and peas.
Otherwise known as
Luke sky Walker.
He is something of a musical and
political and legal legend.
Maybe you know him from
Campbell versus Rose music.
How do you end up different
growing up in Miami than you
would have grown up in L.A.
and New York?
A lot of people would have
said Southern people, whatever
you want to call us, in
actuality we're a Bahaman town.
Very, very different.
How has that mix, how has
that impacted the music?
When people think about me,
this guy makes bootie
shaking music.
Everybody is dancing
in a sexual way.
The girls are
standing up on you.
The girls stand up on you
and put your butt on you.
I've seen this on television.
It's no different
than a lap dance.
You ran for office?
Yeah.
About 70% residents of Miami
speak Spanish at home.
Uh-huh.
Enormous African-American
and Caribbean community.
How come they keep electing
conservative white guys?
You have a whole
quiet community.
You didn't get them
excited about voting.
It is the opposite of get
out the vote program.
It is don't bother to vote.
Don't bother to vote.
African-Americans voted at 20%.
If we would have voted at 50%,
Charlotte Gris would have
won the governor's race.
If you were selling Miami to
somebody, what's the
best thing about Miami?
Best weather.
How do you handle the cold if
you have to tour or something in
Detroit or Chicago or something?
My mind-set is I don't have
to deal with this every day.
I'm going back to sunshine.
I can go into a blizzard.
I know I'm going out.
Y'all stay.
This is really good.
Back inland, another
world of flavors.
Little Haiti.
Just in case Miami didn't
have enough tasty stuff from
elsewhere.
The band market is
tucked away in the back.
They serve some of the dishes
they make me happiest, jerk
chicken, who doesn't love that?
Cow-foot soup.
That looks, by the
way, unbelievable.
That's so good.
What's the best
thing about Miami?
The mix of cultures.
What's the worst thing?
You know what really
pisses me off?
I walk down the street and I say
hi to people and I don't
get a hi back a lot here.
To what do you attribute this?
The transient part of it.
People don't feel rooted.
They are from south
America, central America.
Their whole plan is to come here
do what they can to send money
to their family to live in the
home of their dreams
and then go back.
If I were to think about
coming to Florida to live, what
would seem attractive to me,
find some place on the beach
and just sink in until my
liver-spotted George Hamilton
face, walk up and down metal
detecter, that would be me.
People who go to live that
dream, they don't go to the
beach.
Ask me when the last time
I went to the beach was.
When was the last time
I went to the beach.
About a year and a half ago.
What the [ Muted ] is that?
We're working.
I love it and I always say I
will never live in south Florida
if I didn't live near water.
I live near water and I leave my
doors open a lot, but I
don't go to the beach.
I barely even go into my
swimming pool, but I know it's
there.
Okay.
♪
♪ Standing here in the rain
trying to wash away my singing ♪
♪ baby gone and left me I don't
think she's coming back again ♪
before "Miami vice" before
the Miami sound machine,
there was a Miami sound.
The music, the original Miami
sound we're talking about, came
from this man, Willie
Clark and this space.
What was this space originally?
This was a little restaurant
smaller than this and we were on
the other side with
the record shop.
Now it looks like a nondescript
barbecue joint, but
back in 1963 it was the
home of deep city records.
Willie Clark and his business
partner Johnny Peersol
started deep city.
The label became a showcase for
artists like Betty Wright, frank
Williams and the Rocketeers.
It is a very, very long
list, an amazing list.
It is about 1200.
1200 songs.
It just flows.
I'm like a song mechanic.
You bring it to me.
I'll help you fix it.
William and his writing partner
wrote such classics as
"clean up woman" and
"rocking chair."
50 years, 100 years from now,
if you were to do an Internet
search and punch in the Miami
sound, your name is going to
come up right away as principal
creator of the Miami sound.
What were the distinctive
features of the music you were
making that separated it from
Motown, Philadelphia, New York?
The culture was a mixture of
Bahamian, Jamaican, and people
came down from Georgia and
Alabama, but that Bahamian
influence was dominant.
Right.
We would have bands who would
march from Overtown all the way
to Liberty city and
back in big parades.
This influence, the dancing and
the moving and the marching,
that was the main difference.
And you were teaching school
through a lot of this?
Yeah, I was teaching.
I would look around, put my sign
in, and walk out the back door
and go straight to the studio.
But you know, the principal
knew what I was doing.
Yep.
I did most of the deep city
music using that technique.
♪
♪ If only I could fly I
would take to the air ♪
you're still out there so
your songs are still being
played, still being
sampled, which is good.
It weren't for the samples,
I don't know what I'd do.
The collectors must go crazy.
Maniac collectors in
Europe and Japan.
If I had known back then, I
guess we would still
be over there.
Biggest Motown or bigger.
This is an island, isn't it?
It is kind of an island.
It is worse than an island.
♪ Darling I'm willing to
forget about our past ♪
♪ darling I'm able to
make our love last ♪
♪ I'm a one man's woman and I'm
willing and able to be loved ♪
♪ oh yes I am yeah yeah yeah
Another day, another country.
Miami is like that.
You can eat your way across the
Caribbean and through all of
Latin America and then over
to Africa, if you'd like.
It's all there.
If you know anything about me,
you know I love few things more
than big, new, unusual, comes
from somewhere else, mutant
versions of the giant hamburger
and this one, this one
is something special.
This is a tall Venezuelan.
It is all about a lot of sauces.
We're going to do this.
Absolutely, right?
Okay.
What is this neighborhood?
Some people call it petite
Venezuela, and yeah,
you're way west.
You'll pretty much hear
everybody here speak Spanish.
There's almost no
English spoken.
Even if they are not Latin.
You have to speak Spanish.
Meat on meat is something of
a Venezuelan specialty
and this one has a lot.
A beef Patty, ham, egg, six
varieties of sauces,
potatoes and cheese.
This one is big, big I tell you.
You have to demolish it in
stages like a hyena devouring
an antelope by the hoof.
I'm going to start crying.
All right.
I'm going in.
Good god.
Yes or no?
It's delicious, but...
It's a little much, right.
There's no way this thing is
holding together
until the last bite.
All right.
I can't even get
the whole thing.
That's ridiculous.
This is open until 4:00 A.M.
There's definitely a time of day
when that seems like a
perfectly reasonable idea.
If you drink too much, this
will pretty much take care of
everything that ever ailed you.
Long a refuge for people all
over the Caribbean basin and
Latin America, it was long a
mecca for Americans who
wanted to get off the grid.
You'll remember Travis, the
mystery solving boat bum who
lived on a houseboat in Miami.
People used to live like that.
Less and less today.
When my wife passed away a
few years ago, I was living in a
condo and didn't want
to do that anymore.
Now I'm on this piece of iron.
Bob, aka captain Bob, is still
here and still living on
his boat in the Miami river.
We sit out here and we look
like we're enjoying ourselves,
but it is really hard work.
Just sitting here looking
pretty, it's not for everybody.
But yeah, it's a good life.
I've had many friends over
the years who live on boats,
work on boats, but these were
just degenerate wind addicts.
I wanted to go down to the
Bahamas and get the boat
to earn its own keep.
The steel hauled achievement
doesn't do much moving around
these days, but it
might have to soon.
Who else lives like you?
It used to be very common.
It is getting scarcer.
How long do you
think you've got?
Six months, a year?
Yeah.
We sit here and watch them
put the buildings up and
they're... coming closer.
Creeping this way.
You're not moving onto land
anytime soon if
you can avoid it?
No.
Here life keeps flowing by.
I wave and keep on keeping on.
♪
Miami's the kind of place
you say that could never be me.
And then it is.
So you've been here
how many years?
15 years.
You're a Floridian.
Yeah.
When I was young, this man
was a role model, an ideal,
a roadmap for bad behavior.
His music, it turned out, was
the soundtrack for
most of my life.
Still is.
James Osterburg of Muskegon,
Michigan, known still all
over the world as Iggy pop.
You grew up in Michigan, you
lived in New York for a
long period of time.
I went from Michigan
to lo London.
I went from London to
Hollywood which was rough.
Hollywood to Berlin
which was great.
Back to London.
And New York from '79 to '99.
Was it a conceivable option
at any point, I can live in
Florida?
It wasn't for me.
I was hustling.
Hustling in a big city.
It happened by chance.
I had a shady friend who owned a
condo here, and thought, well,
this is a nice
little trashy hang.
You could just pull up to the
beach any time you wanted and
look out and see the
end of complications.
And anybody could do that
and it was safe and free.
And I thought, that's a
this is beautiful.
♪
So we're eating healthy today.
Yeah.
What do you like here?
I wouldn't have thought back
then in my dorm room that all
those years later I'd be
eating healthy with Iggy pop.
Barbecue shrimp for the
godfather of punk.
I get wild and crazy
with some roast pork.
A little white wine, our only
tilt toward the debauches
of previous lives.
I well remember the first
stooges album coming out, the
context of the time.
This was, what, '69?
'69, August.
In a lot of ways as far as
looking after my health, your
music early on was a
negative example.
I hear you.
And looking at my own life
and career, I'm pretty much
known for traveling around the
world and recklessly drinking
and eating to excess.
Sure.
What does it say about us
that you're now sitting in a
healthy restaurant?
I just came from the gym.
And we're in Florida.
Listen, if you just flamed
out, you're in... you know,
you're in such voluminous and
undistinguished company and all
your works will flame
out quicker with you.
♪
What's the perfect day in Miami?
It's a clear morning.
Hot.
Hot and humid.
No moderate or any of that crap.
No.
Hot, hot, humid.
The sun comes up in a hazy
tropical orange orb, and
you're not working.
You're not on a schedule.
And you have no meetings, but
you have somebody fun
to spend the time with.
And then you would go to the
beach when the sun isn't right
overhead yet because the beach
faces east, the sun
sparkles on the water.
And the sparkle is very nice.
So, positive.
♪
You're the template for the
rock star, meaning other rock
stars sort of look to you to
figure out how should I behave?
Along with that, look, even at
its... even if you're broke,
you're a guy at various points
in life has pretty much been
able to have a lot of things
ordinary people
would never have.
You've had many,
many adventures.
I know... given that,
what thrills you?
The nicest stuff right now,
this is very embarrassing, but
it's really... being loved.
And actually appreciating the
people that are
giving that to me.
♪
I don't see any birds
at all here today.
It's so quiet.
Is this the reward phase
of your life or just...
It's been emotionally I think
a reward phase for stuff I
did up until the age 30.
Stuff you had to do on instinct
and not on intelligence.
See, I think you deserve it.
But when I look at my own life,
you know, I'm actually
I'm ambivalent.
I mean, I'm still not so sure.
You know?
I'm still curious.
You seem like a curious person.
It's my only virtue.
Curious is a good thing to be.
It seems to pay some
unexpected dividends.
♪ I am a passenger and
I ride and ride ♪
♪ I ride through the city ♪
I see the stars come out of
the sky ♪
♪ so let's ride and ride
and ride and ride ♪
I guess that's what
it comes down to.
All of it.
Right here.
Write a book, I get a TV show, I
live my dreams, I meet my hero.
Two old men on a beach.
♪ Singing la, la, la,
la, la, la, la ♪
♪ la, la, la, la, la, la, la