For Korean-Americans,
according to the stereotype
anyway, it used to be that you
grew up to be a doctor,
a lawyer, an engineer.
There were a specific set
of rules and expectations.
Are you asking me
to be in a porno?
Is that what you're asking me?
Thanks to some remarkably
bad Koreans, though,
things are beginning to change.
I went to one year of law
school and I walked out.
So you're a bad Korean.
Yeah, I'm a bad Korean.
Any final advice for somebody
who's actually about to
marry a Korean woman?
Don't do it.
♪ ♪
All I knew was that this
town was going down,
and no one was showing up.
And so we as Koreans
figured that out really quickly.
There's a point where you and I
look at each other and say.
They're not coming.
They're not coming, Tony.
You know? Like, it's you and me.
Right. Right. The choppers
will not be here anytime soon.
You know? Yeah, I mean,
so that's when all the
stuff started to go down.
Roy Choi is a second-generation
Korean American.
He lives in Los Angeles.
He's the owner/operator of
four groundbreaking and much
loved food trucks, among the
first to harness the strange
and terrible powers of social
media to alert customers to
where to find delicious food.
This was the command post.
From here, you know, you could
look, and you could see
if fires were going on.
When the Los Angeles
riots happened in 1992,
Roy was 22 years old.
And this plaza's rooftop played
a central role for Koreans
defending their town.
But let's back up a bit.
After the Immigration Act of
1965, thousands of Koreansof
began arriving in L.A.
The first to arrive were
mostly middle-class,
college-educated, hoping
to make a lateral move
into American society.
But unless you had a medical
or engineering degree,
that turned out to be tough.
They found work as
merchants, store owners,
opened liquor stores,
groceries, massage studios,
dry cleaners.
They did that in an area
that was, as it's called,
underserved.
Where major chains
feared to tread, where
others preferred to
abandon, Koreans moved in.
So, 1992.
Four L.A. police officers
are on trial for what sure as
hell looked to me like a wildly
excessive and prolonged beating
of an unarmed Rodney King.
In April of that year,
they were acquitted.
For me, it was a, "Holy shit, I
never saw that coming" moment. I
For African Americans, it
was a somewhat ruder surprise.
To say people were angry
would be an understatement.
They don't represent
the people no more.
South Central is that way.
So, you could almost feel it
like a tidal wave coming.
The L.A.P.D. were completely
unprepared for what
happened next.
Everything you see right
here, all this, was being
looted.
Chairs and rocks and everything
being thrown through walls.
If you go straight down
Western, on Venice,
the whole plaza burned on fire.
We were calling 911 and
there was no response.
Did cops come at all?
I was here all three days.
I didn't see any cops.
Well, where did they set
up their front line?
Rodeo Drive.
Where did the forces of law
and order set up their
perimeter?
Not here.
Koreatown was left
to its own devices.
The official borders are
Third Street on the north end,
Olympic Boulevard to the south,
Vermont Avenue on the east,
and Western Avenue to the west.
That's three square miles
left pretty much to burn
or fend for itself.
This rooftop quickly became
the command post for
rapidly improvised
Korean defense forces.
They armed themselves, set
up crude but effective
command and control
communication, and patrols.
We weren't going around just
slugging and-and capping people.
All that was happening was,
"Just don't break
down my store."
Making sure our parents,
our uncles, our families,
these stores, this
town, stays alive.
58 people were killed.
Only a quarter of Korean-owned
businesses survived,
either destroyed outright
during the riots
or abandoned afterwards by
owners who felt the entire
underpinning of their contract
with America had shifted.
Yet today, Koreatown is
bigger and better and
forever changed by
what happened in 1992.
Dong Il Jang, however, is
as unwaveringly old school
as you get.
Roy and I sit down with Roy
Kim, whose grandfather
opened the place in 1978.
Like most Korean
restaurants at the time,
you didn't mess with
the original, ever.
And like most Korean
father/son relationships,
you obeyed Dad's
wishes no matter what.
My father put all this,
you know, redwood in,
and all this cherry
and all this.
But, to this day, I
can't touch certain
things here.
I can see he doesn't let
you change the uniforms
either.
Uh, no.
Yeah.
Well, he still controls
the restaurant.
You just do the work.
I just do the work.
As a Korean, he knows.
We start with bonchon, all
those delicious little
freebie plates of pickles,
preserves, kimchi, pickles,
a spicy squid snack or two.
No bonchon?
No meal.
And you know what this
restaurant has that a lot of
restaurants are going away from?
Is the, um... is the
chair-less rooms.
You don't do the-the feet under?
Knees forward, feet under?
All the-the tea ceremonies.
Straight ahead?
Oh, no can do.
That was punishment for Koreans.
Yeah.
That's a punishment.
And with the book
over your head.
Oh, for hours.
What would a crime be?
What got you into
that, uh, position?
Yeah, I mean, it could be
as-as minimal as a
94 on the test.
Korean parents?
Well, let's just say they
veer towards the strict.
Moms and Dads were not,
shall we say, conflicted
about corporal punishment.
I love that you both
immediately recognize this.
Oh, this is the roast gui.
This is what we're known...
It's thinly sliced
rib-eye, marbled rib-eye.
Oh, it's beautiful.
Roast gui.
Thin-sliced rib-eye.
And bulgogi.
Thinly-sliced, fat-marbled
beef, barbecued table-side.
For us Koreans, it's kind of
funny that barbecue has become
the gateway to our food, though.
Hey, it could be worse.
It could be worse, yeah.
At least it's delicious.
It's delicious and we're
like, "Okay, this is the-
this is the portal."
We're cool with that.
Then there's kimchi
bulgogi bokkeumbap.
Basically kimchi fried rice.
But it fries into the
pan like paella.
So many great rice dishes
where that outer layer of
crispy stuff is just the best.
The tableside cooking.
I think people overlook that a lot.
You know,
this is like crepes suzette,
filleting a Dover sole.
Oh man, that's just
ridiculously delicious.
Will you be doing
this in 20 years?
It won't change.
If we did change tonight,
I would get a complaint.
And you'd have to
talk to your dad.
Oh, yeah.
That's-that's a problem.
What do you do if you're
a locavore in L.A.?
You look around.
What's local and delicious,
artisanal and authentic,
and as iconically L.A.
as it gets?
If you're Roy Choi,
you see tacos.
And with Kogi Truck, Roy
Choi brought one of the
first great mutation mash-ups
of Korean and Mexican
to the people.
What started as one truck
became four trucks and
three brick-and-mortar
restaurants to go with them.
For me, Kogi was always
one truck in my mind.
But then the lines
got big, you know?
And it evolved.
Hola, Herlindo.
Roy trained at the Culinary
Institute of America
and interned at Le Bernardin
in New York City.
He runs his trucks like you'd
expect of someone
with that background.
Within our food media
landscape, we've romanticized
certain compositions of
what a great chef and
a-and-and a great kitchen
are supposed to look and
smell and feel like.
But just because those are
beautiful doesn't mean that
this is not beautiful.
For me, I don't see mustard
plants and sheep grazing.
I see barbed wire and
telephone poles,
and I see puddles.
And, you know, all of that
stuff contribute to the
flavor of the food.
So, it's truly what I call
a terroir, you know, uh,
a regional food.
Okay, gracias.
And they're off.
Every lunch shift
and every evening,
the trucks' locations are
sent out over Twitter.
The locations change every day.
And people flock quicklyry day.
To find them, as the
lines can get long.
Very long.
I took a run with Roy as he
made his nightly rounds.
So, how often do you
make the full circuit
between all of your, uh,
various enterprises?
Twice a day, every day,
unless I'm doing something
crazy like this.
So it's kind of like I have
a-a huge Las Vegas hotel,
but the hallways are the
streets.
First stop: Chego, a
rice bowl place in the
Palms neighborhood.
These are my guys right here.
Hola!
Hey, Chef.
Kimchi spam, classic.
Yeah, this is the
menu right here.
A big bowl of rice with meat,
vegetables, and lots of flavor,
for less than 10 bucks.
Good deal.
But it's funny to hear
you're so sentimental
about the business
of feeding people.
It's a trippy state
of romanticism,
like I'm very hard-assed, too.
Like, you pack your own shit.
You get what you get.
If you complain, I take the
food out of your hands.
I give you your money back.
But within those rules,
there's a lot of love,
and there's-there's
a lot of care.
Across town in
Venice is A-Frame,
Roy's first brick-and-mortar.
This used to be an IHOP,
so everything's...
Oh, yeah?
Yeah, everything's
really narrow.
Ah, hence the, uh, the shape.
It's heavily influenced by
local takes on Hawaiianed
by cooking, not that you'd
necessarily notice.
Every dish designed to
be eaten with the hands.
What's good?
The baby back ribs are
air-dried, braised,
then breaded and fried.
Lean cod tacos treated
like shawarma.
Beer can crackling chicken:
it's brined, rotisseried,
then air-dried like
Peking duck, then fried.
Meanwhile, not too far
away, on Sawtelle,
a Kogi truck pulls up,
stops, reverses back to the
corner.
Before the awning is even up,
there's already a line.
Hungry people have been waiting
in cars or around the corner
ever since the Twitter
announcement 30 minutes ago.
Yeah, this is just.
I feel guilty.
I'm jumping the line, right?
Wow. What's the longest line
you've ever had at
one of these things?
600.
600 people for one truck?
Yeah.
The Kogi taco:
double-caramelized Korean
barbecue short rib on fresh
corn tortilla, salsa roja,
cilantro-onion-lime relish, and
a Napa cabbage/romaine slaw ind
a chili-soy vinaigrette.
Oh, yeah.
The-the rep for Kogi is
that we go everywhere.
We go to every single corner
of the county and the city.
We're not just going
to the hip areas.
What about fantastically...
Uh, what about Bel Air?
Can you pull up, like, on
a corner in a residential
area in Bel Air?
Yeah, yeah. We go.
What happens then?
Do you get rousted?
Or...?
No, no, they come out in
the Versace robe and, uh.
That I gotta see.
Yeah, yeah.
Beverly Hills, Beverly
Hills, uh, lunch is crazy.
Why should you be excited
about food trucks?
Because they allow
creative chefs like Roy,
without a lot of money,
to start creating and
selling their stuff,
introducing themselves to
the world, without
having to gather up
a million dollars or
credulous partners.
And they're affordable.
They're democratic.
And they are faster, better,
and infinitely preferable
to fast food like the king
and the clown and the colonel.
Stereotyping?
Coming... Look, how
do I put this?
Good Korean kids grow
up to be doctors,
lawyers, or engineers,
goes the story.
There are expectations.
But what if you're a bad Korean?
What if you were Korean
American and you just
didn't give a...?
What if you looked
around, asked yourself,
"Who am I?
Who am I supposed to be?
Where do I fit in society?"
and were unsatisfied with the
answers you were getting?
What if you were an insanely
talented artist and a small
startup company called Facebook
asked you to do some
murals in their offices,
and they paid you in stock,
and you became
ridiculously wealthy
and you still didn't give a...?
Well, then, you might
be David Choe.
Hi.
I'm Dave Choe.
Be like me.
Is that an AK piñata?
That is an AK-47 piñata.
Wow.
So, I mean, this place is in
downtown L.A., so I try to have
as many weapons, like,
hidden throughout.
I got ninja swords and
ninja stars and stuff.
You need. you need a puppy, man.
You need a puppy.
I do need a puppy.
I'm going to paint you today.
Is that cool?
Yeah, sure.
All right, so, just sit.
Sit?
Right there. And. sorry.
Don't usually paint this
early in the morning.
Okay.
I'm going to go more
expressionistic,
if you don't mind.
I want to know... you were
on record, you said,
you know, uh, young people,
uh, looking to follow
your road to success,
your advice is, whatever you do,
don't date a Korean girl.
Oh, okay.
I try to be open-minded
about things, right?
But, well, I'm racist.
You know, uh, for me,
I've given it a sh-shot.
And then I end up in a
situation where I feel like
I'm dating my mom.
So, what characteristics, uh,
in common were-were-were-w...
Overbearing.
Uh, jealous. Unreasonable.
Like, unrealistic about life.
Demanding. Like, it's...
I mean, I could go on and on.
But also, the men, too.
Like, if you're a woman, I
wouldn't never recommend
dating a Korean guy.
For the very few women out
there that are into Asian guys,
if you are going to go that
route, definitely go Chinese.
Yeah, come check it out.
Oh, yeah.
Whoa, awesome.
Wow.
I don't know;
what do you think?
Dude. I'm honored.
I've never had my
portrait done before.
Thank you, man.
Hey, man.
You're welcome.
And this shit going to be
worth some money on eBay
for sure.
Now I'm definitely
ready for Sizzler.
Nice.
Standing tall and prominent
amongst the many Asian and
Central American restaurants
in the community,
one place holds an unexpectedly
cherished position in the
collective memories of many
second-generation Korean
Americans.
I am personally unfamiliar
with the Sizzler brand.
Oh, I know it by name, but
never have I managed to
actually cross its doors.
After you.
Oh, thank you.
Wow.
How are you doing today?
I'm doing good, thank you.
How about yourself?
I'm doing fantastic.
I got my Sizzler outfit on.
So, here's the thing.
You can get, like, a steak and
then add the salad bar with it.
Right.
You get the best
bang for your buck.
Or you can just get
the salad bar.
I'm gonna have a
little bit of steak.
I am gonna go traditional and
just get just the salad bar.
And just the salad bar only.
Yeah. Thank you.
You can have a seat
anywhere you like.
Terrific. Thanks.
Excellent.
Oh, yeah.
Pouring for your elders.
Oh, now you're getting
all Korean on me.
Yeah. Super embarrassed right
now, because we're in Koreatown
and I'm taking you to eat at
Sizzler, which, for a lot of
Koreans, is the best
food in Koreatown. Um.
So, if you were eating
non-Korean, this was it?
We never ate out, ever.
And if we did, it
was McDonald's.
And if it was a birthday
and a special celebration,
you wanted to kick it up a
notch and go a little bit
more special, then
it was Sizzler.
This is a judgment-free zone,
where there are no mistakes,
a world to explore incongruous
combinations without
shame or guilt,
free of criticism
from snarkologists,
because there are no
snarkologists at Sizzler.
Obviously here's all the
accouterments for making a
nice nacho, taco salad.
Here... Right.
All the stuff for the.
Pasta.
Pasta, spaghetti, whatever.
The move is you get a hard taco
shell and you put meatballs in
it. This is Italian/Mexican
dining, and you make a meatball
taco. And there's nowhere else
in the world where you can have
this. You put three meatballs in
the taco, some guacamole, and
then you put all this nacho
cheese, all this other stuff.
Oh, I-I know what I'm doing.
I'm going for the full South of
the Border experience here.
All right.
Well, there you go.
Oh, no, no.
I'm not kidding around here.
Oh, yeah, now we're
talking, my friend.
It's a little bit nicer
than I remember.
There it is.
That's the best bread
that you can get,
so you tell me if you like that.
Oh, now, wait a minute.
Are you saying that the
cheese toast is complimentary?
It's complimentary.
And once we found that out,
we would order stacks of it.
So, it was our favorite
part of Sizzler.
And we were like, "We need to
figure out how to
manufacture this at home."
So, were you good Sizzler
customers, your family?
Do you think they were happy
to see you when you come in?
I mean.
Um.
I love this dish, man.
I might-I might, uh... when
I go back, I might have
to have a meatball taco.
Um, so, we didn't we, like,
gooched the system a little bit,
but not like
completely abused it.
There would be the guilt
associated with
we never eat out,
but now we're going out to
eat, so you better... eat.
You got to put down at
least three plates.
So, what'd you think
of the bread?
It's delicious.
Yeah. It's the best.
Oh, I totally get why this
would be a wonderland.
Yeah, everything's really good.
For you, Sizzler, a
happy place, still.
Lots of memories.
It's satisfying.
We need more of
this cheese bread.
Something Dave Choe and Roy
Choi have in common is
that they may be Korean
American, but they are also
very much creatures of L.A.
And what is L.A.?
L.A. is Mexican,
Central American,
Filipino, Vietnamese, Thai,
Samoan, Bangladeshi.
Everybody who's left their mark
continues to shape the town,
determine its character.
K-Town exists right upside
its Latino neighbors, and
I guess it's natural
that both Choe and Choi
identify very much with
Mexican street culture.
Few things embody that
particularly Southern
California Latino street
culture more than low-riding.
Estevan Oriol is a photographer.
Go on the other
side of that pole.
Chronicler of everything
iconic at the crossroads of
hip-hop, design, tattooing,
fashion, and low-riding.
The old timers, they
used to cut the coils or
put bricks or sandbags in their
trunk to make them lower.
And then around the '70s
is when it got popular.
Why these particular
models of cars?
It's pretty much always
been, uh, late '50s,
all the way through the
'60s, and into the '70s.
And then the '80s came up.
They started bringing in the
Cadillacs and the Regals.
The most classic, well-known car
for low-riding probably
is the '64 Impala.
How many Korean
low-riders are there?
There's a few Asian ones
sprinkled in the other clubs.
More Asians, more more
Koreans than 15 years ago?
We're seeing a crossover
with the food.
Right.
Uh... For the most part,
things are starting to get
a lot more open.
If you're asking, I think
there's going to be a lot more
Asian/Hispanic mixed babies
coming up in the future.
I ain't mad at that.
Ideal low-riding, is about
getting appreciated by
the people who best appreciate
the traditions and techniques,
the getting it right.
For that, you head to East L.A.
The most famous, notorious
street in L.A. is,
uh, Whittier Boulevard,
because of the history of it.
And then Crenshaw Boulevard
and South Central.
So, that's gonna be your
most critical audience?
And, uh, mo- and at the
same most appreciative?
Yeah, the ones that you want
to see your car, you know?
It's a slow-moving piece of
art. And you treat the car like
a piece of art, acutely
aware of the dangers: cops,
for whom you are a target;
potholes;
other cars.
In East L.A., you see
people ooh and ah.
You see expressions change
from, "Who the... is that?"
to, "Nice ride."
That was, like, a
full-fledged gang member.
Yeah.
You know, giving us, like,
props, giving us respect,
you know?
First you build a
car for yourself.
But at the same time you're
building it for the
streets, you know?
You're building it
for the people.
You want them to appreciate it.
Within the borders of Koreatown,
it's not just Koreans.
There are new
arrivals every day.
There is, in fact, an
official Little Bangladesh
right in the middle of K-town.
Oh, man, this is all so.
It smells so good in here.
Uh, yeah, this is going to work.
So you're not short of
options around here.
Nah. You can get tacos
across the street,
Korean bibimbap right next door,
and then get goat stew.
You can pray to
Mohammed or Buddha.
A tiny mosque next door where
services are held
five times a day.
Just talking to a guy in
the parking lot who said,
"This is the first Little
Bangladesh in America."
Yeah.
And that just happened,
like, two years ago.
Like, we went to
sleep, we woke up,
and it was Little Bangladesh.
Here at Sawada, step right
in to some curried goat,
samosas, tandoori chicken.
Oh, yeah, and this:
Lahori fish curry, with no
small amount of chilies.
It's such fragrant,
aromatic, delicious food.
This is really good.
What good food are you likely
to find within the
confines of Koreatown?
We have El Salvadoran and
Guatemalan all around.
Koreans all throughout.
Pakistani and Bangladesh food.
Yeah, Oaxaca takes over
all of Eighth Street.
Why Oaxaca? Just that's
the way it worked out?
Mm hmm.
Well, you know how it goes.
Yeah.
One guy showed up.
Filipino fast food
just behind us.
Mm hmm.
And then a bunch of
riff-raffs in between.
Yeah. Well, Filipinos oughta
be very proud of their food.
Mm hmm.
Underrepresented.
I think they're going through
kind of what we went through,
where the glass hasn't been
broken yet to-to translate it
but still keep the
core and soul of it.
But it tastes delicious.
A few blocks over, the
iconic Filipino fast food
chain Jollibee's.
Laugh all you want,
but ask any Filipino.
They love this drive-through
mutation for specialties like
this fried Spam sandwich thing.
But it's the desserts where
it gets really crazy.
Decisions, decisions.
Here we go.
Uh, we'll take one Aloha
burger and then one Spam
little big bite.
All right. Anything else?
Uh, let's do a Halo halo, and that's it.
All right.
Oh, look at that.
What is what-what is that?
That's a halo halo.
Oh, yeah, halo halo.
Dig deep and you hit delicious
stratas of red beans,
white beans, and chickpeas,
cubes of red and green
Jell-O, young white coconut,
shaved ice- and is that flan?
It makes no goddamn
sense at all.
I love it.
Part of every Pinoy
Filipino's life, halo halo.
Nutsy, man.
I got to take a picture of that.
It's oddly beautiful.
All right.
You know I'm getting a bite
of that little what is it?
A little.
It's a little big bite.
Little big bite.
Favorite thing in the world.
No, don't say that.
That's actually... I like that.
It's good, right?
Aloha. I mean, it
just sounds magical.
Is there, like, pineapple
in there or something?
Yes. Hence the "aloha."
That's a very tasty burger.
Nice char.
Asian fast food.
It's fast food, but
it's made by like it
was just a single family
owned restaurant.
What family made this?
Yeah, maybe.
Maybe-maybe not your family.
The Jetsons.
You know?
You like it?
It's actually very tasty.
Every single thing
you like here.
Wow. There's so
much I don't know.
It's true, Dad.
We all look the same.
I love it.
He may be a Korean gone bad,
but Dave Choe still tries,
best he can, to be a good son.
He bought them this house in
Los Feliz and visits for
family meals often.
In fact, when we first met,
sensing it had been a long time
without a true home-cooked time
meal, he invited me
to dinner with them.
So, guests are not unusual.
Jane Cho is an amazing cook.
It's going to be very delicious.
Mom? Dad?
Look who's here.
Hello.
Mom, Tony's here.
Can you smell something?
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Good stuff.
Yeah, all the good
stuff's coming.
Maybe somebody going
to hire me later.
Okay, which ones are you?
Are you the eldest?
I'm the middle.
I'm the suicidal pirate.
Oh, already signs
of trouble appear.
My older brother is the
hip-hop Santa, and my...
He was the oldest.
Right.
He'd beat me up.
I'd beat him up.
And then he would just cry.
I'll show you my dad's painting.
Hey, Dad?
Yeah?
Hey, come over
here for a second.
When did you paint this, Dad?
30 years ago?
Uh, '73. 1973.
Every Christmas, he
unrolls it, um, and just,
like, Scotch tapes
it to the wall.
And my Mom's the artist
in the family now.
So, this is a family of artists.
The Choe's are devout
Christians, which is not unusual
in the Korean community.
But they are unusual in that
they're both artists of a sort.
Jane treats the house like
an ongoing art project,
drawing sunglasses
on family pictures,
stapling angels to Dave's
paintings that have hung
in the White House, getting
crazy with the glue gun,
adorning wreaths with Happy Meal
toys, sticker-bombing the
kitchen with birds, cows,
spaceships piloted
by her three boys.
She is relentlessly,
energetically, and inarguably
creative.
She brainwashed me.
From the time we were
kids, she'd-she was like,
"You're the best
artist in the world.
You're the best
artist in the world."
You are.
Oh, thanks.
But now she's telling me
she's going to be the best
artist in the world.
So, she's very competitive.
She said she's gonna destroy me.
Awesome.
Food is ready.
So, do you want to explain
what everything is, Mom?
The food I prepared tonight
is a very common Korean food.
Which is a beef ribs, uh, stew.
The kimchi's looking fresh.
Yeah, the kimchi's fresh.
Today is, uh, chestnut rice.
No one has this kind of rice.
It's a special rice.
Special rice for Tony, you know.
And then stuffed peppers.
Oh, that's David's favorite.
Chung po mook:
seaweed and jellied mung bean.
Vermicelli noodles
with shitake mushrooms
and vegetables.
Avocado egg rolls, fried
squid, and shrimps.
Potato pancake.
Often at the Cho house there's
a few Mexican dishes
sprinkled in as well.
It is always a great meal,
I can tell you that.
Thanks, Mom.
This is delicious.
This is awesome.
It is indeed. Thank you.
I love it.
During the riots of '92, Jim
and Jane Choe worked as
real estate agents and
property managers.
So the destruction in Koreatown
had a direct impact
on their lives.
The Chos watched from home
as the chaos unfolded on TV.
After the riots, Jim
Choe wrote a letter
to the editor that published
in the L.A. Times.
I am extremely angry
with the LAPD
for their outrageous action.
While the cops let looters
run wild and rape our city,
they somehow had time to
bother Korean shop owners
guarding their stores.
How can the owner of a business
just sit back and watch his
life be burned to the ground?
David would have a
different reaction.
My brother stole a car,
and we went into, like,
all the neighborhoods and
then quickly realized it
wasn't, like, about race.
It was just about
people stealing stuff.
And-but we were out looting.
We were causing chaos.
And, you know, I don't think
we got anything good.
I think I got a TV stand.
Was it life-changing for you?
It's like you grow up and
you things are explained to you.
Like, here's the police.
They're not doing anything
they're supposed to do.
There's just, like, normal men
and women of society just, like,
acting like animals.
And I was like, "Oh,
everything I've,
like, been taught and-and
learned my whole life is just
disintegrating before my eyes."
But, in the end, we're-you
know, from great disasters
come great things, right?
I mean, Koreatown burned down.
But it's like we own L.A. now.
It's, like, half of L.A.
Now it's Korean culture.
K-pop and Psy all over the world
influence, you know?
The filmmakers.
All the-all the top, uh,
Korean filmmakers are in
Hollywood.
Yeah. Oh, yeah.
Korean, uh, culture.
What about me?
Yeah, you.
Artists, right.
Yeah, right. Yeah.
Except you.
Sorry.
Sorry, David.
It's incredible.
Today, I went into
all the ways...
Different ways you guys used
to beat us when we were kids.
The stress positions,
like, you know.
Yeah, but what.
All the Korean punishments.
What's remarkable to
me is that every kid.
Right.
I mean, all Korean kids.
Yeah, all Korean kids.
The same position.
Holding-you either hold a book.
Oh, yeah.
That's the way we learn from
the generation to generation.
We don't know why.
To take a peek into the dark
heart of the Korean psyche,
maybe it helps to get
familiar with Han.
It's a concept that,
for non-Koreans,
can be difficult to fully grasp.
All right.
You want it? Here we go.
Han denotes a collective
feeling of oppression and
isolation in the face
of overwhelming odds.
It connotes aspects of lament
and unavenged injustice.
Wow.
In some occasions,
anthropologists have recognized
Han as cultural-specific
medical condition.
Someone who dies
of Han is... Right.
Is said to have died of
It's a heartburn.
Wow. I mean, the-uh,
it's been described to
me in a way that made
it sound benign.
That-this is a burning, uh,
sense of injustice, besiegement,
and-and desire for revenge.
The Han is the reason why,
like, we are who we are.
But it's also the same reason
why I won't marry
a Korean woman.
No. You never know.
No, I know, Mom.
He's cute.
Main drag of K-Town.
Another mini mall among many.
Karaoke?
No.
This is the best
dumpling spot in town.
My mom would just order all
these dumplings and just, like,
leave 'em on my door, 'cause,
uh, she's not allowed in my house.
And then...
I just said, uh, "Where
are you getting these?"
You know, my mom likes
to withhold information.
So, I finally got it out of her.
Myung In Dumplings,
where they serve a mix
between Korean and Chinese.
Each plate handmade
to order, my friends.
Opened in 2007 on
Olympic Boulevard,
it's run by Yu Jin,
a Korean by way of
Shenyang Province in China.
Been coming here for
about two years now.
Uh huh?
There's no one ever in here.
Every time I've ever come
in-and, uh, I don't
understand how they're open.
They're the best
dumplings I've ever had.
Maybe people just get 'em to go.
Right.
They all look like
buttholes, actually.
But... Kind of. Yeah,
pre-prolapse.
Wang mandu.
King dumpling.
Thick dough, stuffed to
the gills with pork,
kimchi, and vegetables.
Precisely made,
weighed, and crimped.
Steamed until soft.
Eat.
Wow.
That's nearly the
size of your head.
Yeah, you know, it's like pizza.
I'll eat 'em cold, too.
Right.
Save two and have
'em for dinner.
And mandu.
Smaller, with thinner
dumpling skins,
served with red chili paste.
Those are the dessert ones.
Those got red bean in it.
Oh, God. Wow.
Oh, these are delicious.
These are just, like, so huge.
Go for it.
So, would this be classically
post-drinking food or
pre-drinking food?
Lay down a base of
absorbent material?
Yeah, I mean, there's
a lot of bread here.
But I've already drank.
I'm just, uh, falling under
peer pressure right now.
I'll be one of the
cool guys, so.
I like this place already.
Good signage. It's important.
Yeah. The sign's awesome.
If that sign does
not sing to you,
then we cannot be friends.
Mari, hi.
Hi, David. How are you?
This is my Uncle Tony.
This is Mari.
How you doing?
This is, uh, Harry
Kim, aka Guam Cruise.
Here's more Koreans right here.
Here's more Koreans.
Some friends of Cho seem
to favor this place.
They are a thirsty
and diverse bunch.
I'm asking everybody:
stress position as a child?
Did you have to do the,
uh, knees forward?
Oh, you know about this.
It went right into it.
Stress positions?
Oh, we did that.
You did that? See?
There's this.
There's this, too.
The speed with which they
assume the position.
You had to hold a bucket
over your head with water.
Water? Wow.
What if your arms get tired?
They make you do it again
another 45 minutes to
an hour, you know?
The whole thing is
doing it again.
Look, I'm not Korean.
I'm not Asian.
I'm a white boy from the suburb.
But I noticed something
over time in my K-Town
adventure.
Similar anecdotes,
you might say.
You know, they've done
this quite a bit.
So they came up with a new one.
I was very aware that all my
Korean friends-no matter how
creative or successful-seem
strangely haunted by something.
But I never knew this.
How do you do it?
Oh, the... It goes
up the ass like this,
and then-it's like opening up
a umbrella inside someone.
You do this to your friends?
Or college.
They think it's hilarious.
And adults do that
shit to each other.
What the hell that's
about, I can only guess.
Cheers... Cheers.
Koreans gone bad.
You're Korean now, officially.
Pretty much any Korean
you meet anywhere,
you can take it for
granted they like food,
that they're passionate about
food, particularly their food,
which of all the immigrant
cuisines has probably been
messed with the least.
Unlike many other new arrivals,
Koreans seem to have been the
most unwilling to
accommodate Western tastes,
Maybe that's why it took us so
much time to love the stuff.
Beverly Tofu House, like
so many of K-Town's
finer establishments, is
tucked away in the corner
of a strip mall.
This is one of my
favorite spots.
This is where I've been
coming for almost 20 years.
This is a soup that's just,
like-it's kind of Korean,
but its really more L.A.,
and so.
So this is not a direct
transplant from Korea?
It became what we're about
to have here in L.A.
Interesting.
They're different because of
the ingredients
we couldn't find.
Right.
But never thinking about
pleasing the American palate,
just to make ourselves happy.
Soondubu is the thing to get.
A fiery, tongue-searing,
ass-burning tofu soup that'll
make you forget every bad thing
you ever thought about tofu.
A spicy, spicy red broth
and tofu are the base.
We're talking soft tofu
here, with the texture of,
like, burrata.
From there, you got a
handful of variations.
But the most common is with
kimchi and a bit of everything.
Beef, oysters, mussels, clams.
Oh, and tableside?
They crack an egg in there.
Wow.
Right in there. Cool.
That looks completely awesome.
Well, we-we better
wait for this to cool,
I'm guessing?
Yeah.
So, how do we eat this?
We just spoon it over rice?
Uh, yeah, yeah,
spoon it over rice.
Mix it in.
Mm. That's good.
Mm.
Yeah, all tofu should be spicy,
by my way of thinking.
It's so good.
Yeah. It's really good.
Koreans can well remember
when nobody was interested in
their food. was interested
in Now it's confusingly
au courant.
Must be strange for the owners,
who've just been doing what
they've been doing for years.
Like, for example, like,
us sitting here like this,
the questions a lot of people
are asking me in Korean, like,
I'm telling them we're filming,
you know, we're trying to
show a piece of Koreatown.
The-the number one
question is they're not mad
or vindictive is, "Why?"
It's still, "Why?"
Like, why.
Why would we be interested?
Why would you waste your time?
There's other things to do.
It's an extraordinarily
beautiful and delicious thing.
But, see, that's the thing,
is the beauty is just
already a given.
It's already a part
of the fabric.
So it's like, you know,
why congratulate you?
You know?
There's no reason to
congratulate you,
because this is like what we do.
That sounds awful, honestly.
That sounds, like, totally joy.
It's, like, totally joyless.
Yeah.
Uh, what do your parents
want you to be when
you grow up?
For me, a doctor or lawyer.
Right. You're obviously
not a doctor or a lawyer.
Did you finish college?
I finished college and I went
to one year of law
school and I walked out.
Right. So, you're a bad Korean.
Yeah, I'm a bad Korean.
If I was a mediocre accountant,
it'd be better than
being a top chef.
Uh, according to who?
According to Korean culture.
Right.
According to Korean
uncles and aunts.
And it's just-it
doesn't register that
that is a profession.
You know?
I wouldn't have to explain
myself if I just
said I was a CPA.
Right.
Never. You know, That's-that's.
..that's weird...
I know. You still got
some 'splaining to do.
Still. To just get it across
that I... that I cook,
and that there was this
phenomenon that happened on the
streets of L.A. that changed
and opened up Korean
culture to-to the world.
What does it mean to
be Korean American?
Does one create one's own world?
I don't know that I'm any
smarter about that now than
when I first came to K-Town
in the middle of the night
and discovered a strange
and fabulous and delicious
slice of America I'd
never known was there.
But I'm trying to figure it out.