"Chapter One.
"To fall in love with Asia
is one thing.
"To fall in love in Asia
is another.
"Both have happened to me.
"The Star Ferry to Kowloon
at night...
"the lights of Hong Kong
behind me...
"it's a gift,
"a dream,
"a curse.
"The best thing,
"the happiest thing,
"yet, also,
the loneliest thing
in the world."
♪ I took a walk
through this ♪
♪ Beautiful world
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good
in this ♪
♪ Beautiful world
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
- ♪ La, la
- ♪ Sha la, la, la, la
♪ Sha la, la, la, la
- ♪ Sha la, la, la
- Sha la, la, la, la ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la, la, la
♪
All of us, when we travel,
look at the places we go,
the things we see
through different eyes.
And how we see them is shaped
by our previous lives.
The books we've read.
The films we've seen.
The baggage we carry.
Years ago, when I first watched
the stunningly beautiful films
of director Wong Kar-wai,
it shaped forever
the way I'd see Hong Kong.
From that point on, my hopes,
my expectations of this city
would be seen through that lens,
a lens that was,
in nearly every case,
pointed by, focused by this man:
Christopher Doyle,
long-time resident of Hong Kong,
known by his Mandarin name
Du Kefeng.
And it won't go away.
His earlier works
with Wong Kar-wai
were distinguished
by unspeakably gorgeous images
of beautiful people
moving through spaces
both unfamiliar
and yet painfully intimate.
Alternately jagged,
frenzied, innovative,
languid, composed,
chaotic.
I obsessed over his work,
fetishized it,
longed to see Hong Kong
like the characters
in so many of his films
longed for each other.
And I feared,
like those characters,
I would be denied.
I was wrong.
The good thing
about the escalator,
it's the best place
to watch people.
♪
The mid-level escalators.
7 million people in Hong Kong,
many of them flowing
through this mile-long
escalator system.
It's Chris Doyle's happy place.
What do you look at
in Hong Kong?
And you've lived here how long?
- Oh, 20, 30 years, almost.
- So...
I-I mean, I've spent more time
in this space
than I have spent in bars.
♪
Look at this, we have people
coming and going.
We have the city passing us by.
We have... to me,
the energy is the noise,
is the people.
I mean, the films that we made
are only this way
because we made them here.
I've made 12 films
within 2 square kilometers
of where we are right now.
In fact, we're gonna pass
by my apartment,
which is
the most famous apartment
in Hong Kong.
You shot in there, right?
It doesn't exist anymore
because the energy changes.
♪
But to tune into the energy...
Ah-ha, hello...
Then we have a movie.
Then we have this conversation.
Then we have something
that the cameraman
is gonna fall over backwards
trying to film.
I think you're just
preparing all the time.
For example,
you watch some of my movies.
- Yes.
- Or we read a book.
- Yeah.
- Or we go out
drinking with friends.
Yeah.
And then bang, bang,
we're doing something
which all of those energies
focus in a way that somehow
connects with other people.
Hello.
What do you want in life?
I mean, you do understand
the impulse, right?
People see work
that you've long ago
just like moved on from.
And they get, you know...
They get a hard-on,
and it won't go away.
I mean, come on, it's...
But the great pleasure is,
I did it...
and it's done.
You want me to reshoot
"Chunking Express"?
♪
But of course
they all do, don't they?
But I don't know how I did it!
Is there a value in
just beautiful people
and objects
moving through space
in beautiful ways?
Is there a value to the color
of a pomegranate?
Yeah, yeah, there is.
Exactly!
This is our challenge,
is to celebrate that.
So-called "beauty" is not,
you know,
"My make-up is so good,
and then I...
I lifted my face a bit."
No.
Beauty is the darkness
and the pleasure
of embracing that
and that giving you
something more
of your experience of life.
I read a script, and it says,
"He looked so sophisticate"...
How do you film "sophisticated"?
How do you convey
the taste of a chili?
We'll never know, but...
the privilege we've been given
is, number one, we've
experienced it personally.
So it becomes part
of who you are.
♪
Leaf Dessert Noodle Shop
is a hundred-year-old
holdout in Central.
Chris has been coming here
for years,
both to film and for this:
Choy noodle soup for him,
and beef brisket noodles
with wonton for me.
♪
Ah, here we go.
So this is family food.
Yeah.
You don't know.
I don't know.
This is the most famous
noodle stand
in cinema history, in Hong Kong.
Has he been
in the films himself?
Many, many, many times.
This is our next nomination
for Hong Kong Film Awards.
Ah, man.
It's good too.
♪
I don't watch movies.
I don't...
watch other people's work.
I can't draw,
but I know if you put this...
♪
And you move it around a bit...
it may take you somewhere.
So, to me, collage is like
the unexpected put together
to perhaps suggest something
that you never thought of.
♪
Our experience actually
gives us a distance
and gives us
this wonderful freedom,
which is called time.
I thought time was running out,
but it's not.
Time is actually
being more condensed,
because we're more focused.
♪
Now our job as artists
is to show you the world
that you think you knew
and celebrate it.
In my wonderful experience
and wonderful journey
with a person
called Wong Kar-wai,
it finally...
After all the films we made,
we made a film called
"In the Mood for Love."
♪
I think everything we did
before then
was preparation.
I think that's it.
If you find this
in your life,
you actually say one sentence
or you make one dish
or you make one image
that is true.
That's pretty good,
because not many people
get that.
♪
The love of money
and shiny new things
is slowly but surely
erasing the past.
So before it's gone,
this is a reminder
of how Hong Kong used to eat,
at dai pai dongs like this one
in Sham Shui Po.
Cheap, delicious food
served from open-air stalls.
Pull up a plastic stool,
crack a beer,
fire up the wok.
So tell me,
what is a dai pai dong?
- "Dai" is "big."
- Big.
"Pai" is "license."
And "dong" is "place."
- So it's...
- So it's "big license place."
Right, and how many of these
are left in, uh...
- 28.
- Whoa, whoa, whoa.
Only 28?
Only 28.
Why? Why don't...
Because the government
doesn't...
They want, uh, street clean.
That's...
That ain't right.
Yeah.
The name of the place
is Keung Kee,
and Gaza Cheung
recently took over as chef.
How do you get
one of the last licenses
for a dai pai dong?
Accident.
- Accident?
- Yeah.
This license is hold
by somebody else,
not by me, but this place,
it's been around for 40 years.
Now, did you change the menu?
Same menu?
No, I changed the menu...
- Right.
- And start a typical,
old-fashioned Chinese meal.
Drunken chicken.
Hacked-up birds
cooked in hot pot,
with medicinal roots and herbs
that will no doubt
make me strong.
What will I feel after I eat it?
- Hyper. I can use...
- Hyper?
- Hyper.
- Energy?
Strength?
Yeah, energy!
Vitality?
No penis in there?
No! No.
- No penis in there.
- I wouldn't eat that.
Myself.
Really?
- Unless you want.
- I've had a fair amount
of penis on this show.
Oh.
♪
A clay-pot dish of fish tripes,
cooked in an egg custard,
topped with
a crispy fried yóu zhá.
Wait a minute, is that egg?
Egg.
So it's like a...
Like a quiche.
Try it.
It's pretty damn good.
Crispy, custardy.
I've never had
anything like this
anywhere in China.
Movies?
Oh, yes.
You know Wong Kar-wai?
I do.
- Do you like him?
- Uh, I love Wong Kar-wai.
Which is your favorite
Wong Kar-wai film?
Oh, "In the Mood of Love."
Me too.
It's the most beautiful film
ever made.
There you are.
No way.
♪
Hong Kong is a mixed culture
with East and West.
- Right.
- Because of the 160 years
as a British colony,
Hong Kong really developed
its own, unique culture.
The people in Hong Kong
really want to see that.
Or for the foreign
people like you,
you want to see, "Oh, it's
really old Hong Kong."
♪
All this is disappearing.
All this could be gone.
It's vanishing before our eyes.
♪
Simon Go is a photographer
who's documented
to 200 small, family-run shops
in the city,
many of them already shuttered.
I go everywhere in Hong Kong.
And I really want to...
To preserve the memories.
Especially in these few years,
I found so many
old shops disappeared
because of some
urban development.
And I think I've got
a mission to preserve that.
♪
To feel sentimental
about the past
is unusual for Hong Kong.
Hong Kong has always been
about changing.
- Yes.
- It's always embraced change.
Realistically,
can these businesses
be protected?
Ah...
It's really difficult to say.
But I think that
when the government
and the Hong Kong people
see more about
our own unique culture,
for many people, try their best
to fight for that.
China Café in Mong Kok,
what's called a cha chaan teng,
or "tea restaurant,"
serving a particularly bizarro
but much-loved bit
of Hong Kong history.
Simon's been coming here
for over 40 years
and orders his favorite:
fried pork cutlet
over rice, with tomato sauce.
Oh!
Thank you.
Wow.
This rice is very popular
in Hong Kong.
- Very popular.
- Especially for a schoolboy,
I came... every time I came
to a cha chaa teng,
I ordered this.
I think it's a...
It's a perfect match for me.
And, well, I had to try this:
macaroni, Spam,
and egg... soup.
I have no idea
where this came from.
I mean, is it a soup?
Is it a stew?
What do I...
Should I break it up?
No, it's okay.
Because in cha chaa teng,
nobody care about...
- Table rules.
- Table manner
or anything, you know?
♪
You know, food and smell
always bring forth
so many memories.
I still remember my parents
and my grandparents,
they would make
some dumpling at home.
And they really worked hard
for prepare the meal
for the family.
The taste is really great
and really sweet.
And...
after my grandmother
and my mother passed away,
I have not any chance
to eat that again.
But about four
or five years ago,
my Auntie made them for me.
When I put it to my mouth,
I burst into tears.
My wife behind...
comforts me.
Speechless.
The taste, the food
recalls so many...
So many memories for me.
♪
In the beginning,
Hong Kong was this:
a fishing village,
like this one.
♪
There you go.
You're gonna give me a camera?
Hell, yeah.
All right, guys, well...
All right,
proceed to smoke weed.
- Can I roll?
- Yeah!
How do I roll?
That button, here.
Yeah, there.
Oh, that's so complicated,
I have to press the button.
♪
Can I close down the aperture
a little bit?
Where is the aperture?
Can you tell me?
You're on a 2-8.
Yeah, you're on it.
I don't smile a lot
on this show,
by the way, but I'm smiling now.
♪
I want to shoot you guys.
So tell us,
you behind the camera,
what are you seeing?
I'm trying really hard
to get footage now.
Really?
Why is that?
This is one of
the most beautiful shots
I've ever made.
I've never made a shot
about cameras before.
So tell us,
what is a camera to you?
I think it's a good thing
to hide behind.
I think, Anthony,
we have one of
the most beautiful images
in all of your film.
This is why we're on...
It's why we're on the damn boat.
Do we have a movie?
- We have a movie.
Are you sure we...
I'm worried we didn't record it!
We'll find out in a second.
Then we have to do it in person.
Oh, sit.
Ha!
♪
Tai O is one of
the last fishing villages
in Hong Kong,
on the western side
of Lantau Island.
The families here
have made their living
from the sea for generations.
For Chris Doyle
and his codirector Jenny Suen,
it's a return to the location
of their recent film,
"The White Girl."
So where are we?
I recognize it.
We're in the Venice
of Hong Kong, obviously.
I mean, there we are.
We've got the canals.
We got canals going
in all directions here.
We got
the most beautiful bridges
outside of Venice.
Don't forget, "Hong Kong"
means "fragrant harbor."
Mmhmm.
So it's a good place
to eat, I guess.
Well, you have experience here.
You guys shot a film here.
'Cause you shot like right here.
We literally shot right here.
This is it.
This is the main location
of the film.
This is the main-actually,
when we were prepping the film,
we had looked at
all the fishing villages
around Hong Kong.
And this one
was the most complete,
in the sense that
it's a real community,
as opposed to, you know,
something closer to the city.
And it's a metaphor
for Hong Kong,
because we feel Hong Kong
is disappearing also.
And so much of what we're doing
is to keep something
that makes us unique alive.
♪
For lunch, there's corn
and fish maw soup...
♪
Fried fish maw
with dried scallop,
dried shrimp, and pork.
♪
Salted egg yolks
are left in the sun
to cure slightly,
then served over rice.
Crispy pork belly
cooked in shrimp paste
and yu choy.
♪
I drink to heaven!
Under which we stand together
and enjoy this.
We drink to earth because...
Well, there's no more earth,
but we drink to sea today.
I drink to heaven,
I drink to earth,
and I drink to you.
Isn't that
the most beautiful way
to share a drink with friends?
I have a tricky moral
question, though, for you.
A moral question? Me?
- Yes. Yeah.
- Oh, great.
I was...
I'm a recovering Catholic.
I can answer any moral question.
We are changing the world
by looking at it
through cameras, as...
As happens every time
you look at real people,
the real world,
real places.
Where does that fall
in your comfort zone?
When the character
of the place changes.
Ah, yeah, it's true.
We're part of the problem,
not... right?
The only way is just
not to be cynical about it.
We want the audience
to feel a certain way.
But if the process is open,
then I think it has integrity.
If we've done what we love
in integrity,
if we've tried to be
as true as possible
to how we see things,
perhaps, perhaps...
Mmhmm.
It transfers.
♪
The only function of what we do
with art or with anything
is to give voice
to the unspoken,
to give it a form
that it's never been
perceived in before.
We can't change
the evolution of history
or the gentrification...
You can't stop that.
But at least you can say,
"Look what you're losing."
That's all... that's the only...
All we can do is give
an image to an idea.
♪
The infamous Chunking Mansions
sit right smack in the center
of high-end Tsim Sha Tsui,
right around the corner
from swank hotels
and surrounded by shops
selling luxury goods
and designer brands.
5 housing blocks and 17 stories
containing, well,
everything and everybody
who the rest of Hong Kong
would like to ignore.
While many locals avoid it
for its, well, reputation
and for some
of its less legitimate
business enterprises,
shall we say,
it offers cheap rooms and asylum
for people,
specifically refugees,
from all over the world
and even a taste of home.
When I met Selena
about 15 years ago,
we decided to open
a restaurant in Hong Kong.
But most
of the African guys here,
to be honest,
they don't have money.
Most of them, they are refugees.
So how do we sell
the food to them?
So we opened us a kitchen
for all of them to come
and cook their food,
enjoy and meet new friends.
Then, uh,
they can enjoy themself.
That's how we started.
I moved from Hong Kong
to Canada.
My husband moved from Ghana
to China and Hong Kong.
But we know that if you move
to another country,
it's not easy.
So we try to provide
a place for them
to feel like they are at home.
After we have this place,
we see a lot of happy face.
I see a lot of them
gains weight.
They have a big tummy.
And I say, "Okay, that's..."
"what we are doing
is the right thing."
♪
Tell me about this building.
It's legendary, of course.
For me, I think it's...
It's really a very unique place.
Like it's a place
that when I come out
from my home,
it's a place that I know
I'm gonna pass in some way.
It's a place I meet new friends.
It's a place that gives me
a lot of confidence.
When I'm in here,
I know where to go.
I know who to talk to.
I know which food to eat.
In the '60s and '70s,
the city relied
on cheap refugee labor.
No longer.
Today, most refugees
are seeking asylum
anywhere they can find it.
Many here are stuck in limbo.
Can't go back, can't work,
can't leave.
Jahan fled Iran six years ago
just ahead of the secret police.
Shermarke is a student
from Somalia,
who had
equally compelling reasons
to leave his home.
What brought you here?
The basic reason
for me to come here
was finding a safe haven, right?
- Yes.
- I mean,
you're in a safe place.
That's the only thing
you're thinking about
in that moment.
You came from Iran.
- Yeah.
- Why did you come
to Hong Kong?
Why did I leave Iran?
The short version goes,
they wanted to kill me,
and I said,
"No thank you."
I end up here.
It was... It wasn't something
that I would dream of
or I planned.
I have no idea
about the currency,
the government.
No, nothing at all.
♪
How long have you been here now?
Uh, going to be six years.
- Six years?
- Yeah.
They tell me that
even if you be accepted
as a refugee,
you are not welcome to stay.
You have to be resettled
in another country.
- Right.
- They are telling me
while you're staying,
you are not allowed
to work, study, even volunteer,
or contribute in society
in any way.
But you can exist.
That's it.
You can exist, yeah.
- You believe me or not...
- Hold on one sec.
Let me reset.
- How is it going?
- Good.
You believe everything he says?
- Yes.
- Oh, Jesus!
I think we're good.
We got a lot of bread.
But if they can bring that
up for eating...
Actually, they brought it in.
Let's just leave it there.
Can we push you
a little bit to your right?
All right?
Let me know
when everybody's up.
Roll sound.
♪
So what is your hope?
What are your prospects
of being able to go to America?
I would love to go to America.
But it's not the way
U.S. sees me
qualified to be there.
Right before
Donald Trump was appointed
to be the American president,
I had my last interview.
And then, unfortunately,
you know what he did?
He banned six, seven countries,
including my country.
So now, currently, I'm...
I'm studying
and I'm planning to move
to somewhere else.
♪
To be honest, um...
I'm not a big fan of hope.
I have no hope in the system.
Or I have no hope
in someone gonna
get me out of here.
I'm trying by my own.
I'm trying to be
my best as possible here
and seek by myself
for ways to get out
of Hong Kong and the system.
♪
♪ You've said you've tried
♪ He just can't comprehend
♪ What is that thing
♪ That we're trying
to defend ♪
♪ No one can decide
♪ How this is going to end
♪
♪ It's in my hot blood
♪ I can't, I can't
♪ I can't,
I can't ♪
♪ I can't, I can't
♪ I can't do it anymore
♪ I can't,
I can't ♪
♪ I can't, I can't
♪ I can't,
I can't ♪
♪
Have you eaten
anything this morning?
Uh, no.
I'm hungry, man.
Oh, come to me.
There we go.
"David Boring"
is a five-piece band
fronted by Janice Lau
and Jason Cheung,
their backgrounds
in architecture and medicine
seemingly at odds
with their somewhat more
nihilistic music.
You know this place.
You've eaten here before
many times, 'cause you guys
went to school
right in the neighborhood.
It's very popular with students.
We always come after deadlines,
so first thing in the morning,
4:00 a.m., all students.
- Yeah.
- And the place is
even more crowded
than right now, yeah.
What are the things
that you see disappearing
in Hong Kong that are
most alarming to you?
Certainly a degree of freedom.
As someone who's
born and raised here,
you can definitely feel a change
in the last five to ten years.
And what we are trying to do
with our music
is to address
that sort of change.
Are you able
to say what you want?
- Yeah.
- Yes.
- In ten years?
I don't know.
Right now, yes.
Say what you want.
You are actually allowed
to play music.
You're allowed to do
whatever you want.
But there's no venue.
There's no space
for you to practice.
I think this is how
the society is limiting
the possibility of young people,
in that sense.
Whatever your feelings
about how things are going,
some things are a constant,
a comfort, a birthright.
Like egg custard buns.
Egg yolks,
sweetened condensed milk.
When steamed,
the custard returns
to more molten form.
Braised chicken feet.
First fried, then braised
with ginger and star anise
before being finished
in the steamer.
Is it possible to make a living
playing your kind of music?
- No.
- Impossible.
- Hence the day job.
Hence the day job.
Actually, Hong Kong is a society
that really values
elitism and professionalism.
- Right.
- But in a way that, um,
we are seeing
even these standards
are falling apart
within the system.
But it's important
to be part of a system
to make any changes at all.
- Right.
- Because,
if you just stay on the fringe,
it's very hard to get people
to listen to you.
What do young people want
in Hong Kong?
Are they different
than the generation before?
Or are they ready
to think about stuff
and get angry?
I think that society itself
is projecting
a really unhealthy image
of what young people
should be like.
Because there's always a model
of what the successful life is,
which is to get a house by 30,
have a family,
that sort of thing.
It's not like you can
actually change anything.
It's quite
a pessimistic thing to say,
but it's...
It's more about doing things
to keep yourself sane.
♪ It's nothing more
than a stuff toy ♪
♪ With a smile
that's so coy ♪
♪ Don't say
what I'm trying to avoid ♪
♪ 'Cause everything
has been destroyed ♪
♪ I can't, I can't,
I can't, I can't ♪
♪ I can't, I can't
♪ I can't take it anymore
♪ I can't,
I can't ♪
♪ I can't, I can't
♪ I can't, I can't,
I can't, I can't ♪
♪ I can't, I can't
♪ I can't
♪ Ow
♪
I may be in the "Hey, you kids",
get off my lawn"
phase of my life
and hostile in principle
about changes
to age-old customs
and traditions I love,
but it turns out
that the new Hong Kong
has its hopeful aspects.
Oh, yes.
This is bread and dip.
This is sourdough, chicken fat,
chicken stock, egg waffle.
And this is
a Taiwanese bottarga.
So just use your hands.
Wow.
I am immediately happy.
Chef-owner May Chow
is the creative force
behind Happy Paradise,
a restaurant and bar
serving traditional
Cantonese dishes
made with modern
cooking techniques.
Joining us are Jenny Suen
and feng shui master
Thierry Chow.
Oh, my God, this food is great.
How long have you been open?
Seven months, only.
Wait a minute.
Only seven months?
- Yeah, yeah.
- So this is your new baby.
It was a little bit
more reflection
about being Chinese.
Like, how do I be modern
but not lose the soul of it?
Now, how important...
And I should be asking...
I should be asking you this...
Feng shui is something
I know nothing about.
When you moved into the space,
did you consult?
- She's my friend, yeah.
- I was guessing.
She's my friend.
Feng shui is just
the environment
and the relationship
between the environment
and the people.
When you're in a restaurant,
when you're eating the food,
the space matters.
It...
It changes the way
you taste the food.
So when you look at this space,
what are you looking for
and what do you do?
There's a couple things.
So number one is,
I use a compass.
So we're northeast, southwest.
So from there,
we have a formula,
and then that will tell us
where the best chi is.
- What is chi?
- The energy
that are given off
by the universe.
So I look around,
and I see the colors
of the decorations
and how the furnitures are.
And then I can say, "Okay,
are these good placements?"
♪
It's all about
the flow of energy,
where... where you're looking at,
where the light comes from.
Which is so...
Wait a minute.
But a lot of what...
A lot of what you've been saying
in fact reminds me
of a certain cinematographer
right now.
Exactly.
I wouldn't know.
Positive energy
harnessed appropriately,
one can turn
one's full attention
to the food.
Sautéed prawns with pomelo pith,
fried shrimp roe, and prawn oil.
Those are dishes that I feel
even Hong Kong people
don't do it so much anymore,
because it's such
an old-fashioned dish.
So we want to make it
cool again.
Tea smoked pigeon,
served medium-rare,
sea salt on the side.
A Hakka-style chicken,
poached in Shaoxing wine
with oyster mushroom fried rice
and shitake broth.
Again, this would feel
like a very traditional
Cantonese dish.
But it's not, because it doesn't
really exist in its form
and combination.
Pig brain
with burnt pear vinaigrette.
All of it truly,
stunningly delicious.
There's something that I think
binds all of us together,
which is,
we're trying to reinterpret
Hong Kong culture
in a way that makes sense to us.
I think as we're getting older,
we start to actually enjoy
our own culture.
Think that's why you do that
movie about "The White Girl."
Or she does, you know,
her feng shui.
Because you want
to create something new...
- Yeah.
- That represents the city
as it is today.
♪
Okay, this is my
prawn grove noodle.
Do you see how...
This is the part I...
Wanna try it?
Yes, please.
- What do you think?
- I love this.
Douglas Young is the founder
and creative force
behind the Hong Kong
lifestyle brand G.O.D.
Okay, this is a classic.
So it's the same stuff,
but without the prawn.
I'm told that, what, two,
maybe three people left
in all of Hong Kong
are making bamboo noodles
the old-school way.
- That's right.
- I mean, I've seen this
process once before,
it's incredible.
♪
Lao Soong Kee is run
by the third generation
of a family who still prepare
their wontons from scratch...
♪
And make their noodles,
their bamboo noodles,
the painfully labor-intensive,
time-consuming, old-school way.
♪
One of the last operations
in Hong Kong
to do this.
♪
It is one of many things
in this city
that are under pressure
or disappearing.
A lot of traditional crafts,
buildings...
Yep.
Are, without remorse
or sentiment,
being bulldozed away.
Well, that's the story
of Hong Kong, you know?
Hong Kong is always
going through change,
and nothing's precious,
it's as if...
As if, you know,
if something's old,
it's, like, torn down,
thrown away,
destroyed.
That's Hong Kong.
♪
When I was a kid,
all the shopping
used to be done on the street.
There did not
used to be shopping malls.
I miss the buildings
three stories high,
instead of like glass facades.
And actually, I think also
in the way people dress,
as well.
'Cause the people around here,
they dress
in this kind of strange mix.
I mean, even the look
of Chinese characters,
to me, is very interesting.
But it's disappearing
because, actually,
mainland China
is trying to get rid
of our Hong Kong
style of writing.
We'll lose that as well.
♪
Those are beautiful to me.
The things that
continually fascinating...
- Yeah.
- Fascinate me about...
That's what the city is about.
But those are disappearing.
Those are disappearing
because I think
the government wants
to present an image
that is like modern and Western.
And so we've got
to clean ourselves
of these sort of messy...
- Yeah.
- Street people.
And I think that's...
I hate that.
Yeah, but I think actually
our generation,
the new generation,
is beginning to appreciate
what we have,
because we grew up
in a wealthy period,
and we had happy
childhood memories.
So we wanted to preserve that.
I really see it happening
in Hong Kong.
Finally.
♪