It's easily the most contentious
piece of real estate
in the world.
And there's no hope, none, of
ever talking about it without
pissing somebody, if not
everybody off.
Maybe that's why it's taken me
so long to come here, a place
where even the names of ordinary
things are ferociously disputed.
Where does falafel come from?
Who makes the best hummus?
Is it a fence or a wall?
By the end of this hour, I'll be
seen by many as a terrorist
sympathizer, a Zionist tool, a
self-hating Jew, an apologist
for American imperialism, an
orientalist, socialist,
fascist, CIA agent, and worse.
So here goes nothing.
♪
I was raised without religion.
One side of the family long
ago, catholic... I think.
The other side, Jewish.
I've never been in a synagogue.
I don't believe in
a higher power.
But that doesn't make me any
less Jewish, I don't think.
These guys sandbagging me at the
wailing wall, they don't
seem to think so either.
Only half.
Jewish?
Yes.
You a righty?
I'm a righty, yes.
Mazel tov.
Thank you, gentlemen.
I've never felt so much like
I'm macerating as
something I'm not.
I am instinctively hostile
to any kind of devotion.
Certainty is any enemy.
I'm all about doubt, questioning
ones self and the
nature of reality.
When they grabbed hold of me and
in a totally nonjudgmental way
essentially... god's happy
to have you, here you go.
Oh, man.
My treachery is complete.
Just because I was raised
outside the faith with no
particular attachment or loyalty
to Israel doesn't mean that
plenty of people on this earth
don't hate me in principle.
I know that.
But the state of Israel, I never
really knew what to think.
First look around, it's like
everybody says... it's pretty.
It's awesome.
It's urban.
Sophisticated.
Hip.
Like Southern California.
Only nicer.
Then you see the undraftees in
the streets and you
start to get the idea.
This is Jerusalem.
I'm taking you through
Damascus gate, which is one of
the gates to the old city.
These walls are pretty ancient.
People say they go
back to king David.
As history progressed,
they built up the wall.
So the top bed is the newest.
And by newest you mean...
Up to about the ottoman time.
The Turks left here
about 150 years ago.
And the Brits came and
they conquered us.
I wasn't here.
Born here, now cooking in
London, he is the widely known
respected chef and co-author
of the book "Jerusalem."
Basically, this city was
divided into two until 1967 when
there was the
famous six-day war.
Yep.
And the hall that we're
traveling in now, walking
in is east Jerusalem.
It's the Palestinian part.
That was up until '67
belonged to Jordan.
So now it's under
Israeli control.
Very controversial because for
the Jews, for the Israelis,
the city has been unified.
But for the Palestinian, they
are under occupation, as
far as they are concerned.
We just have to go for a falafel
because it's so much part
of the culture here.
Again, contentious because Jews
or Israelis make falafel their
own and everybody in the world
thinks falafel is
an Israeli food.
It's been done for
generations here.
And here, you get falafel
that's just been fried.
You don't get it any other way.
When I come to a place like
that, I see there's a few left
from the previous customer,
I don't take that.
I want them to fry them for me.
That makes all the
difference in the world.
A whole different
animal, isn't it?
So is there a historically
provable answer to
who invented it?
Who made it first.
The one thing that's very clear
in this part of the world,
Palestine, Lebanon, Syria, it's
been cooked for many,
many, many generations.
On the other hand, you get Jews
from Yemen coming here...
They say hey, my great uncle
was in Syria at the time.
Hey, I remember distinctly
so there is actually no
answer to it.
But the question of food
appropriation or who owns the
food.
If you go you can go on
arguing about it forever.
The old city is divided
into four quarters.
There is Muslim quarter.
There is a Jewish quarter.
There is a Christian quarter.
And there's an Armenian quarter.
Each one functions
independently, but people that
live in the certain area are
all from that religion.
So here you see these Israeli
flags over this house.
So basically Jews have bought
this house, although it's
in the Muslim quarter.
That's very controversial
because it breaks the separation
that people would normally
expect in this city.
Now we're walking in the steps
of Jesus Christ, right?
As I so often do.
So this is villa de la Rosa,
which is the last trip Jesus did
before he was crucified.
People feel very emotional.
They come here and they feel
like oh, my god, I am walking in
the steps of Muhammad,
David, or Jesus.
It's like Jesus was here.
I feel like I should
be more something.
A little bit more pious?
A little bit.
It's too late for me.
Great.
Get your own crown of thorns?
In answer to the question
what would Jesus wear?
Oh no, that's just wrong.
Israel is bordered by Egypt,
Jordan, Syria, and Lebanon.
In 1967, after the six-day war,
Israel took control of the Gaza
strip, the Sinai peninsula, the
west bank, and east Jerusalem.
In 2003, Israel began
construction on a wall along the
green line representing the
Israeli-Palestinian border.
The wall now
stretches 450 miles.
When completed, it
will span 700 miles.
85% of it in
Palestinian territory.
On one hand, there's no doubt
that the number of suicide
bombings fell drastically.
On the other, there's this.
You cross from Jerusalem
into the west bank.
Also called Judea, Sumaria,
also called Palestine.
Since 1967, half a million
settlers have moved here, all in
contravention of
international law.
Many in contravention
of international law.
Though it seems to make
little difference.
They're here and in
ever-larger numbers.
This is one of our drivers from
Tel Aviv who I asked about
graffiti on this house
near the settlements.
So what is price tagging?
Something happens in a
settlement or some attack with
Jews, kids from the settlement
would come and have a price
tag for every activity.
So they come to a village like
this, they will destroy cars,
they will write on
walls like this.
It says against Arabs, the state
of Israel is alive, and
death to the Arabs.
Intimidating.
I mean, you put two targets
on my house, I'm moving.
This is Ellie, a settlement with
a population of over 3,000,
relatively isolated from
the rest of Israel.
This is the chief executive of
the settlement and its
former head of security.
Here you see from up
above most of our town.
You see the Palestinian
villages all around.
It's an unusual situation.
A lot of your neighbors would
very much like you
to not be here.
I know most of them.
And most of them, they are
happy that we're here.
Because we... actually we gave
them prosperity for
the first 45 years.
Wherever the PLO
came, they lost it.
I'm guessing a lot of people
would disagree with that
statement.
Radars and cameras.
So from the high ground, you
can see anybody
walking at night.
You could see from
pretty far out.
Definitely.
Could you identify
them after the fact?
Depends.
What we have are protocols
that we work with.
And we had our successes.
We drive to another
settlement a few miles away.
Hot, sun-bleached,
suburban feeling.
Behind its ring of electronic
surveillance censors and
security, everything
they feel they need.
A school, public transportation,
and a petting zoo.
He has lived here for ten years.
He's a wine maker
and amateur cook.
You're not kidding around.
The salmon is marinated with
pomegranate juice that... on the
season, I squeeze pomegranates.
I freeze the juice so I'll
have it all year round.
Where were you before here?
I was born in Pennsylvania.
So your parents brought
you over at age 4?
Yeah.
Kids living in the relative
comfort and familiarity of
Pennsylvania.
Heading off to what must have,
at least in part of their mind,
would seem an uncertain.
Yes.
It was very difficult for them.
Almost all Jews say next year,
it's part of prayers that
we say all the time.
The Bible, it's all right there.
It all happened here.
That's sort of a
nonnegotiable position.
You see prophesies coming true.
Things coming to life.
Mountains that nobody wanted to
live on, nobody dared to... for
thousands of years,
nobody wanted this place.
And then finally, we come here
and everything is
flourishing again.
It makes you feel
good, you know?
You've been here since '90.
You look over the edge
there, an Arab village.
Yeah.
There is one that you
can see from here.
At any point during that
time, you ever go to anybody's
house, sit down and eat?
Not there, but in
other villages.
Ever sat down at a Muslim table?
Muslim table... you host
and everybody else...
Coffee.
But not there.
No, because as a religious
Jew, I eat only kosher.
So they respect that.
So they don't offer me.
So I've got to ask you about
something that troubled me.
Coming up, the first house
before you come up the drive to
this village, the graffiti
on the front... yes.
The targets spray painted on.
Yes.
Whodunit?
Villains.
Bad people.
Kids?
I don't know.
Apparently kids.
When we educate kids, kids
are not able to understand
complicated things.
They see the world
in black and white.
When you get older, you're
able to see the gray.
And when someone hits you...
I understand why
kids would do it.
Given what you told me earlier,
identifying the perpetrators
within the realm of possibility?
They're young people.
Why not paint it over?
Good question.
Maybe we should.
You're right.
Elsewhere in the west bank,
just outside of Ramallah
meet Betty and Mona.
Two members of a group of women
who call themselves
the speed sisters.
The first all-female
Palestinian racing team.
Hi.
I'm Tony.
Good to meet you.
When I'm riding a car, I'm
the happiest girl ever.
Racing, it's in my blood.
Here in Palestine,
it's very small.
There's no roads.
So when I drive, I speed.
I feel free.
Do you find that people
underestimated you at first?
At the beginning, they could
maybe make fun of us.
But when we got good
scores... yeah.
A car doesn't know if
you're a woman or a man.
A lot of girls want to
join us as speed sisters.
But some of their families
are very reserved.
Their don't like their daughters
to be between men racing.
Palestine is a very
reserved society.
So are things getting better?
Staying the same, or worse?
You never know what's going
to happen in Palestine.
One day it's good and the other
day it's just... you never know.
It's a crazy country.
The local police would prefer
them off the streets
for obvious reasons.
But the track here, such as
it is, has its drawbacks.
It's basically a parking lot
across from the detention
center.
What do they think
about this next door?
Do they ever give you problems?
This is an Israeli jail.
One time we were here with speed
sisters and there was problems
because of the prisoners.
So I just stopped my car over
there and I was walking.
I wanted to see what's going on.
And the Israeli soldiers, they
came running at me and
they start shooting at me.
And I got shot in the back.
It was tear gas.
So my speed sisters, they
took me to the hospital.
I fainted.
Have you thought of challenging
the Israelis to put
up a team?
I can't race because
my car is Palestinian.
What if they come over here?
They're not allowed to enter
the west bank and we're not
allowed to go to Jerusalem, so
how can we race together?
OK, silly question.
It's right there for all to see.
And it feels like something out
of a science fiction film.
This is the wall.
From the other side, from inside
this place, for instance, the
refugee camp in the district of
Bethlehem, it doesn't feel like
anything other than
what it is, a prison.
Abed is the founder of the
children's theatre center.
So we are at the north
entrance of Bethlehem, heading
to the refugee camp.
So this has been
here since 1950.
Yes.
It started with tents.
People were under the tents
for about seven years.
And later, they started
building shelters.
First impressions of the
camp, there's a remarkable
number of kids.
Now it's about 6,000 people.
And 2/3 are under 18 years old.
So it's a very young population.
Unfortunately, with the
continuing degradation of the
political and economic
situation, we are in the
situation where we have
no playgrounds anymore.
Children play in the streets
beneath walls covered in images
of martyrs, plane hijackers,
political prisoners.
6,000 people, of that number,
66% are under the age of 18.
I don't care where that is in
the world, that's pretty much a
recipe for unruly behavior,
I think would be the best.
Well, yes.
Especially when you don't have
any possibilities to evacuate
the anger and the stress
in a creative way.
So after I finished my studies,
I came back here and I started
using theatre as one of the most
amazing, powerful, civilized and
nonviolent means to
express yourself.
To tell your story.
To be truthful.
And this is for me the remedy
to build peace within.
And hopefully help them to think
that they can grow up and change
the world and create miracles.
Without explode themselves.
But to stay alive.
Abed takes me to the
martyrs quarter to be fed.
She offers Palestinian cooking
classes, helping her provide for
six children, one of
whom is disabled.
In America, kids grow up with
pop stars, sports players.
It's unthinkable for a child to
look up to a politician or to
look up to a military figure.
Sports or entertainment.
Here, kids 4 or 5 years old
every day, they're looking at
somebody who, you know,
brought down a plane.
Yeah.
I'm not questioning why that is.
I know.
Do you think it's helpful?
Well, I guess we have a history.
We are people who are
under occupation.
They are heroes.
And their heroes are those
who resist the occupation.
And to tell you the truth,
sometimes I have been with some
political parties, when they put
images of people who are
killed in their houses.
Ahmed's sister, the 29th of
October, 2001, she was killed in
her kitchen by a sniper.
But when these political parties
take this woman and want to make
a montage of photos with her
carrying a gun to say this is
the hero, sorry, this
is not the truth.
This woman was
killed in her house.
We will go today and ask the
Palestinians who
is the great evil?
You ask these kids, who
will they recognize?
They recognize a man from Gaza,
Mohamed Assa, a
singer who sings.
He becomes more famous than
Arafat and everybody else.
This is another image
of these times.
You can almost believe for a
minute or two that some
kind of peace, some kind of
reconciliation, meeting of the
minds, sanity is possible
after you visit Majda.
It's a restaurant in what looks
like an idyllic village
in the Judean hills.
It feels like an alternate
universe for a number of
reasons.
Someone Jewish.
One is Muslim, from
a nearby village.
They're partners, co-owners of
Majda, and also married.
They're unsurprisingly
friends of Yotan.
Together they grow and raise
much of what's used
in their kitchen.
Their food reflects both their
different backgrounds and
their commonalities.
We're going to spoil you now.
Yeah, here you go.
So you grew up in this town.
Yes, in this village.
Where did you grow up?
Near the beach.
Not the neighborhood.
But we met in the neighborhood.
We work together in hotel.
How did that go down
with the families?
Now wonderful.
In the beginning, not so much.
Started with a lot of questions.
Understand that we love each
other and they can do nothing,
so we continue and
they support us.
This is your special farm eggs.
Farm eggs.
Peppers from your garden?
Tomato.
That looks awesome beyond words.
It is incredibly beautiful here.
I don't know why I
didn't expect that.
A lot of people come and say
it's like Provence,
it's like Italy.
You like it?
I do.
Roasted tomatoes, okra.
Onion and mint.
That's all they do.
What they do a lot here is
char the hell out of it.
So it's really smoky just from
being in the pan
on very high heat.
So generally speaking,
who lives in this area?
Mostly Arab... ethnically
Arab in this part of town?
I'm the only Jewish in...
Hardly any Jewish in the
village.
Zucchini that's been grilled.
Then we use fried yogurt,
so that's the sauce.
That's the go-to flavor.
Very typical for
Palestinian cooking.
It's good.
I just had this incredibly
delicious meal completely
oblivious to the fact that
it's entirely vegetarian.
If any of the vegetarian
restaurants in New York served
food that tasted like this,
I would actually go there.
I'd consider it.
Fried zucchini with mint.
And little sweet apricots.
It's delicious.
Are you hopeful?
Of course.
I have my children.
I need to say that.
Together we can build
something for our kids.
Our future.
That's what we think and that's
what we give the message
for our customers.
The fact that it actually
manages to do whatnot so many
chefs try to do here, and that
is sort of mix the Jewish
ethnicity or background with
Arab food.
Getting out of Gaza from
Israel is truly one of the most
surreal travel experiences
you have on earth.
Over 1.5 million
people live in Gaza.
Most of them
considered refugees.
Meaning they're not from the
place they're compelled
to live now.
In most cases, they're either
prohibited from or
unable to leave.
Israel decides who
comes and goes.
What gets in and what stays out.
Apart from journalists, aid
workers, emergency responders,
very few people are allowed
to cross into Gaza.
In 2005, the Israeli defense
forces left the Gaza strip and
all Israeli settlers
were removed.
Now inside Gaza,
Hamas is in charge.
Considered a terrorist
organization by both the united
states and Israel, they
got elected in 2006.
This is Laila Hadan, a native
Gazan, journalist and author
of "the Gaza kitchen."
They're not as big as they
used to be, that's primarily
because the fishermen can't go
beyond three to six
nautical miles.
If you go beyond, what happens?
They'll shoot at the fishermen,
destroy their boats,
cut their fishing nets,
they'll detain them.
It's obviously really
risky business.
Nine nautical miles, that's
where that deep sea channel is
where you're going to get
the really good catches.
Gaza is the last Palestinian
area with access to the coast.
That's really important
to remember.
You have the west bank just an
hour away, but many of the
Palestinians, they have never
seen the sea, have
never been to the sea.
The family owns a small farm
in the eastern Gaza strip.
She and her husband are unusual
in that they cook together.
This is not typical in this part
of the world or in this culture.
They use their own fresh-killed
chickens to make
the Gazan classic.
The traditional Palestinian dish
comprised of layers of fried
eggplant, tomato, potatoes,
Caramelized onions, and
chicken sauteed, them simmered
in a broth with nutmeg,
cinnamon, cardimum, and rice.
It's a big family.
Children, grandchildren all
living under the same roof,
and it can get chaotic.
So let's talk about
food and eat food.
Yeah, yeah, sure.
What do we have here?
This is called mahmouba.
Traditionally lamb,
in this case chicken.
They're very concerned that
we're being very rude.
We're not allowing
the others to eat.
Wow.
For me, being from Gaza,
being a child of Diaspora, I
always thought food was an
interesting way to tell the
Palestinian story.
Being able to discover this lost
history, this Palestinian past.
Plus, the food is
really dang good.
That it is.
I think it was also important
to be able to provide
Palestinians an image of
themselves that they recognize,
a very humane image, because all
they're seeing in the media,
whether here or there, whether
on Arabic channels or abroad,
you know, is this kind of very
caricatured images of gunned men
and this kind of grim
cinder block landscape.
You're not entering
into the private homes.
What does a kitchen look like,
or what does a
family you see here.
Do you like it, she's asking?
Absolutely delicious.
Really, really good.
Yeah?
She wants you to open
a restaurant for her.
Keep cooking like this.
It's really delicious.
Gaza has three distinctive
culinary heritage.
Those who hail from villages
that were either depopulated
or destroyed in 1948.
And they constitute about 75% of
the population of Gaza.
And they kind of bring with them
their own distinct cuisine.
That's very different from the
cuisine of the city, Gaza city,
which tends to use much more
heat, much more chili peppers,
from the cuisine of the coast,
which is rich with seafood,
of course, and a very
sophisticated, very
urbane cuisine.
I guess the first question
would be, in your lifetime, will
you be able to visit Yahba?
She says she hopes she can.
She also hopes she can
go to Jerusalem as well.
So she's optimistic.
She's saying... first she said
you're not allowing us to.
Then corrected and said the
Israelis aren't allowing us.
Go, go.
This is a normal tone of voice.
Not upset, by the way.
This is how we talk.
We yell.
What's he saying?
Give me a permit.
If they allow, of
course I'll go.
Laila's got something
to show me.
A watermelon salad she
discovered on her recent trip
here that's really
piqued her interest.
So off we go.
This will take a minute.
We arrive at what looks like a
pretty serious gathering.
This is a Duwan, and we're soon
joined by her husband Abu.
It's an area where the elders
gather to, you know, resolve
community problems,
to kind of advise.
All these guys are originally
from an area now part of Israel,
so they're bound together by
traditions and a way of life
very different from here, where
they've been relocated
and lived since 1948.
Does he think he'll be able to
go to his ancestral homeland in
his lifetime, his
children's lifetime?
What's his guess?
This enemy.
And we understand that.
We hope.
Me, my son.
My daughter.
So what they're making now...
It's basically baby watermelon,
underripe watermelon.
This is sort of a specialty of
Southern Gaza, but also Sinai.
It's usually something that's
made specifically by
men, I was told here.
You can see they're fire
roasting the baby watermelons.
They cover them
with aluminum foil.
They put them through a wire,
kind of like a rustic skewer.
And then they just
throw them in there.
And the idea is that they take
the pulp out, so that's
what's going on.
And then what they do while
that's fire roasting is they
knead an unlevined dough over
there with whole-wheat, barley,
plenty of rich, extra
virgin olive oil.
And then they throw that into
the pit as well, or they dig a
pit in the sand over there.
Right in the coals?
Yep.
And they mix that all together.
So it's interesting.
Because right now, we're about,
what, 35 minutes
away from Gaza city.
Ask anyone in Gaza city if
they've heard of
this dish and, no.
So even in an area as small as
Gaza, you see this
very wide variation.
They're going to clean it up.
Many, if not most of these
guys, are not too sympathetic to
my country or my
ethnicity, I'm guessing.
But there's that
hospitality thing.
Anywhere you go in the
Muslim world, it seems.
You feed your guests and do your
best to make them feel at home.
We have to eat.
You're supposed to eat
this with your hands.
Mm, very good.
He's saying if you eat this,
you shouldn't have another
meal for three days.
Where does this dish come from?
This is a dish that's native
to Southern Gaza, the Sinai,
sort of the desert
Bedouin areas.
All the food I've had so far
in Gaza has been very different
than in anything else I've
had in the Arab world.
Different flavor spectrum.
Totally.
It's kind of it's own little
gastronomical bubble.
I find that the food has more
flavor, I get a
better cepsry experience.
They have children, and they
like to eat with their hands.
He's saying god gave us hands
to eat with, not spoons.
One can be forgiven for
thinking, when you see how
similar they are, the two
peoples, both of them cook with
pride, eat with passion, love
their kids, love the land in
which they live or the land they
dream of returning to, who live
so close, who are locked in such
an intimate, if deadly embrace
might somehow, some day, figure
out how to live with each other.
But that would be very
mushy thinking indeed.
Those things in the end probably
don't count for much at all.
Gatan Galkowitz runs a
restaurant just seven miles
from the Gaza strip.
You and your family have paid
the most unbelievable price.
My daughter was killed
by mortar sent by Hamas.
In some Israeli towns and
villages within close proximity
of the Gaza strip, bus stops
double as bomb shelters and air
raid sirens warn of incoming
missiles fired from
less than a mile away.
Rockets and mortar shells have
been known to fall from the sky
in these parts and no one
understands the consequences
more than this man.
You were not a fervent Zionist.
No.
You were not an orthodox Jew.
And yet here you are, at the
spear point, right at the dip.
Here's your restaurant.
There is a shelter.
Here you are.
After the death of my daughter,
I just start to talk,
to whom?
To people who want to listen.
I know that my daughter was
killed for no reason and I know
that people on the other side
have been killed for no reason.
Childrens, old people.
I have been a soldier in Gaza.
I saw very poor people.
I know there is interest in
keeping this poor people.
You can go far, far, but the
bottom line is, let's
stop with the suffering.
You know, I went to
this settler community.
Nice people.
And I said to you, you
know, they were nice.
And you said, you said, you
said, they're all nice.
They're all nice.
I know, nice, very nice
Palestinian people.
They're all nice, but if you
scratch, if you push, they all
want... they'll all say,
throw them in the sea.
Most of the people,
they don't talk.
They are very upset.
They are fed up.
And the same goes from
the other side to us.
You have to find the right
people on both village, also on
the down, also on the up,
and maybe they talk.
And I am sure that is possible.
The opportunities to do that
here are very, very, very
limited, it seemed.
I agree.
And I mean, one doesn't even
have to speak metaphorically,
because there is an actual wall.
Or a fence, depending on
who you're talking to.
Fence or wall.
No, it's a big wall.
It's ugly.
It's really ugly.
You can see it, it's not
far away from here.