♪ ♪
♪ Ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh ♪
♪ Here we are, arms
around each other ♪
♪ White scene, pretty
lights all over ♪
♪ Snow is falling and
everyone seems in love ♪
♪ ♪
♪ Santa's sleigh bells
ringing in the distance ♪
♪ I'm waiting for my
mistletoe and kisses ♪
Happy New Year.
♪ I'll remember this moment ♪
♪ For the rest of my life ♪
♪ ♪
Huh? Early Christmas.
Oh, my gosh.
This is from Albert.
♪ It's Christmastime ♪
We have a request
from the audience.
♪ ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la, la ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la, la, la ♪
♪ ♪
'Twas the week before Christmas
when all through the house
not a creature was stirring,
not even a mouse.
Actually, that's
not true at all.
Metro Manila, bustling,
sprawling, Southeast Asian
capital of the Philippines,
home to somewhere between
12 to 20 million
people, the world's
most densely populated city.
♪ I light a candle ♪
♪ Put the presents
'round the tree ♪
But it is Christmas...
♪ The sound of carols
fills the air ♪
A twinkly, festive
wonderland where the mostly
Catholic population take
their holiday season
very seriously.
Hello.
Merry Christmas.
Because Filipinos
are, for reasons
I have yet to figure out,
probably the most giving
of all people on the planet.
Hello.
Think I'm talking shit?
Keep watching.
♪ I still remember how we get ♪
♪ This time of year ♪
♪ We kissed beneath
the mistletoe ♪
Whoo. Let's go.
Let's go. Let's go.
Good afternoon, everyone.
We're the band called Keystone.
Bye-bye.
OFW stands for Overseas Filipino
Worker, and they are one
of the Philippine's largest
and most important exports:
people.
Go abroad. Make money.
Improve the quality of
life for the whole family.
All over the world,
the Philippines sends
architects, doctors,
construction workers, nurses,
housekeepers, nannies.
The entire Filipino
economy relies heavily
on the money sent back by
more than 10 million OFWs,
roughly 30 billion U.S.
dollars a year, or about 10%
of the nation's GDP.
♪ ♪
Until recently, after
domestic workers,
the largest category of
OFWs were musicians.
Like Filipino cover bands.
They're everywhere, on cruise
ships, in hotel lobbies,
bars, and, of course, in Manila,
where the competition is
fierce and the penalties
for not getting a
beloved biker favorite,
like, I don't know, Billy
Idol, can be severe.
♪ ♪
♪ Hey, little sister,
what have you done? ♪
♪ Hey little sister,
who's the only one? ♪
who's your Superman? ♪
♪ Hey little sister, who's
the one you want? ♪
♪ Hey little sister, shotgun ♪
♪ It's a nice day ♪
♪ To start again ♪
♪ Come on, it's a nice day ♪
♪ For a white wedding ♪
♪ It's a nice day to... ♪
♪ Start again ♪
♪ Come on, it's a nice day ♪
♪ For a white wedding ♪
♪ Yeah, it's a nice day to ♪
♪ Start again ♪
Know this, pampered
rock and roll stars,
at any given moment, somewhere
in the Philippines,
there is at least one person,
and probably many more,
who can step in and do
your act better than you
and after only a couple
of hours practice.
Thank you. Thank you.
♪ ♪
Hi, ma'am. Jolly afternoon.
It is true that I lied to my
daughter and tell her that
Ronald McDonald has been
implicated in the disappearance
of small children, that
I sneer at fast food,
revile it at every opportunity.
But I am also a
hypocrite, because to me,
Filipino chain, Jollibee,
is the wackiest,
jolliest place on Earth.
Thank you.
Hi, sir.
Hello. Hi.
Jolly afternoon.
Could I have a Jolly Spaghetti
with the hotdogs on it, right?
Yes, sir.
Okay. Also Chicken Joy.
Thank you.
Thank you, sir.
Jolly afternoon.
Welcome to Jollibee.
There are over 900 of these
things all over the 7,000-plus
Philippine islands and a whole
lot more internationally
wherever there are
homesick Filipinos.
There's a Jollibee in
New Jersey, by the way.
♪ ♪
I hate mascots.
Hi, ma'am.
Jolly afternoon.
You know they fart
in those suits.
Oh, yeah, chicken and spaghetti,
and not just any spaghetti.
I think it's, like,
sweet, banana, ketchup-y
stuff with hotdogs.
The spaghetti is deranged,
yet strangely alluring.
♪ ♪
Oh, it's not a burger.
It's rice.
Do I eat it in a piece?
Do I pour sinister brown sauce?
I don't know what it's for.
♪ ♪
Oh, that's awesome.
That's what you do
with the brown stuff.
Ugh, I hate myself.
Hi, ma'am. Jolly afternoon.
Did I mention it's Christmas?
The 7,000-plus islands that
make up the Philippines
rank number one, according
to internet scienticians,
when it comes to celebrating
the jolliest time of year.
Holiday cheer begins
a full hundred days
before the 25th of December,
which means there's a lot
to do in this town, especially
if you like crashing
other people's parties.
All right.
Let the party start.
Welcome to the Seven
Continents Travel & Tours'
corporate Christmas party,
held in the fabulous
banquet room of the downtown
Pearl Garden Hotel.
Outstanding.
♪ ♪
♪ Deck the halls with
boughs of holly ♪
♪ Fa la la la la la la la la ♪
♪ 'Tis the season all be jolly ♪
So cheers.
Cheers.
Merry Christmas.
Very Catholic country?
- Very Catholic country.
- Yeah.
About 80-something percent.
Christmas starts in September.
Really? September?
It starts in September.
You go to the mall.
You start hearing their carols,
and then it ends after-
- I would lose my mind.
Yeah. So at 12:00 midnight of
September 1, everyone greets
"Merry Christmas" on Facebook.
Yes.
It's a lechón on the
menu, I believe?
Yeah.
I have very fond memories
of the last time
I had lechón in the Philippines.
In fact, not to kiss your
ass, but it is the finest...
Pig.
Pig I've ever had.
Amazing.
♪ ♪
Providing these babies to holiday
parties is big business,
and standards here, where
pork is king and the lechón
the best in the world,
very, very high.
♪ ♪
Today our little friends
prepared the old-school way:
turned slowly, slowly on a
spit over coals for hours.
Oh, delicious, delicious lechón.
♪ ♪
You know, during this time
of the year, there's a lot
of Christmas parties.
And the lechón is always
the star of the party.
They gauge how grand the
party is by the presence
of the lechón.
So if you have two lechóns,
you must be a big shot.
Man, that is good pig.
♪ ♪
So, like, I... my name
is Jimmy Belleza.
I'm the HR Director.
Whoo.
And I'm also the happiness
guru of the Philippines!
So we have to be happy, this
is the season to be jolly!
♪ ♪
Your taste of Christmas.
All right. Ready. And... ♪
Dashing through the snow ♪
♪ In a one-horse open sleigh ♪
As we all know, one must
at a holiday party,
drink, then get drunk
and tell off the boss.
This, I expected and was
prepared to do, but the games,
I was a little surprised by.
Ladies ♪ Jingle
bells, jingle bells ♪
♪ Jingle all the way ♪
♪ Oh, what fun it is to ride ♪
♪ In a one-horse
open sleigh, hey ♪
Then, if I remember correctly,
I totally kicked ass
at a game of drunken
musical chairs.
But I can't be
absolutely certain.
♪ ♪
♪ Jingle bells, jingle bells ♪
♪ Jingle all the
way oh, what fun ♪
I told them I was Bob
from accounting.
♪ Jingle bells, jingle bells ♪
Damn, girl.
When they find out,
things could get awkward.
♪ Oh, what fun it is to ride ♪
♪ In a one-horse open sleigh ♪
♪ ♪
♪ Jingle bells, jingle bells ♪
♪ Jingle all the way ♪
♪ Oh, what fun it is to ride ♪
♪ In a one-horse open sleigh ♪
♪ Hey, jingle bells,
jingle bells ♪
♪ Jingle all the way ♪
♪ Oh, what fun it is to ride ♪
♪ In a one-horse open sleigh ♪
Whoo!
Oh my God.
♪ ♪
Hello.
Halo-halo, please.
One halo-halo.
♪ ♪
- Thanks so much.
- Thank you, ladies.
Thank you.
Thank you, sir.
Mmm, this is wonderful.
I don't even know half of
these ingredients are.
I mean, it's delicious,
but how is it made?
What's in it?
Let's find out.
Halo-halo!
"Halo-halo" means "mix-mix."
Banana.
And it is delicious...
Nata de coco.
Monggo.
Looking good.
An icy, milky,
technicolor concoction
of sundry sweet mung beans,
candied fruits, and gelatins.
Sweet coconut.
Oh, yeah.
Milk.
Delicious. Delicious.
This is a wonderful creation.
It's like that kind of like
after you let the Froot Loops
marinate in the milk for a
while, the milk kind of tastes
like this.
Yeah, you want one?
Thank you!
You say, "Thank you!"
That's okay.
Very satisfying.
Yeah. I recommend it.
♪ ♪
♪ We wish you a
Merry Christmas ♪
Now sisig. Whoo.
All right. The sisig. Whoa.
This looks really good.
Night in Metro Manila, and
I'm ready for my single
favorite Filipino street food,
possibly the best thing
you could ever eat
with a cold beer.
I'm talking, of
course, about sisig.
Hot, sizzling pig face with a
runny egg on top, and, bitch,
you better ask somebody,
because nothing
is getting in between me
and this spicy, chewy,
fatty goodness.
Just mix it up and go?
Yeah. Exactly.
Yes, right.
There's a lot of sisig
restaurants here,
but here's one is the best.
This is really, really good.
Mmm.
This evening's
dining companions:
cover band, Regatta.
♪ Jingle bells, jingle bells ♪
♪ Jingle all the way ♪
You may remember
them from such epic
office Christmas parties
as last night's.
♪ ♪
This is the Christmas season.
- A lot of Christmas parties?
- Yeah.
There's a lot.
A lot of work?
Yeah.
This is a big season.
All over Southeast Asia, any
hotel lobby, any hotel bar,
there's a Filipino band.
Exactly.
And that is true.
And I've sat there drunk and
challenged band after band.
Shirley Bassey, no problem.
All of Dark Side of
the Moon, no problem.
All of Guns N'
Roses, no problem.
And that is true.
Music and singing are
a huge part of life
in the Philippines.
So making it as a cover band,
being sent abroad to perform,
is a big deal.
But one thing remains
the same always,
to succeed, you better be able
to pick up new material fast.
Whitney Houston, Celine Dion,
Toni Braxton, Beatles,
and Elvis Presley.
How many songs in
your repertoire?
Around how many?
On my repertoire, like,
a thousand already.
And if you don't know
it, you pretty much
can fake it real quick.
Yeah.
♪ ♪
Five years from now, where
would you like to be?
Where would you
like to be playing?
That's a good question.
Like, my biggest dream is to
play in Las Vegas, the U.S.
This is my dream.
When we get to the dream, you
know, playing at Las Vegas,
we want to play first
when we got there,
"We are the Champions,"
if we get there.
♪ ♪
Ho-ho-ho, Merry
Christmas, everyone.
♪ ♪
Ho-ho-ho.
Merry Christmas.
Merry Christmas,
Merry Christmas, everyone.
Ho-ho-ho!
Happy New Year, too.
Despite initial appearances,
the Philippines
is not all holiday cheer, warm
hellos, and dancing bugs.
♪ ♪
The Filipino national
martial art, Kali
is among the most brutal,
the most remorseless
defense systems going.
It was developed to deal with
some very harsh realities
and a very tough,
very bloody history.
Three centuries of brutal
Spanish colonial rule.
Invasion by the Japanese.
Near the end of World War II,
American forces bombed Manila,
pretty much leveling the city.
Ferdinand and Imelda Marcos'
extravagantly corrupt
regime, martial law.
Although the Philippines
has remained
a democracy since then, it
can seem, at times, fragile.
Merry Christmas, everybody.
Merry Christmas.
Cheers.
Now, you both are
photojournalists?
Yeah.
Based out of Manila?
Yeah, me.
Mark lives in Mindanao.
Mindanao?
Mindanao, yep.
Now, does a journalist
need to carry
a firearm in this country?
For me, yes.
In the Philippines, a press
badge is no defense,
particularly in the
south of the country,
where Mark Navales
lives and works.
Mindanao has been war-torn
for the last how many years?
Because of the radicalization
of recent years,
this growing specter of
ISIS, Mindanao is a fertile
ground for that.
Now, traditionally,
the argument against
journalists arming themselves
is that journalists
have always been able
to portray themselves
as non-combatants.
Yes.
There was some presumption -that
they would not shoot you.
Yeah.
But these days, people seem
to not make that distinction.
Yes, dating back to the
Marcos years, even, yeah.
Since 1992, 77
journalists were killed.
Politics here can be deadly.
Just before Christmas in 2009,
the Maguindanao Massacre
claimed the lives of 58
people, dozens of whom
were journalists.
It was the single
deadliest event
for journalists in history.
Mark was the first one on
the scene with a camera.
There is no system of justice.
There is no government
attending to your needs.
Nobody's coming to save you.
Is that what you're saying?
No one's coming to save you.
You know, I have... I
have my family.
I have my small kids.
Yeah.
For me, my last... recourse
there is to defend myself.
Look, it's very much a
do-it-yourself culture.
You can see that. You can
see it in people's homes,
the way they just stacked
one on top of each other,
built out using spare
bits of metal.
And it's like, "Nobody else
is gonna give it for me."
I'll build it."
Right.
"I'll make it myself."
There's a lot of
poverty in this city.
That is for sure.
But there's not a sense
of hopelessness or rage.
You know, they decorate.
You know, they may not have
much, but they decorate.
They sweep the street.
There's still a sense
of humble ownership
in the sense of,
"This is my home,"
and it's going to be safe.
"It's going to be fine."
We're seeing some forecasts
calling for up to
one meter of rain.
This is a super typhoon, in
fact, with sustained winds
well above 200
kilometers per hour.
♪ ♪
In any metropolis, you find
all the good and the bad
in the world.
Manila being bigger than
most, has plenty of both.
Yet, this is a nation of
seven thousand islands,
and I really wanted to see
at least one more of them.
But I learned about
something Filipinos
are only too familiar
with, the typhoon.
So it looks like it's gonna
be Christmas in the city.
♪ ♪
Red alert, red alert.
Thank you.
Cheers.
Whoo.
♪ ♪
♪ I never meant to
be so bad to you ♪
♪ One thing I said that
I would never do ♪
♪ One look from you and I
would fall from grace ♪
♪ And that would wipe the
smile right from my face ♪
♪ 'Cause it's the
heat of the moment ♪
♪ Telling me what
your heart meant ♪
♪ The heat of the moment ♪
♪ Shone in your eyes ♪
Name of the band is?
Keystone.
Keystone?
Yes.
How long have you been
playing together?
Around five years.
Five years?
All right, guys.
Oh, here we go.
Awesome. Yay.
Adobo's in the house.
Yes.
Looking pretty.
Thank you. Thank you.
As one does, I dragoon
the band Keystone
in a lunch, assuming
correctly as it turned out
that one of these young
punks would know
how to make a good adobo.
Is there a single authentic
adobo recipe, or does everybody
do it differently?
Everyone would stake claim
to having the best adobo,
but the basic ingredients, I
think, will remain the same.
So it's garlic, pork.
We can now add the chicken.
Vinegar, peppercorns,
bay leaf, soy sauce.
Mmm, this adobo is amazing.
It's really, really good.
- Oh, man.
- Thank you. Thank you.
And where did you
learn to cook adobo?
I learned this from my mom.
So the answer, as always, to
who makes the best adobo is,
mom makes the... okay.
That would be... that would
be the safest answer.
All right.
Mom.
Filipinos like feeding people.
Yes, yes.
What else do Filipinos like?
Filipinos are hospitable.
Music.
Everybody knows how to sing.
- Everybody knows how to sing.
They don't necessarily
have to be in tune,
but they wanna sing;
they like to sing.
We've been listening
to music from, like,
from a very young age.
I'm the drummer for the
band, but I'm not actually
formally trained.
Up to this day, I don't
even read notes.
Uh-hmm.
But, um... I could
memorize a song.
If you gave it to
me, like, in a day,
I could play the whole thing.
Well, that's pretty
much the stakes.
- You have to, right? I mean...
- Yeah.
You guys have played abroad?
No.
No?
Yeah, so that's one of
the goals, actually.
Five years from now, where
would you like to be?
Well, hopefully, we
get... we get to play
for a bigger crowd, you
know, 'cause I think
the fulfillment for me is
actually getting more people
to enjoy the music.
♪ ♪
♪ Heat of the moment ♪
♪ Shone in your eyes ♪
♪ ♪
♪ Heat of the moment ♪
♪ Shone in your eyes ♪
♪ ♪
♪ Oh, oh, oh ♪
♪ I waited for you
to come back to me ♪
♪ I'm hoping you
make it home early ♪
♪ The scene is all set
for the evening ♪
♪
Filipinos speak about home
with immense pride and love.
And if you're an overseas
Filipino worker, longing...
Good-looking.
Especially during the holidays.
♪ So we can all
celebrate Christmas ♪
Oh, come in. Come in.
Hello. Oh.
Merry Christmas.
God bless you.
Hi.
It's always, always about
family in the Philippines,
or anywhere you find Filipinos.
Oh, God.
For Christmas, of course,
everybody those who can, anyway,
gets together, like
family matriarch Aurora
and her daughter, Anna Lynn...
Okay, Anna Lynn,
you're a big help.
And Amy and Ruben, her
adopted children.
Amy, can you hand
me that bay leaf?
Bay leaf.
Wow, it smells so good.
Also, cousins, nieces,
nephews, grandchildren,
even some great-grandchildren.
♪ La la la la la la ♪
I love cooking.
I really love cooking.
Kare-kare is one of the favorite
of the Filipino people.
And to make a kare-kare, I use
tripes, and I put the oxtail
on the pressure cooker.
Wow, wow, wow.
Now the peanut butter.
Here are the peanut
butter, mother.
Peanut butter, please.
No more. No more.
Now, the banana blossom.
The eggplant.
The eggplant. The eggplant.
♪ Oh, holy night ♪
♪ The stars are
brightly shining ♪
♪ Here is the kare-kare ♪
♪ I hope everybody
will enjoy this ♪
Okay, it's time to eat!
♪ ♪
About to receive
from Your bounty.
Through Christ, our Lord, amen.
Amen.
I'm hungry.
Although we always say
it's ladies first,
I think we'll serve you.
It's okay this time?
Just this once.
So good.
So how long have you been
back in Philippines?
In the Philippines?
Three years.
Yeah.
Three years now.
- Where have you worked?
- Hong Kong for five years?
For five years, and
then I went to America.
I stayed there for almost...
30 years.
Aurora is recently back in
Manila after most of her life
spent abroad.
What kind of work
were you doing?
I did the housekeeping, you
know, and babysitting.
The money she sent home
put everybody here
and many, many more through
school, lifted them up
to a more comfortable life.
And you left family behind?
Yeah.
To go out there and make money.
That's never an easy decision,
a painful, painful choice.
Aurora's children, now
middle-aged, are finally getting
to know their mother.
Okay. Okay. Okay.
Bring in the food inside.
♪ ♪
Many, many, many Filipino women
like you, who had to leave
their families, go abroad.
Yeah, absolutely there is.
Her three children.
My children.
My eldest is about four
years now in Qatar.
Then the other one is two years.
And then the other
one is in Hong Kong.
Working conditions for
OFWs, particularly
in some Gulf States, can
be punishing at best,
abusive, or worse.
So I'm a single mom with
my two grandchildren.
I really cried a lot,
especially this holiday season.
Still, due to lack of opportunity
at home, many Filipinos
have little choice but to
go somewhere far away,
find a job, money.
But hopefully, in a few years,
you think they come back?
Yes. Yeah, -I hope so.
I really ask them to go
home, because I'm not
getting younger anymore.
I need them with my side.
I tell them several
times, they call me up,
"Please get home soon.
I need you."
♪ ♪
Any Filipino watching will
recognize this immediately,
the balikbayan box, a Christmas
tradition, a way for OFWs
to show loved ones, though
separated by oceans,
that you miss them, that
you're still out there.
What's in these boxes?
Whatever you can send,
little things you'd
casually give to a loved
one if you didn't live
on the other side of the world.
This facility alone sorts
thousands of these boxes a day
during the Christmas season,
just one of hundreds
of facilities like it,
some five to seven million
boxes a year.
That's a lot of love.
So how many relatives do
you think have in America?
In America. Oh, my gosh.
Florida.
Seattle.
California. Albert.
My ate, my elder sister,
is in California.
In Hong Kong, we
have at least ten.
Ten.
And then, Dubai around eight.
And Qatar.
Qatar.
I'm at this Christmas
gathering today because of
one of our directors,
Erik Osterholm.
It was Aurora who raised him.
For over 20 years, she
cared for and loved
Erik and his sister, looked
after his whole family.
Erik sent me... a letter
talking about you.
I wanted to read
you what he said.
"Aurora is such an
incredible woman."
She has an infectious
and loving energy
that is so powerful.
I am one hundred percent
the man I am today
because this woman literally
raised me from when I was
six months old.
Singing to me, dancing with
me, wiping away my tears,
cooking for me, and making
me laugh at every turn.
Unfortunately, like so many
Filipinos, her story is not all
smiles and love.
She had to choose a life
away from her daughter
and thousands of miles
from her family.
There are literally thousands
of people around the world...
Thousands of people around
the world, me included,
"who have been influenced by her
endless kindness and love."
♪ ♪
Filipinos' gift of themselves,
of their time, their money,
their love to others.
They do, and continue to
do what needs to be done
to survive.
♪ Edelweiss ♪
♪ Every morning ♪
♪ I greet you ♪
♪ Small and white ♪
♪ Clean and bright ♪
♪ Bless my homeland ♪
♪ Forever ♪
♪ Blossom of snow ♪
♪ May you bloom and grow ♪
♪ Bloom and grow forever ♪
♪ Edelweiss ♪
♪ Bless my homeland ♪
♪ Forever ♪
♪ ♪
Early Christmas. Oh my gosh.
Oh, this is from Albert.
Oh.
Ooh, my gosh.
Wow!
Oh, oh, look at that.
Oh, my gosh!
There, you can have that.
Is that soap?
Yeah.
Mine.
That's my name.
"I really hope you
enjoy the simple gift."
I sent and I know that my
heart is with you always.
I love you very much.
"Albert."
♪ ♪
♪ Joy to the world ♪
♪ The Lord has come ♪
♪ Let Earth receive her King ♪
♪ Let every heart ♪
♪ Prepare Him room ♪
♪ And heaven and nature sing ♪
♪ And heaven and heaven ♪
♪ And nature sing ♪
♪ He rules the world ♪
♪ With truth and grace ♪
♪ And makes the nations prove... ♪
♪ The glories of ♪
♪ His righteousness ♪
♪ And wonders of His love ♪
♪ And wonders, wonders ♪
♪ Of His love ♪
♪ ♪