♪ ♪
Boom.
Oh, my God.
What hurts?
♪ ♪
Yeah!
Aww!
♪ ♪
♪ I took a walk ♪
♪ Through this beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good ♪
♪ In this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain ♪
♪ Getting colder ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la, la ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la, la, la ♪
What if we just get Dino's,
and go to Edgefield
and go to Robert's?
I mean, I'm not
trying to screw...
The only thing is Edgefield
closes at midnight.
You got to see... have
you been to Robert's?
But Dino's definitely
starter and that's it.
Saw the hotel, man.
Oh, I know.
Hold on. Time out.
Stop, stop, stop.
You've never hung in Nashville?
No.
You're gonna have a fun time.
I have no doubt.
♪ ♪
♪ Let's go back to Tennessee ♪
Nashville, if you
haven't been there
you probably know it as what?
A country music capital.
Grand Ole Opry.
And it is Music City.
♪ Let's go back ♪
And there is indeed
plenty of country music,
both genuine and fake-ass.
But it's way more than that.
Nashville is one of the fastest
growing metropolitan areas
in all America.
People who grew up here
will tell you the city
is in a state of perpetual,
never-ending change,
and the rate at which things
are changing is accelerating.
Eighty to a hundred new
faces move to Nashville
every single day.
Some things are constants,
others in flux.
Even with all the
radical cultural shift,
this city still remains
traditionally Southern
in its sensibility,
for now, anyway.
Because Nashville could
just as soon be called
Punk City or Rock City.
You are just as likely to
find the word "artisanal"
hanging over the door
of a sandwich shop,
or a cupcake shop, or the
slow drip coffee laptop zone
as anywhere in the
land of man buns
in the cities of the North.
So, of course, the
chefs are coming.
Carpetbaggers seeking
their fortunes,
attracted by a more affordable
business environment
or just looking for a
better quality of life.
Sons and daughters of the South
looking to honor the
traditions they grew up with,
but with a more
modern sensibility.
♪ Let's go back to Tennessee ♪
Here's four chefs who
helped change things,
who were instrumental
in starting something
truly new and
innovative, but, well,
because of their efforts
and their mentoring,
their early examples
is becoming more
and more accepted practice.
Tyler Brown of Capitol
Grille in Southall.
Tandy Wilson, the City House.
Our old friend, Sean
Brock of Husk Nashville.
And the distinguished Pat Martin
of Martin's Bar-B-Que Joint.
♪ ♪
Sundays are often spent
here at Pat's house.
Friends, family kicking
back and drinking beer,
and cooking over the fire pits.
♪ ♪
All these chefs pride themselves
in celebrating local,
seasonal Southern ingredients
and close relationships
with farmers and food
producers from the area.
Those are 90-day-aged rib eyes
from nearby Bear Creek Farms
slowly cooking there.
And they're gonna be topped
off with oyster mushrooms,
and bourbon soy, and some
nice, runny eggs, and garlic.
Grits, well, of course.
These are called greasy beans,
pressure canned in salt water
then heated up with pork
fat so I'm not hating that
for sure.
There's also homemade
ricotta served with
a cold-smoked sausage and
roasted acorn squash.
♪ ♪
You better get it, friend,
because if you don't,
you're screwed, man.
Let's say everybody gets an egg.
- Everybody cool with that?
- Oh, hell yeah.
So it's a must.
It doesn't really
matter what I'm eating
if I'm eating outdoors.
Really?
I love eating outdoors.
Yeah, me too.
Oh, yeah, now we're talking.
Thank you.
♪ ♪
So who started in the
restaurant hospitality business
in Nashville first?
- He started...
- October of '06.
'06.
We started in 2003.
'03.
What was it like in '03?
What did people wanna eat
in Nashville in '03?
Holy cow.
Well, steak and potatoes.
- Steak house, man.
- That's all it was.
Those were the only
places to eat.
Which came first, the customer
or the chef in this case?
Chef.
Chef showed up first.
How open to new shit?
That's the thing
about Nashville.
Always?
People... yeah.
- 'Cause it's artistic.
- People are very progressive.
It's such a creative... -
It doesn't mean they know
what they're tasting or
at that time they knew
what they were tasting,
but they wanted it.
Who's here... who's
from here originally?
I am.
That's it?
I think so.
So then we're all
carpetbaggers at this table?
Yeah.
I mean, right?
♪ ♪
Nashville's Lower
Broadway or Music Row.
It's what Nashville's selling.
It's what the tourists want.
And the honky-tonks
or McHonky-tonks
that line the strip now
tend to lean more towards
cover bands than
singer-songwriters.
On one hand, it employs a
hell of a lot of musicians,
which is a good thing.
On the other hand... Whoo! Yeah!
This place is killer!
Yeah!
Stray from Lower Broadway,
and you're bound to stumble
upon a genuine dive bar...
Tastes like hipster.
And Nashville's got
some real good ones.
So what is this place?
Dino's?
It's a burger joint that's
been here for a long time.
A lot of country music
history is in here.
A lot of Nashville
It's a fun place where
you see a lot of new
East Nashville life.
♪ ♪
Order up.
I can't tell you how many
burgers that I had in here
that I don't remember.
There's a picture of
them on my phone.
"Oh, I had a burger at Dino's."
What... what is... what is this?
They call these hot fries.
So it's like the flavor of hot
chicken but it's with fries
and Velveeta.
- Wow.
- I think it's Velveeta. Yup.
It's like country poutine.
Exactly, man.
This is like redneck poutine.
It's good.
♪ ♪
That's good.
Yeah.
Tony, what's cool about,
like, these dive bars here
is there's so many
studio musicians here.
If you're not a badass
musician in this town,
you're not gonna make it.
So everywhere you go,
you're hearing the most
incredible players you've ever
seen anywhere in the world.
What music rules here still?
I mean, is it country
music still?
Well, they've f'd up country
music so bad on Music Row,
it's not even funny.
That's not country music.
To me, it's not.
It's bullshit.
But there's also so much
more than country, you know.
Oh, man, that's the thing
that people don't realize
about Nashville is... it's
not just country music.
If you're looking for
iconic Nashville,
what's bone deep,
local, even deeper
than the dive bar culture,
you would be talking
about a thing called
Meat and Three.
Meat and Three is a
cafeteria type institution
offering, for a set
price, the choice of meat
and three sides.
I've been thinking about
this all day since I've...
Have you?
Oh, hell yeah.
It's the real deal.
Dandgure's in downtown Nashville
is just such an institution.
Doors open at 10:00 a.m.
and close at 2:00 p.m.
With a rotating selection
of a dozen lunch staples,
you're pretty sure to
find what you came for.
Okra or black-eyed peas,
what do you think?
What should I do?
Okra.
Okra, okay.
This gentleman too is
something of an institution.
Jesse Boyce, a two-time
Grammy Award nominee,
instrumentalist, songwriter,
producer, and CEO of Sovereign
Music Group in Nashville.
This a big Nashville tradition,
the Meat and Three.
Absolutely. You see...
You see a little bit
of everybody in here from... from
truck drivers to mothers
to lawyers, whomever.
You can see it's multicultural.
Everybody just, like, really
comfortable with each other.
Like a microcosm of what
Nashville is really like.
Yeah, I mean, most people,
I think, who haven't been
to Nashville outside looking
in, they see Nashville,
they think country music.
- Exactly.
- But it's really not that at all.
I mean, yes, it is.
There's a hell lot of
country music here.
But we have two strands of
music that were emerging
at the same time, historically.
'50s and '60s we had Hee
Haw and Night Train.
♪ ♪
All aboard.
The Night Train now boarding.
And you have the best
seat in the house,
so let's get rolling to
great entertainment.
Night Train was the
black TV show.
Mm-hmm.
That had all the
major RnB artists on,
and the local artists on, the
same as we had with "Hee Haw"
and all the country artists.
And then you had
Jefferson Street.
Jefferson Street is where
all the black artists
came to play.
People like Jimi Hendrix,
Little Richard, B.B. King,
Aretha Franklin, Ray
Charles, all of these people
played in Nashville
on Jefferson Street.
We had blacks and whites
coming in to the inner city.
We didn't have Broadway.
We had Jefferson Street.
Back in the day it
was the place to go.
♪ ♪
The Jefferson Street
District no longer resembles
its neon-lit heyday.
Like a lot of historic
neighborhoods in Nashville
it's being slowly
eaten by developers
to make way for the
shiny and the new.
To accommodate all
the new arrivals.
♪ It was over before
it even began ♪
But what's left is a pretty
amazing musical legacy
and one that's often overlooked
or sometimes simply forgotten.
Everybody's moving to Nashville.
This car, affectionately
referred to as the Black Shark,
did in 2012.
Along with its eight cylinders
of Detroit-made awesomeness
came Alison Mosshart,
singer-songwriter
for the London-based band
The Kills, which she formed
over 15 years ago with Jamie
Hince, and more recently,
locally based The Dead Weather.
♪ Oh, my shaking heart ♪
♪ You got me from the start ♪
♪ You got me good ♪
♪ You aimed and then you shot... ♪
Straight through a red light.
Boom.
She needed someplace to
park her car, she says,
and Nashville seemed right.
I lived in London
forever riding a bus.
I really wanted to get a muscle
car, and I needed a garage
to put it in.
There's no way I can be
unhappy in this car.
Completely understand
the relationship.
This is a custom-made
Dodge Challenger.
If it hits you with speed, it
will mess you up real bad.
I love this car.
I'm having car envy.
♪ ♪
This is Nashville hot chicken.
If you order it in its
hottest iteration,
it too will mess you up,
as I came to find out.
Hot chicken recipes are
notoriously kept secret,
but preparation always
begins with the poultry
getting double dredged
and deep fried
for a thick, crispy crust.
Then each piece is given
a wet or dry application
for that sought
after, caustic kick.
With the wet, the chef's
mix of hot spices
comes in an oil-based sauce
or paste that the chicken
is dipped in or coated with.
Other cooks use the dry
method, coating the chicken
with a blistering blend of
cayenne, sugar, paprika,
and other secret spices, to
form a fiery outer layer.
If you come here to the
very fine Bolton's
for your hot chicken or
their optional hot fish,
it can, in its milder
forms, which are still
scorchingly hot, -be delicious.
♪ Yummy ♪
But try the hot stuff
and watch out.
No, really watch out.
How long have you
been in Nashville?
Four years, maybe.
Yeah, I was working
here all the time.
- I loved it.
- I thought it was beautiful.
Lots of people I knew
were moving here.
Lots of bands.
Lots of rock and roll
was coming to town.
Yeah, a real lot.
You know, when I was touring
when I was a teenager,
this is a place you would avoid.
If you were in a punk band,
don't come play Nashville.
No one will come to your show.
That sort of seemed to
change, like, ten years ago
where suddenly it was, like,
people are showing up.
Order.
Right. All right.
From left to right:
hot, medium, mild.
And there's your fish.
Spicy - Okay, thank you.
I didn't even order,
so you guys go for it.
Oh, you're gonna have
to try something.
Matthew Mosshart, Alison's
brother, is a professional chef
who moved here in 2013 to
start a catering business.
Should have gloves on.
Oh, man.
♪ ♪
The medium is really hot.
That's really hot.
And it... and it
just keeps coming.
You're already diving
into the coleslaw
at a million miles an hour.
Yeah.
It's like... -Oh, my God.
Are you done?
Yeah, this isn't good.
- That was...
- Which one did you get?
I think medium.
Mild. Whatever it is.
You know?
I know that I don't have a hot
one, but this is hot anyway.
I'm just... I'm trying
to bond it, you guys.
All right, I'm going in.
Do not resuscitate.
Oh, man, you don't want this.
♪ ♪
Oh, oh, that hurts.
I think I'm hallucinating.
It'll put you in a head spin.
Oh, my God, Anthony.
It's like a sharp burning,
and it just keeps coming,
and coming, and coming.
It's not going away.
You got nothing on yours?
Was it, like, a medium?
- I'm good over here.
- I'm real good.
You're good to go.
This is great.
A little bit of mustard?
There appears to be a little
bit of mustard on here, yes.
♪ ♪
How bad can it be?
I just experienced,
like, 12-hour payback
for... from hot chicken.
Right.
And this was an existentially
awful experience,
and I really... there were
moments when I didn't think
I was gonna make it.
This has got to be so
much better than that,
and it's only three minutes.
Only three minutes.
I'll take it.
They serve snacks in there?
♪ ♪
My friend Dean Fertita
plays guitar and keyboards
for Queens of the Stone Age.
And he also plays with The
Dead Weather, with Alison,
who you just met.
A Nashville resident too,
he trains in Krav Maga,
a lethal martial art at the
same gym where I train
jujitsu when in town.
These things hurt.
They punish the body.
They make a person sore.
Fortunately, I had a
knuckleheaded idea
and a place to do it.
Cryotherapy, the latest in
muscle recovery treatments.
So far so good.
It hurts.
No.
This is a terrible
restaurant, Tony.
Basically you step
inside a big tube
into which liquid nitrogen is
pumped chilling things down
to a less than comfortable
minus 300 degrees... -Oh, God!
To apparently convince
your body that it's dying
on the permafrost,
causing it to kick loose
all sorts of
emergency, lifesaving,
anti-inflammatory proteins,
after which you are supposed
to feel better... -Oh, God!
If your fingers and
penis don't shatter
like Hummel figurines.
Oh, God!
You did it.
Oh.
Watch your head.
All right!
Take it off.
Well, how do you feel?
Good luck.
I'm dying.
In a good way though.
All right, so step right in.
No, I'm not ready.
I don't like... I don't
like the way he looks.
He looks unhappy.
All right?
It's all right.
Did you notice how, like,
the last 40, 50 seconds
were the coldest?
Yeah.
Pretty much his whole
session's gonna be like that
last 40 to 50 seconds.
The whole session because
you're going second.
Oh, yeah.
That's uncomfortable.
Yeah, you're already
at negative 306.
Oh, yeah, that's bad.
That's bad.
That's not good. Oh, my God.
You can do it.
You feeling all right?
No, no, it's bad.
Oh, I wanna rub some hot
chicken all over my body.
It's been... it's
been ten seconds in.
Oh, don't tell me that.
See, he's already
at negative 308.
You didn't hit negative 306
and 308 till the last minute.
How long have I got?
You're not even halfway there.
I'm not even halfway.
I'm trying to be helpful, but
I can't even talk right now.
- Yeah.
- How are we doing for time?
You're almost done.
- Yeah, what's almost mean?
- Ten seconds.
Really?
Oh, yeah.
Ten seconds.
You got it.
Wow.
This is on There's
still a third level.
Level two?
Yeah.
There's still one more level up.
What's the longest
you can go in it?
Three minutes.
Watch your head, sir.
Well, I always wondered
what it was like to have
a micro penis.
Ooh, I feel a little crispy.
That was kind of awesome.
♪ ♪
Freshly invigorated by
our sub-zero experience
with newfound appetites
to go with our newfound
cryogenically induced
superpowers, Dean and I head over
to City House, Tandy Wilson's
place, for some pizza.
So would you say that what
you've seen here is what
you were expecting to find?
I like it here.
It's a friendly town.
- And it's friendly.
- Yeah.
I know we were... I remember
when we first came down here,
we'd go to the gas station
and people would say hello
- and we would be like...
- Yeah, that takes
some getting used to.
- What is that?
- Yeah.
I'm assuming she's half
kidding, but Alison said
it's all about the car.
She needed someplace
to park the car.
- Why she moved here?
- Yeah.
I totally believe that.
You don't doubt that?
- She does love that car.
- Right.
I mean, as much as I talk
about it I would never buy
a muscle car because once I
start, it's like I would never
be satisfied.
I would, you know, I mean, you
don't wanna be like Jay Leno
with, like, 30 muscle cars.
You know, let's face it.
If you own 30 classic
muscle cars,
there comes a point where
people are gonna look at you
and say, you know, sorry
about your penis, you know?
There's something... something
else going on here.
♪ ♪
Music is a $10 billion a
year economy around here,
employing more people than
anywhere else in the country.
Its producers, its
session artists,
even the studios
themselves are legendary.
If you can make it as a
working musician in Nashville
where there's anything but a
shortage -and standards high...
Okay.
You can pretty much
make it anywhere.
Lightning 100.
This is Jason Moon.
In the studio with us today,
Nashville artist, Margo Price.
FADER Magazine has called
her Nashville's favorite
new badass.
We agree and she's here to play
a couple new songs for us.
Thanks for having me.
One, two, three.
♪ ♪
Margo Price grew up
on her family's farm
in Buffalo Prairie, Illinois.
Her family was forced to
sell when she was age two,
which is pretty damn country
already if you ask me.
As a country music traditionalist,
she struggled for years
to find her place within
Nashville's increasingly
pop-driven country scene and
the growing indie rock one.
In 2010, she lost one
of her twin sons
to a rare heart condition,
self-medicated with alcohol,
and ended up with every kind
of problem, including problems
of the legal kind.
She poured her heart
and every cent she had
recording an album in just
three days at the legendary
Sun Studios in Memphis,
selling her car
and her wedding
ring along the way.
♪ Dogs that howl ♪
♪ On dead end roads ♪
♪ They remind me ♪
♪ Where I am ♪
♪ And all the sins ♪
♪ I gave away ♪
♪ Well, I got them ♪
♪ Back again ♪
♪ The pain has made me wise ♪
♪ No wasted tears to cry ♪
♪ So many things ♪
♪ You never said ♪
♪ But you told me ♪
♪ With your eyes ♪
The album, "Midwest
Farmer's Daughter",
was rejected 30 times
by the major labels
until she found herself on
the radar of Jack White
and his brilliant and
eccentric enterprise,
Third Man Records.
Third Man's impact on the
Nashville music scene
can't be understated.
With an eclectic, unpredictable
list of artists,
reissues, and obsessions,
they've tilted
the town's axis a bit making
Nashville the center,
not just of country
music, but also, what?
Of course, White has
also produced albums
for country music legends
like Loretta Lynn.
So if anything, they are
reliably unreliable
when predicting what
they might do next.
Let's get ready for a full take.
Right now what comes
next is Margo Price,
who's recording today at Third
Man's live music venue,
The Blue Room.
The recording, a unique,
one of a kind operation
because it's all going
directly to acetate.
Before digital and
before analog tape
was used for mastering, disk
recording was done live.
No editing.
No overdubs.
Redirecting this process
on this 1953 lathe,
Third Man has mastered a
number of albums like this
giving listeners as close to a
live experience as possible.
Also, it's kind of cool.
Here's at Third Man in the
Blue Room, it's the only place
in the world where
you can actually do
a live to acetate recording.
♪ 'Cause all I wanna do ♪
♪ Is make something last ♪
♪ 'Cause I know what I am ♪
♪ I know what I have ♪
♪ I wanna buy back the farm ♪
♪ And bring my mama
home some wine ♪
♪ Turn back the clock ♪
♪ On the cruel ♪
♪ Hands of time ♪
That album that was
rejected 30 times
debuted on Billboard's Top
Country chart at number 10
in its opening week
and was this year's
number one country
album in the UK.
Margo's promotional tour
includes performances
on Saturday Night Live,
"Conan", "Colbert",
and the Grand Ole Opry itself.
But before heading out on the
road, the band and friends
gather one last time at
Margo's East Nashville home.
Her husband and bass player
in the band, Jeremy,
prepares biscuits with
pimento and cheese,
topped with chopped bacon.
Along with red wine braised
short rib on a crostini
with goat cheese.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, oh, yeah.
Nice.
It's cold.
Do you guys eat like
this all the time?
No.
He cooks.
He cooks like this all the time.
He's worked in, like,
every restaurant in town.
Yeah, we've all been in
the restaurant business.
You, you, you.
He just got fired from a job
over on the west... sorry.
Way to go, Vernon.
First of all, let me
ask, who here is from
Nashville originally?
Exactly, she is.
This has been pretty
much the story
of my experience here so far.
You know, the town
has a reputation.
There are so many really
good musicians here.
Does that make it harder
to break out here?
And ultimately, what
happens if you suck here?
Like, I mean, if you can't,
if you play country Western...
I mean, it is... - And you
cannot... you're not good
at your instrument, can you
make a living here and suck?
Absolutely.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Not to say, like,
there's tons of bands
that suck or something here,
but when I came here,
I wasn't good enough,
and I went out to some,
like, writers rounds, and
I learned very quickly
that I was... I had to
be a better player.
I had to be a better singer.
I had to be a better writer.
And, like, so, you know, you
work hard because you're
surrounded by that.
It's like you're
typically playing to,
like, a whole room of, you
know, pickers and writers.
And so it's like, how many
Nashville musicians does it take
to change a light bulb?
One to do it, and
20 to stand around
and say, "I can do that."
♪ I put a hurting
on the bottle ♪
♪ Baby now I'm blind
enough to see ♪
♪ I've been drinking
whiskey like it's water ♪
♪ That don't touch the
pain you put on me ♪
There seems to be a sense, like,
a lot of established bands
have always come here for
something metaphysical.
I mean, they say, "Well, it's
I wanna work with particular"
session musicians,"
or "I wanna record at
a particular studio."
Yes.
But that's really a kind
of a metaphysical decision.
Does that particular mixing
board actually possess
magical powers...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That will make
your record better?
I kind of feel like there's
something special about a room.
You go into RCA Studio B
where all the Elvis singles
were cut, all the Orbison
singles were cut,
Everly Brothers.
There's something special
about that room.
Yeah, I mean, you joke around
about, like, the thing about,
"Oh, there's something
special in the board."
Sometimes there is.
♪ I put a hurting
on the bottle ♪
♪ Baby now I'm blind
enough to see ♪
♪ Been drinking whiskey
like it's water ♪
♪ But that don't touch ♪
♪ The pain ♪
♪ You put ♪
♪ On ♪
♪ Me... ♪
♪ ♪
All right, let's take it home.
Sign of the apocalypse or
an age of enlightenment,
you decide.
The craft cocktail
program has arrived,
and it's spreading fast.
Josh Habiger's cocktail
bar, Patterson House,
and its upstairs,
20-seat counter-only
restaurant Catbird Seat,
has been catering to
the sophisticated palates
of Nashvillians since 2011.
♪ ♪
Josh rolled in from Chicago,
a self-trained mixologist,
as they call makers
of drinks these days,
and professional chef.
He's got five acclaimed
restaurants across the city.
- Cheers.
- Thanks for playing.
Yeah.
♪ ♪
So, do places like this
represent that the town
has changed, or did
they change the town?
When we opened this, I was
amazed by the support
that we got from people.
People didn't wanna hate us.
They wanted to like it here.
Really?
I mean, in New York,
particularly if you come
from out of town.
- Mm-hmm.
- We kind of wanna hate you.
I mean, we're not the
cold-hearted town
that people portray us to be,
but, especially if you're
hot shit somewhere else...
Yeah.
You're gonna have a real
steep climb in New York.
We are kind of hoping
you're gonna fail.
Yeah.
If we can help you, we will.
It's not like that here
from what I understand.
The carpetbagging interlopers
are welcome here
in a way that they are
not in a lot of places.
Mm-hmm.
Whether it's music or
restaurants, or are... come here
and do creative shit.
Yeah, it's a really cool place.
It's a... it's a lot of fun.
A little crumble of sea salt.
Let me know when it's ready.
The idea of this place
was to cook the way
the bartender bartends.
When you're looking the person
in the eye and handing them
a plate of food, there's
no... there's no hiding.
If... if they love it,
then you see that.
If they don't love it, then...
Plan B.
Yeah.
So menu changes every night?
At the... at the whim
of Poli right now.
♪ ♪
Chef Ryan Poli is the new kid
in town fresh from Chicago.
A veteran of Mercadito,
Hospitality's Tavernita,
Little Market
Brasserie, and Barcito.
All right, the first serving
we have, this is risotto,
but instead of using rice
we use sunflower seeds.
♪ ♪
We treat it like a normal
risotto, we add parmesan cheese
and a little bit of butter.
We topped it with a little
bit of fermented sun chokes,
the base of the sunflower plant,
and just garnished it with
a little green sunflower sprout.
So we use three different
cooking techniques
of one ingredient
to make this dish.
Enjoy.
Beautiful.
♪ ♪
Mmm. Wow.
That's insanely delicious.
Nothing about that description
sounded particularly
interesting to me.
Delicious.
This next course is a play
on a very traditional
Italian dish.
Linguini, chili flakes, a
sea urchin or crab meat.
This is our version, we just
use Japanese ingredients.
So we made a wakame
seaweed bucatini.
We use yuzu kosho to
represent the chili flakes.
A little bit citrusy.
A little bit spicy.
And then we took scallops,
and dried and smoked them,
- and grated it over the top.
- Enjoy.
Oh.
Thank you.
Man, you are talking
my language here.
♪ ♪
That's obscenely good.
I would face-plant in a
big [...] bowl of this.
This would be good...
Remember when Tony Soprano
would come home?
Like, he'd come home
after a night of whoring
and killing people,
and he'd go home,
and he'd open the refrigerator,
and there would be,
like, a Tupperware container,
and there'd be, like,
some cold, leftover zini
that Carmela had made him,
like, maybe the night before
or maybe two nights ago,
but the fact is it was there.
As completely awesome as
this is, I would wake up
and eat this cold,
like in a Tupperware
container the next morning.
I would totally eat this.
It's completely awesome.
It's a great compliment.
There's a couple cookies
in here for you.
One's a macaroon,
chocolate, and raspberry.
- So, thank you.
- It's been a pleasure.
Wow.
Enjoy.
♪ ♪
Mmm.
I like rooting around
in Gene Simmons' brain.
Yeah, I do not approve of
your right-wing politics.
Oh, yeah.
♪ ♪
Why?
Welcome to Disgraceland,
Alison's Nashville home.
It's a house party, so
there's got to be food.
You're just doing a small
series there where you
weren't looking?
You don't have to look
when you cut, right?
- No.
- We can look at each other.
Yeah. Watch.
Ready?
Okay.
♪ ♪
And as one must at any
reputable house party,
live entertainment.
Dean Fertita, Jack Lawrence, Mr.
Jack White,
and Alison Mosshart.
Known, I believe, as
The Dead Weather.
♪ I never know how
to treat you ♪
♪ You say I love you
but it ain't true ♪
♪ I'm walking away now ♪
♪ Hey ♪
♪ One step forward ♪
♪ And back two ♪
♪ I like you grab
you by the hair ♪
♪ And hang you up
from the heavens ♪
In the galley, Matthew and I
slave over celeriac, apple,
and walnut salad,
fried pork dumplings,
pulled pork with red
cabbage, and deviled eggs,
because it ain't a party without
deviled eggs, and brisket.
♪ ♪
♪ Ooh ♪
♪ I wanna grab you by the hair ♪
♪ And hang you up
from the heavens ♪
Ow!
♪ ♪
Thank you.
In another part of the
house, free party favors
for everyone.
Permanent ones.
Choose your tattoo carefully,
my drunken friends.
Choose well.
Oh, you spelled
"Donald Trump" wrong.
Damn it!
♪ ♪
Also on the bill, The Kills.
♪ Hollywood 2 a.m. ♪
♪ Oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh ♪
♪ Questioning everything ♪
A tooth tattoo in
some cultures means...
Actually, I have no idea
what it means until Alison
said she chose it because she
liked it and it's for biting.
Upper hand.
Nice.
♪ Get the vision ♪
♪ Come on ♪
♪ ♪
I, on the other hand,
gave this scorpion
careful consideration
after a less carefully
considered number of tequilas.
Yeah?
That looks amazing.
- It bends, but...
- It's sinister.
- I like it.
- Totally sinister.
♪ ♪
♪ Nothing is a color
I cross the desert ♪
♪ Nothing is alive ♪
♪ What does the black top know ♪
♪ That I have not
cracked with my mind ♪
♪ Nothing is a color ♪
♪ Gray as the pill ♪
♪ Nobody cries ♪
I'm pretty proud of that.
That came out pretty good.
Thank you.
♪ I feel love ♪
♪ Every million miles ♪
♪ Every once in a while ♪
♪ I feel love ♪
♪ Every million miles ♪
♪ Every once in a while ♪
♪ ♪
I'm still... I'm still so drunk.
A drink'll help.
♪ ♪
- Man, good party.
- Yeah.
It was, like, the greatest.
As I was driving here, I
just couldn't stop smiling.
Just remembering, like, the
things I can remember,
which is not all of it,
but there's a timeline.
- What...
- You, yeah.
- Oh, my God.
- Seriously, I have bite marks.
No, no, no way.
- No, I do, I've got...
- Who bit you?
That's a cigarette.
That's a bite mark.
What's that?
Awesome.
That's a bruise.
What's that?
There's a timeline here, people.
- The last I was gonna get...
- Let's work it out.
I feel so complete.
And I was gonna wear that today,
but I... -Oh, my goodness.
Nailed it.
That guy was wearing a tutu.
So I guess it could be
worse this morning.
I mean, I could be...
♪ ♪
- Wow, what's that?
- Ooh.
Bloody Mary.
Yeah.
Apparently we took
some casualties
at last night's house party.
But for every throbbing
skull, every unremembered
blunt force trauma,
there is a cure:
a Bloody Mary, a Mimosa, or
both, should you prefer.
Pinewood Social.
Our friend Josh's place,
where natural allies,
alcohol, hangovers, and
bowling coexist peacefully
in an atmosphere
of mutual respect.
Also food.
Tony, how many times
do you eat a day?
No, because when I watch
that show, I think about it.
I'm like, "Wow, you've
had, like, seven meals"
and it's only 1:00."
♪ ♪
- Who's up?
- You're up first.
I'm up? Okay.
Yeah.
♪ ♪
Oh.
Going well.
Not a promising beginning.
It can only get better.
I don't think he's American.
If there's any hustler,
it would be I.J.
You know?
Yeah.
The unassuming guy who
just happens to show up
after being missing
for a little while.
Right.
I can see that.
♪ So many promises,
favors, and lies ♪
♪ Most of the town wears
a good disguise ♪
That might have been the
quickest gutter of the day.
♪ As the saying goes,
it's not who you know ♪
♪ But it's who you blow
that'll get you in the show ♪
♪ And if that's not the case ♪
♪ I hear you pay 'em ♪
♪ But I don't come easy ♪
♪ And I'm flat broke ♪
Oh!
♪ Maybe I'd be smarter ♪
♪ If I played dumb ♪
Oh, yes.
Yeah.
Oh!
♪ Now I know much better ♪
♪ Than to let that make me mad ♪
Over the line.
That's the one!
♪ ♪
Yes!
Oh!
I was like... I was going,
okay, get into character.
In a safer world, all of us
here would be prohibited
from hurling heavy
objects in any direction
given our sorry states and
our general ineptness
at this sport of kings.
But that's Nashville for you.
A welcoming place.
A forgiving one.
I feel right at home.
♪ ♪
♪ When I first came here ♪
♪ The streets were
paved with gold ♪
♪ And you can walk that
road I've been told ♪
♪ But I won't put out
or be controlled ♪
♪ I don't write the shit
that gets bought and sold ♪
♪ Ask any man, he might know ♪
♪ Who used to live
on Music Row ♪
♪ But that was then
and this is now ♪
♪ And he told me ♪
♪ This town gets around ♪
♪ From what I've found ♪
♪ ♪