Welcome to my place of dreams.
My spirit house.
A city of ghosts.
♪
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la la
♪
Way in central Vietnam is
some place I've never been
before.
But it's still Vietnam.
Where all the things, the
smells, the sounds, the
details, I love so much.
First night in country, it's
like sliding into a warm, deeply
comforting familiar bath.
I've been all over Vietnam,
a place I feel a special
connection to.
My first love, a place I remain,
beed soed with, fascinated by...
Besodded with, fascinated by.
So back in Vietnam, one of
my favorite places on earth.
And all of the things
I need for happiness.
Plastic stool, tiny little
plastic table, check.
Oh.
Something delicious in a bowl.
Check.
In this case a local
specialty, com hen, clam rice,
sweet clams out of their shells,
tossed with a wild swirl, beans,
spicy green chillies, krumpbly
roasted peanuts, fried
pork riend, and cilantro.
And a similar
variation with rices.
That fish sauce with chilies in
it, and oh, that'll just
singe your eyebrows off.
Chilies in.
Hit with hot clam broth,
and you're on your way.
I'm back.
Back in Vietnam.
Grin for the duration.
A giddy, silly, foolish
man beyond caring.
And a cold local beer.
My preferred brand.
Ah.
Clams with pork cracklings.
How could that not be good?
This is the way so many of the
great meals of my life
have been enjoyed.
Sitting in the street, eating
something out of a bowl that I'm
not exactly sure what it is.
Scooters going by.
So delicious.
I feel like an animal.
Where have you been all my life?
Fellow travelers, this
is what you want.
This is what you need.
This is the path to true
happiness and wisdom.
Located on the north and
south banks of the perfume river
in central Vietnam, mountains
behind, sea ahead, an
arrangement determined by
criteria both military and
spiritual.
For 143 years, way was the seat
of power for the dynasty which
ruled the entire country until
the late 1800s when the French
started taking power and
land under their control.
The French allow the imperial
throne to rule nominally the
center of the country, until the
end of world war ii in 1945.
Way has been celebrated for its
fantastic architectures since
the early 1800s, vast
palaces, pagodas, and tombs.
The center is wealth of the
intellectual, artists, and
spiritual life of the country.
Oh yeah, that's tempting.
Around here somewhere.
This is dong Ba market, and deep
inside, somewhere in
there is what I want.
My way of thinking, in the
hierarchy of delicious, Slurpee
stuff in a bowl, it
is at the very top.
He is an author and journalist
that spent much of his
childhood in hue.
This will be it.
Let's do it, man.
Here he creates an elaborate
broth of mixed bones scented
with a lemon grass, spice,
and fermented shrimp paste.
At the bottom, rice noodles
garnished, heaped with tender
slow cooked beef shank,
pig's foot, and blood cake.
Garnished with lime wedge,
cilantro, green onions, shredded
banana blossoms, it's a...
Blossoms, it's a wonder of
flavor and texture.
The greatest soup in the world.
Look at that, man, that
is just unbelievable.
Blood cake.
The sauce.
I want to see how
much he put in there.
You have to make it look
really red in there, it has to
be blood red.
And the broth is wonderful.
People are put on earth for
various purposes, I was
put on earth to do this.
Eat noodles right here.
When I was a kid, we used to
tell each other, do not take a
date to go out to eat, if you
start sweat, your hair stick up.
Really?
I would definitely bring a date
to this, if she doesn't like
this, there's no hope of a
relationship.
Exactly.
If she said I don't know,
there's icy stuff in there, that
would be a relationship
of offender for me.
I'm not kidding.
Here you are having it
in a market like this.
She makes this place like
would be a real cuisine.
It's just sophisticated a
bowl of food as any French
restaurant.
It really is the, just
the top of the mountain.
How long has she been here?
She started out when she was 12.
You live in a great country,
man, any country that could
produce this is a
superpower, I'm concerned.
I'm getting down to
the pepper residue.
How long does that broth have to
simmer to get good?
An hour.
Wow, really?
I would have guessed
like 14 hours.
Yum.
Happy.
Nice burny feeling on my
lips, flop sweat, check.
Happy.
So, we can pretty much
cancel the rest of the show.
I've achieved the,
my happy zone.
It's really all down
hill from here.
My oldest friend in Vietnam.
Originally assigned to
translate, the guide, to escort,
and to report on me back in 2000
when I first came
to this country.
How are you, brother?
My brother.
Good to see you.
His responsibilities to his
employers have never been an
impediment to our friendship.
We meet where you pick your own
seafood out of the tank,
and you cook it yourself.
You really do look
exactly the same.
You look good.
Yeah?
Oh yeah.
No trace of time on your face.
My hair is white, I
have lines on my face.
I look completely
different in 2000.
People told me the sea food
is from the lagoon over here.
It is one of the biggest
ones in southeast Asia.
I'm going for some eel.
Season with lemon grass, green
chilly and pepper, drizzle with
house special sauce, grill
over charcoal and dig in.
I have the picture with you.
You have some old photos?
Oh, look at me, come on.
I look like my aunt Sonia, look
that the public I look
30 years younger.
My son.
Ming.
He's now 17.
Oh my god, he's going
to college soon.
Wow.
This is the island of Mr. Sang.
Yes, on the bay.
Oh my god, look at that.
We look cool.
We totally look cool here.
But does everybody fall in love
with the country like I did?
I came here, and
it stole my heart.
You know.
I think it's a very
good meeting point.
But in the past, it was over,
and now is a new time.
Mm.
Wow, that's great.
Dude, that's pretty spicy.
Perfect with beer.
We need more drinks.
Lobster from the
south China sea.
Give it a nice haircut table
side, and it's perfect.
Sweet.
Sweet, just like I remember.
Yeah.
Yep.
Sentimental guy.
Sometimes at work I try to be
serious, and I just think about
work, but I don't know why, when
I think about you, I think about
drinking and getting
something good to eat.
One more cheer.
Good to see you
again, my friend.
Its ban long time since my...
Been a long time since
my old friend and I met.
A hell of a lot of
road with this guy.
♪
One of the great joys of life is
riding a scooter
through Vietnam.
To be part of this mysterious,
thrilling, beautiful
choreography.
Thousands upon thousands of
people, families, friends,
lovers, each an individual story
glinsed for a second or two in
passing, sliding alongside,
pouring like a torrent
through the city.
A flowing, gorgeous thing.
As you ride, you not only see,
but overhear a hundred
intimate moment moments.
You smell wonderful
unnamed things cooking.
Issuing from store
fronts and food stalls.
The sounds of beeping, laughing.
Announcements from speakers, the
putt putt and roar of a
million tiny engines.
Hue's place in history long
regarded as the heart of the
imperial dynasty, changed
forever during the Vietnam war.
♪
In 1968, hue became the sight of
some... site of some of the most
bitter fighting of the war.
During the holiday, when usually
there was a sensation of
hostilities, more than 100
cities all over south Vietnam
were attacked by the
north Vietnamese and VC.
Hue quickly fell.
You have seen these images.
It was footage like this that
turned finally a great part of
the American public
against the war.
The U.S. marines fought house to
house to retake the city.
A vicious three and a
half week long battle.
Eventually, artillery and
air support were called in.
The city was saved.
And of course, largely
destroyed in the saving.
The civilian population caught
in the cross fire were
equally devastated.
The north Vietnamese to their
enduring shame had while
controlling the city, round up
anyone seen as a potential enemy
and either disappeared them away
to unknown prisons or
killed them outright.
Most notoriously when they
massacred almost 3,000 people,
rolling them, many of them still
alive in a mass graves
in and around hue.
He knows full well the horrors
and heartbreak of that time.
In his memoir, where the ashes
are, the odyssey of an American
family, he captures the terror
of a nine-year-old boy, the son
of a high ranking civil servant
caught up in the
nightmare of war.
Where were you in 1968?
I was at the place where
it's now a hotel.
My parents were staying there,
we were staying there, we were
surrounded during the
night, we didn't even know.
My father looked out the window
and thought it was south
Vietnamese soldiers.
Even was surprised.
We thought it was something
happening out in the
battlefields and the mountains,
out in the countryside, and all
the sudden, we come here, and
there's the flag of the national
liberation front, and to see
that was complete shock.
We stayed for a week in the
basement, and the American
soldiers came.
By that time they marched
my father away, the north
Vietnamese soldiers, we didn't
know where he was taken to and
we had no idea whether
he was alive or not.
My mother went out to the mass
graves and she saws the bodies
and she said I can't go
there and look for him.
♪
A lot of people died here.
You cannot help thinking
about these people who died when
they're young, who
died for no reason.
Who just got caught
in the fire fights.
We have the day of the dead
here, the day of the souls, and
we honor those who are not
buried within their home
village, and are not taken care
of, their spirits are
not taken care of.
There are families here who
don't have a death date.
Which is huge, a death
anniversary in the Vietnamese is
when you do the ceremonies, you
pay attention to the dead.
You can't do that if you don't
know when they really died.
You just assume those people
are just never liberated,
spiritually, that they
are stuck in that space.
It was like that for my father
because he was in prison,
we had no news from him.
You couldn't set up an alter,
you just hoped
that he was alive.
Ten, 12, 15 of your friends are
going out and doing things, you
just had that weight on you that
your father is somewhere
imprisoned or in the jungles.
And that stuff stayed with
me for 40 years in my mind.
I don't know how many Vietnamese
have that kind of experience.
At the same time, I come back to
hue, my hometown, my family's
hometown, I'm glad people are
alive, people are living, things
are happening,
things are changing.
We need to let the country open
up and let the people have a
moment of enjoyment,
have a better life.
I mean, obviously I'm an
outsider, but it seems to me as
a casual observer, you
can survive anything.
That's what my brother reminds
me, things happening in
Vietnam, it survived
4,000 years.
It will do okay.
When you ask me to be
hopeful, I am hopeful.
It's a young country.
It's a young population.
It's energetic and that drives
me, that gives me hope that
makes me young, that makes me to
want believe in this country.
And this town.
Such a wonderful place to be.
♪
Boi Tran is a painter, and
something of a throwback, an
anomaly, a creature from another
earlier time in the life of
the one time imperial city.
She lives in an area called the
hill, in a magnificently
restored compound.
These traditional wooden houses
were once part of the regal
style with slope grooves to
handle all the
rainy hue weather.
But most importantly, they
feature a garden at the center,
which follows the eastern
philosophy that all things
originate from a single source,
and expand in all directions.
Since the loss of her beloved
son, she's lived here.
Surrounded by her
garden and her art.
Occasionally, she invites
guests and friends.
There's duck, writer and food
blogger, art collector,
and fi leap.
This is also a gallery?
Yes, I design and
my people work.
She also cooks, magnificently
from a repertoire of imperial
hue dishes numbering over 100.
Back in dynastic time, the
emperor ts demanded varieties in
wives of sometimes
over 100, and in food.
The menus of the 19th century
boasted new dishes every night.
Small, flavorful, and
beautifully presented.
And that cultural tradition
continues today.
How much of that persists?
Those imperial roots
that need for variety?
Yes, the tradition has stayed,
and it will stay forever
here to cook all these
different things all the time.
We start with bird's nest soup.
A delicacy to which I
am usually immune.
This one is unusually flavorful.
These are swallow's nests
from high up on cliffs.
They're soaked in water, cooked
in chicken stock, and
served with crab meat.
A symbol of purity, nobility and
Patience from a nearby lake.
Steamed.
Crab row is mixed with red
onion, pepper, and seasoning
and added to the soup.
And simmered.
The symbolic and health aspects
of many of these dishes
not to be overlooked.
This is fantastic.
Lovely.
How does hue differ from
the rest of Vietnam?
A wonderful architecture,
and very quiet people.
If you stay some time in hue,
after some day you feel
quiet, you take your time.
It is a traditional dish
that's seldom made these days
because of the complexity and
the time needed to do it right.
A fish stock is made.
A fish from the perfume river.
Pineapples, onion, chilies,
shallots, and coriander.
A salad of quickly cooked
prongs, rice noodles, ginger,
red chili, garlic.
Layer of rice noodle, banana
flower, then the prongs,
garnishes.
The strained fish stock is
brought to the table with the
salad in separate bowls and
combined just before eating.
Spicy for you?
No, it's good.
I love it.
It is very spicy.
Oh no, I like it.
What I found when I first came
to the this part of the
world, Vietnam particular.
My pallet changed, I need and
elevated level of
chilies and heat.
Much of Vietnamese cooking
abided by principles
of ying and Yang.
Heat and cold.
This one a lobster dish with
five spices balances the
coldness of the lobster with
the heat of the spices.
Red onion ginger, lemongrass is
added to cook the lobster.
Once the lobster's cooked, it's
presented in a bowl
of lime leaves.
And the stock is poured over it.
Whoa.
That's beautiful.
We're getting into this with
our hand, I'm guessing.
I like this.
Beautiful.
The winter sheer unbelievable,
it's very... here
is unbelievable,
very cold and wet.
That's why we have
chili to keep us warm.
Spoils all of with us a
succession of dishes.
But the past as it often does in
a place like this, intrudes.
Its dealt with a
lot of suffering.
The people are very
withdrawn in some ways.
Smiling, but off course as
they remember everything.
They have to remember
the war in 1968.
I was visiting my grandfather's
house, and I got goose bumps
because I knew during the war in
1968 lots of people were killed.
And they were buried on
all the sidewalks there.
And I'd walk around
there and I feel it.
It's dark, it's somber,
and the history is there.
My mom, she never wanted me
to go home after like 10:00.
She get angry if I got home
at 11:00 or something.
When I got home at 9:00.
I tried to go home very early.
Riding a boat along the
river, you sort of feel there
are things living in the water
and in the trees and in
the darkness out there.
Know your enemy they say.
Know who it is you're
facing out there.
Who are they?
Why do they fight?
What are they willing to endure
in the furtherence
of their cause.
These one would think are simple
questions, useful
in any conflict.
Meet the enemy.
Okay.
He was only an infant during our
nine year long war, but
his experience should be
instructive.
In 1965:00 with the united
states initiated a sustained
bombing campaign called
rolling thunder.
Hoping to destroy an elusive
enemy in villages like this one.
Vinh Moc which was less than 20
miles from marine fire bases
just south of the DMZ.
This is where he was born.
As the target of frequent
bombings, the village of Vinh
Moc moved underground.
Up to 100 feet down
into darkness.
The villagers carved over
5,000 feet of tunnels
out of the earth.
Creating a complex that would
house all 90 families
of Vinh Moc.
13 entrances and exits leading
from the inland to the beach.
Showing me through the
labyrinth.
She since moved to the
DMZ to work as a guide.
How did they dispose of all of
this earth at rock without
revealing the tunnels?
The craters, the craters were
everywhere on the landscape of
the moon, and you know, the dirt
of the craters are so fresh,
look new, so they
just left them there.
This was the maternity
ward where Todd was born.
Where did people sleep?
They have sleeping places.
Just like this, but smaller.
Two square meters only,
just enough to put a bed.
How long did it take to build?
20 months of digging.
By hand.
The farmer dug with their tools.
Right.
Under the bombing.
While the bombing is going
on, they're down here
digging this out.
Wow.
How many children here?
How did they play?
So much of the time you
were in total darkness.
Yeah.
You can't see your mother.
Some people say that even
when the parents, you know, fit
the children, they need to touch
their face and find their
mouth and feed them.
Wow.
Children played here.
But people also emerged from
these tunnels to kill
or cripple Americans.
To shoot them, to plant Bobby
traps, and that's what
they did... booby traps.
And that's what they did.
Six years in darkness.
And at the end of the war, the
people of Vinh Moc emerged
from the darkness.
And what did they do?
What was that like after living
in darkness for so long?
What was it like to come out and
be able to spend the rest
of his life in the sun?
Thank you, wow, ready.
Thank you.
Looks kind of like a mackerel.
Good.
Good?
Yeah.
Really?
Yes.
Last question, hypothetical,
if the French or the Japanese,
or the Americans, suddenly
decided they wanted for some
reason to come back,
would he fight?
That's different.
They're all welcome
if they're tourists.
There are particular sounds
that come with waking
up in rice country.
At lagoon however, early
morning... lagoon however,
it is the end of a workday.
As fishermen who have been out
on the water and sell their
catch in the early mist.
I'm meeting up for a
tasty afternoon snack.
It is set back from a quiet Lane
in the outskirts of town.
It's a neighborhood place
specializing in this.
Little pancake-like things made
of rice flour, steamed in molds,
and topped with crispy fried
shallots and crumbled
fried shrimp.
Show me how you eat this.
I have this when I
was a little girl.
So you try to pick
it up like this.
Right.
I got it.
Just cut around the edge here.
I feel so clumsy.
Its been a while.
Fold it over.
Oh it just... mm.
This is great.
This is so nostalgic to me.
I will sit there in front
of our house... waiting.
Waiting for her, with a dish,
she would come and my mom
would buy for me.
At the end of the day,
we see who eat the most.
Good, glad I'm fitting in here.
What do they have
in the banana leaf?
Are we having one of those too?
We have everything.
I don't want to
leave anything out.
It's made of tap yolka with
pork and shrimp from the lagoon,
wrapped like a tamale in
banana leaf, then steamed.
So, you can open.
In Vietnam, we learn how
to unwrap the thing.
So unwrap with these.
Cause I'm watching you.
Let's get this right.
You do it perfect.
I think you an expert.
Maybe in I a past life,
you were born here.
In a past life.
So this is shrimp.
Pick it up and dip.
Hmm.
Very nice.
They're pretty too.
Look at that.
You can see what's inside.
You call this type
of eating an-choi.
It's like for fun or playing.
Recreational eating.
Yeah.
So it's not a main meal.
It's for snacking.
Sticky rice dumplings.
Started with frying the
paste in cooking oil.
Then unpeeled shrimp are
stuffed into dough.
Place the chewy part with the
crunchy part and sprinkle
with chopped, fried shrimp.
Oh, wow, that is awesome.
What is underneath?
Rice base.
Oh, okay.
But on the top is thin.
At the back.
Oh, that's great.
Nice and crispy and greasy.
I love it.
Anybody would love this.
It's just amazing.
It's a combination
between the soft...
The soft and the
crispy, crunchy.
Delicious.
Last ride, a few miles out
of town, whip across
the rice paddies.
Just getting from here to there,
this part of the world,
it's pure pleasure.
♪
I'm meeting my friends
for a country lunch.
What's a specialty
at this restaurant?
Chicken baked in Clay?
Yes.
Another friend from the past,
Pham, Lin, of course,
and a new friend tan.
A last meal, some goodbyes.
I have a question.
What make you stay so long?
Because normally travelers come
and stay only one or two nights.
What's your
impressions about it?
It's very laid back.
The food's great.
It's pretty.
There's a lot to see.
It's a perfect place to go if
you want to take your time.
It's beautiful to me.
♪
Food's coming.
Out here, there are a lot
of dishes like this.
Fill a chicken in banana grass
and cover it with Clay
from the rice paddies.
Took in a burning pile of straw,
unwrap carefully tableside.
Section with sheers.
Smells so good.
Make me hungry.
Serve with a little lime and
salt, maybe some chili sauce.
Squash, bitter
morning, for veggies.
Tastes good.
That's good.
Some unexpected last words.
On behalf of people, thank
you for you coming.
Thank you for having me.
We wish you would have a
blessed trip, safe and
sound and success.
Thank you.
I learned many things
from American.
I still remember some poems.
On a snowy evening.
Please.
Sometime drink a lot of beer.
I think I know, this
house is in the village.
You will not see
me stopping here.
He gives a second to ask if
there's mistakes, the only other
sound... and something else.
Bravo.
So we wish you have a
good trip, a good fly.
Will you come back after
you return to New York?
I'll come back to
Vietnam, always.
Cheers, everybody, and thank
you, all of you for
all of your help.
Cheers one more time.
♪
This is who came out of the
ground, out of the jungle, the
darkness, when it was all over.
And this is what they did.
♪