Rise and shine, it's a
beautiful day in Houston.
But it's gonna be a hot one.
♪ I took a walk through this ♪
♪ Beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain ♪
♪ On my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good ♪
♪ In this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la, la ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la, la, la ♪
Close minded, prejudicial,
quick to make assumptions
about places different
than where we grew up.
I'm not talking about Texas.
I'm talking about, well,
me and people like me,
who are way too comfortable
thinking of Texas
as a big space filled
with intolerant,
invariably right-wing
white people.
Waddling between the fast-food
outlet and the gun store.
That, of course, is wrong.
♪
But then I'm used
to being wrong.
Texas, Houston in particular,
is a very different place
than you might imagine
from the stereotypes
and the sound bytes of its
national political figures.
Immigrants, refugees,
and non-white Americans
have, in fact, been
transforming the city,
the food and culture
of Houston, for years.
♪
Welcome to America people.
Just another day at the
supermarket, a sleepy strip mall on
Houston's Hillcroft Avenue.
Keemat Grocers, serving
the community since 1994.
Today they're hosting a
quiet, low-key affair.
Good afternoon,
ladies and gentlemen,
how are we doing today?
We're here in Little
India in Keemat Grocers,
and I think this is
the best Little India
in all of USA, right?
DJ Zee, I wanna throw
a party right now.
Everybody, let's
start this party!
♪
Put your hands up, everybody!
How large is the community here?
Two hundred thousand people.
Two hundred thousand?
And that's India and Pakistan?
Yeah, Indians, Pakistanis.
Some Bangladeshis,
very few Nepalis.
So 200,000 and rising quick?
Yeah.
Sunil Thakkar is an owner
of Masala Radio 1320
on your AM dial.
Himalaya is a beloved
Indian-Pakistani restaurant
run by Karachi native
Kaiser Lashkari.
So the food here is amazing.
It's like Indian and
Pakistani mixed together.
Right.
Now, how's that work?
Because over there, the
relation's not so friendly.
Here, does everybody... is
it all peace and love?
Yeah, you know, there's
no boundaries here.
I see so many homes, new
homes, new subdivisions
and people just buying them up.
And on my street, 18 homes,
12 out of them are from
other countries.
India, Pakistan,
Malaysia, Indonesia.
And once you live together, it
just sort of you become family.
How many brown people here?
- Any non-Indians?
- I want to see non-Indians.
You're the non-Indians?
What I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
see how good this Asian guy
can do a Bollywood step.
Move like this.
Yeah, good. Good.
So how old were you
when you moved here?
I was 17 when I came here.
And growing up, I wanted
to be a Bollywood star.
I wanna be a movie star.
But my mom didn't
want to do anything
- -with this whole movie business.
- Right.
When I came here,
and something about
this country, something
about the openness
got me just kind of doing
what I wanted to do.
And I said, "I always wanted
to be an entertainer."
I always wanted to
be a comedian."
And radio was perfect for
me to bring Bollywood
in people's cars.
Houston's got the biggest
drive time... So people listen
to the radio here.
I couldn't do this back home.
But here, you get a chance
to just be a new you.
You can just be a new person.
You know, they say,
"Oh, Hindus reincarnate
thousands of times."
I feel like I reincarnated
live when I came here.
♪
An intensely aromatic biryani,
goat marinated in yogurt,
garlic, and ginger, then
slow-cooked with cumin,
cardamom, and star anise.
Green curry chicken
done Texas-Desi style
with a blend of tomatillos
and green chilies,
cilantro, and cumin.
Steak tikka and hunter's beef,
sort of an Indian-inflected
pastrami, an invention of the
chefs, brined for 10 days,
cooked and served with
homemade mustard sauce.
What about your kids?
Do they feel American, or
do they feel Indian, or do
they feel Indian-American?
So they're definitely
Indian-American.
- You know, they eat Indian food.
- Right.
But if you give
my son an option,
he wants to go to Taco Bell.
They speak Gujarati.
- They like Bollywood dancing.
- Uh-huh.
But yet they're not
as Indian as I am.
I want my kids and I want
all of the kids to come in
and feel that these
are our traditions
that we got to continue.
We got a panipuri-eating
contest coming up.
Who can tell me
what a panipuri is?
Like a little dumpling,
and it has a hole in it
and filled with
potatoes and chickpeas.
And then it has a
spicy filling in it.
All right, on the count of
three, what I'm gonna do is,
I'm gonna give you 30 seconds,
and I want to see who can eat
the most panipuris.
DJ Zee, you got
some music ready?
On the count of three.
One, two.
One, two, three, four!
♪
Thirty seconds.
Most panipuris in 30 seconds.
Come on. Eat the puris.
I'm gonna give you thirty
more seconds 'cause I think
you guys are little slow.
Ten! Nine!
Eight, seven, six, five,
four, three, two... One.
Out of 20, you got one, two,
three, four, five, six, seven.
Twenty minus seven.
Thirteen.
She is the winner!
♪
I find Houston to be
probably the most accepting
place for me.
- Why?
- I love it here.
I love... I love... I love
being Indian in Houston.
It's not one of those
towns that you say,
"Oh, I want to live in Houston."
But once you come here,
once you live here,
you don't want to
move out of here.
You know, I always consider
India as my motherland,
but Houston's my home.
♪
It's Saturday night in Houston.
And at the Acapulco Ballroom,
in the city's Pasadena
neighborhood, tonight
is all about
15-year-old Evelyn Araña.
If you're Mexican
or Mexican-American
or anywhere in between and
you've got a daughter
turning 15, you better be
throwing her a quince,
or a quinceañera, to be precise.
Quinceañera, what is it?
It's the becoming of a young
lady and whenever they turn
15-years-old.
If you're of Mexican heritage
in Houston, I gather you kind
of have to have one if you've
got a daughter, right?
In Houston, yes.
It is an honor to have a
quinceañera and for your parents
to be able to give you one.
♪
The quinceañera business is a
multi-million dollar a year
industry around here.
The competition is
fierce, it is a big deal
is what I'm saying.
And the style and budget
can vary enormously,
depending on means and ambition.
Friends, relatives,
and neighbors gather
to eat, drink, dance.
And Acapulco owners Elizabeth
and Ezequiel Ortuño
are keeping a close
eye on the action,
making sure everything
goes according to plan.
Who gets invited
to these things?
I mean, this is a lot of people.
- I don't have this many friends.
- Friends and family.
Friends and families and
from the school too.
Right. Oh, so you got to
invite all the girl's friends
from school.
You have kids?
Yes.
You have family?
Any girls?
Four girls.
So they all had these.
All of them have had
their quinceañeras,
and a couple of them have
had their sweet 16s.
You get a quinceañera
and a sweet 16?
Yes.
Oh, my God.
I was really happy about having
a girl, but it's expensive.
What... what do boys get?
A soccer ball.
That's cost-effective.
♪
The way we think about
Houston, Texas, today
is very much stuck in the past.
In the late '70s, early '80s,
Houston was the boomtown
of popular television
and movie imagination.
Oil, shipping, NASA, and
football combined to create
a big-spending, big-haired,
quasi-cowboy stereotype.
That, to some extent, still
lives with us today,
even if the reality
is different.
♪
Though the oil is not gone, a
massive glut in the mid-80s
sent prices into freefall,
more or less killing
the city's oil industry.
The resulting economic downturn
and lower cost of living
made Houston, however improbable
it might seem to you,
you Yankee trash,
much more welcoming
to people with less means,
people getting away
from bad situations, people
from somewhere else.
What that means is that now,
Houston... you know, Houston...
Is a place where minorities
are now the majority.
♪
At the end of the
war, Jonathan escaped
Vietnam on a makeshift
raft with his family.
After serving in the
United States Marine Corps
and obtaining a master's
degree in education,
he became the principal of
this school, Lee Senior High,
the most ethnically diverse
school in the city.
What percentage of... of your
student body, English is not
their first language?
I would say about 80% of them.
Do those kids get sent
here specifically?
- Or is it just...
- Oh, no, no, no, no.
...reflective of the community?
- It just...
- So 80%.
By chance, you know.
In the city of Houston and the
surrounding suburban area,
it's very well integrated.
It's like it's not... it's not... Why?
How did that happen?
I think one of the main
reasons is the strong
economic base here.
It's because of the availability
for you to get a job
and make a decent wage.
It allow for immigrants,
families to come over
and build a nest egg,
to own their own home
or go to a better neighborhood.
It has to be a strong
economic, viable base
for them to quickly
overcome that poverty
and allow them to make
a life for themselves.
♪
Good morning.
All right, repeat after me.
Positive affirmations.
"Today's a beautiful day."
Today is a beautiful day.
"I will work hard."
I will work hard.
"I am important."
I am important.
Repeat.
"I will succeed."
I will succeed.
More than 40
languages are spoken
among the 1,700 students
here, many of them
from conflict zones where the
alternatives were stark,
leave quickly or die.
Often, their first exposure
to the American educational
system is here, ESL, English
as a Second Language class,
where teacher Gary Reed,
a 30-year veteran,
does his very best to
get them up to speed
and ready for the next steps.
You see these people?
What did they do?
All of these people right
here, they came to Houston
from Salvador,
Vietnam, Iraq, Syria.
Just like you, they came.
No money, no home.
And what happened?
Yeah, they graduated.
So don't say, "Oh, I can't do it.
I can't..."
You can do it.
What part of the world are
most kids -coming from now?
Currently, it's Central America.
Guatemala?
Guatemala, El
Salvador, Nicaragua.
El Salvador's the major one.
In many cases, if you were
to send these kids back,
it's a death sentence.
I mean, let's call
it what it is.
Yes.
Other classes, -math, history.
Uh-hmm.
Taught in their own
language or English?
No, no. They're
taught in English.
- So this class is absolutely essential.
- Uh-hmm.
Now, we're working on
personal introductions.
Who's brave enough to
introduce themselves?
Hello.
My name is Omeri.
Hi, my name is Mr. Reed.
Nice to meet you.
Nice to meet you too.
Now, what are the things you do?
What do you do with your eyes?
Repeat, "eye contact."
Eye contact.
Good, good.
What about his hands?
You can do that.
Grab it firm.
Firm handshake.
It's a first impression.
Stand up. Stand up.
Okay, this is side A.
You present to side B.
Ready?
One, two, three, go.
Nice to meet you.
Good, good.
So it's you shake.
Look in the eye like that, okay?
That's expected.
Girls... Ana, in America,
you can do it.
It's okay to get a
nice handshake.
What happens if it doesn't
work, if they don't have this?
What's the future looking
like if they don't acquire
language skills?
They become a third-class
citizen here.
What kind of work are you
getting, and what are your
opportunities?
Oh, yes, the service
market in any major city
is always there.
Landscaping, valet, car washers.
But our students
are very gifted.
They are talented kids.
They just need opportunity
to learn English
and opportunity to learn.
These kids, when they grow up,
they will be part American,
and they have kids.
They will pick up arms
and defend this country
just like I expected to do and
I expect my three boys to do
not because someone forced me
but because I believe in it.
I believe in the opportunity
that it provides.
I believe that no matter
how poor you are,
how uneducated you are
when you first come
to the United States,
if you have the will
to educate yourself, work
hard at it, you can achieve.
♪
Chicken sandwich
and French fries,
fruit salad, carton of milk.
Welcome to America, kids.
I haven't had one of
these in a long time.
So what country is
everybody from?
I'm from Africa, like
Ghana, Cote d'Ivoire.
Honduras.
Iraq.
Where in Iraq?
Baghdad.
Pakistan.
And you've been here how long?
One year.
Everybody's English is pretty good.
Very good.
It took me at least two
years just to be brave
enough to... to open up, you know.
No, they're progressing
very, very well.
Mister, do you
like African food?
Yeah, I've been to Africa a lot.
I have not been to
Burkina Faso, but I love
the food in Ghana.
The food in Senegal
is very, very nice.
You already been to Senegal?
Oh, yes, fantastic.
Your first day in school,
was it frightening?
I didn't know nobody here, and
nobody here from my country.
So I feel scared,
but step by step,
I start to learn
English and then start
to communicate with people.
So after school, when you
graduate high school,
what do you want to do next?
I want to be a fashion designer.
And I want to go to college.
I want to study more.
What are you going to do?
I want to go to college, and
I want to study medicine.
I am between medicine
and engineering.
What do you want to do?
I plan soccer.
Soccer is not a plan, my friend.
♪
Pearland is the
quintessential sprawl
of suburban Americana.
And more and more these days,
this is the quintessential
American family, Jonathan his
Salvadoran-born wife, Silvia.
Along with his sister, Kim
and her husband, Ron.
Jonathan's mom, Nina and
Silvia's mom, Ayela.
So if you have, like, a... on
Christmas or Fourth of July
or a big holiday, how
many extended family?
How many people are coming over?
Oh, everyone.
A lot.
Wow, okay.
What's a lot? How many?
Forty. Fifty.
About 40, 50 people.
I mean, I don't even
see us as interracial
until people point it out.
Well, it's a typical Texan
family at this point.
Yeah.
Uh-hmm.
♪
Ayela cooks tamales de
gallina from scratch.
Outside, fresh papusas are
being made on a hot griddle.
Jonathan's mom,
Nina, makes a dish
of jellyfish, shrimp, and pork
tossed with mint, carrots,
red onion, and peanuts
dressed with nuoc mam,
the pungent Vietnamese
fish sauce.
And mi Quang, a rice noodle
dish from central Vietnam
made with pork ribs,
shrimp, and chilies.
Very mixed-up meal here.
Yeah.
Awesome!
Did... did you speak English
when you arrived here?
Oh, not a word.
I couldn't even say "hi."
So I learned it literally
within a year.
Yeah?
'Cause I had to.
By fifth grade, this one
teacher, Miss Spikes,
just made me feel like I was
the smartest little thing
in the whole world.
She built up my confidence
that I could do anything.
You know, we learned how
to speak Spanish first
before we learned how
to speak English.
Of course.
So you came over in
'78, did you say?
Late '77.
I was 10 years old, uh-hmm.
And we literally left
on... I don't even know
if we'd call it a boat.
It was more like a raft.
There was a hole in the boat.
We sat in water the entire time,
just sit in soaking water.
They let us come in as
refugees, United States.
You know, we lived in
government housing projects.
Me, my sister, and my brother
all were placed in the same
category for ESL.
We were probably one of the
first wave of boat people
resettlement to Houston.
So what was the urgency to
take such a tremendous risk?
Our parents felt we need to
take a chance on freedom
and opportunity than to
live under communist rule.
♪
Ain't nothing more American
than Viet-bayou-style crawdad
steamed with sriracha,
orange juice, and beer.
You got to have corn, of course,
and potatoes and sausage
and beer.
Did I mention beer?
♪
Texas, we get the bad
rep that we... we are
not compassionate.
And I think that's
a wrong portrayal.
Texans, as a whole,
when the crisis come,
are the most generous and the
most compassionate people
that I know.
It doesn't matter if
you're red or blue,
left or right, middle.
When... when that time come,
they are very generous,
and they... they will help out.
It's hot in Houston, so
things move a little
slower around here.
Maybe that explains this.
♪
♪ I wake up in the morning ♪
♪ Still high from last night ♪
♪ Ain't got no time to chill ♪
♪ I gots to get my cash right ♪
L.A. may have low riders,
but Houston has slab,
its own car culture, with
it's own accompanying sound.
Its own chopped and
screwed hip-hop style.
♪
♪ Born and raised
in Houston, Texas ♪
♪
This is pretty much, like,
one of the most classic
designs of a slab.
It's the Cadillac.
See how you got the insides
custom with the stitching
and all that?
So, you know, this is a
complete slab, you know.
- Full reclining is...
- Full reclining.
It's a laidback thing.
Houston musical artist Slim Thug
and his friends Bone and
David called some people
to bring their cars over
to MacGregor Park in the
southern part of the city.
If you're gonna do it,
what do you have to have?
- What are the rules?
- Candy paint.
Got to have these type of
rims with the elbow swingers.
Fifth wheel and grille is
mainly, like, for slab.
That's what make it a
complete, you know?
And the music, you know how
they got the pop trunk
with the custom music?
You got to have that also.
♪
♪ I need to stop it,
but it taste so good ♪
♪ Every time I stop drinkin',
drank keeps callin' me back ♪
♪ I need to stop it,
but it taste so good ♪
If you hit the block,
there's not a bunch
of dudes just standing up.
It's a bunch of everything.
You know, take the old
and mix it with the new.
These two pink
Cadillacs are awesome.
That's a married couple,
a man and woman,
and they have their
kids with them.
Each trunk that say something,
it's your autograph.
If you see it coming and
then you see the car
and the grille and then you see
the 2-2 chromes, it's like,
"Oh, my God, here comes"
whoever the guard is
of your neighborhood.
They basically, like,
legends in the streets.
Are all of these... like, are
they works in progress?
- Are people constantly... - I think it's got to be
- a work in progress.
I think a slab, you
gonna stay doing it.
Yeah, always changing 'em.
They get expensive, real talk.
Like, all these cars out
here, they probably spent
a bankroll on all of 'em.
♪ I wonder last year how
many sweets I rolled ♪
many cups I poured ♪
♪ Of that muddy, muddy
purple I purchased by... ♪
You're not eating Pizza
Hut in the back of that
are either, are you?
Well, really, we barely see
people in the back seat
of somebody car out here.
He's shaking his head.
"Nobody's getting
in the back seat."
Because you got to lean.
You got to lean back.
So that mean whoever
back here can't be long.
So I'm thinking about my
Lincoln now, you know.
Maybe I'm thinking, like,
crocodile skin on the outside.
I'm thinking about pony.
Pony?
From a horse or cow skin.
Like Palomino kind of a thing?
Palomino?
That'd be fresh.
It'd be evil.
Pay him no mind.
♪
Acres Homes is a predominantly
black community
where many of the original
slab pioneers come from.
It's also where you can find
the legendary family-run
Burns BBQ, a place not
unfamiliar to me.
I first came here 15 years
ago on some long-lost
travel program on a
network far, far away.
Founder Roy Burns has passed
on to the great open pit
in the sky since last I
was here, but his son
and his grandchildren carry
on the tradition of making
some of the best East
Texas-style barbecue
you can find around here.
It's been a while.
I mean, last time I was
here, the grandfather
was here back then.
You in the right place
for some barbecue, man.
What do you do?
You do ribs and brisket?
They do all that.
You do all that.
What is that?
Moonshine.
"Dukes of Hazzard."
Boss Hogg.
Wow. I could drink
a lot of that.
Baked potato.
Okay, that's gonna work.
A torpedo-size baked potato
filled with cheddar cheese
and chopped barbecue beef
and homemade link sausage,
slow-cooked pork ribs, big-ass
beef ribs, and brisket.
Whoa. Okay, I got
a baked potato.
This baked potato is yours.
It's... it's marvelous.
That thing is, like, gigantic.
My mother always said,
"Never eat anything
bigger than your head."
And that's about the
size of a human head.
That look good, though.
Ain't gonna lie.
So everybody born here?
Born and raised.
Has the town changed at all?
A lot.
Yeah, in what way?
You know, it was like a
big small town at first.
Now it's becoming like
a real city, you know.
Is that good or bad?
Depend on what you do.
Good and bad, kind of.
A lot of the stuff we was
really into back in the day,
these new kids or these
people from out of town
really ain't into,
even the music.
Like, back in the day,
Houston was so independent.
Like, I was selling so many
records out of the trunk
- -that I didn't want a major deal.
- -♪ I'm from H-Town ♪
♪ So you know what I'm sippin' ♪
♪ I'm from H-Town, so you
know what I'm sippin' ♪
♪ Hit the boulevard, got
the candy paint drippin' ♪
♪ And I'm from H-Town, so
you know what I'm sippin' ♪
♪ Hey ♪
Is there a distinctive
Houston sound?
Very. You know, the whole
culture from the cars
to the sippin' syrup and the
music itself... First of all,
what's sippin' syrup?
Syrup is promethazine
and codeine.
It was a cough syrup.
But then they mixed it
with soda out here.
Why is that the drug
of choice here?
Maybe because you
just see how it is.
Everything is so
chill and laidback.
In Atlanta, everything
was turnt up.
Out here, everything is slowed
down, 'cause I guess we're
a more laidback culture.
So at various points
in your career,
clearly, somebody
said, "Well, look."
"Why don't you move out here?"
L.A. is good.
- The money's out here.
- "The deals are out here."
Right.
But here you are.
Why stay?
I tried to go to I.A.,
and the people out
there are so thirsty to
try to be a star that
they fake and they crooked.
It was like I don't want to be
around those type of people.
I want to be around
good, genuine people.
Is Houston a good place to live?
Yup, great place.
Cost of living is cheap.
It stays hot and warm.
It's never snowing
to where you got
to shovel your driveway.
And the food is the
greatest out here,
and... and the black women... I
don't care where you go.
There ain't no better black women.
And that's what it is.
♪ I'm from H-Town, so you
know what I'm sippin' ♪
♪ And I'm from H-Town,
so you know what's... ♪
♪
It's a 90-minute drive
south from Houston
to the town of Palacios
on the Matagorda Bay.
And like a lot of the communities
down here, the principal
industry is fishing,
shrimp in particular.
It's also where,
beginning in the 1970s,
as the Vietnam War ground to
its ignominious conclusion,
the thousands of Vietnamese
found new lives and a new home.
To have remained would have
meant, in most cases, arrest,
imprisonment, reeducation
camps, or worse.
So all you want is
shrimp at this point.
Yeah.
I got shrimp and fish.
But I got enough fish.
Shrimp, you take.
Yup, yup. Big shrimp.
- The small, we don't get the shrimp.
- You don't want it.
No, I don't want to.
The shrimping has declined
considerably since the 1980s,
but the bay still provides
a solid livelihood
for people like Vin Nguyen,
who made it out of Vietnam
on a tiny handmade boat.
His engine died, and he
and his family were lost
in the South China Sea for
nine days before being rescued
by a cargo ship.
He became a United
States citizen in 1990
and raised his family
here in Palacios.
So what year did you come here?
How long have you
been doing this?
I have been... I start
for shrimp on 1985.
And what year did you
arrive in this country?
I left my country 1979.
How old were you
when you got here?
21-year-old.
You were 21.
So why shrimp?
How did you come
to this business?
- Because my... my... my cousin.
- Cousin, okay.
- He was living here.
- Right.
And I work on a job first.
But he told me... my cousin
told me that it's very good
for shrimping.
Good for shrimp.
Make money more.
♪
Back on dry land, Vince
first stop is The Point.
The town's general store.
It's owned and operated by
pillars of the community
Yen and Bryan Tran, who
separately came over from Vietnam
around the same
time, met, married,
and raised three children here.
This is fulfilling my dream.
I came here with
nothing, 17-years-old.
First job I ever worked
in washing dishes.
So my boss told me and say,
"Hey, you are hard worker.
You know, maybe one day,
you gonna be the boss."
So I have that thing in my mind.
After I get married, I
told my wife, said,
"Open a restaurant."
And she stopped me.
And she say, "No. You crazy."
So after all my kid went to
college, they got a good job,
I would mention again,
and she say, "Okay."
Aw, that's... that's nice.
♪
Convenience store, bait shop,
quick stop for a meal,
The Point is, in many ways,
typical in a way it's geared
towards serving the immediate
needs of its community.
Food for Vietnamese and
food for Mexicans.
Yen, Bryan, their kids
Jennifer and Kimberly,
as well as cousin TV
and his son Donnie...
All proud citizens
of the United States
of America, by the way.
You know, I... I really feel
fortunate we live in this town
and we have a lot of support.
When we went to open this store,
all my friends say, "I want"
to have Vietnamese food."
I know that here, you have
to have Mexican food.
So I went and talked
to the best Mexican
cook in town, Maricela.
Yeah, this is the
chef right here.
Yeah.
Good chef.
Yes.
Here's Maricela.
♪
The pho here is good.
Brisket, eye round,
meatball, tripe, and tendon
just like back home.
Ceviche made from
Vin's fresh shrimp.
And of course tacos, migas
style, with eggs, jalapeños,
and tomatoes.
The kids who grew up
in this community...
These are the kids.
Yeah, these the kids right here.
What are they doing?
I was born here in '76, so
I'm a natural-born citizen.
Working with my dad, right-hand
man, you know, shrimping,
doing the boats.
Just kind of seeing
what they went through,
I mean, it's... I definitely
appreciate life, you know.
Jenn here is a lawyer.
My sister's an engineer.
I'm in the medical field.
So there's still that...
You know, your parents
want you to have practical jobs.
So... Right.
So you came here what year?
1975.
So you came over in the
first... Yeah, I get
on American ship and get
the hell out of there.
I come over here no shoe.
I tell the truth, I don't
have even penny in my pocket
when I come over here.
No, serious.
And now I have a great business,
and, you know, really,
I say this a great country.
♪
This community of Vietnamese
people are very fortunate.
We always see the generosity
of people over here,
because we live in, what,
30 years of civil war?
Yeah.
So no one trusts anyone.
But when you come over
here, people take you in,
and they trust you.
And I... I always say that
United States opened a house
for the immigrant and
for the refugee.
I feel this is my home.
♪
My name is Gertrude.
I'm from Congo, Brazzaville.
I'm married to Albert, and
we have four children.
♪
It's my dream... my dream,
I need to big boss.
I need to have my land.
For sure, we like the
weather, because we don't
we have snow here.
On summer, I know it's very
hot here, but it's good
for planting, and people
are nice in Houston.
♪
Many of the more recent
arrivals in Houston
come from places where
life is unbelievably hard
and often dangerous.
Many come from agrarian
backgrounds, arriving here without
- the skill set needed to compete for jobs
- in an urban situation.
Plant It Forward, a non-profit
urban farming program,
provides refuges like
Gertrude and Albert Lombo
access to land where
they can make a living
from the ground.
So here we are, middle of
Houston, a lush, fertile plot
where eggplant,
squash, string beans,
and other produce is grown to
be sold at farmers' markets
and to restaurants around town.
♪
Fellow Congolese
Houston transplants
Gimoule and Constant Ngouala,
chefs when not tending
their crops, prepare an
outdoor meal for the Lombos
and a group of friends
and fellow farmers,
Congolese but with a
definite Cajun touch.
Or is it the other way around?
A slow-cooked stew
of sausage, shrimp,
dried mackerel, and Malabar
spinach over fufu.
Then Texas beef brochettes
marinated in chilies
and cilantro and Maggi bouillon
with a ratatouille made from
produce grown right here.
What did you all think when...
When you heard that you were
gonna be resettled in Texas?
In... in my country,
when... when people
are talking about Texas,
they know that is where
many farmer is.
Really? And now, do
you feel welcome?
Yes.
Do you feel the community
is happy you're here?
Wonderful.
The first challenge
was the language.
It wasn't easy.
Even now, it's not easy.
But you already speak
how many languages?
In Congo principal, we
have three languages.
Of course.
We have French, Lingala,
and Mono Kutuba.
So don't feel too bad.
Most Americans
struggle with one.
It's okay.
♪
I'm a refugee from DRC.
What did you do in Kinshasa?
I... I did electrician
and construction too.
And here?
I was machine operator.
After that, I decide
to be farmer.
It was my dream.
My dream, it was to
get my own garden.
Uh-hmm.
And when I harvest,
I need to cook.
What are you cooking now?
I work at Four Seasons Hotel.
- Oh, that's not a bad gig.
- Yeah, yeah.
How African will Houston
be in 20 years?
Oh!
A lot, right?
I want all my family still over
there... -my mom, my sister.
And you'd like them to come?
I want them to come.
A lot of first-generation
and second-generation
African babies
gonna be happening.
Yeah. Yeah.
Houston is gonna
look real different.
You'll hear Lingala
at the 7-Eleven?
No problem?
No problem.
In 10 years?
♪
The crack of the bat,
the roar of the crowd.
Two teams locked in struggle.
Take me out to the ballgame,
man, though the smell wafting
from behind the bleachers is
not hot dogs, or popcorn,
or roasting peanuts.
It's a hell of a lot
better, actually.
Basically, it's practically
like baseball.
First international game,
believe it or not,
was USA versus Canada.
Really?
Yes, in 1844.
Yeah, I don't know if you knew,
but cricket is second-most
watched sport... I... I
just read that.
Yes.
India is number one.
USA is number two.
I do like a sport
where you can aim
at somebody's crotch, though.
I think that's sort of awesome.
I'm not even gonna
try and explain
the sport of cricket to you.
There's a ball, and there's
bats, and I think you run
to, like, base.
Go out to Sardar Patel Stadium
in Houston's Richmond
neighborhood, and ask
league president
of the Houston Indian Cricket
Club, Kuldeep Patel,
what it's all about.
He knows. He was once a
big cricket star himself.
Let's go. Let's go!
Who's winning?
The first team scored 120 runs.
- Right.
- They're chasing right now.
I see.
So we can't really say,
'cause they haven't
had an opportunity.
Exactly, right?
See, this is why
it didn't happen.
We need... we like
winners in America.
We like to know who's
winning at all times.
But this is very
high-energetic game.
Baseball, when we watch baseball,
it's kind of slow to us.
- When we're playing... Well, even us, it is.
- It's a slow game.
It's really all about
the snacks in baseball.
Hot dogs.
The shitty hot dogs too.
And the beer's even worse.
Now for a hot dog.
Oh, no, right.
Now for some tandoori chicken,
cooked to perfection.
Some spicy, tender, and totally
delicious curried goat.
And made-to-order
potato masala dosas.
Are there fewer rules here?
The caste system, you
lose that right away?
It's not right away,
you got to understand,
because when... when
somebody's come from a rich,
middle-class family, it's
gonna take them a minute
to get used to that
culture shock over here.
It's going to take
about two years.
Like when I got married,
back then, in the '90s,
it was like I was supposed to
marry a girl from my caste.
It was an issue then, but
now it's not an issue.
Now, you know, 20 years
later, it's changed.
What about white Houstonians?
Welcoming? Nice?
In my experience, I
moved from Singapore.
Right.
First six months, whenever
we used to go anywhere
and say we recently moved
to USA, and everybody go,
"Welcome to Texas."
Welcome to Houston.
"Welcome to USA."
And, like, that made
us very comforted.
I mean, that's not
the stereotype.
The stereotype is that this
is an intolerant state
filled with, you know,
right-wing cowboys
who don't like foreigners.
Not Houston.
Definitely not.
In the beginning, you might
feel that Texans are,
like, not that friendly to
you, but once you know them,
they are really friendly people.
We see this is the
best place to dream
and achieve the dream.
The same opportunities in India
I get, I won't make as much
of my life as I would over here.
You work hard in this
country, and if you put your
mind to something, you
know, it is achievable,
and I think so America
is land of opportunity
and best place to
stay in the world.
Some people say, "Make
America great again."
I say America was
great all along.
Some of us just forgot why.
It's great because your
grandfather and my grandfather
and just about everybody's
damn grandfather
or great-grandfather
crammed themselves,
snuck, bought their way,
or was dragged onto a boat
and one way or another
allowed themselves
eventually to dream.
You still can.
There's still room.
And in some places in
America, apparently you
are still welcome.
Welcome, stranger.
This land is your land.
♪ Jose can you see, how
diversity in Texas is ♪
♪ Don't mess with it,
the best with it ♪
♪ It's intricate,
complex with it ♪
♪ Headlights is beamin' ♪
♪ Twilights is gleamin' ♪
♪ Broad stripes, bright stars ♪
♪ Racing stripes, bright cars ♪
♪ Yo, you could end
up dead there ♪
♪ The Houston Rockets'
red glare ♪
♪ Hardened on the hardwood ♪
♪ The finals, they
might get there ♪
♪ Thug brought the whips out ♪
♪ He posted at MacGregor ♪
♪ Houston are go-getters ♪
♪ They hustle, very clever ♪
♪ Eating migas with my 'migos ♪
♪ I'm at Guadalupana ♪
♪ My tia make birria with
tortillas chichicana ♪
♪ They can't deport us all ♪
♪ Chinga bling make
the tamale good ♪
♪ Shop and get Masala Radio ♪
♪ Bumpin' that Bollywood ♪
♪ Sugar from my mama
out in Sugar Land ♪
♪ My cousins and my family
♪ That's my hood ♪
♪ Sugar from my mama ♪
♪ Out in Sugar Land molasses ♪
♪ Hanging with my homies ♪
♪ When I kick it in Palacios ♪