Mexico is a country where
every day, people fight to live.
All too often, they
lose that battle.
The magnificent, heartbreakingly
beautiful country, the music and
food, and a uniquely Mexican,
darkly funny, deeply
felt world view.
Right down there, cuddled up in
ethos, our brother
from another mother.
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la la
Holy mother of Santa Muerte,
please protect my stash of
cocaine.
Let it not be interfered with by
the cops, or the competition.
Let any who would mess
with me be killed.
My enemies destroyed.
Please forgive us our
sins, for they are many.
So is business good?
I mean, is there more murders
particularly narco murders?
[ Speaking in a
foreign language ]
Every day, Mexico wakes
up to count the dead.
They are, after all,
left out to be seen.
Often with a helpful note,
identifying who done what and
generally speaking, why.
There is a language to the
never-ending violence, a coded
message in the twists and
marks of the bodies.
And Valente Rojas is one of many
documenting them for the press.
This is what he does every
night, rides around waiting for
a phone call or a radio message
telling him that
there's another one.
So who's buying drugs?
Who's selling drugs to who?
[ Speaking in a
foreign language ]
Here, you kill each
other for a reason.
It's business?
Si.
More Mexican civilians have
been killed since 2006 than all
the American military lost in
ten years of the Vietnam war and
eight years of wars in Iraq.
What do you do if you're one of
these cops, you're driving
around one night, you see some
guy outside of a bar beating
somebody or disturbing the
peace, you start to arrest him
and he's got a diamond studded
pistol, it's got his name on it.
Now you realize you've just
arrested somebody with
serious connections.
What do you do?
Let him go?
Si.
Why do they always
pull their pants down?
Our local fixer, Alex,
is here to translate.
In this case, he thinks that
they pull the pants down
so check for weapons.
They are loading
them into the sheet.
This is the CSI team so when
they were pulling his pants off,
money and jewelry started
falling from the pockets.
Basically, they took the money
out his pockets and that was
the only available spot.
To show they didn't
take anything.
Yeah, exactly.
So this is also a drug dealer.
The thing here in Mexico, as
soon as someone's killed,
normally they get candles
just right next to them.
Sometimes it's related to
drug dealings and criminals.
How long have you
been doing this?
About nine years.
How many bodies do you think?
Hundreds?
Si.
How do you push them out of
your mind when you're not
working?
A lot of people ask
him about this.
But he said like it's a job, not
like any other kind of job, but
as soon as he gets home, he just
takes this cover off
and just keep living.
That's a terrible picture.
It's sad, what happened here.
She run away from a circus so
she basically was crossing the
highway and just run over.
The world we live in now, of
all of these pictures, this is
the one that would get people
most upset, you would get the
most mail, the most oh, my god,
you know, what kind of
a world do we live in.
This was the most run picture
from different media
around the world.
80,000 Mexicans have died in
the last seven years
in narco violence.
And this is the most
important picture.
As our crew gets ready to
crawl back to our hotel, Valente
gets the call we thought
we had been waiting for.
One dead male, shot in head.
A note pinned to his chest.
In Mexico, people fight
to live every day.
One man stands alone,
facing another man.
His intent, to beat his opponent
with his fists until
he can resist no more.
A match, yes, but more
accurately, a fight.
Jorge is a former bantamweight
title holder with his father,
Jorge senior and his son Alexis,
he trains aspiring fighters in
the Santa Anita neighborhood
of Mexico City.
He knows these young men, like
generations of boxers everywhere
from other neighborhoods like
this, are looking for a way out.
In Mexico, boxing is kind
of... boxing give them
a little discipline.
Say you're good but
not that good.
Can you make a living
just being a contender?
No, but a lot of fighters,
they try to make it.
They want to be a champion.
Everybody wants
to be a champion.
Everybody.
Everybody wants the big shot.
Those are bad odds.
The history of
boxing is not kind.
Most managers and owners don't
give a... about the fighters.
They use them up but at the end
they leave a guy all broken
down, no money and
scrambled brains.
Just like prostitutes,
you know what I mean?
What are your options?
Nothing.
Snatching, robbing.
Like kids in the hood
go kidnap that guy.
Big industry.
Everybody here now wants
to be a soccer player.
Why boxing?
Because they make money.
Who's got a longer career,
a narco or a boxer?
I don't know.
Might be 50/50.
Narco, you can last longer.
You can.
You are protected by the police.
You just pay off, nobody's
going to touch you.
Expensive protein shakes and
dietary supplements,
not so much.
Boxers here eat what
they can afford.
The food is good and it's cheap.
You know, in Mexico, there
is no middle class.
You are either poor or
really, really rich.
It's a crazy thing.
The minimum wage here is like
50, 60 pesos, which
is like five bucks.
Not an hour, a day.
But on the other hand, that's
why Mexican fighters
are so exciting.
They're hungry.
Exactly.
We're hungry.
Topito is a city
within its city.
Either the dark center or the
beating heart of Mexico City,
depending on your point of view.
It's the home of Santa Muerta,
the skeletal St. death.
This is where they come, the
impoverished, the oppressed, the
marginalized, the criminal.
People for whom the traditional
church has less relevancy.
For the unforgiven and
the unforgiveable.
For those on whom the catholic
saints have turned their
backs, there is Santa Muerte.
This is a place and Santa Muerte
is a Saint that
accepts everybody.
Death to my enemies written
on a votive candle.
Let's face it, we have all
prayed for that at one
point or another.
Topito is a poor neighborhood,
for sure, and a tough one.
A center of commerce both
above-board and not.
Perhaps a breakfast
beverage first.
A michelada.
One giant beer with lemon, chili
powder, salt and magi sauce.
That's a sizeable
morning beverage.
My companion, blogger and
chronicler of the city, Jorge
Pedro.
Wow.
A whole season of the
walking dead for 25 cents.
You want to buy something,
Topito's got it.
Looking for some cheap
underwear, pirated copies of man
versus food seasons
one through five?
This is where you find them.
So this all seems
very wholesome.
Where can I buy a gun, some
heroin and a prostitute.
I was looking forward to that.
Let's say Topito
has many layers.
Right.
And we are in the surface.
Okay.
We are among movies,
clothing, families.
But I don't think it's... to ask
where can I get the gun.
Probably they will kill
you if you ask that.
You know the patron Saint
of hopeless cases.
Lost causes.
It's become very popular
in the last years.
A lot of good smells here, man.
A lot of good-looking food.
My happy place is
somewhere in here.
Oh, there it is.
Yeah.
Beautiful.
Wherever there's bones and guts
simmering in broth, chances
are I'll be happy.
Writer, sociologist and
life-long resident of Topito,
Alphonso Hernandez, apparently
feels the same way.
Is this supposed to be
a bad neighborhood?
This is the best.
I love this neighborhood.
This is known for being the
lost souls neighborhood.
In Topito, there are no
angels but lost souls.
What's the saying?
Show your... to the devil?
To death.
The boil comes from cracked
hambones to release the marrow
which onion and pepper is added.
Thickened with stale bread
and leftover tortillas.
You make something
awesome out of nothing.
Grandmothers take advantage
of the bones of the pigs.
Any great old culture where
there's poverty, there's
something like this.
If you're watching this after
you do this, you really got to
wash your hands before you touch
your... that's a rookie mistake.
She's asking you if
you like the meal.
Yeah, it's good.
Delicious.
So this has been open 65 years?
All the members of the
crew are relatives.
Is there hope for social
change in this country?
Unfortunately, Mexico has
become the Topito of the world.
Topito, this is still the
emphasis of the Mexican.
Not a lot of upward
mobility here.
The rich get richer, the poor
get ground slowly
under the wheel.
Edwardo Garcia has hacked his
way up the ladder to become chef
owner of the city's
hottest restaurant.
I grew up in the states.
I was a migrant worker picking
fruits and vegetables as a kid.
My parents didn't earn a lot of
money, so I decided to work
rather than go to school.
The restaurant business as I
well know ain't no picnic.
In Mexico City, it's
particularly rough.
Mexico has a reputation where
we all know that the country's
run by corrupt politics.
You have to stand up
for what you believe.
If you don't, people
will run you over.
You won't last a minute.
I don't let people
bully me around.
Garcia runs Maximo bistro
with his wife, Gabriella.
Here's the extra crap you have
to deal with if you run the
hottest restaurant
in Mexico city.
In 2013, the spoiled daughter of
the head of Mexico's consumer
protection agency walks in and
demands a table when there's
unsurprisingly, no table
available.
When Garcia says sorry, no can
do, she pulls a you know who I
am and then calls daddy and gets
the health inspectors in
to shut the place down.
So your other customers
basically started taking
pictures with their cell phones?
Next thing you know, we have
the media outside
and this is Friday.
Right.
Sunday morning, we're front
page of one of the most
important newspapers in Mexico.
It was very embarrassing
to the government.
And it should be.
Because they got caught doing
what they do all the time but if
you were not the hottest
restaurant in town, you were
just running a cantina
a few blocks away...
I would have... they
would have closed you
down and that's that.
Right now, the defiant young
creative generation of chefs
like Edwardo are performing some
of the most exciting cooking
anywhere on earth, a mixing of
the very old and traditional
with the very new.
As a kid, one of the jobs
throughout the whole time that I
worked is how old
are you, I'm 18.
You've been 18 for three years.
Those are abilone.
I told you I love butter.
I use it even for some Mexican
dishes and then just roasted
chilies just to give it a
nice little kick for me.
They are finished with lemon
and of course, brown butter.
Beautiful.
Mm.
Very delicious.
Very Mexican, very French.
Brown butter, awesome.
Makes everything better.
Of course.
I think the most important thing
about Mexican cuisine in general
if it's traditional,
it's the ingredients.
Successling pig topped
with grandma's salsa.
An instant classic.
Have at it.
You do it like the Mexican way.
Pick it up and go.
Wow.
Pretty hard to imagine
anything better than that.
You're stuck with this
dish forever, man.
It's going to be like Mick
Jagger 50 years from now
singing "satisfaction."
There's no getting
away from it, man.
This is so good.
This is a classic.
But even now with all his
success, Garcia is still
fighting a struggle most
Mexicans are all too familiar
with.
What happened that day
happens every day.
And the promise always is we're
going to shut you down,
you don't know who I am.
And for me, I would rather close
my restaurant than
live like that.
If you close my restaurant, I
will go across the street, I
will go to another state or I
will go to another country, and
I still will make a
good restaurant.
Under former president Felipe
Calderon, Mexico launched
a concerted war on drugs.
Ostensibly against the notorious
and seemingly
untouchable cartels.
Absolutely no one can say with
any credibility, by the way,
that Mexico's war or our
trillion dollar war has had any
effect in diminishing the flow
of drugs into our country.
One very brave journalist has
uncovered exactly how deep the
rot of corruption and dirty
money has penetrated into every
level of Mexican institutions.
My grandmother, how we used
to drink is never with
lemon, it was with orange.
It is not what a lot of
people wanted to hear,
much less see published.
Today, Anibelle Hernandez
lives under guard in a secret
location.
The threat, very, very
real and very explicit.
You think there was ever a
minute when the Calderon war on
drugs, was it ever genuine?
No.
Calderon start the war against
the drug cartels, he just
followed that instruction but he
didn't really do anything new.
He just did it worse.
Since the beginning, the plan
was protect the cartel and fight
against the enemies
of this cartel.
Of the seven major Mexican
cartels, the Cineloa cartel is
considered the most powerful
with the farthest reaching
and most pervasive tentacles
extending deep into every corner
of government, banking
and private industry.
Its rivals, the Tijuana cartel,
the Gulf cartel, the Juarez
cartel, la Familia Micharcana.
The cartels are responsible for
importing roughly three quarters
of all illegal
narcotics to America.
In your work, you uncovered what
had to be some very embarrassing
and incriminating associations
and connections between very
high elected officials,
the presidents and entire
administrations, and acts
of incredible criminality.
How did that change your life?
When I started to make this
investigation in 2005, I really
understand that it would
be very dangerous.
I have to say that it wasn't
really a surprise for me what
happened after I
published my book.
What I didn't expect is that the
threats came from the
federal government.
She says that one of her
sources warned her that the
biggest threat was from within,
that one of the most highly
placed, most senior law
enforcement officials in
Mexico had ordered her killed.
Because in my book, I put his
name and also showed some
documents that proves that he
was involved, he was on the
payroll of this cartel.
What happened to this man?
Right now, he's very happy
drinking rum, I think, building
many enterprises, fake
enterprises, laundry his money.
To me, a banker who launders
money, he's got a family, he's
got a reputation, he gives money
to charity, his neighbors think
he's great, his kids think he's
wonderful, he's got
something to lose.
So I wouldn't be
prosecuting drug dealers.
I would be prosecuting bankers.
The name of my book is what
it is because the leaders of
these cartels know,
they are also this.
The politicians and bankers and
the businessmen, the people have
to know who are these
people by name.
You have been a
journalist for how long?
20.
20 years.
Your father was killed,
kidnapped and killed in 2000?
My father was a businessman.
In that year, many gangs used to
kidnap businessmen
just for money.
So when we went to the police
and asked them to investigate,
they said well, if you pay us,
we will make the investigation.
So as family, we decide to pay
because you cannot
buy the justice.
Since that, I really tried
to fight against corruption.
That's why I'm doing what I do,
because I think that corruption
is the worst problem in Mexico.
The drug cartels are maybe the
worst face of that problem, but
the problem in the deep
is the corruption.
The corruption is the mother of
all our problems in Mexico.
It should be pointed out that
88 journalists, how many
journalists have been
killed in this country?
90 now.
90 journalists have now been
killed or disappeared
over the last few years.
Yeah.
You can kill a journalist
and get away with it.
Why are you still here?
I have lost many
things in my life.
My father was the most
important person in my life.
I already lost everything.
I don't have any life anymore.
I don't have a social life.
I don't have a sentimental life.
I don't have anything.
I just have my work
and my family.
And my work of a journalist
is everything for me.
I really believe that good
journalists can change the
world.
I have received many offers to
go outside to France, to
Sweden and other countries.
I don't want to leave.
It's my choice.
My choice is fight.
I came to Ahawka for mescal.
I like mescal more and more
these days and this guy, Ron
Cooper, finds and sells some of
the best mescal in the world.
We're at the Zappatec
ruins of Monte Alba.
In pre-conquest Mexico, there
were gods and goddesses of
intoxication and ecstasy.
The touch of a lover, the smell
of a flower, the a-ha of an
idea, all had gods and goddesses
that took responsibility
for those things.
All of your mescals come from
different villages and
only that village?
And only one maker
in that village.
We call ourself single village
mescal because most mescals are
made with a blend of different
villages all put together.
No one goes home and has a
cocktail in these Indian
villages.
They wait until there's
a special occasion.
Every birth, death, confirmation,
baptism, there's a
fiesta.
A wedding is eight days.
You invite 200 people.
You feed them breakfast,
lunch and dinner.
You have a band every day.
And then they really consume.
Don't drink yet.
For mother earth
and her ancestors.
That's extraordinary.
Back in the day, it was cheap
stuff with a worm in it and
there were rumors that if you
ate the worm, you would
start tripping, there was a
hallucinogenic component
to that stuff.
Is there a particular
kind of high?
Is this an enlightening high?
Is this a good high?
The high is humorous.
There are funny thoughts dancing
around the back of your head.
Happy, witty thoughts.
Yes.
Ancient, indigenous traditions
of ingredients define
not only the mescal
but also the food.
One of the main reasons
people visit our city is to eat.
This is Alejandro Romedo,
one of Mexico's best chefs.
He started cooking young.
When he was 12, his mother died
and it fell on him to raise
and feed his five siblings.
This is what we call...
Today he draws much of his
inspiration from Wahawka's
central market.
Probably America's most beloved
food is what they think
is Mexican food.
Yes.
And I think most Americans'
view of Mexican food is beans,
fried tortilla, melted
cheese, some chicken.
Yes.
In fact, in particular when
talking about Wahawka, this is a
deep, really
sophisticated cuisine.
That's correct.
Wahawka has different
microclimates all over our
territory.
That gives us this enormous
amount of surprises,
produce, fruits, chilis.
Like 500,000 varieties of corn.
This is where the good... grows.
This lady here is
always making the best.
Tender.
Yes.
Tender, tasty.
Crunch.
Cabbage and cilantro.
Oh, unbelievably good.
So tasty.
Mm.
Deep.
It's good.
I'll finish this.
This is just too damn good.
People have this barbecue
especially on Sundays.
It's a tradition.
So tasty.
All this is full of chilis.
People think that Mexican food
is spicy because of
all the chili we use.
We go for flavor,
not for the spices.
What most people miss is
how really deep and really
sophisticated the
sauces here can be.
Like Lyon is to France, wahawka
is to Mexico, in my experience.
You're right.
Also in my experience.
Not kissing your ass here.
I was just in Lyon.
This is Vicky's place.
She has been cooking up
traditional Wahawkan dishes in
the market for 30 years.
Whoa, that's awesome.
Oh, man.
So the guy working, first of
all, a lot of what you
see now are metal.
That's old school,
super old school.
That's the way they did
back on the Clay Kamal.
I'm looking there, he's doing
tortillas and doing one of my
favorite things, zucchini
flour with string cheese.
So pretty to see.
His cooking is focused, his
passion have very
old, very deep roots.
Since you are 6, 7, 8, you
have the responsibility to help
water the plantation, milk the
cows and help my mom when she
was making tortillas like that,
she would give me directions and
say okay, roll the chilis, roll
the tomatoes, I will tell you
how to prepare the salsa.
It was the beginning of my
profession, learning from the
knowledge of how a tomato should
taste like when you cut it
directly from the plant.
The way it should taste.
That's right.
Oh, man.
Happy.
This is what I should do.
Try it first like this.
Just grab a hunk.
Yes.
Put salsa.
Yeah.
I haven't been anywhere in
Mexico where the cooking is
better than here.
This is the way to share our
culture, through our food.
The quiet little town of Teo
de Kline El beye is outside of
wahawka, a town where the crafts
and traditions of prehispanic
Mexico are celebrated and
packaged for consumption.
Abigail Mendosa and her sister
are Zapotec, original people
from Mexico before the
Spanish, before the Aztecs.
This is her restaurant, where
Abigail has been grinding corn
by hand, making food like this,
the ridiculously faithful,
time-consuming traditional way
she was taught to make these
things and the way she's been
making them since she
was 6 years old.
Look at her hands, by the way.
Small, surprisingly delicate,
given all the hard work, all the
pushing, kneading, grinding,
stone against stone
over the years.
Then look at her forearms.
The power there.
It's impressive and beautiful.
Every time you enter the
house, in wahawka, especially in
the small villages, they always
offer you a shot of mescal.
Mm, so good.
A molee and chicken dish, this
sauce like a lot of the old
school sauces made by masters
like Abigail use 35 different
types of chili peppers and take
more than two weeks to make.
Do you think that until
recently, until guys like you,
that Mexicans were not looking
back at their own food culture,
they were looking elsewhere?
What was going on?
We were conquerers.
We are were also a culture that
was conquered first by the
Aztecs and then conquered by the
Spaniards so we were always
taught everything that was
good and excellent has to be
imported.
Right.
What we have here, it
was just not good.
Right.
Another zapotecan classic, chili
agua, a simpler dish of cow and
pork brains cooked with chili,
tomatoes and yorba Santa.
As a cook, the main thing
was to develop a little
bit my cuisine here.
There was this space where
nobody tried to innovate.
Still using the same techniques,
the same ingredient, the same
flavors, herbs, et cetera, but
developing them a little bit.
I mean, that's as
old-school as it gets.
A final dish, this one, this
is something that you do not
find anywhere as Mexico.
The quoi yet night.
The central square of Wahaka.
But even tonight there's plenty
of evidence of the struggle, the
discontent boiling just
under the surface.
The graffiti and painting of
this street artist captures
that spirit of protest.
♪
Tie last supper, for sure.
Last supper by Mexican.
Who are these people?
These are most powerful
people in Mexico.
People that is driving Mexico.
This is the president right now.
This is Calderon.
Right.
The last president.
That guy is like
the economy guy.
Right.
Who's moving the
economy in Mexico.
And this is the army.
This is a prostitute.
This represent because
they are like prostitutes.
Right.
You know?
And narco traffic.
Oh.
He is like the god in Mexico.
You know?
Because he is, like,
over... all of it.
Yeah.
So this is the way Mexico works?
For me, the most problem in
Mexico is the corruption.
Mexico can be a dangerous
place for journalists, for
politicians, for police.
Is it a dangerous
place for artists in.
Yeah.
I think so a little bit because
you do not agree with the
government, you are like enemy.
Right.
In 1936, the town 50 miles
from Mexico City was
visited by Malcolm Lowry.
The tormented self loathing
brilliant and hopelessly
alcoholic author.
His life work under the
volcano was set here.
It is widely believed to be one
of the great novels
of the 20th century.
Lowry saw symbolism and
evil everywhere here.
In the deep areas, the looming
volcano that towered overhead.
Writer, poet, Javier Cecilia,
has reason to see evil, too.
On march 28th, 2011, narcos
kidnapped and murdered his son
and six other equally
blameless victims.
Cecilia found himself to march
to Mexico City to demand an end
to the increasingly futile
so-called war on drugs that was
mindlessly grinding up so many
victims in the crossfire
and in the margins.
In "Under the volcano," the evil
that's coming is
fascism, Naziism.
When's the heart of the
infernal machine today?
What does he want to say?
What does he want
people to hear?
Can he think of one place on
earth where the good guys are
winning and where you are not
ground under the
wheels of the machine?
Have you written a poem since
the death of your son?
As I have come to know in my
own life, drugs, even drug
addiction, can be a
survivable event.
Death is not.
Death is final.