♪ I wish I could see
you in many times ♪
♪ As the masses celebrated ♪
♪ By the high priest ♪
♪ As many times as
the friar says ♪
♪ "Let's pray" ♪
♪ I won't say ♪
♪ How much I love you ♪
♪ I'd love to see you ♪
♪ Hanging by a bridge ♪
♪ With your head cut off ♪
♪ Rolling down the street ♪
♪ I took a walk ♪
♪ Through this beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain ♪
♪ On my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good ♪
♪ In this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain ♪
♪ Getting colder ♪
- ♪ La, la ♪
- ♪ Sha la, la, la, la ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la, la, la ♪
As so many have found
throughout history,
it's easy to fall
in love with Rome.
She is seductively beautiful.
She has endured and
survived many things.
What's left of her former
glories, her days of empire,
are in ruins, but those ruins
continue to enchant us.
You fall into a trance here.
You think, "No matter what,
this beautiful dream
will last forever."
And then suddenly,
shit gets real.
Before World War I, Benito
Mussolini was considered
a bully and a crackpot.
A short-tempered,
ever-pontificating soap box orator
from the small
town of Predappio.
In time though, the country
was divided and in crisis.
It saw itself as besieged
by enemies within
and without.
It needed someone who
said he could make Italy
great again.
He was a man on a horse
saying, "Follow me,"
and they did.
When fascists marched on Rome,
the Prime Minister resigned
and Benito Mussolini
was appointed
leader by the king.
It can happen anywhere.
It happened here.
Nearly a century later, this
is what he left behind.
The Rome that many Romans
still live in today.
So this is not a show about
monuments or statues
or the treasures of antiquity.
This is about people,
often extraordinary ones,
living their lives in the
Rome you don't see much of
in the travel
guides or TV shows.
♪
Ah, nice painting of Anna
Magnani on the wall.
I was just watching her in
such films as "Mamma Roma."
Ettore.
Don't you have a little
kiss for your mother?
♪
Oh, all right.
Grazie.
♪
Mmm, yeah.
I love this place.
I wanna die here already,
and I might yet.
Some people asked me at my
hotel where they should eat.
Just... wherever the
concierge tells you to go,
don't go there.
Goddamn.
♪
That's beautiful.
Oh, man, that's so
completely awesome.
♪
Biancofiore, I need your help.
Would you blackmail
a guy for me?
Pier Paolo Pasolini
was one of Italy's
great film makers.
A revolutionary figure
in cinema who celebrated
the working-class
suburbs of Rome.
He was a vocal
opponent of fascism
and of those he felt
allowed it to happen.
His characters were down and
out, victims, predators,
broodish, and wounded, often
played by real people
rather than actors.
Even stolen goods, I don't care.
I buy them anyway.
But they were always,
even at their worst,
depicted as angelic
in all their flawed
and damaged glory.
Rome's true heroes.
♪
Ah.
The hard slap of leather
against wet skin.
The thud of muscle and
bone and collision
with muscle and bone.
There is blood and
sweat and bitter tears
as these warriors face each
other in brutal combat.
But, hey, there's pasta
and a nice glass of wine.
Hey, this is pretty absurd.
These people are fighting
their hearts out,
getting brain damaged,
and I'm merely
eating spaghetti.
This is violent, too.
It looks like somebody's
been opened and I'm looking
at the insides of
one of those guys.
Actor, director Asia
Argento is a member
of a dynastic film family
stretching back generations.
Her father is Dario Argento.
Credited with creating
a wildly innovative
and whole new style to
the modern horror film
as we know it.
♪
How big is your family?
- Like, if you were to have a, like...
- We don't.
- You don't.
You don't do, like, a big
gathering of the clans?
I love the expression.
You're like Asia
has a reputation
for saying what she feels.
-Yeah, [...] him up.
Regardless of what
people might think.
Papa, is it true that
you're leaving Her
semi-autobiographical
film "Misunderstood"
played at the Cannes
Film Festival.
I'll be back soon.
I have to shoot a movie and...
Yes, your daddy is going.
But he is not brave enough
to tell his daughter
he is leaving her.
- She's crazy!
- It's all her fault.
It's my fault for
having a daughter
with a dickhead like you.
Asia is the single
mother of two children,
and lives modestly in a
middle-class neighborhood
on the outskirts of Rome.
She was born, raised,
and remains a Roman
by blood and attitude.
- How is it?
- This is fantastic.
Mm, yeah, it's
actually [...] great.
The gladiators, looks like
Ancient Rome in a way.
♪
So Romans complain?
The Romans, they complain
about everything.
- Oh, yeah?
- Oh, it's a nightmare.
- Complaining about the Gypsies...
- Right.
-About the mayor.
The... who will run Rome next.
Who's taking over?
What about fascism?
- Like, Mussolini.
- Yeah.
- My daughter, okay?
- Uh-huh?
She goes to a private
school, but not, like,
you know, expensive.
Like, not... it's a...
It's a nun school
- for [...] sakes, okay?
- Uh-huh.
A kid would get on
the teacher's desk
and they would start
chanting, like,
- "Hitler, I love you,"
and, uh... - Right. Right.
At the same time,
as you see around,
there's an obelisk
with "Mussolini"
and it hasn't been torn down.
In Berlin, you wouldn't
see something like that
- from Hitler.
- Right.
It would be absurd.
Here? No.
♪
The series of high-speed
straightaways
interrupted by sharp
turns with no shoulders,
the Via del Mare was central
to Mussolini's dream
of connecting Rome to
the Mediterranean.
It is, today, Italy's
most dangerous road.
♪
The Via del Mare makes
an abrupt dead-end
in the beach-front
suburb of Ostia.
♪
There's a monument
here to Pasolini,
on the spot he was brutally
beaten to death by a band
of young male hustlers.
Though many attribute the
murder to neofascists enraged
by his politics.
Hey, how you doing? Hi, guys.
Grazie.
-Eat.
- I meet my good friend,
Sara, among Ostia's
post-war housing blocks, just
off the beach at a place
that's new to us both.
The people here are
originally from Sardinia.
- Many people in Ostia are originally from Sardinia.
- Oh, really?
L'angolo Amici, or
"The Friends Corner,"
is a bar where everyone
knows everybody's name...
if they're sober
enough to remember.
He's a professional boxer.
-He's a professional boxer?
- He was.
- His ears look good.
That's because I would
just knock people down.
They used to call
me "Little Tyson."
He calls himself
"The Little Tyson."
- It's true I swear.
-Here, everybody has a nickname.
I have done the world
amateur championships,
the Italian amateur
championships, and I've joined
the Olympics team.
Now he is a champion
at changing time.
♪
Ostia might be described,
unflatteringly,
as Rome's equivalant
to the Jersey Shore.
A suburban seaside near
the airport that grew up
as decidedly working class
despite Mussolini's
never-realized intent
that it would one day
be Rome's front door.
Ostia is a beautiful town.
No, talk to him.
Who are you talking to?
- To him.
- Well talk to him instead.
- Forget about the camera.
- Okay?
- Where are the cameras?
- That's right.
-I'm not used to this.
So tell us about Ostia.
Where are... where are we?
Ostia is a part of Rome.
We're not detached.
We're like one of
the its districts.
I studied in a school
called "Italian Youth,"
built by Mussolini.
People live in... these
are not vacation homes?
No. No, no, no.
Forget about tourists.
-There are not many.
- This is, like, the
closest beach to Rome.
Right?
Everybody likes the beach.
Why is it not all
expensive hotels
and money, money, money,
and casinos, and...
In the 60's Fregene
was the place to go,
where all the VIPs would
go Here is for the workers
and is... has always
been considered,
-uh, not very interesting.
But the sea here is
super beautiful.
Everybody comes
here to the beach.
- Even if they are judgmental about it.
- Mm-hmm.
- Anyway, cheers!
- Okay.
-Cheers.
Ah!
Uh, I'm curious, 'cause
we're always interested
- in food.
- Oh.
Typical day, what's
for breakfast?
- What's for lunch?
- What's for dinner?
- First, breakfast.
- Breakfast?
Like, coffee and a pastry, what?
For breakfast you have a
variety of salami and...
- It's called Italian starter...
- Salami, ham...
- In Sordinia!
- We don't have that in Rome!
-No, here in Rome!
-Here in Rome we have Cornetto
and cappuccino in the morning!
He say... he says that,
that... that's a Sardinia,
but here we have
cappuccino and croissant.
Biscuits, milk coffee,
that's shall I can have.
I'd love to have some
sausage and salami.
No, no, I'll say what she says.
- What are you talking about?
- In your health condition?
- She said...
- You have diabetes!
So you must not eat those things!
But I wish I could!
- You're talking bullshit!
- " salami, but I cannot anymore."
-Right.
- You figure that their
wives have them wash
the dishes at home, and
when they come here,
they act like bosses!
What's a typical
dish from Ostia?
Grilled rats!
Brings us another pitcher!
I've been introduced to these
traditional Roman songs
with titles like, "I Never Want
To Stop Stabbing You"... -Ah.
"Your Dead Relatives."
These wonderful songs, like,
- filled with very regional...
- Put it together.
- And I... Apparently, they
were originally invented
by people in bars and prisons.
Do you know anything
about these songs?
Oh, Stornello is like
making fun of somebody...
Stornello is like a sonnet.
- Or so... a situation...
- Right.
And uses swear words.
- This is very romantic.
- There is one that goes.
This is like a serenade
for a girl, so...
"Zucchini flowers are big.
Your girlfriend
stinks like a pig."
They're these wonderful
expressions like,
if I hear that... if you tell
me, - "I'm having a baby."
- Mm-hmm.
I can say, "Your
dead relatives"?
- This is an acceptable expression?
- "To your lousy dead."
But you're not even angry
when you say this.
- This is a sort of a
casual expression?
- It depends -on why
you're saying this.
- When I meet him,
- I may whisper,
- "To your lousy dead."
- It means, "Ciao."
If you go like this...
"To your bloody
dead relatives,"
- uh, it's a nice thing.
- You just take this... wait.
- But if I'm angry at him, I change tone.
- It's a nice thing.
But if you change the hand and
the hand becomes like an
axe, you're really angry.
-So this is okay.
- This is okay.
- But like this is not good.
- No, no, no, no, no.
- Now I'm mad.
- Yeah, this is the worst.
- No.
This is the worst.
Some swear word,
different occasions.
♪
♪ Alimo and Taccitu ♪
♪ Were two Hindu brothers ♪
♪ Alimo was feeling sleepy ♪
♪ Taccitu - to you and your
grandpa's lousy dead ♪
♪ Alimo and Taccitu ♪
♪ Were two Hindu brothers ♪
♪ Your brother's eaten
up the grapes ♪
♪ Taccitu - to you
and his lousy dead ♪
♪ Your sister's eaten
up the mortadella ♪
♪ Taccitu - to you
and her lousy dead ♪
♪ She's eaten a loaf of bread ♪
♪ Taccitu - you're a
bloody son of a bitch! ♪
♪ Got married in Istanbul ♪
♪ They've got a lot of kids ♪
♪ To everybody's lousy dead ♪
♪
Roma Nord, the 'burbs.
Asia lives here
with her two kids.
Today, her sister, Fiore, is
visiting and making lunch.
♪
- Cheese.
A quick stop at a typical
artisanal Italian grocery.
-Fava beans?
- Fava beans, yeah.
For some last minute purchases.
♪
- So we get this?
- Yeah.
Yeah.
How they gonna... like,
or they do the... yeah.
- Ah, all the way from...
- Think about it.
♪
This is one of the things
that fascinates me
about the Italian baby food.
I don't... I don't see here,
like, rabbit flavor
- and horse flavor and stuff.
- Oh, yeah.
♪
Ah, looks good.
Anthony, you're gonna be here.
Asia's son, Nicola,
and daughter, Anna.
♪
When I was little, one
time, they were putting
my underpant, -and I was, um...
- Uh, you peed
on your face.
I peed on my face.
I wanna cry.
Nicola, you're not supposed
to say these things
like, um, good things.
♪
Today's menu?
Some Roman classics.
Tripe, some nice ragù,
rigatoni with guanciale
and fava beans.
Mmm...
-Anthony, how is it?
-It's good. Oh, I'm very happy.
♪
You liking Rome?
You like it here?
Yeah. Yeah, like, of course.
What do you like?
I like this, uh... This
neighborhood, right?
We like this neighborhood.
Why do you live here?
I don't know.
I've lived, um,
away for many years
-and then I always come back.
- Mm, she lived in
Southeast Asia, no?
- Yeah.
- Really? Where?
Singapore and Bali.
Those are not bad
places to live.
Yeah, not bad place to live.
-Bali's nice.
- Bali's nice, but then every
time, um, when I'm away,
I miss Rome.
When I'm in Rome,
I wanna go away.
So do you take it for
granted when you drive by
- this magnificent... Colosseum?
- Like the Colosseum?
Yeah, I don't even look at it.
What about you?
Do you think, "Well, it's
kind of awesome here?"
Mm, yeah, I do, actually.
I appreciate it a lot,
but it's not like
every time I drive by I'm
like, "Wow, like..."
Like, this year, it's
a bit better than
the other year.
- What, the Colosseum?
-Yeah, like... Why is it better?
It's been there for
2,000 and plus years.
- Yeah, but the other year, it was, um...
- Dirty.
And... and it was, uh,
like, plastic somewhere.
Oh, they were... when
they were renovating,
- they covered it.
- Yeah. Oh.
And this year, it's all perfect.
This is ox tail.
- This is really good.
- Mmm... Fiore.
It's really good.
- It's fantastic.
- Mamma mia.
Brava.
What is this, eh?
That is... - La Trippa.
- Trippa.
Do you know what that is?
Trippa?
- Don't tell him.
- This is good meat.
- Meat.
It's just meat, bro.
-You love meat.
- I love it.
It's one of my favorite things.
And Romans with
the sauce, right?
- In Rome...
- See, Romans with tomato.
Romans, with the sauce.
I ate one in Florence
without the sauce,
it tasted like human fingers.
Like, skin.
Like, it was... Yeah, it's one
of my favorite things on
Earth, but if you don't do it
right, -it smells like wet dog.
- Yeah.
It's got that kind of funky...
I used to like it as a kid,
even though I was very
particular about food,
- kind of like Nicola.
I didn't... I was
not adventurous.
I hated food because my
mother would impose us to eat
all this crazy stuff, -like brains, like...
- Yes.
Like it was horrible.
Boiled brains when your five,
then you see the veins
and such.
Yeah, because they were
sure that the brain
- make you...
- It was to make you smarter.
-Make you smarter.
- And, uh, somebody's
hitting the tripe hard.
Nic, you don't have
to eat, like, um...
- If you don't...
- If you don't like.
-I mean... I know you.
- I saw your face.
- Like, eat some bread.
He's like, "Yeah, I like this."
Look, love, I understand.
We understand.
- Now give him some bread.
- It's all good, man.
- It's all good, my friend.
You tried. And, uh...
You did good.
Hang in there, dude.
♪
The EUR, built by Mussolini
as a symbol of the triumph
of fascism.
♪
These buildings were
not designed to thrill
or elevate or warm
with their beauty.
They are designed to
dwarf the individual,
to intimidate, to
remind constantly
that the state is all
powerful and supreme.
That the individual is
meaningless in the grand scheme
of things.
One person just like the other.
Fungible, replaceable.
Ultimately, worthless.
♪
- Hey. Hi, Tony. Hi.
- How are you?
This is Christina.
Hi. How are you?
- Good to meet you.
- Yeah.
- Lucia.
That's my sister, Jacoba.
You say "hi" to Tony.
Hello. Hi.
There's a big
difference right away
between living in Italy
and living in New York.
They're happy to see kids
in restaurants here.
It's a whole different thing.
When you bring a kid into
a restaurant in New York,
- these guys shoot you a look like...
- Right.
- "You gotta be kidding."
You know, "We're trying to
do coke in the bathroom,
- you think we wanna look at..."
- Right.
The notorious, once
demonic, Abel Ferrara
is a married man
now and a daddy.
Things are different.
I was able to really get
sober for the first time.
I remember it was
my 61st birthday,
and I'm looking at this
cake with a 16 backwards,
it was the first time
since I was 16 years old
when I had my birthday,
I was sober.
The director of "Pasolini,"
"Bad Lieutenant,"
and "King of New York,"
among others.
Ooh...
How long have you been here now?
Living steady here,
um, two years.
I came to shoot the
film "Pasolini."
- Right.
- Then we met Christina.
It was the craziest
scene we shot, right?
It was the most crazy scene.
An orgy.
We got 30 people naked,
it's 40 degrees out,
and it was love at first sight.
And then... -And
then she was born.
- Yeah, then she arrived, -so...
- Very soon.
Wow. This is good.
Most beautiful
thing of Italy is,
every city you go to, -it's
totally different cuisine.
- Yeah, I mean, this is Roman.
All Roman. Oh, there you are.
-Hey, ciao, ciao.
-Ciao, my dear.
- Say "hello."
- This is Tony.
Hi, ciao.
♪
I grew up in a southern
Italian family in...
- Catholic.
- Yeah, Catholic...
- We die in the Bronx.
- How Catholic were you?
You'd have to get on your
knees and say the rosary,
you know, like, when
your six years old,
- seven years old, right?
- Right. Right.
And with the nuns
walking back and forth
beating the shit out
of you for any reason,
and even though some of 'em
looked like Angelina Jolie,
some of the nuns
I had, actually.
-Oh, okay, the... really?
I don't know if I wanna...
There were some beauties.
This was an issue I had
with "Bad Lieutenant."
The nuns were hot.
- Oh, well...
- I never saw any nuns
-that looked like that, okay?
-No, no, no.
Those boys.
Those sad, raging boys.
- It's okay, it's okay,
- it's okay, it's okay.
- Typical Roman dish?
A typical Roman dish, please.
- Roman snails?
- Snails?
Like, uh, this... from the sea?
The Whelk?
-No.
- No? Or... no, the...
- Normal.
-Yeah.
-The terra.
-Ah, really?
♪
- Oh, man, this is serious.
What's the best thing
about this city?
Everything you talked about.
That when you bring
the baby in here,
there's a love for life.
The work, the art, the
attitude on how to live.
If I'm in a bad mood, I'm
negative, I'm down, okay?
- Right.
- And then I walk out,
I see this chick.
See this chick here, Lucia?
Okay. Okay, I might
be personally like,
"Eh, I don't feel like
going to the market,"
but this chick is
running the market.
She's like... you
know what I mean?
I don't know how old
she is, but you dig?
And never... like seeing you,
was like, "Wow, we're alive.
We have this moment on earth,"
and that's part of the food.
-Artichoke.
- Artichoke.
Mm. Oh, man, that's amazing.
Okay, when you care about
the people your feeding,
you're gonna do it.
If people come in, you don't
care, you don't know,
it's just, "I'm trying
to make money."
Then I... I'll cook anything.
These guys can't make bad food.
- Right.
- Because they're caring
about you eating.
♪
I am very glad to
be able to express
my personal feelings towards
the American nation.
My fellow citizens,
who are working
to make America great.
♪
Traditional Roman breakfast.
Cappuccino before
12:00, some say 11:00.
♪
Ah, definitely having this.
Oh, man.
There's no dignified
way to eat this.
That's good.
I was unaware of this
phenomenon previously.
This bomba thing.
I believe we call it a donut.
♪
To Pasolini, it was the
outskirts, the margins of Rome
that were interesting
and beautiful.
The real Rome.
Not the temples and monuments
- of a long-dead empire.
A place where people
struggled every day
to live and to love.
♪
Grazia.
You've been eating
here for how long?
Since I was a kid.
I used to love it as a child.
It's comforting.
- Food the same more or less?
- Always the same.
- I mean, it changes, but...
- Yes, that's the thing.
That's why I keep coming back.
The grandma makes it.
It's always her cooking.
She cooks every time that
she makes fettuccine fresh.
Rome is a city where you
find the most extraordinary
of pleasures in the
most ordinary things.
Like this place.
Which I am not ever going
to tell you the name of.
Asia's been coming
here regularly.
- Grazie.
- Forever.
She brings her kids
still, so I'm not gonna
screw it up for her.
-Oh, it's good.
- That's good. It's good.
Children's food.
Isn't it comforting?
♪
Is it possible to look at
Rome in a non-cinematic way?
I mean, it's a city that
kind of demands it.
To me, it's how to shoot
it the way it has never
been shot.
There's sides of Rome that...
Pasolini, for instance,
who wasn't from Rome,
or we shoot here.
- Mm-hmm.
- And he would do the suburbs
and get the strengths
of the real Rome.
That's our house over there.
The one with the
window in the sun
the panties hanging out.
I went to the Colosseum the
first time when I was 16.
Well, how often do New Yorkers
go to the Empire State
Building? I mean... Why
would you go inside?
Yeah. I know.
'Cause it's tall?
I guess.
So we were talking
before about that church
-with the paintings of martyrs.
-Yeah.
These super violent... ♪
And you said something
to me inter...
Interesting. You said, you
know, "In times of trouble
and stress, when people
are afraid or angry,
that people are in
a buying mood."
Yeah, you want people
scared at home
taping their windows,
so they become buyers.
♪
The Church did something
similar in the sense that,
if you have sinned, you
have greatly sinned.
Only if you repent
and you go there,
you will be forgiven.
- Right.
You're scared.
It's, like, kind of the
first horror movies
of all time, the Christian art.
♪
- When people are scared...
- Uh-hmm?
They go running to the Church.
What about fascism?
- Like, Mussolini.
- Yeah.
What... very popular man.
Yeah, and people say,
the Romans, "Mussolini
was a good man."
-Uh-hmm.
- Hitler came and him
up, but he did good.
Architecture, build things,
and my grandma would say,
"Mussolini, a good-looking man,"
and she would like, like,
you know, "A realman."
- Like, with the?
-Uh-hmm.
You know? Like, some...
A man... a manly man.
- Right.
- "A manly man."
- "Mussolini was a manly man."
So you're not optimistic
about the-the-the...
- Optimistic?
- The political
health of the world?
-I don't even care.
I don't vote.
- I never voted.
- Really?
Never once.
I don't go on the news.
I don't want to bring
that stuff with me.
That shit is poison.
There's just, like,
this Italian way
of like, "Let it go.
You know, as long as
it doesn't bother me,"
and I am completely like that.
Like, I care about
my neighborhood,
my children, my building.
- You know?
- I care about that.
It's a lot to care
about already.
♪
Pick an autocratic ideology,
German, Italian, or
Soviet, and you end up
with structures like this.
So this was... I
forget what it was
- in "The 10th Victim." I think
- it's a... it's a chase scene?
- The runaway... yeah.
It's a chase scene, right?
- He's running, yep.
But in "The Conformist,"
it was a men... this was
a mental institution.
- Yeah.
♪
I mean, the ideas, I
understand it was...
This was gonna be the shining
example of, you know,
the new Superman, the
new... the fascist, uh...
-For a fair.
- This is what fascism
can do for the...
For the World's Fair, -I
think it was the plan,
and it... -Yeah.
20 years... celebrating
20 years of fascism,
- but it never happened.
- The war... the war broke out.
The war broke before.
And then, after the
war, this neighborhood
was overgrown by
weeds and trees.
It was forgotten.
People wouldn't come here.
It was shameful.
They haven't bombed it
as much as in Berlin.
They bombed everything
else, but they... you know,
this is still standing even
though they... to this day,
they don't use it very much.
Do you have any
family history here?
What was, uh... I always ask...
Anytime I meet a German,
I always ask... I'm always
thinking, "What did they do,
you know, during the war,"
and I'm... you know, I
always assume the worst.
My grandmother and her brother
were the photographers
of fascism.
She made beautiful pictures,
very much grandiose
like this architecture,
of muscular men,
women, and, uh...
What do you think
of this style of architecture?
I think it's beautiful.
I like the fact that
it's called rationalist,
but grandiose, huge.
I mean, this is link... it looks
just like Lincoln Center
to me.
I mean, in New York.
It's the same... -Yeah.
- Exactly the same style
of, uh, -of architecture.
-So what are you trying to say?
- I'm saying, "What's the problem?"
- "They're fascists too"?
You're... there's a
little fascists
-inside each one of you too.
- Um... Look. Visit the
States these days.
It's, uh... it's coming back.
It's big.
It's coming back in what sense?
-What is, uh, about the fascism?
- I think we're looking...
- We're looking for, you know,
a man on a horse -to
make everything better.
- That we are... yes,
but we always have.
Humans always have.
God figure, father
figure, that is going
to tell you what to do.
People in Italy... in Rome
still love Mussolini.
And what happened
to Mussolini again?
- As I recall, um...
- Uh, he got hung
upside down in Milan,
Piazzale Loreto.
Everybody would go there
and throw stones.
What a turn around.
I mean, he... one time,
so popular and then...
That's what happens
with all the idols.
You know?
With... you create them,
so you can destroy them.
Wow.
♪
Thank you for bringing me here.
I don't think I've ever been
or ever will come back.
Maybe for movies.
♪