What are our expectations?
Which of the things we
desire are within reach?
If not now, when?
And will there be
some left for me?
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la la
China's younger generation
is driving a growth
in consumption.
This is where the real power is.
China.
If you live in Manhattan like
I do and you think you live in
the center of the world, this
place, Shanghai, will confront
you with a very
different reality.
Turn down a side street,
it's an ancient culture.
Centuries old mix of culinary
traditions, smells, flavors,
a block away, this.
An ultramodern ever clanging
cash register, levels of wealth,
luxury, sheer volume of things
and services unimagined by the
greediest, most of
capitalist imperialists.
The city is split by the river,
a tributary of the yank sea in
the oldest section which
features the newer built up
section.
The one thing I know for sure
about China is I will
never know China.
It's too big, too old,
too diverse, too deep.
There's simply not enough time.
That's for me, the joy of China.
Facing a learning curve
that impossibly steep.
The certain knowledge that even
if I dedicated my life to
learning about China, I'd
die mostly ignorant.
That's exciting.
It's too much.
And it's changing.
So fast.
China has a population of around
$1.3 billion people, and the
number of them who are joining
an explosive middle class
demanding their share of all
that good stuff, infrastructure,
the clothes, the cars, the gas,
the fuel, is well, it's the
engine that might well
drive the whole world.
Very much, yes.
Okay, what do you want?
Order, of course,
some good dumplings.
The professor is an economist
and the current Dean of the
college of economics and
management that
Shanghai university.
Like so many people you meet
here, he's Chinese, but
was educated in American
universities and taught at Yale,
Duke, and Arizona state.
Forgive me, economics are not my
area of expertise, I wallow in
ignorance, but China looks
different every time I come.
It's changing so, so, so
quickly, how did that happen?
China, enjoyed this long
period of peace, no serious
enemy.
No major wars.
Right.
So the manufacturing
industry really took off.
Internally, formed
an open door policy.
Every country willing
to trade with China.
There's certainly no doubt
that at this point, we are, our
destinies are inextricably bound
up, our economies are hope
legislationly interming med, if
one fails, the effect
would be disastrous.
Global impact.
We are, to say the least.
It's certainly... beautiful.
This is what I was waiting for.
Literally small
steaming basket buns.
But I translate them in my head
to pillows of happiness that
will scald your tongue and
throat if you don't
know what you're doing.
Look, there are a lot of reasons
to come to China and Shanghai in
particular, but these babies,
done right, these things
alone are worth the trip.
Ground pork and shrimp, folded
exactly and always 20 times
inside freshly made
individually rolled out dough.
As their steamed a delicious,
delicious fat renders into the
soup of the gods, which then if
you're not careful, causes
unforgettable damage as it
changes your life forever.
So good.
In the China of the future,
places like this will be even
more packed by Chinese, by
expats, by visitors looking for
the deeply satisfying rush of
screamingly hot goodness.
The chewy, deeply savory,
fragrant, perfectly shaped and
folded ballistically designed
vehicles for pure pleasure.
And the allure of Shanghai's
style pork chop, served with the
local take on Worcestershire sauce.
It's unbelievable.
I really believe the word is
con verget, and China will again
be privatizing more and more,
but the difficulty, nowadays,
it's just, the technology is so
advanced, we don't really meet
that many people to do things
that many people used to do.
In which the population, seven
billion people, probably doesn't
need that many people
working anymore.
Right.
So the question is, what
should human beings do?
You know.
How can you let them not doing
anything, and they're
still living a good life?
Right.
I don't know.
It's going to be a big issue
that can face the whole world.
What is the future?
I don't know.
But to a very great extent, it
is surely being determined here.
Is there a plan?
Probably not.
Only appetites.
And increasingly, the means to
fulfill those appetites.
Those dreams and aspirations.
Who will drive the car that
takes us to wherever
we are going?
They will be young,
whoever they are.
And not unlike yow, a
30-year-old Shanghai native
ejtsed in the USA, current lay
feature's reporter for
the Shanghai daily.
She may be the picture of modern
China, but this is her
favorite restaurant.
China and Shanghai in particular
might be transforming fast, but
this place stays
resolutely the same.
She runs the place, serving
classic, home style food.
There's no menu,
no waiting list.
And you only get a
seat if she likes you.
I ordered too much, sorry.
Fantastic.
Very happy.
We're joined by her friend,
Lu an artist, and
Matthew, a restauranteur.
How do you eat these?
Whole.
I eat them whole because
I really like this.
That works.
Oh, they're good.
I think they cook a few seconds.
They are tiny little shrimp,
deep fried first and quicklies
toed in the wok with garlic,
ginger, salt, and soy.
What is classic Shanghai food?
What's distinctive about it?
Well this frinz, it's often...
Friends, it's... for instance,
it's often black, and dark.
It has been for some time
a city of immigrants.
The food reflects
that genealogy.
A combination of people from the
province known for soy and
vinegar, and others known for
fresh ingredients and attention
to preserving the
aliveness of its dishes.
It's the best of both worlds.
Great sauces, great ingredients.
There's braised pork belly in a
deep red glaze of dark and light
soy sauce, cinnamon,
sugar, and annise.
A small fish poached first in
rice wine, salt and light soy,
then fried in ginger garlic oil,
more soy and sugar until it's
reduced into a
gorgeous sticky sauce.
Duck that's been marinated,
blanched, then reheated,
smothered in a sauce made from
the reduced drippings left in
the wok with dark
soy, salt, and sugar.
And this to round things out, a
Clay pot soup of bean curd based
stock with salted pork belly,
tofu ribbons, and bamboo chutes.
Oh good flavor.
This is a socialist
country, supposedly.
Yep.
But it's a communist
country, supposedly.
It is in fact from evidence that
I've seen, the most dynamic
capitalist country on earth.
What do you think about that?
I think a lot of my western
friends come here thinking China
is a version of North Korea or
the party controls everything,
but they come here, they are
surprised, it's
actually not that much.
They do seem to be promoting the
free market even more with
the free trade zone, just
established in Shanghai.
It's amazing.
From what I see, everywhere
we go, more Chinese, Chinese
influence, Chinese food, if you
build a casino in Vegas or a
hotel in Singapore, you have to
consider what will the Chinese
think, is that exciting?
It's exciting that we finally
have a thing that we wouldn't.
China is sort of in a spotlight
in the central, we wouldn't have
dreamed of, like say
only a decade ago.
For me, I think, you know,
the communist menace that we
always used to talk about in
America, I think the most
terrifying scenario is that
China becomes a completely
free market, non-socialist,
non-communist society
because you'd bury us.
I love few things more than
quoting that impeccable
communist Deng Sho Peng
to be rich is glorious.
All isms are Wasims.
Dig deep, and it's
always about the money.
Meet Tim Si.
Resident of communist China, man
of impeccable taste, one of more
than 150,000 Shanghainese
millionaires accustomed
to the good life.
Take the sea water out,
we place with champagne.
Have it only once.
Hopefully you like it.
He likes nice things.
And he makes Donald Trump's
ticky tacky empire look like the
back of Pauly D.'S Van.
Where are these from?
They're great.
France.
France, fantastic.
Good shape.
I keep them happy.
Every single one is flown from
jet so they're nice
and happy and safe.
Apparently.
Tim is an investor into real
estate, telecoms, and the newly
expanding service industries
of the new China.
He's also the president of
Roosevelt China investments, a
very old company with a long
history doing business here.
Created by the Roosevelt family,
maybe you've heard of them.
This is his clubhouse, really,
the house of Roosevelt right
in the middle of it all.
Wine is big here now.
The French chateaus more and
more they look to China as the
indicators of price
as the market maker.
Tim alone has stocked
around 4,000 labels here.
China in general bought two
billion bottles of red
wine last year alone.
Think about that for a minute.
They are now the leading market
for red wine in the world.
It's pretty amazing here.
I designed this place
in five minutes.
I look at this place like
six months... uh-huh.
Daytime, nighttime, and
finally one morning, I said, I'm
going to make a wine
cellar out of this.
It looks so good.
Thank you.
This is nice.
Hi.
Tim invited me to dinner
alongside of people who have
taken full advantage of
the booming economy.
Daniel, a real estate developer,
and cocoa, a party planner.
You eat like this all the time?
Nice wine cellar.
Twice a night.
Today we're surrounded by
Southern French wine, and
Italian wine.
And if you like it, you can
drink from wine
country every night.
Isn't this supposed to
be communist China?
I mean, it seems like... can
I ask one question, any
one of the communist party
comrades party member?
No.
I'm a bit of a red diaper baby.
What I mean to say, it just
seems that the realm of the
possible here is very big.
Absolutely.
It's a big stage.
I mean, in New York City, you
can see that, and why
a massive party.
That's probably the only
one in the whole city.
There's tenth massive parties
going on, and there's ten more
coming up in the next
couple of years.
It's a big city, but small
village at the end.
And I think food is the best
weapons on earth to make peace.
It's the food.
It's the drink.
We have better peace on earth.
And you probably the
united nation ambassador.
In time.
From south pole.
Only New Zealand has found them.
Try it, wasabi if you'd like.
A lot of Chinese
restaurant in New York...
I grew up in the 50s and 60s,
even then, Chinese restaurant,
Chinese food was really an
essential part of
being a new yorker.
I mean if you don't know
thousand use chop sticks as a
new yorker, you were a
terrible new yorker.
I'll ask one thing, you know
how to speak like a
Brooklyn person?
It's a tough accent.
Queens is easier, it's more of
a, I can't, I mean, I live right
next to it my whole life.
We don't want to hear it.
I just to want hear
not for nothing.
What?
Not for nothing.
That's Brooklyn.
Not for nothing, but I could
use a little more wine.
There.
Not for nothing.
Nothing, nothing.
All right.
Shanghai chef prepares a meal
of a style that will become
without a doubt more and more
typical and in demand here among
those who can afford it.
And more and more people
every day can afford it.
What is it?
We have tomato and
potato, and that's it.
What else do we have?
Australian beef, a massive,
perfectly cooked Tom hawk chop,
$150 a pound, that
includes bones and fat.
This is about a thousand
dollars worth of steak.
Even if Tim wanted to serve good
old USA beef, still the finest
on earth in my
opinion, he can't.
China has banned imports over
concerns of mad cow disease.
While they carve, the quick
trip behind the bookshelf.
Now I want to show
you the best place.
Wow.
So you name, your label,
the village of wines.
There's a chance we have it.
And so this size is our
interesting wine that they can
keep ageing themselves.
This is the house collection.
That's correct.
Right.
And I want to show you
the membership area.
The newest member,
Anthony Bourdain.
Me?
And it's all our collection
of wriens, please, open it.
Ah.
Well, cool.
It's good being
the... thank you.
Thank you so much.
Close that up, man.
Close it up.
Here's the thing, even with
the modern China rising out of
the ground all around you, even
with all the things the same
things you see for sale
everywhere where people have
money these days, even with all
that, there's still this China.
Shoning road, just south
of people's square.
It's still happening.
The good old stuff.
The China you first
fell in love with.
Walk down the street and look in
any direction, and there's
something to eat.
I may not know what it is
immediately, but chances
are, it's good.
We talk about foodies and
what does that mean?
By current definition, best I
can understand it, that makes
just about every Chinese person
I ever laid eyes on a foodie.
Which is to say a perfectly
reasonable person who enjoys and
pays attention to where
the good stuff is.
Look at this.
One street, and look, stuffed
oysters grilled over charcoal.
Snake bits, why yes.
And yes, it does taste
kind of like chicken.
There used to be a lot of
streets like this full of it
where you could look, shop
around, then eat all
out in the open.
Happy, delicious torrent of
food, but the government, as
governments do, are
tightening the screws.
Old is bad, new is good.
Not everybody thinks this
is a good idea though.
Bill Wang was born in Shanghai
and studied here at the
university.
He began teaching English before
he was out of college.
He suggested we meet, and there
may be stalls all over Shanghai,
but bill says this one,
this one is the one.
So you're an English teacher?
Yes, yes.
Most of the people I meet of
Chinese background who speak
English have, their teachers
were British, sometimes
Australian, or New Zealand.
Younger generation, there's more
of that sort of TV accent.
Is that good or bad?
I think it's good.
You know, TV series, especially
American TV series are
so popular in China.
What are the most popular?
Right now, house of cards.
House of cards.
Yeah.
So popular.
House of card.
That's really interesting, what
do you think the appeal is here?
You know, in the show,
American, they talk about
president, in China there's no
way you can talk about
those sensitive topics.
So many people love that show,
it's really, really good.
Wow, that's really
a surprise to me.
Wow.
This is huge.
Yes.
Yeah.
Yum, good.
Is it good?
Uh-huh.
Minced pork, ginger, moistened
with rice wine, soy,
it all gets mixed up nicely
and folded into the dough.
Boiled until just right and
sauced with soy sauce, vinegar,
sesame oil, and peanut butter.
You have a sweet, savory thing
going on with every bite.
You want this.
Believe me, you want this bad.
In fact, you need it.
What do your students want to do
when they enter the
professional field?
What's the dream?
I think this generation,
there are a lot of them are
lost.
They don't know what to do.
If you ask like the university,
what is the dream?
Right.
Buy an apartment in Shanghai,
buy a car, you know,
that kinds of things.
Are there enough
jobs for everybody?
It's becoming more and
more competitive.
Right.
Everybody wants the best job,
so many very few
of them out there.
But I think there's like a huge
gap between company
and new graduates.
Right.
Company wants
experienced workers.
Right.
New graduates also
want a good job.
Now.
Yeah, now.
They are not ready for it.
Right.
They don't want to do some,
you know, hard work,
start from scratch.
Right.
So that's the problem.
It looks to me, China in
general, Shanghai in particular,
is changing very, very fast.
Very, very fast.
Every time I come,
it's different.
And in your recent memory, in
the last ten years, what's the
most noticeable change to you?
Food like this.
It's becoming more and
more difficult to find.
This is handmade.
And I think this is real food.
It's not very expensive, and it
tastes great, but a lot of food,
you know, processed
food right now.
And also, of course Internet.
It has pros and cons, the good
part is that you can get
information easily.
Right.
That part is people don't
talk to each other, that's bad.
People go to a restaurant, you
know, like a couple, they take
pictures, and use their cell
phone, they don't
talk to each other.
They're communicating with
everybody else in the world
except who's at the table.
What's the point.
It didn't happen until
you tweeted, as we say.
Oh my gosh.
What's clear very quickly
here is the way China claims
things are the way they're
supposed to be, and the way they
actually are, two
different things.
Meet Thomas you.
Hacker turned entrepreneur.
He recently received significant
startup money to build what he
calls an open source
project sharing platform.
To connect Chinese college
students with the world.
When you say hacking, what is,
what do you do when you hack?
What's the intent?
Actually, it starts from MIT.
If you go to the computer
science and artificial
intelligence building, MIT, it
will show you the
definition of hack.
It's actually a very positive
word that's been in
a negative word.
One hacker is people who are
really, they really like
programming, and they love
to share information.
Just like cooking.
You love to share recipes to
other friend for a lot of
cooking.
Legally, there might be
something wrong with it, but
morally do you think there's
anything wrong with you're
essentially breaking into
an information base.
I'm not doing any damage, I'm
going to look around, see how
things work, and I'll leave
without disturbing anything.
Would most hackers say
that that's okay?
Yes.
It's in the service
of knowledge.
It's okay for most of the
hackers in our communities.
I was lucky, I got into a big
hacker community here in shank
lie and met great mentors.
Started in business in 21.
I did.
Great accomplishment.
You didn't go to college?
I didn't.
Why not?
The country is so advanced in
so many other ways,
why in this area?
Network problem here in
China, we have GFW, it blocks a
lot of important
information websites.
And a lot of people, we can't
use in college at all.
And so the human resource
problem and power problem is
getting more and more
serious here in China.
Because everyone's going
to silicon valley?
They offer better, obviously.
These are the famous ribs?
Yes.
Maybe the number one thing
that the seriously food crazed
traveler coming back from
Shanghai will tell you to eat,
other than the soup
dumplings of course, ribs.
It takes two cooks working
at once to make this dish.
One deep fries the ribs in
hot oil until just right.
Another toasts the ginger,
cumin, and other
spices in a wok.
And then, in go the ribs.
And if you're devoted of what's
called wok, you sit as close as
possible to capture that
elusive, fast dissipating
breath, flavor of
the wok itself.
Toss them around coating those
bones with all that
good stuff, then serve.
And because we like it to burn,
Thomas orders some
spicy chicken dish.
Hey means energy, light force,
or breath, and that's what
you're looking for of the
flavor, the essence of a very
old, carefully seasoned
cooking vessel.
Oddly enough, Thomas tells me
there's no mandarin or at least
Shanghainese work for wok, it's
simply called a cooking pot.
To which I say I really do know
nothing about this country.
Fantastic.
Wow.
Yeah.
I love that.
Not too good.
Not bad.
To me, and I've eat an lot of
food, this is spicy,
fresh, bright, vibrant...
I will take you
somewhere better.
So are you a foodie?
Yeah, I eat a lot.
Were you born here, in Shanghai?
Yeah.
At least in modern times,
it's hard to imagine that any
place has changed as profoundly
and changing as quickly
as it is changing here.
We feel very proud.
We really feel proud.
Our qualities of life is
improving really, really faster.
In a poll, 85% of Chinese who
were asked the question, do you
feel that your life will
be better next year?
85% said yes, it will
be better next year.
This is an extraordinary number.
Yeah.
I don't know a lot of other
countries that would say that.
Yeah.
Well that looks great.
Famous chicken.
So good.
Not bad.
You know, I'm finding this
food really, really delicious.
And you're saying it's
just... it's so-so.
Wow.
Shanghai is one of the
biggest cities in the world
right now.
A global financial center and
transportation hub and the
world's busiest port.
You can smell the money.
But maybe the real story is the
newly emerging participants
in global capitalism.
The middle class.
The working class.
Who also want flat screen TVs
and cars, and vacations, and the
promise of better
for their kids.
Take this couple, typical
working class Chinese from
the worker's paradise.
Mei, a bus driver, and
Don, his bride to be.
Today is their wedding day.
And custom must be observed.
When it comes to weddings, the
Chinese have always gone big,
and these days, bigger still.
Lots of food, lots of
booze, lots of people.
Getting crazy.
Which is why Thomas and I have
become wedding crashers.
The constellation bar
for a prewedding drink.
The classic Chinese
cocktail, the Moscow mule.
Okay, maybe not Chinese.
These are good.
Yeah.
This is the reason why
I love this place.
Are you married?
No.
Not yet.
I'm not a big fan of marriage.
You've been to weddings, yes?
Yes.
Have you ever crashed
a wedding before?
No.
It's going to be a little weird.
I mean, we don't
know anybody there.
How do you do?
Well, I hope the food's
good that the thing.
You probably have
a lot of drinks.
Could be really crazy.
Oh really?
Yeah.
Uh-oh.
Drink a lot.
Really?
So, ready to crash a wedding?
Yeah, let's do it.
All right.
♪
Yeah.
The Chinese wedding
is not cheap.
You need a banquet room, in this
case the families rented out
this place at the historic
park hotel Shanghai.
Chinese weddings generally
speaking, mean the presence of a
number of formalities.
First, meet the bride and
groom upon entering.
Red envelope, also known as the
hung bow, like in good fellas,
it's a little something
for the bride and groom.
Help them get started
in their new life.
Thank you.
Okay.
Table setting.
Often with some
must-haves present.
Booze, whisky, smokes
for the guests.
So this is kind of like a
traditional Chinese wedding.
Oh, I know, I do
this every week.
Hotel to hotel, and
I crash weddings.
Okay.
Roast duck, that I will have,
of course, and some beef fried ♪
kona crab, shelled and then
sauted in garlic and ginger
before being stuffed
back into the shell.
Steamed turbo with scallions.
♪
A wedding in China, have this
kind of meal for whole
two days, whole weekend.
See, I'm telling you, we
should do this every week.
I'm going to come back, I'm
going to move to Shanghai.
And you and me, twice a week,
we'll just go to weddings.
[ Cheers and app
You may kiss the bride.
♪
And there is, of
course, drinking.
Much drinking.
She wants to share with you.
Oh.
♪
Again.
When I first came to China,
it was for business, and
one after the other.
Everyone at the table came up
and said, ah, Mr. Bourdain, I
would like to do a
drink with you.
And then, all of it.
I didn't know how
to politely say no.
I can't, I can't.
I just kept doing
it and doing it.
I got super [ Bleep ] up.
I ended up going
like to karaoke.
I ended up singing a Billy idol
song, I think I sang
"white wedding."
♪
Making it a personal mission
to get me seriously drunk.
I'm just wondering how
you got out of that.
When I sat down and I looked
around the table and I tried to
figure out, who at this table is
going to try really
hard to get me drunk?
I wouldn't have guessed
it was going to be her.
Drinking this white
wine all day long.
I don't drink a
lot, just a taste.
We have to get this straight.
That is not wine.
That's like grain alcohol.
That's what we call liquor.
Okay, so we're clear on that.
♪
Now, this is a small
wedding by most standards.
About a hundred guests.
But just booking the
room took two years.
♪
A toast, followed by many
more toasts, to the bride, to
the groom, to happiness,
to prosperity.
♪
There is a place.
There is always a place where
something delicious in a bowl
is waiting just for you.
Down a street, down an alley,
there's a place like this one,
where locals will tell
you, the good stuff lives.
They call this stuff
long-leg noodles.
Because they say the woman
who runs it is tall.
Noodles for me are a solitary
pleasure, between
me and my bowl.
Fen Li and her husband Wong
understand this, I think.
Now, this is a deceptively
good business.
What used tab a typical,
low-cost working stall of the
street variety has
in fact blown up.
Along with the rest
of the economy.
Rich kids and TV guys
like me want to eat here.
And they do.
How do you make a bowl
of perfect happiness?
Cook noodles in boiling water,
flavored with chiles and lard.
Immerse your noodles in a soy
bath of deeply
sinister pork stock.
A little bit of bock choi, heat
for a few seconds, simmering,
and garnish with a slowly
cooked, heavily reduced,
almost candied pork.
Then suck those noodles loudly.
And enjoy.
♪
Where are we going?
Who will drive us there?
What will it be like
when we get there?
I think it will look like this.
♪