I'm told you're a man
who can help me.
Some time in mid 19th century
1850s my great, great
grandfather immigrated
to south America.
Utopian dreams.
My aunt used to tell stories he
was into arms smuggling
or who knows, you know?
No idea.
♪
For most people Paraguay is
an empty space on the
lap of Latin America.
A country of only six million
where a vast percentage of the
land is steaming hot
jungle or a huge desert.
Only a few large cities offer a
respite from the
impressive heat.
A thousand miles up river
from the Atlantic ocean sits
Paraguay's remote capitol city
known largely for being a post
war refuge for freeing Nazis and
extremely unpleasant dictators.
This place of all places in the
world is where my great, great,
great grandfather disappeared
without explanation
sometime in 1850s.
I'm told your a man
that can help me.
How do you do?
May I call you Tony.
Please.
You're here for the first time.
First time in Paraguay, yes.
Lido bar has always been like
the central switchboard.
A gathering place.
Ladies in orange tanks serve
working class food to people
of every walk of life.
This place is very unique.
I've been here for
more than 50 years.
Let's get something to eat.
It's beef, onion, and hard
cooked egg deep fried to
perfection.
Cattle is the big
business of this country.
It used to be cattle
and smuggling.
These days it's still cattle.
You see a lot of beef
is what I'm saying.
This is a mystery
to most people.
What we know comes Nazi's
and Germans and crimes.
Do you think that's an
undeserved reputation?
It's a nice country.
A beautiful country.
He was one of a team of
people I sent out looking for
the mysterious lost Bourdain.
What are you called upon to do?
Normally counterfeiting.
In the old days it's said much
of this counterfeiting had
partners in the government.
Not so much anymore.
He was the last of his
kind in Paraguay.
Of German heritage he ruled the
country until 1989 with a quite
charm but behind the scenes was
another thing utilizing an
outfit of trained secret
police he to toured and tossed
of helicopters over the jungle.
The list goes on.
One in four was said to have
cooperated willingly or not as
paid informers on their
fellow citizens.
It's quite a history
in this country.
Crazy, tragic, violent.
Things are changing, a lot.
And now.
Sometime in the mid 19th
centuries or 1850s he immigrated
to south America, first
Argentina but apparently came
here.
That's really almost
all I know for sure.
Did he die of old age?
Did he die of syphilis?
I have no idea.
I'd like to know.
I'd like to find a grave site.
That would be great.
My father died at 57.
His father in his 20s I believe.
I'll be 58 in June.
I think I am the longest living
male Bourdain possibly ever.
You're lonely in the world?
I'm lonely in the world, yes.
If I could solve the mystery of
John Bourdain I would be happy.
It would be great if you found
out he owned a huge ranch and
they have been waiting for his
relatives to claim his property.
Maybe not.
I am trying to make some
sense of this country.
You lived here how long?
22 years.
What a strange and nice country.
Go to Paraguay and find a
German to show you around.
Not so crazy or
unrepresentative.
People came to this country from
everywhere to as Emmerson called
it make their own world.
What's good to eat here?
I suppose you want
something Paraguay.
Yes.
It's rice with fried
beef with egg on top.
I'm there.
Good.
And there's a soup that is
very very old Paraguay stuff.
That looks good.
That looks very good.
Yeah.
That's good, man.
I'm trying to make some
sense of this country.
You lived here how long?
22 years.
Why did you come here
in the first place?
I was born in east Germany
and then in '89 the wall break
down and you say
wow, you will go.
I haven't seen anything of
this country yet but what I read
was the world's back water
filled with banked that had been
looted, institutions
that didn't work.
Every carried a gun.
It was like the
wild west but poor.
It's not that anymore.
A bit of this is true.
I by myself got a .45
on my head last week.
That's common for me.
Seldom have I seen a country
where one after the other you've
had the most insane suicidal
group of dictators
century after century.
You are right.
Even in times the better part of
Paraguay was behind him.
They're very very easy to
influence and business I believe
unchanged until a short time ago
now there is a growing
middle class.
Better education than before and
that makes the people say no.
How was the soup?
I liked it.
The way my wife cooks it.
I like it better with chicken.
But chicken is
more for Saturday.
Paraguay was a very poor
country. Spaniards came because
there was a lot of silver in the area.
They found none,
so they lost interest
in Paraguay.
This is the only country
in Latin America where the
indigenous language is
the official language.
I am married to a Paraguay
woman and when her fathers come
in they automatically talk that
and I'm more or less out.
El supremo.
Got to love it.
A nearly 200 year succession of
dictators began in 1811 when he
declared himself El
supremo for life.
He insisted Paraguay become
a mixed race society.
They're neither
Spanish nor Indians.
El supremos prevented marriage
between white and white.
Today 95% are of mixed blood.
And we usually speak
two languages.
Right.
This is the central market?
This is the biggest one
and the most popular one.
I'm hungry.
What's good here?
We opted for a little catfish.
And okay the saying is that
it makes man very powerful.
What's he got?
That looks good.
There was a good Italian
influence in Paraguay.
So maybe this stew
comes from this.
It's from all over the world.
So you invite them and
get the catfish stew?
Could you pass me the soup.
The soup is very unique.
Our dictator Lopez's favorite
soup was corn soup and one day
he ordered his favorite soup and
the cook when he opened
the pot it was a cake.
Paraguay has not been noted
for its history of kinder,
gentler leaders.
In the 1800 two generations of
Lopez, father and son, one
dictator after the other
certainly left their
marks on this country.
Lopez was pretty much known
for putting a wrong
stamp on a letter.
You get shot.
So the cook didn't
want to get shot.
He showed up in front of Lopez
and says this is soup and the
dictator ate it and he liked it
and later the entire
country eat it.
So it's cheesey cornbread?
Yeah.
Awesome.
Good meal.
So this was the house or one
of the houses of madam lynch.
Exactly.
The journalist, poet, and
author has written books on
Paraguay's history.
Now who was madam lynch.
A murky background
would you say?
There's talk about that.
Somebody say she was a great
woman or she was
a very evil one.
She came over on the
famous trip from France.
Right.
In 1840s Lopez senior
reversed many of Paraguay's
isolationist policies.
He invited foreigners to settle
here and built one of south
America's first rail ways.
It's steam engines taken out of
service only a few years ago and
he sent his son to Europe.
His mission his father sent
him out to get what arms?
Arms and technicians,
engineers and machinery.
Junior by most contemporary
accounts was an idiot.
So he came back with a
mistress, madam lynch.
Yes.
Which dad wasn't
too happy about.
Right.
He was very traditional and
wanted his son to marry a
Paraguayan woman and do
everything by the book.
She was the daughter
of an Irish doctor.
Ambitious, social climbing,
fond of nice things.
Clothes imported from France.
And there were parties here.
He showed madam lynch to his
father and his father was
upset so she was put aside.
Kept as a mistress.
And that was the way society
tried to treat her and she
wanted to be treated
as the... Princess?
Yes.
Tell me about her
famous boat trip.
On one of her more notorious
adventures as hostess she
organized an outing.
She invited all of
society to join her.
Right.
The river steamer was
engaged for the party.
Well, there were some issues
between the ladies
and madam lynch.
Once on board they treated
their hostess like trash.
So she got upset and threw
over board all the food they
were supposed to eat.
She had it all
thrown in the river?
Yes.
Then she ordered the captain
to stop the boat and let her
guests just sit there in
that jungle heat for hours.
Throwing tubs of caviar and
whole roasted pigs into the
river in front of the
starving aristocrats?
Somehow that pleases me.
Going back to the very
beginnings, various groups with
stars in their eyes came here
seeking to create a utopia
along the lines, a paradise.
Repopulate Latin
America with Germans.
British, Italians,
you had everybody.
Yeah.
I had a great, great, great
grandfather come over to
Paraguay around the 1850s.
Right.
Might have been, myself, a
seeker of some kind
of utopian dreams.
Originally from France?
From France, yes.
What city?
Do you know?
My great, great, grandfather
was from near Bourdeax.
So I'm curious about
this settlement.
The Paraguay river still as
it was 150 years ago the
country's main artery.
A thoroughfare for
transporting people and goods.
Who lives out there?
Of all the people we see
fishing on the river banks.
Are they fishing for dinner?
Most of them are
fishing for dinner.
They decide by
themselves to live here.
They could go and start working
on a construction place
tomorrow.
Peter organized a trip up
river to see new Bourdeaux.
What was hoped would
be a new France.
The fish today 14 kilo that's
half a month's salary and you
get with a bit of good
luck in one night.
Right.
Outside of the cities Paraguay
is sparsely populated.
Indigenous groups, a few settled
Europeans, Mennonites, Germans
and a fishing lure and
shotgun salesman.
What are the shotguns for?
Bandits?
Varmentes?
To hunt deer and water pig.
That's a peacemaker.
Any rogue Nazis
we can shoot now?
I am tempted by the offer of
a cheap shotgun for sale.
Figures Peter would know this
guy but reason wins out.
I don't think we're going
to buy a shotgun today.
Me, fear, shotgun,
shot sunny day.
That's not a good mix.
Unlike madam lynch's guests
I'm making sure I eat
on this boat trip.
The most important
part of my meal.
Cold, frosty beverages.
I started early.
Cheers.
Fish and a man goe salsa.
You have the two most
appreciated fish here on the
table of Paraguay.
That's the catfish.
And that's the... oh, of course.
Yes.
That's tasty.
That's nice.
I'm curious about this whole
episode of the settlement.
They were supposed to be
most of them farmers.
But just 86 were farmers.
Who were the other people
they were Taylors and
shoemakers.
They were put in the jungle
and left by himself.
Right.
Why here of all the
people in the world.
People talk about it as a hell.
It's hot here... it's dry,
it's red, it's difficult.
You have all the mosquitos.
A flatland of cactus
and thorns and misery.
There's a part where you enter
the country you are good
food.
Did they ever see
this as utopia?
No, I'm sure not.
That?
This.
Wow that's not how
I pictured it.
Doesn't look like
Bordeaux to me.
There's nothing much left.
I'm told a small museum
of artifacts.
The site where it once existed.
It was money for each settler.
Perhaps there was a
communication break down
somewhere and he might have told
them I'm bringing you the finest
farmers France has to offer.
Right and he might have told
these Frenchmen they're going to
give you free property.
You don't have to do anything.
You'll live like kings.
Just reach up in the trees
and fruit and gold bars are
dropping.
In fact, they were thrown
out and say here you are.
That's your land.
Go ahead.
These four French guys show up.
Right.
Lopez senior and the
government kept their side of
the bargain.
They provided them with
houses, equipment.
Tours and animals
and everything.
Needs to have one of these.
Pressed sandwiches I think.
And that's it.
Dig, grow.
The settlers quickly discovered
that farming is hard
work and that the conditions in
no way resembled the new
France of their dreams.
That's a big snake.
So they get broke and they
decide to leave the colony.
How many French were left at
the end of the new
Bordeaux experiment?
Did any stay?
Some of them but few.
Any chance he ended his life
here ending the unclaimed escape
and what was prime cattle
country turns quickly to dust.
So, you have some
information perhaps of the
elusive John Bourdain I hear?
I don't know what he did here.
Of course I'm hoping for
something extremely glamorous.
A gun runner, drug smuggler.
Maybe he died in the saddle.
Maybe he died happy.
Maybe he was living out in the
bush surrounded by adoring
indigenous women.
I don't know.
You know if he was a masseur for
madam lynch I guess I
would be let down.
I had contact with another
historian around the world and
the history of your family
is very interesting.
Oh, really?
Okay.
Interesting.
Yeah, your family, your
grandfather John Bourdain came
following the sun.
Okay the facts as I know them
so far I think are this.
My great, great, granddad, John,
his son came to live
with his uncle.
1850 John Bourdain moves.
This is the document that we
have showing him arriving.
There he is.
In that time, he worked
with... with a hat maker.
A hat maker?
I'm pretty sure he said hat
maker which have to say
disappoints me like a lot.
The whole elusive wing of south
American Bourdains were project
runway contestants of their day?
In 1855 Lopez's son arrives.
With madam lynch.
Madame lynch was fond of
things like French couture.
Yes and that changed
the way of dress.
She might have been
good for business.
I'm trying to put this in a
light I can be enthusiastic
about.
Like how clearly forward
thinking they were.
His customers were a hat maker.
The people that treated her
with such utter contempt.
Did they live in the
colonial homes?
In that type of residence?
Yes.
Times were changing in south
America too in those days.
Society ladies craved the
latest French fashion.
There was money to be made.
I'm bummed.
He would have died in 1858.
Or before.
It was a good way to die
because he wouldn't have
to join this horrible war.
He missed the war?
Yeah.
The old Lopez died.
The young Lopez got in power.
Our man becomes president.
Yes, Francisco Lopez.
Absolutely the most
megomaniacal dictator.
You're right.
He was unkind to his siblings.
His brothers were tortured
and killed and the
sisters were jailed.
Taken into tiger cages.
Tiger cages.
Tiger cages and the mother
was given some beating.
The 60 something-year-old
mother was flogged and
beaten in front of him.
Not a nice man.
He believed that he had a
chance to get married with the
daughter of the
emperor of Brazil.
That's right.
He was refused on very
unflattering terms.
Thanks presumably to his
expansionist ambitions he
dragged Paraguay into the
triple alliance war.
He essentially challenged
all three neighbors.
Brazil, Argentina and Uruguay.
To war.
This doesn't seem
like a good idea.
In what would become the
bloodiest war in Latin America's
history, hundreds
of thousands died.
When Lopez ran out of adults he
sent children into the field
dressed only in rags, armed with
sticks, painted to
look like guns.
My great grandfather was a
10-year-old boy and he was
dressed alike because otherwise
he was going to be
enrolled into the army.
Madam lynch survived.
Yes.
But with her money she was
allowed to keep her possessions?
Yes.
In history it's hard to find
a more disastrous or more cruel
or pointless campaign
it would seem.
When all was said and done as
much as 60% of the population
and 90% of the men of
this country were dead.
The survivors were just
like 50 or 40,000 people.
There was nothing here
for like 100 years.
John Bourdain dies here?
Yes.
An adult natural of France by
the name of John Bourdain.
Cause of death.
Not specified here.
Is there a grave site?
We're looking.
We are looking for it.
So I'm hungry.
I'm really hungry.
You know you want it.
It's late.
You had a few.
No, you had a lot.
You want something greasy,
savory, juicy and nasty.
This is it.
Right.
That's what today's people
eat in the streets.
An egg a little runny please.
Soy sauce I think too.
Like the ruins of ancient Troy,
egg on top of cheese
on top of meat.
Now get in my stomach now.
Awesome.
Really awesome.
And the last thing I give a
steaming loaf about anymore,
I mean, I am over it.
Here comes news of the
big break through.
I talked with the historian
and he says it looks like your
great grandfather what he was
merchandising it was
definitely not hats.
Really?
We have here Bourdain.
Right.
And what is he bringing?
Like fire crackers?
There is not even more than
200 or 300 wealthy families who
sometimes in a birthday
would crack a little bit.
Are you suggesting
something untoward?
Weapons.
Weapons?
Yeah.
Awesome.
My aunt always said
he was a gun runner.
We figured she was full of shit.
She also said she was in the
resistance, but everybody
in France said that.
So, arms.
Was he a hat-maker slash arms...
Are all these historians and
gene uses on the money?
Was great grampy an arms dealer?
What hat makers needs 200
pounds of gun powder?
I've got you now.
Or was he a party supplier,
selling fine French hats and fik
crackers to school kids?
I don't know what to believe.
And in '58, he died.
Right.
And he was buried, here, two
miles from here in the
rich people's cemetery.
We can pretty well say in
which area he remains.
He is there.
Wow.
Well, I guess we'll
have to go look, huh?
Definitely.
Sorry little buddy
there's no escaping it.
Paraguay loves their beef.
Perfect ratio, lot of meat,
little bit of vegetables.
Perfect.
Oh, whoa, that's good.
This is the.
A sprawling ranch and it's been
in the family back to the war.
Hard life?
No, we are happy.
We have everything.
20 years ago, it was not used.
In the last years, it's booming.
Where does the boom come from?
We are the second biggest
soybean exporter, eighth
biggest cattle supporter.
Paraguay feeds the entire
world for eight days a year.
How many acres?
100,000 hectares.
I could eat this all day.
And I will.
Barbecue.
You are complete.
It's good.
♪
Mmm, that's awesome.
So were there a lot of
vegetarians in this part of
Paraguay?
Here comes the highlight.
Oh, look at that.
Pretty.
Beef short ribs are amazing.
Mmm, so good.
♪
All of the books I read about
Paraguay are maybe 15 years old.
The first thing, everybody
has to go and buy a gun.
This was not the Paraguay
I expected at all.
He wants to sing a song for you.
A welcome song.
♪
It not say welcome stranger.
It says welcome
brother stranger.
♪
The man who died here was
my great grandfather.
Yes.
This old cemetery.
It seems most likely that
he was buried there.
♪
Nobody I know.
It's very, very likely that
the tomb was just overbuilt.
Right.
Something on top.
♪