This is your first
time to Denmark?
I've got to be honest, I
usually try to avoid clean,
orderly countries without
massive social countries.
If you're not the poster boy for
the entire country,
you should be.
We go?
Yes, let's go.
You were saddled with the weight
of best restaurant in the world.
This looks totally bogus.
It's fantastic.
You have to work 20 hours a
day in order to achieve this.
They're waiting now.
Let's go.
It's so much mess about... whoo!
It's about bang.
And elements, elements.
What places have you been that
you can compare to Noma?
No place.
It's a whole different world.
Beautiful!
♪
Once upon a time in a land
far, far away, there was a
place, a very special place, a
clean, orderly, and nice place.
Usually I hate clean,
orderly, and nice.
The air smells fresh and
physically fit, statuesque
blondes lined by old
buildings and canals.
I read something
disturbing on my way here.
Apparently Denmark is, like, the
happiest place on earth.
They actually keep
stats on this.
Apparently Denmark is far and
away number one the happiest,
most content place on earth.
Well, the colleges are
the same for everybody.
Free?
Free.
That's un-American.
That's socialism, isn't it?
Yes.
I mean, here, that's
not a bad word.
Okay, they pay, like, 60%
of their earnings in taxes.
But then they do get things
like free health care.
52 weeks maternity
leave on full pay.
When I had my kids two rooms
down, that's where the
future king had his kids.
There's no, like, Beyonce suite.
No.
We're all there.
We're all the same.
That makes people more happy.
That looks like a
nightmare to me.
By the way, it would be
helpful to point out, this
show is not about Denmark.
It's not about Copenhagen.
I'm here for one man.
Follow this way.
And one restaurant.
And then we can start.
Noma is the place where Renee
pretty much changed the
whole world of gastronomy.
For three years in a world, it
was named the world's best
restaurant by a jury of world
chefs and food writers who
presumably know such things.
Whoa.
And so, the question.
How does this nice, down to
earth guy rise to the top of the
food world all while presenting
things that no one could
possibly think would
taste that good?
The flowers.
Oh, man.
I'm not sure, but that's
what I'm here to find out.
The moss?
Yes, chef.
We know that Noma has been
said to be the world's best.
This is a dish that
is 20 man hours.
What we've heard outside of
Denmark is that Rene sources his
ingredients exclusively from the
Nordic region, mostly from
within 60 miles of the
restaurant.
Think about that.
Denmark is not exactly
the Mediterranean.
Summers are short.
What Rene and crew started, what
they're famous for,
is their ingredients.
And color me dubious.
Did you ever eat moss before?
No.
That is incredible.
There's no way that this is
going to look convincingly
delicious on TV.
But it is really delicious.
Alsandro Porcheli is
Italian living in Denmark.
I met Rene in 2004.
Basically the restaurant
was just opened.
Ten years after Noma's
inception, Rene is arguably the
most famous Dane since Hamlet.
So it's happily
ever after, right?
Not quite.
All this happened
actually in Copenhagen.
You have all these rules, these
guidelines where you never
brag about yourself.
The law which discourages
attention-seeking is part and
parcel of living in Denmark.
Danes who think too big are
often cut down by their peers.
It's hard to really make an
effort, and if you stand out too
much, you know, get
off your horse.
Okay, so let's say you start
a restaurant and you announce
right away, this restaurant is
going to be different than
anybody else's restaurant.
Are people mean originally?
Do they talk... about you?
I mean, how much foul language
can I use on this show?
We very quickly became the
big band of the seal...
People can be so cruel.
Do Danes like this place?
No?
It's got the attention
of the whole world.
Yeah, exactly.
To tell the truth, food
nerds, captains of industry,
celebrities, you name it have
been flocking here for years.
Some waiting months for a
reservation in a 45-seat
restaurant.
Do we have the leek?
It's marinating.
All of this green snow
is made from leaves.
That's good.
You don't notice it.
You notice the flavor.
That's delicious.
That's really intensely... like
I've never tasted a green
vegetable that good.
You see lawns, people sit
down, the sun is out.
The birds are singing.
This is where happiness
was invented.
Tubali gardens, it is said,
is the second-oldest
amusement park in the world.
Watch the pantomime that
is hundreds of years old.
I've only been here once
with my kids, actually.
I work all the time,
unfortunately.
This is usually the place where
young kids take
their first date.
How old is this thing?
I don't know, man.
This is made for kids.
Does it feel a bit wobbly?
Copenhagen is dangerous, too.
Yeah, right.
Whoa.
There you go.
This is not bad.
There you see.
It's a little tiny cart.
It's not huge, is it?
Squished in the middle.
It's like Singapore.
All dense together.
No death penalty.
Only the public humiliation.
Oh, here we go.
Firearms, apparently,
it's okay here.
You know, I've actually never
fired a firearm in my life.
Really?
And I've never driven a car.
You've never driven a car?
Never driven a car.
Okay.
This will be empowering.
This could change
your whole life.
You don't need to tell
him, he's American.
Is this a competition?
Call it what you like.
All right.
Oh, this is exciting.
We definitely have a winner.
Oh, my god.
Not a single one?
That's what we call
a nice grouping.
This is like public
school, shooting range.
After this, we're
going to steal a car.
I'll teach you to drive.
Come on, guys.
They're waiting.
Familiar with this one at all?
No.
It's served around
Christmas time.
You've got a little fish
rammed right through.
I love it.
Isn't this tweet?
There's a pickled
cucumber in the middle.
That's great.
Very traditional flavors.
There's all these old school
restaurants that have been
here hundreds of years.
The herring, smoked fish,
the traditional stuff.
There we go.
Thank you, my good man.
Welcome to the happiest
place... on earth.
On earth.
There we go.
Smoked eel.
Pickled herring.
These tiny little shrimps, one
of the few seasonal offerings
that Danes look forward to.
Our eating traditions
aren't that big here.
Historically, we've
eaten for survival.
It was fuel to us.
Not exactly the most fun bunch.
It was sinful to take too
much pleasure in food.
You're sitting at the table,
like oh, my god, that's so good.
It's delicious.
You're already going down a
slippery slope of who knows what
other kinds of behaviors.
My father is an immigrant here.
I'm not even a full Dane.
Your father was... the
former Yugoslavia.
And left Yugoslavia at what age?
14.
People make fun of me when I say
I've never driven a car.
I never had a Coca-Cola
until I was, like, 17.
It just wasn't in a small little
village where there's two cars.
The first food I have is also
from there, and
it was my father.
And the day before we had been
into the mountain
picking chestnuts.
And I remember it so vividly as
a little child, I saw my
father roasting chestnuts.
And then I start hearing
all these things popping.
20 minutes later, they were in a
bowl and my aunt poured milk
that she had just taken from the
cow and we had that
for breakfast.
It was so natural that we
went to the mountain for the
chestnuts, you grew
your food yourself.
These sort of experiences
growing up, they really shaped
the type of cook I am today.
So now you have a generation
of young cooks like myself all
over town looking for
the flavor of a region.
What is the flavor?
What are the ingredients we
have, and how do we combine them
in a way that tells something of
where you are in the world?
Between me and nature,
there's not so much love.
Nature is where bugs live.
But I'm learning reluctantly
over time how much
I've been missing.
Rene's proclivity to scrounge
around for flavorful
stuff that grows wild...
Welcome to the beach.
Pretty much kick started the
restaurant world's now widely
emulated practice of foraging.
You see all this?
Grass.
But these are succulents.
Rene's thing, since the
beginning, how to put
in what's around you.
To be a 19th century naturalist,
you're going to have
to do this.
Yes, a naturalist.
Chew on this.
Taste delightful?
Yes, it's wonderful.
Disguised as grass.
Here, here, here.
It's everywhere.
Good to go.
So, I know these ingredients,
we were plucking
them just today.
Yes.
Wow.
This will be the future.
Let's go forage, guys.
Come on, kids.
There you go.
Sea beans.
Salty, juicy, crunchy.
If I were looking at this
home, I would very much be
thinking, come on, man.
It's grass.
It's green stuff.
It all tastes the say.
It totally doesn't.
Is some of this stuff poison?
Yeah.
Have you ever eaten
something that... oh, yeah.
On-the-spot diarrhea.
Really?
Yeah.
The dark side of foraging.
Two fish heads.
Growing your own food,
finding your own food.
Yeah.
That was life in Macedonia.
But for a lot of people
now, it is an affectation.
The worst meals are people
following a culinary trend.
They'll say there's an edible.
But it tastes like... but it's
edible and it will go on
the fish no matter what.
Oher, okay.
You just pick off
every little bit.
But I think even at its most
ludicrous manifestation, surely
it is a positive thing that
people are actually starting to
look around and see,
where it grows...
It still is good.
People are being connected
to the place they're in.
What's edible and what's not.
What is there to eat.
This is beach mustard.
In three weeks, this is gone.
New things come up.
It's sour dough bread.
It's butter that has not
been churned all the way.
It's called virgin butter.
Oh, god.
This is amazing, huh?
Butter like this where you
can pretty much taste
what the cow ate.
Anyone who's milked a cow, this
is a flavor of childhood.
There aren't a lot of people
left where I came from
who milked a cow.
This has become more important
to what these guys are
doing.
A relationship also that
they had with the farmers.
This is Soren's farm, but
we always say our farm.
We feel like it's our place.
Soren is his primary
supplier of vegetables.
You see all the shells?
These are shellfish.
Like Rene, he's not your
ordinary Dane and his farm is
unlike the others around here.
This used to be monoculture.
Yep.
Just carrots.
Now what are you growing?
Between 120 and 170
different things.
True, there are tractors and
rows where potatoes
and carrots grow.
But much of what's happening
here is a mix of wild and
cultivated.
This is wild Angelica.
That's chives and the purple
flowers, wild onions.
Let's grow some for next year.
First time you come up here, you
go into this, like
oh, flower garden.
You say no, no, no,
this is the leek field.
Touching them like
they're jewels.
They are jewels.
Let's grab a bunch of
these for lunch, no?
The pressure to provide year
in, year out what you know is
going to sell and what
the market demands.
Do you mind grabbing a
few of these plants?
They're going to grow up,
so don't take the root.
It's very, very hard for a
small guy to say I'm not going
to grow carrots anymore, I'm
going to grow interesting things
and grow them as well as I can.
This is pretty much
a first for me.
This is the first time you
fall to your knees
for a green plant?
Yeah.
How long for leeks?
Do you think we'll ever reach
a point where guys like
Supervissoren will be
in a very good place?
I think if we cut the middle
men, the producers, the farmer,
to talk directly with
a guy like Rene.
Nobody ever teaches you it's
with these people
that grow the food.
You're never taught that as
a cook, which is strange.
Can we have another leek that
looks more similar in
size to that one, please?
I think also, respect to you
all chefs, how should you know
anything about this landscape?
I've been here for 30 years and
I just know small, tiny parts.
So we just scoop it up.
I think we picked
these yesterday.
Oh yeah?
Oh, man.
That is the meatiest
vegetable I've ever had.
Maybe we'll cook this for
lunch spiced with a tartar.
Chop that up with the freshly
slaughtered meat, one
of Soren's cows.
What else?
The asparagus?
Yes, let's do that.
I'm hungry.
Asparagus.
Beautiful.
Let's go.
Just one dollop, okay?
Do not eat that branch.
Okay.
Underneath is a small pile of
tender... asparagus sauce
and fresh green paste.
That is incredible.
Wow.
The flavor of this, huh?
So this is actually beer
made from asparagus.
It's tasty.
What was the name of the cow?
76377330.
Chef, do you want
to do the tartar?
What are you thinking,
just hack up the meat?
Hack up the meat.
It already looks good.
I'm going to go on the
asparagus and the leeks.
Clean them up, grill then.
Do you want to do
a potato salad?
Yeah.
What you would put
on the tartar.
Wild onions.
A bit of this horseradish.
That's the chives.
Chive flowers.
Okay.
A little salt on the leek
and a little cheese?
Yes.
That's the Angelica.
Take all these flowers
and we mix that in.
Some vinegar.
Done.
Didn't take us ten minutes,
but we have four courses.
This is like three
Michelin stars.
Oh, yeah.
Oh, man.
Perfect.
Look at that.
Wow.
Wow, wow, wow.
And that egg.
What an egg.
Do you eat like
this all the time?
I bring my kids up here.
All the staff comes here often.
This becomes your reference
frame for how fresh an
asparagus should be?
Just harvest.
Just cooked.
Just eaten.
I think a place like this, in
addition to being the best
restaurant in the world and
whatever else, it offers a real
possibility that there is food
around that with a little
effort, or a lot of effort, you
can make into something
really delicious.
That is the hard thing.
To change the way people
think about food.
Thank you for joining.
Thank you, chef.
It's magnificent.
There are always going to be
some people out there who hate
the very idea of your existence.
Yeah.
From the very minute they
even think about you.
There's a Danish expression for
not wanting to stand out.
Yeah.
Not wanting to talk
about yourself.
The law of yenta.
Yeast broth.
It's beautiful.
Here we are ten years ago,
we're opening, we're saying
we're going to try
something else.
Stuff like that in that
time was just unheard of.
It was beyond stupid.
And why do you even try?
Why are you fiddling
with stupid concepts?
This is very complex.
I know in the beginning, a lot
of Danes were calling him...
They were laughing at him.
It's a very new thing.
It's not something they
have in Italy, France.
Here it's a different story.
You have a huge part of people
that are still so much in
love with the old world.
I mean, I've even been told that
I have fascist tendencies.
There's been op-eds written in
Danish papers linking what we do
at the restaurant to some of the
most horrible moments
in recent history.
This is the tail of the lobster,
with a little bit of the
head juices underneath.
Use your hands.
I will.
It's luxurious.
So how is it changing?
That's what's interesting.
In ten years, it's really gone
from, you know... to igniting a
new confidence in this city in
this part of the world
that I never grew up with.
A possible forebearer to this
new challenging of the status
quo can be found right in the
heart of this great-laced
Danish capital.
The well established
hippie squatte squatters.
But there are some
interesting features.
There's no government to intrude
on your personal freedom.
You're free to behave as
eccentric fashion as you wish.
If you want to spend your day
talking to a tree, you can do
that without being frowned upon.
They are in local
government, such as it is.
He has been here
for some 40 years.
It was a military area that was
abandoned and then occupied by
squatters and hippies, despite
the fact that the different
governments didn't really
appreciate what was going on
here, nobody actually had the
will or strength
to put people out.
Who makes up the traction?
We do.
What about the essentials,
electric, water.
We buy it from providers.
We pay only one bill.
But I like the fact that my
kids get to walk around the
streets without worrying about
being run over by a car.
There's no cars running
in the streets.
It's like a little village.
It's very secure.
Are you a hippie?
He is.
Two eggs smoking now.
Right down there, we have
pusher street, probably
the most famous part.
The green section, right?
Weed, hash oil.
I would never do that as a
responsible journalist, but I'm
interested in investigating it.
It is a beloved
institution here.
You are free to try an array
of cannabis products.
Theoretically, marijuana is,
like, not legal in Denmark.
But there's a great tolerance
for marijuana here and I think
that's because it
isn't really harmful.
People who smoke too much,
maybe they pass out.
Right.
Quail egg cooked.
Wow.
That's like the
greatest thing ever.
I want more of those.
So there's nobody in charge.
I am.
I'm in charge.
Yeah.
The only problem is
everybody else is, too.
It seems utopia.
We have the same problems as
anybody, but we try to solve
them in a different way.
One of the ways we try to
solve the sort of challenges by
embracing people
as much as we can.
And trying to make space
Do we have two peas
ready for table four?
Can I go over that now?
Yes.
Extraordinary.
I was reading something that's
very un-American in its concept,
which is don't be
afraid to fail.
When we did this issue, to us
it was a very big moment.
We burnt it by mistake.
We thought okay, it's a mistake.
Let's see what happens.
We cooked it.
Then we had a new spice.
That's indescribably delicious.
All cook books, particularly
American cook books, are written
from the point of view that if
you only follow this recipe,
it will turn out great.
You're safe.
This is what we try to talk
about every day in the kitchen
with the cooks on
Saturday night projects.
Apparently this is when you
invite members of your crew to
put up a new dish for comment.
After each grueling workweek
concludes, cooks from every
level of the brigade stay late
to submit their newest
culinary ideas.
Everybody's in on this?
Everybody's in.
This could be a very
uncomfortable... you're heading
it out.
This forum is about failure.
Yes.
So let's see what you got.
Luke, go for it.
In no point in my career
would I have wanted to subject
myself to this kind
of mass scrutiny.
But watch.
It's not bad.
It can be bad.
Fermented apple tea.
This one I did with razor clam
and some cammomile as well.
It just ferments in
water and 2% salt.
This is fondue
with brown butter.
What we have here, ice
cream with some barley.
Mushroom ice cream and
fermented barley sauce.
Personally I'm not getting
what they brought to the party.
It's a little sweet.
With this broth,
it's quite sweet.
So it becomes very
one-dimensional.
Why can't you do that
for your next project?
Dry salt versus brine salt.
He uses things I
would never use.
And it tastes good.
I like it.
Given a choice of a
traditional dessert and this,
I'm very happy with this.
I think it's delicious.
Thank you.
Who's next?
Oh!
So here we have a dish of
strawberries and cream.
I just decided to go on my bike
and see what I could get.
All the flowers that are here,
the lady let me pick
them in her garden.
So strawberries that are
pickled in Rose vinegar.
The base has been infused with
burnt roses and Rose pollen.
Do we just clap or... yes.
And that might well
end up on the menu?
No.
This is not about putting
things on the menu.
I mean, if somebody makes
a masterpiece, it's their
masterpiece.
Really?
Yeah, yeah.
Of course.
Isn't it your hysterical
imperative as the chef to take
his good work and innovation and
put it on the menu and take
credit for it as your own?
I mean, that's the way it's
been done for centuries.
This is not the point here.
The pursuit of enlightenment
and knowledge is its own reward?
To me, yes.
Is that it?
Cheers, everybody.
Table four is being cleared.
Let's start dressing.
They're waiting.
Yes, chef.
Now I travel a lot.
You know, I want to be
number one in the world.
I was in Mexico, the Yucatan.
They don't even know how
to make a tortilla.
They lose touch with
what tradition is.
That looks good.
It's good for you to try
this, the herring, the rye
bread, the traditional stuff.
When you grow up as a cook here,
you don't see it as an
inspiration for your future
endeavors.
The next thing we serve
you is flat bread.
Very traditional here.
We spice ours with chutes
of spruce and oak tree.
This is amazing.
Amazing.
Sophistication.
Something that is so down
to earth flavor-wise.
No doubt about it.
That seems both really
classic and totally new.
Cheers.
I'm learning, Danes may be
stiff, but they sure as
hell know how to drink.
Nils is a Danish
renaissance man.
Drinker, sailor, charter tour
boat operator, musician.
I have known him from
the absolute beginning.
When Noma... can we start now?
Yeah, we're going.
Well, what did you think of him
when you first met him?
I saw an ordinary man.
He fight for what
he think about.
He had a vision.
Yeah, a vision.
And fight for this.
It's very close.
Yeah.
Nicely done, chef.
There we are.
Look at the beautiful
girl there.
Cheers.
Here we go.
What was that?
What's in it?
What is that?
I don't know exactly
how you make that.
But it has been drinking
in Denmark for many years.
So we have gameldansk.
It has about 30
different herbs or so.
So we made an ice cream.
It was delicious.
Oh, here we go.
Gameldansk.
It is good.
It works.
Look at this.
Where you come from, New York?
Yeah.
What?
It works.
He says.
They are perfect.
What would traditional
Danish food be for you?
Potatoes.
Two potatoes.
And some kind of meat and sauce.
Do you taste the sauce?
Yeah?
Hello, fellows.
Fermented barley, and we cooked
the potatoes in that and served
with sturgeon roll
from the lakes.
It has homemade whiskey...
I know the flavor well.
Here we go!
What are we doing?
I'm a little bit hungry.
The Danish national
late night dish.
John's hot dog?
Yes.
I'll have the deluxe.
Organic sausage.
Sounds good to me.
He made his own mustard.
Wow.
Whoa.
Here we go.
That's a classic one.
All my happiest moments seem
to revolve around
meat in two forms.
That's superb.
It's really good.
Don't thrill me when I eat that.
Only the moments
when you look good.
These onions are awesome.
I think that's the way.
You have to make something new.
But respect the classics.
The passion to present
something on a plate that is
delicious, also make sense of
your own environment,
something that is yours.
Come to Copenhagen, Noma for
lunch, John's for dinner.
Just across from Noma,
located in a converted
houseboat, an entity separate
from the restaurant.
The place where Rene set
up to further ideas and
experimentation.
He is one of the
guys in charge here.
Nutmeg is a bit of
a hallucinogenic.
Leave it a while and
see what happens.
Hallucinogenic fish
sauce potentially?
In theory.
Some of the things we are doing,
they are pure experimentation
for experimentation sake and
it's pretty damn delicious.
I like that.
It's another food
item on your shelf.
Me as a cook,
that's what I want.
These are two years old
cherries with the cherry pits.
Five years old wild roses.
This is amazing.
They're talking about will it
taste good in two years if you
ferment it or age it or dry it.
We like to ferment it.
We add bacteria to it, so in
three years time, it
becomes delicious.
The diversity, you're looking at
fermentations and different
bacteria, looking at different
molds, yeast, all sorts.
There is stuff rotting in
jars, these experiments of
fermentation and flavor.
Doing some sinister down there.
This is the ferment from wild
spinach which grows around here.
May this is from a weed
that grows everywhere.
You can do it with gooseberries.
Like to ferment gooseberries.
You get golden drops
of perfection.
We have two berries.
The next thing we serve you is
the dried juices from last
year's harvest of black
currant, and then so creamy.
It's like superpower.
You need to ask about this.
Well, this is
pretty interesting.
This is born out of a desire
to study mummify kags.
Everyone used to eat
mummies, apparently.
So this has been cured with
resins, alcohol,
spices, with honey.
All kinds of things that
would have been used in a
mummification process.
So it's quite moldy.
I mean, it's like an experiment.
It's a 6-month-old piece here.
I guess it's
somewhat inevitable.
It's not unpleasant.
Interesting.
Tastes like Egyptian.
We just have one project.
Deliciousness is an argument
for eating insects.
Wow.
Here we have grilled onions
and salt made out of wood ants.
That's delicious.
Some of the ants we've
been experimenting with.
It's like zing,
excitement in your mouth.
The other ones, they
need a lot of work.
Here we've got wax
lava worm mousse.
This tastes like insects.
Next fermented fish, herrings
molded with stuffed Greens.
These have been
here since January.
So it's been filtered and put
with Juniper and a little squirt
of aged apple vinegar.
Wow.
That's delicious.
That's lethally good.
I can think of ten different
ways I'd like to eat that.
Definitely.
Standing up, sitting
down, with beer.
Beings are being fed.
It takes awhile to stumble
across these things.
Surely they come out
of the woodwork.
Let's have some crayfish.
Delicious.
Cheers, guys.
Cheers.
Mid-summer's day.
Longest day of the year.
The day to Mark the
mid-summer's Eve gather and
partake in traditions.
Then sun comes out,
we salute you.
Building picnics and bonfires.
There's going to be a fire.
And burning witches.
We made those fires back in
the days to keep
the witches away.
Because they thought all the
witches was meeting
on this solstice.
Where's the Pork?
This is the roast pork.
Very traditional.
Without this they
could not live.
So we have pork skin
and dried chocolate.
That's wild.
Roasted pork with cabbage.
That is a serious sandwich.
That's just amazing.
Oh, a rainbow.
This is almost too pretty.
And there you go.
Super cool, huh?
Why don't we have
the strawberries?
With triple cream, huh?
It's delicious.
We have wild blueberry desserts.
The sandwich, one
for each of you.
And the first of the
wild strawberries.
Look at this.
Like a picnic in the park, yeah?
Mm.
Wow.
So the mid-summer
day in Denmark.
Wow.
Look at the witch.
Burn, witch, burn.
You done?
Terrific, thank you.
Unbelievable.
Look, I've eaten at a lot of
great restaurants around the
world, and there was still a
little part of me that was
saying this the going to be bull
The guy's out in the field
yanking weeds out of the ground.
I didn't expect it to
be as good as it was.
It was delicious.
Amazingly delicious.
Amazing.
Yes, I thought it was amazing.
It's not just about coming
up with the concept.
It's assembling what is out
there in a new, beautiful,
authentic and delicious way.
He has single handedly
transformed everybody's
understanding of
Nordic cuisines.
They all tell a bit of a story.
Of the land, the tradition.
But always delicious.
Always, always, always
delicious first.
You may be an ordinary guy,
grounded, comes
from a poor family.
But he has big dreams.
He wants to change the world.
And we can change it.
Never forget that.
We can do that.