Everything changes.
Nothing changes at all.
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ Sha, la, la, la, la, la,
♪ sha, la, la, la, la, la,
♪ sha, la, la, la, la,
Drinking at 4:30 in the
afternoon, it's the perfect time
when the light is just right.
It's important.
Also it's not too crowded.
It's quiet.
A man can have a drink, a pint,
in a dignified fashion
free of care.
Ice, son?
No, thank you.
Here you go.
Thank you so much.
So you're on holiday?
Sort of.
It's your first time in Glasgow?
No, I've been in a
number of times before.
I haven't been in
this pub before.
Oldest in... 1510.
1510, amazing.
From my very first
time, it was Glasgow.
My favorite city in Scotland.
One of my favorite
cities on earth.
It was going to say one of my
favorite cities in Europe,
but is Glasgow Europe?
I don't think so.
It feels somehow
older than that.
To many outsiders, Glasgow is
seen as a hard scrabble, even
fearsome place, a place that
history has moved on from, but
there is definitely a sense here
that something different
is around the corner.
It'll be one of the most
important events in Scottish
and British history.
More than 4 million people will
decide whether Scotland should
stay in the U.K. Or become
an independent country.
Will Scotland stay or
will it leave the union?
Scottish independence could
Mark the beginning of the end of
the U.K. As we know it.
But in the end, 55% of Scotts
voted to stay in the union.
That left almost half the
population still hungry for
independence and with 17.5% of
teenagers voting yes, England
had its undies in a bunch over
the possibility of an
unraveling Scotland.
Glasgow is a gutsy city.
Different outlook.
New generation, but I still here
the cries of yesterday.
Why does the possibility of
independence have such a
powerful hold on Glasgow?
The past.
Glasgow has along endured among
other things a reputation for
being the most violent
area in the U.K.
It's a familiar cycle, amal gos
in many ways to what
we see elsewhere.
Hard times, unemployment, a
general sense of apathy that the
government can't or won't fix
what's broken, that in the
corridors of power of London,
they just don't give a
shit about Glasgow.
Especially Glasgow's east side.
Like most cities,
Glasgow is divided.
The river divides the north and
south sides, but the bigger more
tangible divide is
between east and west.
The west, things are
expected to be, well, nice.
Nice cars, nice families, all
the nice stuff that affluence
supposedly brings.
East side, that's where you grow
up hard, where things are
rougher, where you've got,
according to popular legend, to
fight to live every day.
In Scotland, if you're a
young boy in Scotland and you're
9 or 10 and you're coming home
from school a big guy beats you
up and you run home crying,
you know what she'll do?
She'll give you a cuddle and
then she'll tell you get
back there and get him.
Don't let anybody
ever do that to you.
That's what we do.
And it makes us dangerous
enemies, resourceful enemies,
but it also makes us
very loyal allies.
Detective John Karnish 38
years on the job, much of it is
murder police on the east side.
He's seen it all.
Confronted with violent
hooliganism, the traditional
approach has been to get out
there, bust some heads,
lock up some perpetrators.
But after decades of dealing
with generation after generation
of violence, he took a
controversial new tactic.
Along with a colleague, he
established a new unit called
the violence reduction effort
and focused their efforts on the
social problems he felt led
directly to violent crime.
As of 2014, Scotland is at a 40
year low of violent crime.
When in town, though,
he likes to come here.
Typical Scottish
fare, mother India.
For a curry served in spicy
gravy served with traditional
non-Scottish bread.
I know Glasgow is a
traditionally tough town.
I've always seen it as a
warm and welcoming place.
Do you think the town's
reputation is deserved or is
this a... nope.
I mean in terms of labeling the
violence, the fights
are the fights.
But statistically, if you don't
live or come from Glasgow, your
chances of being a victim of a
violent attack in Glasgow
is something like .000.
I've done a fair amount of
stupid behavior here, a fair
amount of drinking, a fair
amount of putting myself in the
sort of situations they advise
visitors to a new
town not to take.
I've never felt
uncomfortable here.
I could be wrong in that after a
few drinks I notice that I
don't understand anyone.
They could be making various
threats of violence to me at the
bar, and I could just
be smiling and nodding.
Indian food is, of course,
huge here as it is
everywhere in the U.K.
You could venture to guess that
the cold, damp weather causes
the heart to yearn for
food from spicy climates.
That whole takeover India thing.
All I can say is pass this.
So how do you reduce violence?
I mean traditionally we
would just get more police.
Crack some skulls
and problem solved.
A good number of Americans
probably still believe
that very much.
We're very fond of
throwing people in prison.
To suggest otherwise would be
seen as coddling criminals.
Absolutely, and it
was the same here.
We started to think about
it entirely different ways.
Violence is a public
health issue.
We all have the
capacity for violence.
People at home learn
not to be violent.
Things that happen then will
effect their whole life course
about how they make decisions
about themselves and
how they judge risk.
No matter how good the police
service is, it will just contain
and manage the problem.
It won't make it better.
First of all, it's not what I
expect to hear from somebody who
spent 30 years with murder
police, busting heads with
people, that we should hug
these bastards more...
Yes, absolutely.
Everything you've said...
This is going to take a
generation.
They go, oh, politicians
don't have a generation.
They're worried about the
newscast on Monday at 6:00.
The headlines, absolutely.
We don't have it sorted here,
but we're on a journey.
So what's going right here?
This is one of the most
awesome cities anywhere.
People.
I say shit we can't
keep doing this.
Let's try something different.
Look, I don't want to give
you the impression that
Glasgow is an impoverished
wasteland filled
with violence and
hooligans.
Let's face it.
Detroit or New Orleans, most
American cities make this
town look like club med by
comparison.
Glasgow remains the
region's noble shit zone.
What I find most endearing in
this town is if you're a native,
you're probably an
expert at taking a piss.
Well, it's good to be
back at work again.
No one excels more at
deflating the pompous, making
fun of self-importance, turning
even the darkest tragedy
into comedy than them.
That is, if you can
understand the bastards.
This can be a challenge after a
couple of pints of heavy.
Glasgow has a reputation of
being a hard drinking, two
fisted town.
Yeah.
I've always found it to
be this very funny town.
Very dark humor.
If you say in America,
my father died.
People are immediately
sympathetic.
If you say it here, they say
what size was his shoes.
We have that.
Jamie Godley grew up on the
east end, married into an
organized crime dynasty, worked
as a bartender, became a very
famous playwright, author,
and stand-up comedian.
I thought I'd meet her here at a
very old-school institution.
She's working some goat
cheese thing with figs.
For me, Scottish oysters are
an irresistible impulse.
They are magnificent,
by the way.
What a lot of people abroad
don't understand is wine is the
backbone of the industry.
That still exists, Tony.
The age expectancy is still 55.
In Iraq, it is still 65.
Wow, that's still an
extraordinary thing.
Yeah, I know.
I think the fact that we are a
bit shit helps us because we
have the commonwealth games here
and I loved that everybody tried
not to shout in the street and
swear and sell stolen
goods in public.
I loved the operation of
let's be nice for a week.
I loved that.
Main course, Jamie goes
for the pan-fried grill.
I can't pass up the fabulously
loved dish, lobster
thermostat.
It is Scottish, as is the
cheese, eggs, everything really.
Do you have anything
to say on the diet?
The diet, it's
really interesting.
The healthwise as far as
heart problems right behind
Tonga.
When I was a kid, we ate fish,
butter beans, potatoes.
Then we would have liver and
onions and potatoes
and cabbage and peas.
Somewhere from the mid 70s
onwards, it just became crap.
Now you have a generation of
women who don't know how
to make a pot of soup.
To be a real housewife, you have
to be able to make
a pot of soup.
I can't make soup.
The joke is I'm
apparently good at sex.
Sex takes five minutes.
Soup takes five days.
My husband has never
asked for soup.
There's a terrific music
scene in Glasgow.
The pubs are among
the finest anywhere.
They say they have more fun at a
funeral than people in Eden
borough have at a wedding.
That does invite, from time to
time, a fair amount of
knuckle-headed behaviors.
If you're looking for a beer and
a beating, Glasgow will have it.
The toughness thing is no joke.
If you ever try to choke a small
one into unconsciousness, as I
have, long story, it is like
wrestling with an
angry fire plug.
Also it hurts.
Access to guns is
extremely difficult here.
The old country way.
One person at a time.
A stabbing might not get more
than a few lines down in a
column in the Glasgow papers,
because in this city, ordinary
stabbing is hardly news anymore.
Where violence is an affliction,
there must be a cure.
He began his career working as a
bouncer in some of the east
side's toughest drinking
establishments where he had
plenty of opportunities
to hone his skill.
Now he runs tactical edge.
Come at him with a knife, the
overwhelming likelihood is that
it will soon be hanging
out of your ass.
Generally these courses start
come at me with a knife and a
guy comes at you like
it is Friday 13th.
Nobody outside "Friday 13th" has
ever come at anybody like this.
If somebody does come, they're
rushing at you with multiple...
In a manic, frenzy of
slashing movements.
Yeah.
You tend to get these
repeated lines of attack.
If they're going for the
stomach, it is a sewing
machine kind of action.
Is your first order of
business deflecting or getting
the knife from them?
I'm going to either gain
control of the weapon or go to a
returning blade technique.
Right.
Show me.
Okay.
The thing about knife defense is
there's no magic bullet.
Any technique can fail.
Any technique can go wrong.
If there's multiple opponents,
that can get difficult as well.
Here, this sort of thing, yeah?
If we've got the knife held up
close, okay, yeah, pull hit.
Now I'm going to force this
thing back into your sternum
repeatedly like I'm a
woodpecker.
Put your hands up, brute
force, forth, charge.
That's it.
Charge.
So ATM mugging, I'm going to pin
your hand to me so I own the
weapon and I'm going to slap
backwards into the groin.
I'm going to hit, come up, grab.
Now I'm going to introduce
point a with point B.
You're going to want to let go,
so bang, bang, bang, bang.
This is a little bit more
close and sort of vicious.
Everybody doesn't see it.
I've cleared the weapon.
Shift yourself, knee him in
the balls, straight under.
That was an education.
No problem.
I enjoyed that.
Last night in Glasgow I had
enough with the deeper issues.
Now I want to go no deeper than
the bottom of a bubbling
calduron of haggis.
A happy place from my past where
once I frolicked young and
carefree in the field
of fried arts.
The university cafe where I
learned at the foot of the
masters the Dao of hot
fat and crispy batter.
Yes, they do a deep-fried Mars
bar and deep-fried pizza.
Been there, done that.
They've been keeping the
tradition alive since 1918 and
it ain't about no Mars bar.
> I'm tempted to go completely
nuts for all the things I like,
like pies, beans, and chips.
Cheese beano, I don't know what
that is, but I kind of want it.
Ooh, sausage roll.
I do like a good sausage.
I order the fish and
chips and some haggis.
Haddock battered and floating, a
drift in a sea of life-giving
oil as it Bobs like Noah's
ark bringing life in all its
infinite variety.
In tube form in this case.
If you don't like chopped up
liver and lungs and all
that stuff, believe me.
The curry sauce sets you right.
Guy Fieri in a kilt,
but what the hey.
I'm pretty sure god
is against this.
Oh, yeah, definitely.
That's good.
Doesn't eat well with a fork.
You really have to pick this up.
So ashamed.
Oh, yeah.
Clean living.
That's really one of
life's great pleasures.
Don't let them tell
you otherwise.
They're lying about you, Mr.
Haggis.
There was no other reviled
food on earth than haggis.
It's ingredients are no
more unusual or bizarre or
unappetizing than any
hot dog you ever ate.
How many anal glands are
in a chicken nugget?
I don't know and I'm not
suggesting there are anal glands
in a chicken nugget, but would
you be surprised if there were?
Back to you, wolf.
Heading north out of
Glasgow, Scotland quickly
becomes something else.
A savagely beautiful harsh, but
absolutely mesmerizing landscape
that seems to have changed not
at all for thousands,
even millions of years.
And across loch Marie and only
accessible by boat, one of the
great isolated
estates, letter U.
It's the favorite retreat
of my friend, Adrian Gill.
More widely known as a Gill.
He's the much feared and widely
followed restaurant critic for
the "London Sunday times,"
author, traveler, and one of the
finest essayists of our time.
Letter U. As it stands today was
built as a shooting lodge.
Deer stalking like they do here
is something from another era,
but it persists in places like
this which both protect and
cull deer populations.
If you are, like us, of course,
two murderous aristocrats
looking to put venison on the
table, you need help,
professional help.
Stephen Miller has been working
here for eight seasons now, both
protecting the animals who live
on it and helping people like us
in the arduous and delicate task
of sneaking up on them.
We would as gentlemen of leisure
require a cook and Adrian has
recommended a well-suited woman
who excels at this
Scottish game cookery.
For dinner, it's grouse.
Shot, then hung until the
already funky game bird gets
pleasingly ripe.
The birds are rubbed inside and
out with salt and pepper, some
fresh thyme jammed
in the cavity.
Bread sauce is a must.
We don't do this in America,
but here it's essential.
Basically it's milk simmered
with flavoring agent like nutmeg
and bay leaf and then thickened
with raspings of bread.
Grouse barded with bacon,
then roasted in the oven.
They are moved to rest.
Game stock is added and the
sauce reduced, topped with water
cross along side with
parsnips and beet root.
So explain what we're eating,
because this is as
classic as it gets?
This is specifically Scottish.
This is a grouse, which is the
only truly wild game
bird in Britain.
They're the most highly
prized as a sporting bird.
They're the most difficult to
shoot, but more importantly
they're the most prized to eat.
This bread sauce
thing, what is that?
Bread sauce, you have to
grow up here to love this.
It is like pottage.
It's soft.
It's a very old dish, but it
goes very well... grouse,
they're a very gamey meat.
It's a very grown-up taste that
is slightly repellant, but
within that, it is
particularly Al alluring.
Right.
There is something also
sexual about it that people
don't often talk about.
Right, right.
So good.
I'm going to a
vegetarian school.
My parents sent me to a
vegetarian boarding school, and
for nine years, the year after I
left, I was a vegetarian.
Nine years as a vegetarian,
that's unthinkable to me.
Then I decided not to be.
I made the decision if I was
going to eat meat again, then I
had to be prepared to
do the whole business.
Right.
You've got to be accountable.
For all of it.
So I started with the fish and
getting the guts and gutting it.
You want to eat it?
Come and kill it.
You go, well, then I
have to do that as well.
When I started doing it,
it was like coming home.
And that's the thing
with being on the hill.
Until the 19th century, the
Scottish highlands were seen by
many as a mysterious, hostile,
and dangerous land, populated
when populated at all by scary
ass barbarians, tribes so
ferocious, so extravagant in
their violence and toughness
that even in the Roman legions
decided not to mess with them,
hoping to keep them out of the
way of civilized society.
Later hunting estates like this
were home to farmers who
scrounged a living by growing
potatoes.
The highland clans
later by newer money.
Today around half the land in
Scotland is owned by
fewer than 500 people.
It's seductive as well.
Who wouldn't do this,
if they could?
Enjoy this kind of rugged
solitude from a warm,
inviting 17th century lodge.
Play a little snooker, enjoy
a single malt or two, the
substantial game meal, maybe
another whiskey perhaps,
contemplate the mysteries of the
universe under the sky and then
to sleep in the arms of
Morpheus, then to rise in the
morning as bringer of death.
Stephen and Adrian keep calling
it the hill, but that ain't
no hill I've ever seen.
It's a behemoth, an endless
range of behemoths, one mountain
way giving away to a moor, then
another, then
another, then more.
It's a daunting hike.
The climb gradual, then steep.
The footing ranging from
rocky to spongy and wet.
Mile after mile.
Me trying to look cool, make it
seem like this is nothing
unusual, but really I'm dying.
We walked the
highlands for hours.
Our stalker Stephen finally
identifies a red stag of
suitable age and size, one ready
in parlance to be
taken off the hill.
Getting in a range without
scaring them off, however,
is another challenge.
We need to circle around the
mountain to close the distance.
There's not a lot I can do.
So we go slowly.
Just pretend we're
hikers at the moment.
Bobble hat.
What?
If you put a bobble hat on,
the deer think you're a hiker.
Can you see the antlers?
Yeah.
Get down.
Stay down, stay down.
Dig in nice and steady.
Take your time.
That's a nice stag.
Ten points.
Is that good?
He was never going
to get any better.
Do you want to use your knife?
♪
For shooting your first
red stag in Scotland.
You'll get blooded.
Oh.
Best if you close your eyes.
Ah.
Oh, okay.
And the rule is you
have to leave it on.
Yeah.
All day.
♪
You going, chaps?
As getting vehicles up here
would be both physical and
destructive they use highland
ponies to retrieve
the stalked deer.
They are bred to be strong
and trained to do this work.
They will likely make it
back sooner than we will.
Thanks, chaps.
We'll catch you
around at some point.
See ya.
Good boys through.
I thought coming up my legs
burning, I can't wait until that
nice easy downhill walk back,
but as I soon find out, the
walk down is even harder.
Knees screaming, face crusted
with dry blood, I'm looking
forward to a warm fire, a strong
whiskey and spot good
country ass cooking.
So venison stew with wine?
They always marinate
Juniper and all of that.
Super simple.
Okay.
We'll do that.
♪
The venison is seasoned with
salt and pepper and Rosemary
seared in duck fat and
then into the oven.
A pan sauce made from the Fawn,
red wine and deep game stock,
sweetened with currentant jelly
and finishing with a nod of
whole butter and served with
clap shot, basically mashed turnips and potatoes.
That's it.
That's the end of the season.
Hugely the girls will be killing
it, and you start
killing the girls.
Have you traditionally where
there's the leather mask to the
stag and you... and you send
them notes beforehand
saying I'm watching you.
I know where you live.
We deserve this.
We've worked for it, huh?
Yeah.
Literally the greatest feat
of strength in my entire life.
Never in my entire life have I
done anything so remotely
physical over a sustained
period of time.
Really?
Never.
Look how well.
At no point previously in my
life would I have
been able to do it.
Thank you, guys.
Here's to the best
of health, folks.
All the best.
Good shot.
I say to a place for ramblers.
A lot safer now that
we're not on our land.
I came to Scotland this time
to shoot an animal in the heart,
to take part, to be fully
culpable in a practice nearly
as old as these hills.
You walk this country stalking
an animal across the rocks and
wet Heather, you feel little has
changed from how your distant
ancestors must have searched for
their food with a rifle,
with a spear, with a club.
I drag my knuckles up a hill and
like my ape-like predecessors
return tired, happy
and covered in blood.
Everything changes.
Nothing changes at all.