In Bahia, you find yourself
in the heart of the heart of
Brazil, where the
magic comes from.
If you want to get there, just
follow the sound of the drums.
This is Salvadore de Bahia, city
of three million people.
First capital of Brazil.
The wellspring for everything
African and spicy, where things
seem to just sway and
move constantly.
It's a place where everybody is
sexy, where even the
ugly people are hot.
Unsurprisingly, this is
where artists come from.
African spiritualism, cult
magic, ondomble and caipirinhas.
Did I mention caipirinhas?
They do those here, too.
I like them.
I like them a lot.
What's magical about this
cocktail is the first taste,
it's like I don't know, man,
it's a little too something.
Then like that second sip, it's
like oh, that's kind of good.
Then the third sip, it's
where are my pants.
Fortunately, food in these parts
tends to be, shall
we say, hearty.
For instance, a delightful meal
of fried meat with plenty of
absorbent starch product
like baropha, the perfect
accompaniment to many,
many caipirinhas.
Excellent.
Now we're talking.
Tough town for vegetarians.
Oh, good.
I'll have six more
of these, please.
People are staring at me.
Look at the American,
how much he's eating.
Line them up, my friend.
Oh, yeah.
So nice walking around here.
It's really amazing.
There are always
drums somewhere.
♪
Welcome, my friend.
Good to be here again.
Oh, yeah?
Love it here.
Please.
Welcome to Salvadore.
Thank you.
This is Claudio and Maurelia.
It's good to have friends
in a place like Salvador.
In fact, you're pretty
much lost without them.
Tuesday night.
Yeah, man.
Tuesday nights are
very impressive.
Many people come to church
first, then they go drinking
around.
You have to work
tomorrow, right?
I guess that's Brazil, right?
Yes, Brazil, but you have
this kind of behavior
here, not in whole city.
How different is Salvador
from Rio and Sao Paolo?
This area is amazing.
It is.
Amazing.
Eat, drink, history,
memory, anything.
Pellorinio, pello for short,
was Salvadore during the
Portuguese period.
It's always a party, a series of
parties, actually, but
tonight is special.
♪
Look at this, man.
Smells good.
Yes.
Oh, that's good.
Isn't that good?
Where to next?
Go to [ Inaudible ].
I like to bring you because
coming here, people
everywhere, it's free party.
You can dance, you can
drink everywhere.
It's amazing.
♪
What is it?
It's caramio, mix
of honey and limon.
Alcohol?
Yes.
Alcohol of unknown original
in dispensed from atop
the head of a stranger?
It's good.
Mama always said that
was a good idea.
I don't know if it's the booze
or the music or the tropical
heat, but after awhile bouncing
from place to place, wandering
down old cobblestone streets,
different music issuing from
everywhere, a different party,
people flowing out of buildings,
one gathering, comingling with
another, the music mixing, it
really does seem that everybody
is moving to some mysterious
unknowable pulse, some unheard
throb that moves people to
constantly touch each other,
stroke hips, necks, limbs.
♪
It is useful to know that
of over 12 million Africans
dragged, ripped and kidnapped
from their homelands, nearly
five million ended up in Brazil.
1.5 million of them
in Bahia alone.
Pellorinio became the locus
of a vast infrastructure of
plantations and the slave
trade that powered them.
Making this city in northeastern
Brazil the most opulent
in the new world.
Pellorinio, it's worth pointing
out, gets its name from
the whipping post.
A hundred years after slavery
was outlawed in Brazil,
pellorinio had been forgotten
but of course, the
neighborhood had its charms.
If you were an artist, a
musician, a writer, you could
afford to live here.
Cheap rent for long-time locals
or shiny new art galleries at
hipster cafes, we know which way
the current of history runs.
♪
Here, though, one
man stands alone.
A poet, sculptor, painter,
musician, now perhaps his own
greatest artistic creation.
He has chosen to hide his face
from view and to stand in
opposition, an eyesore, a
rebuke, a defy ant gwar-like
embarrassment to the occupiers.
As he dresses now, this is
for protection but as I
understand, also protest.
It's a kind of protest
but also protection.
You know?
Who's the enemy?
Everyone.
You see face, you see heart.
How long have you been
wearing the armor?
How long?
46 years.
That was a long time ago.
You ever been on the beach?
No, sir.
Only shadow.
Goth, dude.
Whiskey.
It's about not sun.
No sun.
Not water, not sun.
Just down from where we're
sitting, Gymez pellorinio
studio.
His water and power have been
shut off but he insists
he's going nowhere.
Brazil is supposed to be about
what, music, dancing,
sun, hot women.
Does he reject those things?
Does he think that's bull?
I am the wrong country.
Where would the
perfect place be?
Rock city.
That's Detroit.
Detroit.
Detroit, rock city.
What music inspires him?
Iron maiden.
I think they're
touring, actually.
Nirvana.
Metallica?
Beethoven.
What do you think of this?
Anybody who comes here
recognizes immediately that this
is a really uniquely
extraordinary and despite many
problems, a uniquely
wonderful, magical place.
It's a magical place but also
for us, for me and for him, here
is a place where many
people have suffered.
There is still one kind of Karma
of this old history
here, you know?
So what is the real pellorinio?
We are.
I don't like pina coladas
but I like walking in the rain.
I like wandering through markets
as much as the next guy, but
what I really like
are neuro toxins.
In Japan, they call it fugu.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, it's eyes,
ovaries and internal organs are
packed with varying amounts of
toxins and some people will tell
you the toxin present in the
blowfish is 1200 times more
potent than cyanide and they
will tell you how if it's
consumed, you remain conscious
while your muscles gradually
become paralyzed and death, like
a slow-moving freight train,
moves closer and closer.
And whatever you do, just make
sure you cut out that liver.
I say bull... So we're
eating blowfish.
Yes.
It's an adventure.
Like the Japanese,
they like the poisons?
No I know, I know, yeah.
They remove the
liver and the skin?
Supposed to be removed properly.
Properly, right.
I saw a "Simpsons"
episode, I think.
This guy make it great.
Poisonous blowfish
will take a recipe.
Add coriander, coconut
milk, cover and simmer.
I am confident in this
cook I don't know.
And in this man, my host and
aficionado of this dish.
Smelling good.
Bon appetit.
Thank you.
This is a lot of pepper, huh?
Oh, yeah.
Good pepper.
Nice and spicy.
I can't feel my legs.
Is that a bad thing?
Bel is an artist, after all.
A very famous one.
So he knows about neurotoxins.
He comes from a long tradition
of artists who have found
inspiration in Bahia.
Is there something about
Salvador you think that's
conducive to an
artistic sensibility?
There is so much color
here and music.
The light here is beautiful.
The light is really special.
Just the colors of the
city are amazing.
The colors of the people are
amazing, and the way they move.
They move.
I don't know, when I first
came here, I thought everybody
in this city looks like they
just got or they're on their
way to go...
So this was the central
market back before supermarkets,
this is where everybody did
their shopping, right?
Oh, yes.
This is the real Brazil here.
The real Bahia.
Right.
This place is fantastic.
They sell oil and stuff,
this kind of oil, palm oil.
Oh, yeah.
Whoever you want to call it.
I love the dende oil.
It takes some getting used to.
The first time I was here, you
eat it, you... like a mink
for hours afterwards.
Now, no problems.
I've been eating this all week.
Love it.
You spend time in Brazil
you develop resistance.
There you go.
Hope you like spicy.
He's a Brazilian guy.
He's got to like spicy.
A little cachaca.
Oh, yes.
That will set you right.
That will protect you
from the poison.
We're coming up to the world
cup and I know a lot of people
will be reading about
crime and all that.
How do you think it's going
to go, the world cup?
Disaster or it's going
to somehow work out?
I think it will be a success.
You think it will be a success.
I'm sure of it.
Salvador is one of the host
cities for the 2014 world cup.
A huge stadium has recently been
completed, but a lot of people
are worried, concerned,
if Brazil is ready.
I have been told thousands
of prostitutes are studying
tourist-appropriate languages in
preparation, so probably a lot
of people are going to get laid,
a lot of people are going to get
robbed, a lot of people are
going to get laid and robbed.
Have you ever been
here in carnival?
No.
The world cup is that carnival.
That works out, right?
That's not a slaughterfest.
It's a breakfast.
Right.
Things happen but it works.
Salvador in particular is
a place where... may I?
Thank you.
No matter what,
people should come.
Even people who are afraid to
travel, who say oh,
well, but I hear.
No, you know what,
live your life, man.
You should not miss a place like
this, because there aren't a lot
of places in the world that
even come close to this.
Where we are today, I invited
you to have this dish.
We are not born to die.
I'm pretty sure Mr. Muffin
stuff over here is suddenly
going to jump on me,
start clawing my face.
The poison was
active, she's dead.
I didn't think of that.
We call you canary.
We are not born for dying.
No.
The bay of all saints, a
vast natural harbor allowed
Salvador to prosper.
Tucked along its shore, if you
look hard enough, you'll find a
small grouping of shacks
roofed in corrugated tin.
This is where a local
fishermen's association brings
their catch to sell to
wholesalers, then relax after a
long day on the water.
Catch of the day, the
prized big red snapper.
Rub with sea salt, lemon, olive
oil, grill over charcoal.
Enjoy view.
So everybody here is fishermen?
Meet Maloca, a very special guy.
He's been working as our head of
security and as for reasons that
are immediately obvious, he
enjoys respect and
reputation on the streets.
But he also comes out of this
neighborhood and these
guys are his friends.
How's business now?
Lot of fish out there?
Fishing business good?
Lunch wouldn't be complete
without a delicious spicy salsa
of garlic, tomato,
onions and peppers.
On the side, some deep
fried little smelts.
Don't forget the beer and
the cachaca and enjoy.
That will work.
Looks like a big grouper.
It's a big redfish.
I have to advise you
that... it's spicy.
What do they drink,
beer or cachaca?
Both.
Still working?
He work more than all of us.
They use a line or net?
A line.
My secret is just the hand
around a piece of wood like
that and take like that.
They don't cut the hands?
Always cut the hands.
Fishing anywhere is hard and
the way these guys do it,
particularly hard.
Mostly hand lines
from small boats.
Just look at these hands.
You're a hard man.
Literally.
♪
Yeah, that's what I
want, right here.
Oh, yeah.
Jackpot.
That's, you'll pardon the
expression, some good head.
The fisherman loves the head.
It's awesome.
It's the best part.
Looking good.
Good piece of fish.
Beautiful.
In Rio if you're anything
less than perfectly cut, you
feel terrible going
to the beach.
You never want to
go to the beach.
Here, you can frolic in a speedo
and feel pretty
good about myself.
Let it all hang out here.
Caipirinha?
Ah, the caipirinha man.
This indispensable icon of
Brazilian beach culture is known
to start with fresh lime, muddle
and mash with more lime
juice, sugar, ice.
The magic ingredient, cachaca.
That's basically the distilled
liquor of the sugar cane.
Shaken, not stirred, and you've
got yourself one of the world's
truly great cocktails.
The utility beverage good for
any time of day or
any social occasion.
Very satisfying.
♪
Toasted cheese things
here, awesome.
If there's anything better than
cheese, it's semi-melted cheese.
What's the best part
of French onion soup?
The little bits of burned
cheese around the edge.
Oh, yeah.
Just as good as it looks.
♪
Look at this line.
These guys are famous.
I've had it before.
I have had it here, in fact.
These ladies make it good.
Really good.
The clothes go back to the newly
freed slaves who now were able
to practice their religion and
began selling the acaraje
to support the community.
What is acaraje?
Behold.
A paste, a batter, a filafel
like wad with peas, seasoned
with shrimp and onions, deep
fried to crispy and
golden in dende oil.
Already if you're a rookie
you're guaranteed some quality
time on the porcelain
bus real soon.
On the top, you got sort
of a shrimp curry paste.
And your tomato, your
fried shrimp, a must.
All right.
Beautiful.
Don't forget the hot chili
oil and prepare for liftoff.
Really good.
When millions of Africans
were taken by force to Brazil,
the traditions, the musical
roots they had, instruments they
played, their gods and
their food came with them.
In the days of slavery, you
would hide that stuff, whether
it was your religion or
your self-defense skills.
So tell me about kapuara.
It was a kind of martial art
but in the beginning of the
century, it became more like a
game and the music
instruments were associated.
No hats, right?
Why no hands?
We use the hands in
just a few movements.
Where did that come from and
why do you think that became...
Some people say that this
is inspired by the animal
movements.
In a recent study observing
the comparative destructive
power between kicks from various
martial arts, of karate, muy
Thai and tie Kwan Doe, capuara
packed the most
ferocious impact.
The leaders knew this and made
it illegal for much
of Brazil's history.
Today, it's taught in
classrooms and on stages.
Originally it was a
male-dominated activity.
When did that change?
Since the '60s.
We start in the beginning of the
'80s and nowadays, we have
hundreds of women practice.
What was it like in the
beginning, the very first women
who did it?
Mothers or fathers or
the family... right.
Sad that capuara is not for
women, why do you
decide to do this.
Afro Brazilian cuisine is the
result of many, many years of
cooks experimenting with African
and Portuguese dishes combined
with local ingredients like
seafood, chilies, coconut milk.
This is Angelica's house.
Open one day a week as a
restaurant serving her unique
style of bahian dishes.
Beautiful.
Wow.
Look at that.
Looks very good.
How has being a master of
capuara, how has that changed
the rest of your life?
I think changed it a lot.
Women in general, they
don't learn to fight.
Learning how to be involved in
real fights, game and fight at
the same time, we became more
prepared to be involved in
symbolic fight and in our
society, the women, they are not
so well prepared like men.
It was purely African in the
beginning, and now it's
Afro-Brazilian form,
is that correct?
All the instruments are
African instruments.
Right.
They're singing.
A lot of singing,
and it's important.
Yeah.
In Portuguese, but we in
capuara, we start to include
music from multi-cultural
African cultural traditions
including lyrics in
African language.
All the things that we look
at as Brazilian from outside
looking in, the cuisine, samba,
all of these things are
very African in origin.
This is kind of where
that all started, yes?
I mean, I don't want to
say it's the real Brazil.
Everyone looks at Rio as the
postcard Brazil, but here
it's really, you feel it.
Those things.
It has to do with this big
concentration of Africans
since the beginning.
It's different.
If you, say, found yourself
in Brazil and had a chance to
hire a boat, head for the beach
with a bunch of new friends,
bring along a skilled
mixologist, expertly trained in
the arts of drink making,
why wouldn't you?
Charge across the water, headed
for a nice, quiet island.
Order up some sun to come out
from some dark clouds
right about now.
Sometimes cliches are
cliches for a reason.
Because they're good ideas to
start with, which is why people
keep looking for them and
doing them over and over.
In a perfect world upon
reaching said enchanted island,
you jump into the warm Atlantic
water, and if you could, you
would have a classic soundtrack
to this adventure, like
samba, for instance.
Splash around for a while, maybe
enjoy a nice cold beer or two.
You truly have not taken a
beach until a man has set
up the Caporina station.
Then you know the lz is secure.
I love nature.
Oh what's going on here?
Capoirina.
Please.
Sweet.
This alone is an argument for
the greatness of this country.
And what goes great with
drinks on the beach?
How about some barbecue?
Please, don't eat me.
Look in your heart.
Don't eat me.
Oh, no.
Not my head.
To complete the picture,
make a large fish.
Maybe some crab.
You know, anytime you get your
Chinese, Brazilians and Italians
all agreeing on something, it's
really clear it's a good idea.
Everybody agrees this complic
complicated creature with
troublesome shells
is worth the work.
Tear off the little limbs.
We'll get to you a little
later, my friends.
Rip out the tail.
These are the lungs
you don't want them.
Now you've got all this
nice fat in there.
Oh, yeah.
Now we're getting to the claw.
Look at that.
Let's poke him out of there.
Oh, yeah.
That little melon of goodness.
Like a celestial nibble.
When people started demanding
boneless stuff like chicken
without a bone or crab meat
without the actual crab.
Or lazy lobster.
That was the beginning of the
erosion of our society
as we know it.
If you're not willing to work
for a payoff like this, how do
you expect us to, like, fight Al
qaeda if you can't suck
the meat out of a crab?
Character builder.
And delicious.
And if your perfect day
really did happen, you would
probably let yourself
be swept away.
By liquor and good food and gin
clear water, all all around you,
Brazilians casually fondle each
other, get all dozy
and fall asleep.