>> I ALWAYS FEEL SLIGHTLY
DEPRESSED BY BEAUTIFUL VISTAS,
YOU KNOW I MEAN?
*
>>> AH, THE STORYBOOK KINGDOM OF
GRENADA.
ONE OF THE OLDEST, MOST COMPLEX,
MAGICALLY SURREAL PLACES IN
SPAIN.
AND ONE OF THE MOST BEAUTIFUL.
GRENADA IS TUCKED AGAINST THE
SIERRA NEVADA MOUNTAINS OF
ANDALUCIA IN SOUTHERN SPAIN.
IT'S NOT LIKE BARCELONA.
IT AIN'T MADRID.
ANY REASONABLE PERSON WHO LOOKS
AT SPAIN, COMES TO SPAIN, EATS
IN SPAIN, DRINKS IN SPAIN,
THEY'RE GOING TO FALL IN LOVE.
OTHERWISE, THERE'S SOMETHING
DEEPLY WRONG WITH YOU.
SPAIN IS THE SORT OF PLACE THAT
NEVER REALLY MADE ANY SENSE
ANYWAY.
BUT IN THE VERY BEST POSSIBLE
WAY.
THIS IS THE COUNTRY THAT GAVE US
THE SPANISH INQUISITION.
ALSO ANARCHY.
THIS IS WHERE DEVOUT CATHOLICISM
MIXES WITH SURREALISM, MODERNIST
CUISINE.
CHRISTIANITY AND ISLAM SPARED
SPACE.
THE EFFECTS OF INFLUENCES OF ALL
THOSE THINGS ARE RIGHT HERE TO
SEE.
YOU CAN ALMOST LOOK BACK THROUGH
TIME AND SEE THE VENETIANS
MARCHING UP.
OR ARE THOSE FERAL HIPPIES?
MANY OF THEM MADE THINGS
INTERESTING.
WHEREVER YOU ARE ON THE
IDEOLOGICAL SPECTRUM, SOME
THINGS ARE CONSTANT, IT SEEMS.
SOME STEREOTYPICAL EXPECTATIONS.
IT'S TRUE, THERE ARE FREE TAPAS
EVERYWHERE.
FLAMEN
FLAMENCO, YES, THEY DO THAT
ALSO.
BUT IN GRANADA, THEY DO IT OLD
SCHOOL.
AND OH YEAH, BULLFIGHTING.
THEY DO THAT HERE, TOO.
BUT I DIGRESS.
I'M HERE TO ANSWER A QUESTION.
WHAT HAPPENS IF YOU GO OVER TO
THE OTHER SIDE?
SAY YOU GREW UP IN THE STATES
AND WONDERED, FANTASIZED ABOUT
WHAT IT WOULD BE LIKE LIVING
ABROAD IN OLD EUROPE, SURROUNDED
BY CRUSADER CASTLES, DELICIOUS
FOOD, ANOTHER LANGUAGE, ANOTHER
CULTURE?
WHAT WOULD THAT ALTERNATE LIFE,
THAT ROAD NOT TAKEN BE LIKE?
MY LONGTIME FRIEND AND CAMERAMAN
FROM MAINE ZACK IS FINDING OUT.
SO WHERE ARE WE GOING?
>> RIGHT HERE, ONE OF THESE
TABLES.
MAYBE WE WANT TO DO THIS WITH.
SEE?
HOW OFTEN CAN YOU GO OUT WITH
SOMEBODY WHO CAN APPROPRIATELY
BLOCK THE TABLE?
>> AY, YES, OF COURSE.
SNAILS IN AN ALMOND SAUCE.
ABOUT AS TRADITIONAL AND
DELICIOUS AS IT GETS.
TAPAS COME FROM HERE.
THIS IS STILL ONE OF THE FEW
PLACES IN SPAIN WHERE THEY'RE
FREE.
ALL YOU HAVE TO DO IS KEEP
DRINKING.
>> YOU CAN SIT HERE ALL DAY.
ORDER A COUPLE DRINKS.
>> NO RUSH.
I'M GLAD I'M SPENDING SOME TIME
HERE.
RED WINE ORDERED.
TRIPE TO FOLLOW.
SPENDER, SPICY, DELICIOUS TRIPE.
>> GUTS.
PRETTY GOOD.
>> HELLO.
HELLO.
>> NOT TOO LONG AGO, BEFORE ZACK
BASICALLY DEFECTED TO SPAIN, HE
MET FUEN.
THE NEXT THING YOU KNOW, HE'S
LIVING HERE.
PART OF AN EXTENDED ANDALUCIAN
FAMILY.
LIVING THE LIFE OF THE SPANISH
DANDY.
IN FREAKING GRANADA, NO LESS.
>> CLASSICALLY, CULTURALLY
SPEAKING, DO YOU WANT A
SENSITIVE, NICE, CARING
THOUGHTFUL GUY?
>> WELL, IT DEPENDS ON THE
WOMAN, FIRST.
BUT USUALLY WE LOOK FOR THIS
KIND OF PERSON THAT WE KNOW HE
WILL PROTECT US.
>> FROM WHAT?
FERAL HIPPIES?
>> I WOULD LIKE TO DO THE VOWS
OF YOUR WEDDING.
DO YOU SWEAR TO PROTECT FUEN
SANCHEZ ATTACKS BY CAVE-DWELLING
HIPPIES?
WHO ATTEMPT TO SELL HER JEWELRY
OR OTHER THINGS OF LITTLE VALUE.
>> I FIGURE NOW THAT ZACK IS
MARRYING INTO A SPANISH FAMILY,
I CAN PIGGY BACK ALONG, SUCK OF
THE LURE OF THE MAGIC, LIVE ON
WHAT HAS BEEN MY DREAM, TOO.
>> IF WE CAN GET WEIRD FOR A
SECOND HERE, MAN.
SOME PLACES, DO THEY HAVE AN
ENERGY, MAN, ABOUT THEM?
>> WHAT ARE YOU SAYING?
>> YOU KNOW, I DON'T WANT TO GET
INTO METAPHYSICS.
>> YOU ARE GOING TO END UP
LIVING IN A CAVE IF YOU KEEP
TALKING LIKE THIS.
MORE WINE.
TO SEE SPAIN, TO SEE IT
STRAIGHT, TO UNDERSTAND IT AT
ALL, YOU SHOULD PROBABLY PEEK,
IF ONLY THROUGH SPREAD FINGERS,
AT THAT MOST SPANISH OF
TRADITIONS.
BULLFIGHTING.
MEET ALFANDI, ONE OF SPAIN'S
MOST DASHING AND RESPECTED
BULLFIGHTERS.
HE'S INVITED ME TO A RANCH, A
PRIVATE BULL RING WHERE HE LIKES
TO PRACTICE.
>> SO WHAT YOU'RE GOING TO DO
NOW IS SEE HOW BRAVE --
>> AND IF THE CALF IS NOT BRAVE,
STEW.
>> AND FUEN'S BROTHER ALEJANDRO,
WHO LIKE MANY SPANIARDS,
CONSIDER BULLFIGHTING AN ART.
TODAY A LITTLE PRACTICE FIRST.
DON'T WORRY, THIS GUY IS TOO
YOUNG TO FIGHT.
>> YOU SEE THE RED CAPE, YOU
KNOW THIS IS THE MOST THING.
WHERE THEY MAKE ALL THE ART, ALL
THE POETRY.
>> WHY THE CAPE?
>> BECAUSE IT'S MOVING.
>> SO THAT'S IMPORTANT?
>> YOU DON'T WANT IT TO BE
MOVING AT ALL.
>> THIS GUY CLEARLY HAS SPIRIT.
RIGHT AWAY HE TRIES TO TAKE A
POKE AT ZACK'S FEMORAL ARTERY.
PROMISING.
>> HE'S GOING TO TEACH YOU.
>> NO.
>> SURE.
>> NO ONE LIKES TO LOOK LIKE A
PUSSY ON TV, SO WHEN HE
SUGGESTED I JOIN HIM TO WAVE A
PINK CAPE AT AN AGGRESSIVE YOUNG
BULL, I SAID WHAT ANY IDIOT
WOULD SAY -- SI.
IT ALL STARTS WELL ENOUGH.
HEY, THIS IS FUN.
THIS IS EASY.
UNTIL I GET A HORN HOOKED RIGHT
UP NEXT TO MY NUTSACK.
THEN IT'S NOT SO FUN.
THANKS, GUYS.
THIS YOUNGSTER SHALL LIVE,
PERHAPS TO GORE A FUTURE TV HOST
WITH HIS MIGHTY HORNS.
NOW THIS IS WHAT A REAL BULL
LOOKS LIKE.
THIS IS A WHOLE DIFFERENT THING.
500-FREAKING-KILOS OF AGGRESSIVE
CHARGING KILLDOZER AIMING AT
YOUR MEAT.
IT'S A LOT OF MUSCLE.
>> YEAH, IT'S A LOT OF MUSCLE.
THAT'S A BIG BULL.
*
>> NO MATTER HOW BIG, HOW
STRONG, HOW SCARY, FOR THIS
INTREPID REPORTER WHO'S SEEN
MANY ANIMALS DIE FOR HIS DINNER,
THIS PART IS NEVER EASY.
>> SO AS YOU SEE, HE PUTS THE
CAPE LOWER.
SO WHEN THE BULL BRINGS THE FACE
FORWARD, SHOWING THE NECK --
THAT'S IT.
THAT WAS VERY GOOD.
>> IT'S TIME FOR STU.
BULL STEW.
OUR FRIEND WENT TO A BETTER
PLACE.
LOCAL HERBS, POE TODAY TOES.
NOTHING LIKE A ROARING FIRE,
SPANISH CHEESES, BREAD, AND GOOD
OLIVE OIL TO TAKE THE STING OUT
OF A NEAR GENITAL MUTILATION.
>> IT'S NOT A BAD PLACE.
>> HE STARTED AT AGE 19?
WHEN YOU WERE A LITTLE BOY
GROWING UP, YOU ASPIRED TO BE A
MATADOR.
THE MATADORS WERE THE ORIGINAL
ROCK STARS, THE IDEAL OF
MASCULINITY, MALE BEAUTY, AND
GRACE.
THAT RUNS DEEP.
LIKE IT OR NOT, YOU SHOULD
PROBABLY KNOW THIS BEFORE DATING
A SPANISH GUY.
THERE IS NO DENYING THE TERRIBLE
BEAUTY OF THE VERY COMPLEX
TRADITION.
>> IT'S NOT ABOUT WINNING.
IT'S NOT ABOUT KILLING THE BULL.
AND NOR IS IT ABOUT BEING JUST
SKILLFUL.
YOU HAVE TO LOOK GOOD DOING IT,
TOO.
ARE THERE ANY UGLY ASS
BULLFIGHTERS?
A REALLY OUT OF SHAPE -- A
MUFFIN TOP.
HOW DO YOU CALL A MUFFIN TOP?
>> WE HAVE EVERYTHING.
>> WELL, IT WAS AN EDUCATION
TODAY, AND A GREAT MEAL.
THANK YOU.
>> CHEERS.
>>> HOLY WEEK.
OR SEMANA SANTA AS IT'S CALLED.
OBSERVED ALL OVER SOUTHERN SPAIN
WITH A SERIOUSNESS AND FERVOR
YOU MIGHT NOT SEE ELSEWHERE.
FOR SEVEN DAYS LEADING UP TO
EASTER, NEARLY EVERY CITY IN
ANDALUCIA GETS TAKEN OVER BY
ANCIENT PROCESSIONS.
TO AN OUTSIDER, IT'S AN
IMPENETRABLE MONTAGE OF
CONFUSING, YET DEEPLY EVOCATIVE
IMAGES.
FIGURES IN DARK HOODS LOOM UP
FROM EVERY DIRECTION.
SPOKE POTS OF INSECTS, CANDLES,
RELIGIOUS IMAGERY, AND THE
CROWDS.
FLASHES OF GOYA, DIMLY
REMEMBERED IMPRESSIONS OF THE
INQUISITION.
OKAY, WATCH THIS.
THESE GUYS GOT TO GET THEIR
PAINSTAKINGLY CRAFTED MASSIVELY
SIZED AND INCREDIBLY HEAVY AND
CUMBERSOME FLOAT THROUGH THE
DOOR, DOWN THE STEPS, AND OUT
INTO THE STREET.
PEDRO IS ANOTHER OF FUEN'S
BROTHERS, THE YOUNGEST, AND WHEN
NOT WORKING FOR AN I.T. COMPANY
IN IRELAND, HE DOES THIS.
HE CARRIES CRUSHINGLY HEAVY
RELIGIOUS FLOATS.
THEY'RE CALLED ED CASTELEROS.
THE VIRGIN FLOAT, ABOUT 3,500
POUNDS TOTAL, AND PRECISE
DIMENSIONS THAT HAVE TO MAKE IT
THROUGH DOOR JUST SO.
THE BEARERS HAVE TO KNEEL.
CRAWL ALONG WITH IT ON THEIR
BACKS TO GET IT THROUGH THE
DOOR.
AND THE MAIN EVENT.
READY, SET, UP.
LET'S FACE IT.
I LIKE A PROCESSION AND ALL, BUT
WHO LIKES A BUNCH OF GUYS IN
HOODS COMING IN YOUR GENERAL
DIRECTION?
I DON'T.
FRANKLY, IT FREAKS ME OUT.
TIME FOR A DRINK, PERHAPS.
THIS IS AN EASTERN JESUS AND
MARY-THEMED DRINKING
ESTABLISHMENT, WHERE BETWEEN
DRINKS, ONE CAN PONDER THE AGONY
OF CHRIST, BUT WITH SOME SAUSA
SAUSAGES.
IS IT LIKE THIS ALL YEAR?
>> THE WHOLE YEAR.
YOU HAVE INCENSE ALL YEAR.
EASTERN MUSIC ALL YEAR.
>> IS THIS A WEEK FOR QUIET
CONTEMPLATION AND WORSHIP OR IS
THIS A PARTY WEEK OR BOTH?
>> BOTH OF THEM.
>> THROUGHOUT THE COURSE OF THE
WEEK, OVER 40-ODD PROCESSIONS
WILL CREEP SLOWLY FROM THESE
STREETS.
THERE ARE DIFFERENT
BROTHERHOODS, EACH WITH THEIR
OWN SACRED COLORS, CRESTS,
INSIGNIA AND SO ON.
IT'S THEIR MEDALLIONS OF
PARTICULAR CHRIST IMAGES THAT
ADORN THE BAR.
AND FRANKLY, THEY'RE KIND OF
BUMMING ME OUT.
MAYBE IT'S JUST ME, BUT WHEN I'M
GETTING A NICE LATE MORNING
BUZZ, I DON'T PARTICULARLY WANT
JESUS LOOKING DOWN AT ME FROM,
LIKE, EVERYWHERE.
>> HOW DRUNK CAN YOU GET HERE?
DON'T YOU FEEL A LITTLE GUILTY
FOR GETTING REALLY DRUNK HERE?
>> OF COURSE.
>> THIS IS ONE OF MY FAVORITE
THINGS.
>> TRY IT.
IT'S AMAZING.
>> GAZE AWAY UNAPPROVINGLY ALL
YOU LIKE, JESUS.
I AM HAPPY NOW.
OVERLOOKING GRANADA, THE
HILLSIDE OF SACRAMONTE IS
RIDDLED WITH CAVES, MANY OLDER
THAN ANYONE EVEN REMEMBERS.
SPANISH GYPSIES HAVE LIVED HERE
IN CAVES TURNED HOMES LIKE THIS
FOR HUNDREDS OF YEARS.
*
>> THEY CALL THIS AN JEURGA,
WHAT JAZZ MUSICIANS MIGHT
RECOGNIZE AS A JAM SESSION.
>> GRANADA.
THE ONLY PLACE IN THE WORLD
WHERE YOU GET TO SEE REAL
FLAMENCO IN A CAVE.
>> ALISSIA IS AN AFICIONADO.
OUR HOST IS A POET, HISTORIAN,
AND A PATRIARCH OF THE COMMUNITY
HERE.
AN ICON OF THE FLAMENCO WORLD.
YOU SEE TRAVELERS, ROMA PEOPLE
ARE MORE EMBRACED BY THE CULTURE
HERE THAN MOST OTHER PLACES IN
EUROPE.
>> WE HAVE OUR OWN GYPSIES.
THOSE ARE OURS.
WE CAN TELL YOU THREE THINGS FOR
SURE WE DO HERE.
WE DO FLAMENCO.
WE DO TAPAS.
AND WE DO SIESTAS.
>> YOU DO THEM WELL.
>> WE KNOW HOW TO LIVE, DON'T
WE?
>> YEAH.
*
>> THEY DIG DEEP FOR THEIR
MATERIAL HERE.
IT MEANS SOMETHING.
THEY'RE TELLING YOU SOMETHING
ABOUT THEMSELVES.
>> WHAT IS -- I'VE HEARD IT.
IS IT AN EMOTIONAL STATE OR A
TECHNICAL --
>> NO.
>> IS UNHAPPINESS NECESSARY FOR
GREAT ART?
>> IT'S NECESSARY, BUT
MAGNIFICO.
>> YOU'D HAVE TO THINK ABOUT
THAT.
>> YOU PERFORM VERY WELL AFTER A
COUPLE DAYS.
>> I MAY NOT HAVE ONE DAY,
DUENDE, BUT I HAVE VALENTINE'S.
I KNOW THAT EXPRESSION.
WAIT A MINUTE.
>>> NIGHTTIME IN GRANADA.
IT'S TIME TO PURSUE THAT
GREATEST OF SPANISH TRADITIONS,
TAPAS.
YOU MAY THINK YOU KNOW WHAT A
TAPA IS.
SMALL BITES AT SOME FUSION
HIPSTER BAR.
YEAH, THAT AIN'T A TAPA.
>> HOW OFTEN DO YOU DO THIS?
>> I DO IT FIVE DAYS A WEEK.
BUT, YOU KNOW, IT'S LIKE ON A
WEEKEND, YOU COME OUT FOR A
BUNCH.
WEEKDAY, YOU COME OUT FOR ONE.
>> THIS IS LATANA, A LITTLE
PLACE RUN BY JESUS AND LOUISA,
ONE BARTENDER, ONE COOK, TAKING
CARE OF EVERYTHING.
>> IT'S FREE.
>> SO YOU'RE JUST PAYING FOR THE
WINE.
>> SO IF I'M A WINO, I CAN STILL
EAT WELL.
>> LET US PUT THIS THEORY INTO
PRACTICE.
WITH OUR FIRST ROUND OF DRINKS
COMES THIS.
>> TOMATO WITH BREAD, GARLIC,
AND BLENDED.
>> I COULD PRETTY MUCH EAT THAT
ALL DAY.
THAT'S RIGHT.
TAPAS ARE FREE.
IT SHOULDN'T WORK, BUT SOMEHOW
IT DOES.
ANOTHER DRINK, ANOTHER TAPA.
TOMATO
TOMATOES, OLIVE OIL, BREAD.
>> AWESOME.
IT'S AMAZING.
>> SO ALL I'VE GOT TO DO IS KEEP
DRINKING.
>> MAYBE YOU'D BE INTERESTED IN
CAVIAR.
>> REALLY?
THAT'S NOT INCLUDED?
>> THAT'S NOT THE POINT OF THE
TAPAS.
USUALLY YOU HAVE A FEW TAPAS.
>> THEY'RE JUST HOOKING YOU IN
WITH THIS.
>> IT'S ALL A SCAM.
COUPLE LITTLE NIBBLES, THE NEXT
THING YOU KNOW, YOU'RE ORDERING
200 GRAMS OF KAVIER.
CAVIAR AIN'T FREE, MY FRIEND.
>> YOU CAN GO INTO A PLACE LIKE
THIS.
>> SOME HIGH TEST CAVIAR.
>> OH!
>> YOU GUYS ARE GOING TO EAT THE
WHOLE THING IN ONE.
>> SORRY, IS THERE SOMETHING
WRONG WITH THAT?
NOT EVEN MARRIED YET, IT'S NAG,
NAG, NAG.
LET'S DO IT.
AH TAPAS.
WHAT A NOVEL CONCEPT.
TAPAYAR.
MEANING TO TAKE TAPAS.
IF WE'RE GOING TO TAPAYAR SOME
MORE, WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO
ELBOW PAST THIS CROWD OF
CATHOLICS.
>> IS IT EXTRA INSANE?
YES, BUT IT'S ALWAYS BUSY HERE,
MAN.
>> IT'S JUST ON THE OTHER SIDE.
>> WITH PARADES CRISSCROSSING
THE CITY IN EVERY DIRECTION, THE
STEADY DRUM BEAT WARNS THAT YOUR
ROUTE IS ABOUT TO BE CUT OFF
ENTIRELY FOR THE NEXT 40
MINUTES.
>> WE CAN GET ACROSS.
>> WE HAVE TO GO AROUND.
>> WHERE?
GOING AROUND, GOING AROUND,
GOING AROUND.
>> WE NEED TO WALK PAST.
>> PEOPLE TAKE THEIR PROCESSIONS
VERY SERIOUSLY HERE AND AREN'T
EXACTLY ACCOMMODATING TO ANYONE
WHO THREATENS TO BLOCK THE VIEW.
>> THAT WAS AMAZING, RIGHT?
>> THAT MUSIC.
>> FINALLY, BAR NUMBER TWO.
OLIVER.
THIS PLACE IS ALWAYS PACKED.
BEER, PLEASE.
AND WITH IT COMES A DELIGHTFUL
TAPA OF MUSSELS SEEMED IN BUTTER
AND OLIVE OIL.
>> THAT'S A GREAT TAPA.
THIS IS WHAT'S DIFFERENT.
PEOPLE COME IN HERE AND THEY
WILL EAT LIKE THIS PERFECTLY
HAPPY.
PERFECTLY CONTENT TO FOREGO THE
TABLE, COME HERE, STAND AROUND
AND EAT LIKE THIS.
>> THE GLASS OF WINE COMES WITH
FRIED EGGPLANT AND CURRY.
MORE WINE FOLLOWED BY THESE
DELICIOUS LITTLE CLAMS.
AND THE MAIN EVENT.
>> NOW WE ARE TALKING.
THESE ARE NOT TAPAS AND
CONSEQUENTLY NOT FREE.
BUT WORTH IT AT ANY PRICE.
>> THAT'S SO TOTALLY AWESOME.
WE DID GOOD WORK HERE.
>> SHOULD WE GO ON?
>> NO, LET'S MOVE ON.
>> AS THIS DEATH MARCH OF TAPAS
CONTINUES, THINGS START TO GET A
LITTLE WEIRD.
THIS IS THE STORY OF MY LIFE.
HE DOESN'T DO THIS AT HOME?
>> NO.
NOW I UNDERSTAND HOW YOU FEEL.
>> YES.
>> EVERY DAY.
>> GOOD.
FINALLY.
A LITTLE EMPATHY.
I DO LIKE THE INCREASINGLY
META-ASPECT OF THIS SHOW.
I SHOULD REALLY BE LIVE
SCREENING.
THAT WOULD REALLY BE
INTERESTING.
FINALLY, JUST BAR GALLADO.
JUST MAKING IT.
WE'VE HAD A LOT TO EAT AND DRINK
AT THIS POINT.
SOME RESTRAINT NEEDS TO BE
SHOWN.
DUDE, FRIED FISH.
LITTLE ONES.
>> THEN WE'RE TALKING.
>> AND CHEESE.
>> BUT INSTEAD, THREE MORE
BEERS, THREE MORE TAPAS.
BABY LAMB CHOPS.
>> THESE ARE SUPER GOOD.
I'M UNCOMFORTABLE WITH THE IDEA
OF SOMETHING FOR NOTHING.
>> IT'S NOT SOMETHING FOR
NOTHING.
>> IF SOMEBODY CAN GET DEMAND
FOR IT IN THE U.S., THIS WILL
TAKE OFF.
>> NO, NEVER.
>> REALLY?
>> YOU WILL NEVER HAVE TAPAS
CULTURE.
YOU'RE LOOKING TO CHANGE THE
ENTIRE DAY, FROM THE MINUTE YOU
GET UP IN AMERICA.
NOT IN THE AFTERNOON.
ARE YOU OUT OF YOUR MIND?
>> I WANT TO WALK TO MY BAR, I
WANT TO HAVE A LITTLE BEER.
>> I WANT A GOLDEN UNICORN.
BOTH OF THOSE SCENARIOS ARE
EQUALLY LIKELY.
>>> EVERY STORYBOOK KINGDOM
NEEDS A CASTLE.
GRANADA, IT'S GOT A GOOD ONE.
ONE OF THE MOST ENCHANTED,
INSCRUTABLE, MADDENINGLY
BEAUTIFUL STRUCTURES EVER
CREATED BY MAN.
BUILT ON TOP OF NINTH CENTURY
FORTIFICATIONS AND ADDED TO AND
ADDED TO AS HISTORY UNFOLDED
THROUGH WARS AND TRAGEDY AND
INVASION AND CONQUEST.
>> IT'S VERY BARE.
ALL YOU SEE ARE THE TINY
WINDOWS.
AND IT'S PROJECTING IING IMP
IMPENATRABILITY.
ZACK IS A CINEMATOGRAPHER, SO
YOU CAN UNDERSTAND HOW THAT
MIGHT GET A GRIP ON A GUY WHOSE
PROFESSION IS THE INTRICATE PLAY
BETWEEN LIGHT AND DARKNESS.
>> TRYING TO WEAVE NATURE,
CALLIGRAPHY, SYMBOLS.
THESE ARE ALL INSCRIPTIONS,
TURNED INTO GRAPHICS.
>> DEPICT WORDS FROM GOD.
>> YES, BUT WHAT YOU CAN DEPICT,
AND THIS IS WHAT THIS ENTIRE
PLACE IS, IS GEOMETRIC SYSTEMS.
>> YES.
>> WHEN THE NASRI DYNASTY LIVED
HERE, IT WAS A HARMONIOUS SPACE
WHERE LIGHT, SHADE, WATER, THE
TRANSIT OF THE MOON AND STARS
WERE HARNESSED AND GLORIFIED.
>> I THINK THE BEST ASSUMPTION
IS NOTHING IS RANDOM.
THEY CAME HERE AND LAID OUT
EVERYTHING ACCORDING TO --
>> A PLAN.
IT WAS A PLACE FOR REFLECTION.
EACH ELEMENT OF DESIGN
PRESUMABLY INTENDED TO HAVE
EFFECTS BOTH PSYCHOLOGICAL AND
RELIGIOUS.
>> IT'S REALLY A
CINEMATOGRAPHER'S PARADISE.
EVERYTHING IS ABOUT LIGHT AND
MAN.
EVERYTHING IS FRAMING FOR THEM.
>> HOW LONG DID IT TAKE THEM TO
BUILD THIS?
>> HUNDREDS OF YEARS.
>> THAT'S WHY IT TAKES SO LONG
FOR YOU TO GET THE SHOT?
>> OH, SNAP.
>> IN THE BUILDERS TIME,
ASTRONOMIES, MATHEMATICIANS WERE
LIKE PRIESTS, POSSESSORS OF
DIVINE KNOWLEDGE OF HOW THE
UNIVERSE WORKED.
DID THEY WANT TO CONTEMPLATE
NATURE OR CONQUER IT, CONTROL
IT?
>> THEY WERE CERTAINLY TRYING TO
EMULATE IT.
THEIR MATHEMATICS WERE TRYING TO
FIGURE OUT HOW NATURE WORKED,
PARTICULARLY THE SQUARE ROOTS
AND THE REPETITION OF PATTERN.
>> THEY SAW MATHEMATICAL
PATTERNS IN THE SKY AND ON
EARTH, THE WAY WATER MOVED AND
RIPPLED, THE WAY THINGS GREW,
THE SIMPLE PINE CONE, A FERN, A
POMEGRANATE, AND THEY THOUGHT
ABOUT THE BASIC TRUTHS THESE
THINGS MIGHT REPRESENT.
>> THESE SYMMETRIES CAN ALL BE
SHUFFLED, SPUN ON ANY POINT AND
THEY ALIGN AGAIN WITH
THEMSELVES.
SO IF YOU STRETCHED THEM OUT,
FOR THEM THEY POINTED TO
INFINI
INFINITY.
>> WE WILL UNDERSTAND ALL
THINGS.
>> THROUGH CONTEMPLATING SACRED
GEE OK TOMETRY
GEOMETRY.
>> HOW DID NATURE UNFOLD,
PATTERN ITSELF?
COULD THE BASIC DESIGNS OF
NATURE, EVEN IF DIVINE, BE
REPLICATED IN THIS MAGNIFICENT
STRUCTURE?
THEY'RE TRYING TO SOLVE THE
RIDDLE OF GOD HERE.
>> EXACTLY.
>>> AN HOUR'S DRIVE FROM
GRANADA, THE MEDITERRANEAN.
UNLIKE MUCH OF SPAIN'S COASTLINE
RUINED BY REAL ESTATE
SPECULATORS AND OVERDEVELOPMENT,
THE COAST AROUND HERE IS LARGELY
UNSPOILED.
I'M ON MY WAY TO A MORAGA, A
TRADITION IN THESE PARTS BEST
DESCRIBED AS THE LOCAL VERSION
OF A BEACH BARBECUE.
WORKING THE GRILL, CHEF JUAN
ANDRES MORIA.
HE HEADS THE EL CLAUSTRO IN
GRANADA.
WE'RE JOINED BY FELLOW CHEF
RAFAEL LUCA.
>> THIS IS SOME GOOD-LOOKING
FOOD HERE.
>> SOME OF THAT SIMPLE SALMAREHO
ON TOAST.
ONE OF MY FAVORITE THINGS.
>> SOME OLIVE OIL.
>> IT'S SPICY.
AND BITTER.
>> AWESOME.
>> SPAIN IS A BEAUTIFUL COUNTRY.
WE'RE NOT EVEN EATING YET AND
IT'S GOOD.
>> OH, SWEET.
>> WANT MASS.
THAT IS LIKE THE BEST THING IN
THE WORLD.
>> THE WHOLE THING?
>> THIS?
YEAH.
CHOCOLATE.
THIS IS THE CHOCOLATE OF THE
GODS.
>> SOME GRILLED OCTOPUS, AND
SOME NICE PORK TENDERLOIN.
AND MY PERSONAL FAVORITE, A
PARTICULARLY DELICIOUS MORCIA,
FLESH BLOOD SAUSAGE.
>> I'M
BEAUTIFUL.
LOOKING GOOD.
WOW.
LOOK AT THAT.
A LOT OF FAT.
>> YEAH.
IT'S QUITE NICE.
>> THOSE WERE HAPPY PIGS.
LAZY PIGS.
>> THE ONES WE BREED HERE.
>> YEAH, THE PIGS AND THE BULLS
ARE VERY HAPPY HERE.
OKAY.
ENOUGH WITH THE WORK.
LET'S EAT.
NICE.
AWESOME.
GREAT MEAL.
GREAT, GREAT, GREAT.
THIS IS THE DREAM OF ALL THE
WORLD.
THE DREAM IS TO LIVE IN GRENADA.
WORK IN THE MORNING AND GO OUT
AND HAVE THAT LIFE.
GO OUT AND SEE YOUR FRIENDS AND
EAT DAPA AND DRINK RED WINE AND
BE IN A BEAUTIFUL PLACE.
TO HAVE THIS KIND OF MUSIC AND
THIS FOOD AND THIS KIND OF
CULTURE AND TO LOOK OUT THE
WINDOW AND TO SEE SPAIN.
>> ONE THING.
FAMILY.
FAMILY IS VERY, VERY, VERY
IMPORTANT.
>> SEE.
HE DID IT RIGHT.
HE'S MARRYING INTO A SPANISH
FAMILY IN GRENADA.
CHEATING, MAN.
>> HE'S VERY LUCKY.
AND A SMART GUY.
>> RIGHT.
LOOK, NOW ONE IS GOING TO DARE
DREAM OF THIS BECAUSE THIS IS
TOO MUCH TO DREAM FOR.
THIS IS EXTRAORDINARY.
BUT AN ORDINARY LIFE IN SPAIN
LOOKS PRETTY GOOD TO ME.
>>> THE NEW SWINGING ZAMBONI
LIFESTYLE.
RISE EARLY LIKE 9:00 A.M.
THEN DOWN FOR A CAFE COLECHE.
MAYBE MORE LIKE TOMATO.
NO MORE THAN THAT.
LIGHT.
SIMPLE.
BECAUSE THERE WILL BE A LOT MORE
EATING AND DRINKING TODAY, AND
YOU WANT TO BE READY.
BY 2:00 P.M., HE'S MADE HIS WAY
BACK UP HILL TO MOM'S PLACE.
>> EVERY DAY I COME HERE FOR
LUNCH.
AND I WALK IN AND SHE SAYS GET
US TWO BEERS.
SO I'LL GET TWO BEERS FROM THE
FRIDGE AND WATCH HER COOK.
>> EVERYBODY'S HOME FOR EASTER.
MARIA JOSE, ZACH'S SOON TO BE
MOTHER-IN-LAW AND DAD.
PLUS THE SOON TO BE
BROTHERS-IN-LAW WHO YOU'VE
ALREADY MET.
WHAT THIS NICE FAMILY DOESN'T
REALIZE, THEY'RE NOT JUST
GAINING A SON BUT AN ANNOYING
HALF DRUNK UNCLE TONY.
>> AND I KNOW WHAT HAPPENS HERE.
>> SITTING THERE READY TO BE
CARVED.
[ SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE ]
>> HE HAD TO CUT THE HAM BEFORE
HE PROPOSED TO MY SISTER.
>> I THINK THAT'S A COMPLETELY
REASONABLE POLICY.
EVENTUALLY THE APPROPRIATE HOUR
FOR LUNCH APPROACHES.
IS NOT TO EMBARRASS YOU
PUBLICLY, BUT MAINE IS NOT
EXACTLY THE MEDITERRANEAN OF
AMERICA.
HOW'S HE ADAPTING?
>> HE'S MORE SPANISH THAN ME.
>> REALLY?
>> YEAH.
IN THE FIRST WEEK HE WAS LIKE I
DON'T UNDERSTAND.
WEEK AFTER.
>> IT'S INTERESTING TO SEE HOW
YOU'VE MADE THE TRANSITION.
CHEERS.
[ SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE ]
>> FIRST OFF, THIS.
BAKALOU SALAD.
EGG, BLACK OLIVES, ORANGES,
TOMATOES DRESSED IN OLIVE OIL.
REMEMBER, THIS IS HOLY WEEK.
MARIA JOSE IS PREPARING RECIPES
THAT GO BACK THROUGH THE FAMILY
SO FAR THAT NOBODY KNOWS EXACTLY
WHERE THEY EVEN CAME FROM.
MIGAS, ANOTHER ICONIC DISH.
FORMALLY REFERRED TO AS THE
SHEPHERD'S LUNCH.
BORN AS A WAY TO USE OLD, HARD
BREAD AND COMBINE ALL THE WEEK'S
LEFTOVERS.
I'M TOLD EVERY HOUSEHOLD IN
SPAIN HAS A VARIATION.
WHAT CHANGES IS WHAT YOU PUT ON
IT.
TODAY IT'S SARDINES, COD, CHO
CHORIZO, AND MELONS.
SO HOW OFTEN DO YOU EAT THIS
WELL?
>> EVERY LUNCH IS LIKE THIS.
EVERY DAY I'M HERE.
BUT LUNCH IS BIG.
BIG LUNCH, SIESTA.
BUT YOU CAN'T -- YOU KNOW, I
USED TO TRY TO RESIST SIESTA.
YOU CAN'T DO IT HERE.
SOCIETY WILL NOT ACCEPT YOU NOT
TAKING SIESTA HERE.
>> THAT BEGS THE QUESTION, WHILE
I'M BUSY HATING YOU FOR YOUR
LIFE, HOW OFTEN ARE YOU GETTING
A DRUNK A DAY?
>> TWICE.
ONE AND A HALF.
[ SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE ]
>> THAT IS SO SPANISH.
EVERYBODY HAS A VERY DISTINCT
OPINION AND IT'S COMPLETELY
DIFFERENT.
LIKE THIS IS A FACT.
>> WHEN MY TIME COMES, I PRETTY
MUCH WANT TO DIE AT A TABLE LIKE
THIS.
GOOD WORK, ZAMBONI.
GOOD WORK.
SO ZACH, HAPPY WITH THE SHOW?
>> HOPE WE DON'T SUCK ON
TELEVISION.
>> DUDE, I THINK I'M SETTING A
PRETTY LOW BAR.
I'M GOING TO TELL YOU THIS
RELAXED LIFESTYLE, LOUNGING
AROUND EATING AND DRINKING.
NO NAP IS LONG ENOUGH FOR ME.
LIFE IS GOOD.
I ENVY YOU ZACH, ZAMBONI.
AND WE'RE OUT. NICE END.