♪
There's no place else
even remotely like it.
Everything great and all the
world's ills all in one glorious
messed up magical
and maddening city.
♪
Beirut.
It's good to be back.
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ Sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la la
♪ sha la la la la
The Mediterranean sea itself
trembles.
The ground shakes beneath the
wheels of our heavy metal
thunder.
Back in Beirut, after
all these ye years.
The first time I was here it did
not end well but it made no
difference to me.
I love it here.
In spite of everything,
Nice ride.
It's a good way to see Beirut.
This is very similar to that
place we went to years ago.
This is your traditional
chicken sandwich.
The roasted chicken was this
man's idea, Ramsey Short who I
met in the bad old days of 2006.
Apparently he's in with the
Lebanese chapter of the Harley
Davidson group,
or hog for short.
So when you roll into some
religiously conservative
villages on the bikes and
leather jackets what is the
reaction?
Two types.
Once we were pelted with rice
and the other extreme was stones
at the wheels like
just get out of here.
I wouldn't throw stones
at people on Harleys.
Whoa.
Look at this.
Let's dig in.
This is a famous neighborhood.
This area was central
during the civil war.
The sheer volume of fire that
was poured into some of these
buildings is absolutely
unbelievable.
So many have been in the same
place over and over and over
again.
Clearly.
I notice this every time
someone visiting the city they
just point at that.
Look at that.
But you know, we don't
see them any many.
Just pass by them.
Beirut, seemingly the
world in literature.
18 religious sects recognized.
More than 2 million Christians,
over a million and a half
Shiites, a million and a half
Sunni and 500,000 Palestinians
and now as many as 2 million
Syrians, all living and somehow
getting along, kind of, in a
country the size of Connecticut.
But along its borders the
country has what you might call
serious neighbor issues.
Isis in Syria threatening
to expand into Lebanon.
Isis in many ways is something
we have never really
seen before.
A really large well organized
well equipped terrorist army.
The country simply
can't take any more.
A quarter of Lebanon's
population is now Syrian.
That is the equivalent of the U.S.
taking in 83 million
Syrians.
The real fear is that
violence cross the border now
spilling into an
already fragile area.
Beirut struggles to put a lid
on the simmering sectarian
tensions.
♪
The aftermath of Beirut
and some of the flashes.
♪
Exchange for Shia as two
Palestinian brothers were shot.
♪
Here block by block you see the
scars from the 15 year civil
war that only ended in the 90s.
But also nightclubs, discos,
beaches, bikinis, where much of
the Arab world comes to
let their hair down.
It is an incongruous mix.
The violence since
the beginning.
This neighborhood has long
been the home to principally
Palestinian refugees but it has
become an area for Syrians
fleeing Isis.
The camp saw heavy fighting,
shelling and outright massacres
during the the religious
conflict known as the Lebanese
civil war.
Everywhere you see posters
representing factions and
affiliations from Asad loyalists
to every flavor of extremist.
A victory for jihad.
Do you know of any other place
in the region where all of
these groups are co-existing
within a confined space?
It is stunning to be walking
down the street behind short
skirts and red wine flowing
and drive straight into an
extraordinarily conservative
Shiite district.
It is kind of mind blowing.
I am not a gee owe political
expert and as much time as I
have spent in this part of the
world I spent nowhere near the
amount of time this guy has.
CNN senior international
course respondent.
Most of the groups are more
terrified of the crazy radicals
in Syria than they ever
have been of each other.
What do we call
this neighborhood?
It's one of the mixed
areas that Beirut has.
Close to 2 million
people from Syria alone.
Yeah.
That's a hell of a lot to be
absorbed by a tiny little
nation.
It's just loads of people
with nowhere to go.
You see it in how cell phones
don't sometimes work the way
they should.
Bad infrastructure and more.
We'll follow you.
The first time, see the leads.
The name is there.
In Syria, he was an
English teacher.
Needles to say he had at one
time a better life back there.
I came from Syria.
After the civil war
started... yeah.
Many, many problems.
Sectarian problems and we don't
want to add more problems
for those people.
But what can we do?
We live here.
Imagine the situation here.
It is unbelievable.
He is there by the way
and he has three kids.
He works construction.
His family bought this to
protect from the rats.
These children need medical
operation but this family can't
pay for those operation.
It is expensive.
They wait for nothing.
They wait for the hand of god.
Straining under the weight of
all of these unasked for guests
the Lebanese government has
begun making it very
difficult for them.
He doesn't work because he
doesn't have an official
resident so he can't
leave the camp.
Otherwise he will be homeless.
Being stopped at any of the
military check points could mean
a one way ticket back to Syria,
trapped, unable to work, they
exist invisibly on the margins
of society.
This is military.
You don't want to get
involved in any problem.
Syrian food, it is
called the seven countries.
It consists of many
kinds of vegetables.
Seven kinds of fruit.
Most of them are doctors,
engineers, lawyers, teachers.
Here now it's the opposite.
Here in Lebanon even if you
were a doctor or a lawyer or a
teacher, you can't
work only in the camp.
We don't know how to go, where
to go, to go back to Syria.
No can do.
To cross the sea.
Yeah.
Suppose that there is authority
to collect us to throw
us away to Syria,
what will we do?
We have no area in the world.
We have no place
in this universe.
We belong to nowhere.
Nowhere.
Once known as the Paris of the
middle east, Beirut still
clings to its glamorous 1960s
image where you could famously
ski and go to the beach
all in the same day.
Walking it's easy to forget, for
a moment anyway, what's
going on not far from here.
All the people who
live here feel safe.
They expand outside of their
houses and this is one of their
traditions.
This is how I live my life.
Mo is a local security
specialist on assignment to
keep, well, me and my
crew safe from harm.
He lives with his daughter and
family in Beirut, a mixed
neighborhood of Christians,
Muslims and Jews were a little
oil in the middle?
Yes.
So good.
Very good fish.
I missed this country.
I really did.
You have been here before?
This is my third time.
My first time was 2006.
We came here and had two perfect
days and then the war broke out.
During my first trip here in
2006, Hezbollah had a 44 day war
that followed and much of Beirut
was heavily pounded by bombs
and artilleries.
You have this really
extraordinary mix of religions
and people.
What's so special?
Why?
Of course, somebody on Friday
going pray, somebody on Sunday
going pray.
They go the same restaurant and
have the same food and they
have the same traditions.
There is no place
better than Lebanon.
You have everything.
People are friendly.
Beautiful, fantastic.
It is a democracy here.
Of course.
You have choice to sit down.
I like this.
I don't like this.
So what's it look like now?
We looked like before 2006.
That's not good.
Tension is a little bit high
but the people, we are very
happy.
I go with my family.
I was watching the news last
night in the hotel and it is
genuinely terrifying.
Tomorrow is sunny.
It's happening all the time.
You get used to it.
Are you concerned or optimistic.
Optimistic.
Do your friends
feel the same way?
Not really.
Your friends are
less optimistic?
Yeah.
We have only one good neighbor
that don't affect us.
They help us all the time.
We bring the fish
and we have fish.
And he never get upset from us.
♪
We are back in the house.
This is radio Beirut.
I ain't afraid.
Is that, why yes.
Yes, I think it is.
Ironic glasses, vintage
clothing and neck beards.
It appears the Brooklyn strain
has spread even to Beirut.
Radio Beirut.
CNN and everything.
CNN has become the most
trusted name in news.
Same way a broken clock
is right twice a day.
CNN changed their slogan from
this is CNN to at least
it's not fox news.
How is it possible that this
mix of religions and cultures?
You have got mountains, the
sea, and we're surrounded and
there are so many factions
that you have to deal with ♪
♪
Monday is hip hop
at radio Beirut.
It is a really awesome place
where there is live bands
playing all week long.
We created a platform for
emcees to try their skills in
front of people
without judgment.
Although we do judge but
we don't make fun of them.
Lebanese free style legend
Hussein, the preacher man.
You were arrested?
Yeah yeah yeah.
That's not the first
time it happened.
What?
Basically I was profiled.
If there's an explosion, the big
dude with the beard who is bald.
These are beard related issues.
They are.
Hip hop?
That's the glue that binds us.
What is it about hip hop?
I see it like this.
It's a traditional riming scheme
where they speak about
their problems.
It's in our core to be poetic.
I'm from a background where
you have governments that are
dictators and you can't
really voice anything.
♪
We're trying to find
our own identity.
We don't want to be like our
ancestors fighting each other.
That's nothing.
You know?
We don't even mention
that when we're on stage.
Afternoon in Beirut and this
family, like many others across
the city, prepares dinner.
Extraordinary spread of food.
All this food, you see, my
brother wants to go burger king.
He want some chicken
burger from burger king.
Thank you so much for
having me in your home.
This is sweet potato.
It is a deep fried potato with
red pepper, chili, garlic and
lemon just.
This is raw meat, lamb,
fresh mint, onion.
Mixed all together.
This is minced meat, baked,
green and red pepper and chick
peas and tomato
and tomato paste.
Please help yourself.
Thank you.
I was in Beirut in 2006 this
neighborhood was hit very hard.
Were you here at that time?
Yes.
Why this neighborhood?
Because the people of this
area support us so much.
As Israel buries its dead, a
radical group celebrates victory
and things are at a
fever pitch right now.
This is the deadliest Hezbollah
attack since the two
sides went to war in 2006.
Hezbollah means
the party of god.
They are a Shia military
political organization lavishly
supported by Iran.
The party is more powerful, more
effective on the ground
than the Lebanese army.
The United States officially
designates them a terrorist
organization.
In 1983, they did this.
The U.S. embassy bombing.
And this, the marine where over
200 servicemen were killed.
Please put it down now.
They are dangerous.
They are well funded and
whatever else they may be, they
are not stupid.
I have two sisters.
Hezbollah take care of them.
Here everybody support
Hezbollah, even the people who
are not religious
for one reason.
Because they feel
protected by them.
My host's support for
Hezbollah, typical of south
Beirut, is staunch.
Before Hezbollah, Lebanese
were always scared.
Now what?
Now we say ha ha.
We don't care.
In the early days Hezbollah
used tactics that just about
anyone would call terrorism.
When is it permissible to use
a car bomb or using civilian
targets?
For me?
For you?
I'm against killing.
Against killing
anybody, even Israel.
This person that I'm going to
kill, car bomb or whatever, he
has family.
What's the most important
thing happening in the world
right now that needs to be
resolved for things to be
better?
Isis.
They are rebels.
They are against like everything
on the earth they are against.
Recently Hezbollah has become
heavily involved in the war in
Syria, in defense
of the Asad regime.
Complicating matters and
uncomfortably enough they are
probably the best organized,
best equipped most serious
obstacle to Isis and
Al Qaeda in the area.
Most of the villages in
eastern Lebanon, they are
Christian and they are Sunni.
Correct.
If Hezbollah wasn't there, it
was Christian in that area.
This is the only reason, this is
the only reason just to protect
my children and my wife.
20 years, 30 years?
Yeah.
Will things be better?
I hope so.
That many years, now, next year.
I hate war.
♪
Who is buying these apartments?
Two kinds of people.
Lebanese who are living abroad
or Arabs especially from the
Gulf region.
For whom Beirut is a wonderland.
Compared to where they are yes.
But we cannot generalize this
and say that Beirut is a place
where sexual expression
is encouraged.
Her books are banned in many
countries in the region.
She is regularly threatened
the rape, stoning and murder.
She is culture editor of
Lebanon's biggest newspaper.
Yesterday I had my first TV
show about sexual freedom and
you cannot imagine how many doors
have opened just because I
dare said that girls are
allowed sexuality like boys.
We pretend to be a democracy.
This is yogurt sauce
and Cranberries.
Fried.
Stuffed grape please.
Yes.
The fact that Lebanon and
Beirut works at all.
If all of these religious
groups, this is a fully
functioning more or less
by world standards.
We don't have a president.
It's going to be a year now
that we are without one.
It's sort of awesome.
Don't you think that the main
reason behind you seeing this as
thrilling, exciting place to
live in is that you're a visitor
and not someone who
actually lives here?
Am I wrong to love this place?
You're not wrong to love it.
I love living on the tip of a
volcano, but there has to be
some point where I can
breathe and relax.
I don't want to seem like I'm
only criticizing because I
really also as much as I hate
this place, I love it as well.
And I know that it's very
precious to have such a freedom
in a place like Beirut.
I don't need to tell you about
Islamic states even though they
are not inside Beirut yet,
we can feel it every day.
Should people come here?
Yes, definitely.
They should come.
They will enjoy it
as much as you have.
I wouldn't advise them to stay
more than a month, though.
I often go to events and I
asked him to call me your
highness.
I love it.
I go there and I dress
like an emperor.
Sometimes I dress
There have been two
attempts on your life?
Yes.
That you're aware of.
It means the third one succeeds.
I don't know when the
third one will be.
An activist, a labor organizer.
You have been arrested
in your life?
Yes, many times.
When I was 14 years old I became
a communist in a region that was
under control of the extreme
right wing militia.
I ended up in a torture room.
Later after joining and then
leaving the Lebanese army,
Michelle formed the NRU, an
armed revolutionary group.
Your life now is
music and culture?
I think that I was made to
be a musician but when war
happened, I took a gun.
I understood that I could not
face someone who was attacking
my house with a guitar.
In 2003, by now a music
producer, entrepreneur,
politician, artist and film
maker, he founded the Beirut
musical in a bullet popped
theater empty since the civil
war.
This is his kingdom.
Some people come
because it's trendy.
They come with sexy ladies.
Some come because they like
to discover new things.
We have up to 15 acts, each act
coming from a different culture.
Who needs culture?
I think that culture
can save the world.
Someone who had looks, someone
to listen to beautiful music
cannot become an animal again.
If you were the emperor of
the world, hypothetically.
Hopefully.
Hopefully, what would Beirut
be like in ten years?
Best case scenario it goes
back to before the creation of
separate.
When all communities were
living together well.
We would have a Jewish
neighborhood here.
I think we would have to be
united to fight the monster,
Isis.
Once the monster is defeated you
can start arguing again
about other things.
How you doing?
I'm Tony?
This feels very formal.
Yes.
But it's not so please relax.
I am relaxed.
Can I get my beer.
By all means, yes please.
Lots of people come here.
They are mostly musicians
and sick people.
Lots of jamming here and it's
like we're a family hanging out.
This cafe is a typical Beirut
establishment from Syria and
any number of other countries.
The owners are both Lebanese and
Syrian and acutely aware of the
tricky political realities
with which they must live.
They were concerned about us filming
here and wanted us to understand
clearly that the cafe has no
political affiliation and that
the opinions of this young lady
are not that of the cafe or
even that of the clientele.
You are born and bred sue knee?
Yes.
I was born and brought
up in Syria, Damascus.
The army entered our house and
I found them in our bedroom
looking for the free
Syrian army.
My dad knew he couldn't protect
us because he was old.
Three hours later we decided to
leave, so we came to Beirut.
We always eat here.
Grape leaves are my and I
have four months left and
I have no idea what to do.
What do you think, will
they renew your visa?
So far, I don't think so.
And do they the arrest you?
Do they take you to the border
and kick you over
to the other side?
They send you back to Syria.
What happens if you
go back to Syria?
Most probably die.
On the way or to some people get
arrested or be taken to the
army.
How different is
Damascus from Beirut?
Oh, it is really, really
different, and in Damascus, I
was always afraid of the
government, and some people died
because they cursed
the president.
I left Syria, and I found hope
here, and I screamed in the
streets cursing all of the
politicians, and everything.
It is all right, nobody is
going to come to arrest you.
I really love this place
with all of my heart.
Is all of the chaos and the
violence worth it for change?
It is is worth dying for?
I mean, things were, there was
order when you grew up, there
was order?
Yes.
No freedom, but order.
Would you go back to that?
I don't think that there's
anything worthy in the world of
a human blood.
There is nothing more
important than human being.
You have never been able to
yell out loud, and you have
never been able to do the things
that you could do right
now, you would go back?
I was alive.
A lot of people were alive, too.
♪
During the day, widespread
shocking bombing and widespread
finger pointing.
This has set off a tide of
unrest and civil unrest.
For capitalists like
myself and Ramsey.
It is a communist-themed bar.
What is this?
I don't know, it is
put in front of us.
Well, we should drink it and
not try to figure it out.
Oh, with well.
Vodka.
I had somebody who lives here
tell me, oh, this place is very
good, and stay the here longer.
And I was like, what?
You are trying to kill us, man.
Who is this man?
Yeah, yeah.
He is trying to hurt us.
Cheers.
And after a more than a few
indigenous beverages, and now we
are talking.
Cheers.
Enter Ernesto.
Hey, hey.
I have something for you.
Yeah, yeah.
It is a Cuban cigar.
And in the words of Vladimir
Illitch Lennon, let's get this
party started.
My mom, she made some cheese,
and it is the kind of
the rotten cheese.
Oh.
I called my dad and I said, there
is a dad called Tony, CNN,
and he said, I don't watch CNN
and I said, but he is a cool
guy.
He wants to make the
best food for you.
This is someone that
I know in Beirut.
It is lamb and spices.
Oh, man.
That is good.
Are we picking up a gun or not?
They will fight these people.
Oh, no, we have to have it.
I seem to remember mom at
some point pulling out a some
kind of automatic weapon.
I will take it up in
arms, and I will fight.
Let me tell you about it.
And then Bootsy Collins came
over the intercom system, and
the rest dissolved into a fog.
It is am amazing
that it persists.
And I have been a number of
places, and this the place,
it is the world's finest.
I think so, too.
Here is to Tony, man.
Beirut... everybody
should come here.
Everybody should see how
complicated and deeply trouble
and yet at the same time how
beautiful and awesome the world
can be.
Everyone should experience even
as the clouds gather what's
at stake, what could be lost,
what's still here and
never let that hope go.
Beirut, there is
no place like it.
Captions by vitac...
www.Vitac.Com