I went looking for
the dream of Africa.
I woke up in Tanzania.
♪
♪ I took a walk through
this beautiful world ♪
♪ felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ found something good in
this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ sha la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la
♪ sha la la la la la la
♪
The narrow streets of the
neatly dressed schoolchildren
make it feel like a very
different Africa than
I've ever known.
It's tight, small.
The architecture
speaks of many layers.
The hierarchy long gone
but still evident.
The famous Zanzibar
door, for instance.
Meticulously carved from
mohagany and tique.
They reveal the professions.
Brass bikes similar to India.
The lotis flower and the symbol
meant to promote fertility.
And chains, a reminder that this
once was a central hub
of the slave trade.
♪
What Zanzibar is today is
overwhelmingly Muslim.
99% of the population.
And you see a strong influence
everywhere you look.
The children are coming from the
Medrassa, the streets are neat
and private homes even of the
very poor are maintained
with great pride.
The call to prayer,
five times a day.
Zanzibar part of Tanzania but
also an autonomous state
sits just off the mainland.
The minute you cross the
ocean from the mainland, you
feel like you're in a different
country and different
culture, different vibe.
This is a native of Zanzibar
and former tour guide and knows
his way around these parts.
So, what are our options here?
This is what we call Mandazi.
Mandazi, a Swahili treat or
basically a donut
spiced with cormeander.
Care for a cup of coffee?
Yeah, let's do it.
If you live here, if you're from
here, chances are you start your
day with bitter spiced coffee.
Talk about the issues of
the day, politics for one.
Maybe a pastry.
Oh, that's good.
So, you were born and bred here.
How long has your
family been here?
How far back do you guys go?
I'm half Indian, half African,
and my mother has been
here four generation.
Four generations, that's
starting out in the...
Late 1700s.
Wow.
Who built this neighborhood?
Construction started in 1830s
in a Portuguese colony.
And it started in 1864 but they
lost a lot of power in 1996.
Confused?
Let's take a step back.
The Persians were the first
major power to set up here back
around 975 a.D. Expanding their
empire onto the strategically
positioned island.
Then the Portuguese used
Zanzibar a hub for their slave
trade and spices.
Then they did the same
ultimately with the British who
ruled from them.
1964, revolution.
As with most revolutions, the
days following were
violent, chaotic and ugly.
After overthrowing the mostly
Arab government, reprisals.
It wasn't intended for a
revolution where more than 3,000
Arabs and Indians were
moved out of this country.
But your family stayed?
My family stayed.
Why?
There was no money for
the family to move out.
Tough times?
Very tough times.
In about two hours from stone
town, this is John Biani,
a tiny fishing village.
Here the first revolutionaries
met from an independent
Zanzibar.
Total assassination in 1972.
This, too, is a grandson of the
country's first president.
Well, what was the political
situation back then?
Well, it wasn't good.
Basically it was English...
Arabs in the middle and then the
Africans way, way at the bottom.
And it was a form of
apartheid, you know.
Was this village sort of a
center for revolutionary...
This village was important in
terms of the political support
prior to the revolution.
When my grandfather and my
grandmother stayed right here
and had meetings on the
field right over there.
That's where they would have
their meetings to raise support
for the African people,
their it into identity.
The objective was to give
identity to Zanzibar.
Well, this is the house.
They are preparing a
wonderful lunch for us.
She used to take care of my
grandmother many,
many years ago.
She was a close family friend
to him and his grandparents and
she's putting together
quite a spread.
Coconut rice, freshly caught
fish called tasi simmered in
broth of garlic and wine topped
with a fresh salad of chopped
tomato, eggplant,
cucumber and potato.
Another fish called mackerel
marinated in juice and
garlic an pan fried.
That's looking good.
So coconut rice.
Japati bread from the other
side of the water there.
That's it.
This is Kasaba.
Two different types
of fried bread.
Wow, what a spread here.
And you can use your hands.
Good.
This I can do by hand.
The rice, I need help.
Good.
What do you think of the Kasaba?
Lovely.
The rice is great, too.
Whatever your feelings on
revolutions, it is probably
worth remembering that they
start in places like this.
People talking.
And when they are one, they are
often won by feet of the
original planners, people who
look like this.
Look at all these kids.
Watch out future
revolutionaries.
There's no ideas.
How to change comes from them.
Think about it, the challenges
we face as a small island
country, doesn't the whole world
face a similar challenge?
Yeah.
How to preserve all these
things, find balance?
To me, I see Africa as a whole.
I see a very interesting timing.
Optimistic?
I'm very optimistic and think
we have a lot of great people.
And given the opportunity, I
think they can put a lot on the
table, not only for themselves
but also for the culture of east
Africa and possibly the world.
I think they are great people.
Why not?
The sky is the limit, right?
Say you're going to Zanzibar
and people will tell
you about the seafood.
It's pretty impressive.
In stone towns for downey
gardens, vendors set up an
insane variety of
a seafood snack.
Oh, yeah, I would
love some of that.
We have shellfish, we have a
mussel small shell, a tune
tuna fish, mahi-mahi.
Good.
Let me find some of the octopus.
I like hot.
Okay, good.
Mmm.
I like it, chewy but tasty.
Lobster is working for me.
Too spicy for you, ma'am.
Believe me, only one of us is
going to be [ Bleep ] tonight.
And it's not going to be you.
The famous Zanzibar pizza.
Awesome.
Sounds awesome to me.
Looks good.
Thank you.
Mmm.
Weird and wonderful.
These stands are extremely
popular with locals and visitors
alike, so of course the
government raised the rents.
One guy, Juma, decided to pick
up and move his place
a bit out of town.
His customers came with him.
This is Juma.
Hi, Juma.
How are you?
So what are we having?
Chick up and steak.
Half chicken and all the spices.
I ordered beef for now.
Beef is good.
I'll take half a chicken.
Chicken?
Yeah, sure.
Juma is famous for his chicken.
The bird is slathered with
a mixture of garlic, lime,
coriandor, salt and pepper and
grilled and served as a saw stay
or whole pieces topped
with chili sauce.
Preparation for this is
Saturday morning, prepare
cutting and then coming here at
6:30 to finish about 10:00.
How many guys are working here?
It's about six, seven of them.
Six or seven of them.
All around the table.
Wow, it's like a big operation.
He's finishing the skewers, I
guess he's half-cooking
or saucing.
He's re-heating,
finishing the skewers.
That guy doesn't just set up
plates for him to top with meat.
Then I guess they have the bread
and the sauce and
finishing to go, also.
What are they squirting
on the fries?
His hot sauce, ketchup.
So you never go hungry here.
There's always food
many the street.
If you come here to buy ten
skewers, you are eventually
going to buy 20 or 30 because
someone is always asking for
food and you always buy it.
It's just the culture.
You always shell out food.
There we go.
And you use the
stick as your fork.
Hot, hot, hot.
Where do you think the
recipe came from?
This is a real mixed
up history here?
Mostly Arabic/Indian components
with the spices, most
of the trees like mangos came
from India, pineapples
from Brazil.
Tamron, southeast
Asia, not even India.
Damn, that's good.
The chicken is really awesome.
I might need some more of this.
I'm liking the heat, man.
Good stuff.
Incredible.
The 250-mile flight from
Zanzibar across the water to the
town of Arusha takes
an hour and a half.
But culturely you are flying
from Texas to the Philippines.
Kilimanjaro into whose white
peak the hero saw himself
disappear as he
slipped into death.
From there we head into
the Sarang Sarangeti.
♪
The journey of this kind one
must expect an occasional
setback.
We reached the eastern edge of
the Sanghetti where it is a
significant descent to the
crater.
A long time ago the crater
collapsed on itself creating
this kaldera, creating
a truly lost word.
Inside the creator, an entire
ecosystem within an ecosystem.
Wildlife pretty much stayed put.
Coming to drink, well,
right below my place.
It's nice.
Very, very nice if you
find yourself here.
A hot bubble bath awaits after
a long day in the bush.
Perhaps a dry cherry of
a glass of decanter.
The next morning one rises to
breakfast in one's chambers
on the balcony, perhaps.
Silver service, hot coffee,
freshly baked croissant.
Good morning.
Thank you, sir.
You're welcome.
The rules of the house while
slightly restricting are
sensible enough and given the
luxurious surroundings and
the view, hardly a burden.
You're not supposed to wander
around at night here unescorted.
There's lions and hyenas
and baboons and stuff.
I heard they can get a little
rakey, but there were
no knocks on the door.
I know what you're thinking
already, you're not going to go
out there and shoot some
beautiful animal in the brain.
Answer?
No.
What kind of sick [ Bleep ]
Wants to shoot an elephant?
Even the toilet has a nice view.
This is pretty much what you see
because you're sitting
on the snakes.
Idyllic natural setting and
good plumbing, it's
pretty much paradise.
It's nuts driving
into the Serangeti.
After a short while you actually
get used to the jungle book
scene playing out in
front of your car.
It's interesting to see the
giraffe and wild beasts, zebra,
they all seem to pretty
much hang together.
The buffalos take
the big stuff out.
The zebras follow it down and
the wild beasts are
the closed crop.
My guide is a fourth generation
African born in Kenya, lives in
Tanzania and knows this area
like I know the Barney counter.
About every tree you see here
that's lying on its side has not
fallen over by choice, it's
being pushed over by elephants.
There's an elephant over there.
Oh, yeah.
Whoo!
It's a big bull.
Magnificent.
Will he charge us?
No.
If we piss him off?
If we piss him off he would.
They sleep so
soundly, the zebra.
You can creep right up.
Zebras as and more zebras you
almost get bored looking at
them.
Giraffes look slightly irritated
to be interrupted and
stadium-sized crowds
of wild beasts.
The unkept looking
things every 100 yards.
All that's missing
is a happy sound.
Everyone thinks wild beasts
jump into the rivers, but that
only happens two
months of the year.
The rest of the year they are
trekking through the bush.
To me this is so much more
spectacular when you
see the big numbers.
You'll be in an area this
morning that was full of wild
beasts and go there this
afternoon and there's not one.
They have moved.
Thousands and thousands of
wild beasts are on their
migration everywhere.
A big circle stretched out
across Tanzania in search of
prime grazing.
It's all about water and grass
and a good place to make babies.
I mean, look at this little guy.
He's keeping up with his mom.
He's doing okay.
Within 15 minutes of being
born, they are up and standing.
Really.
Running as fast as their moms
within a couple of hours.
There's a wild beast
that didn't make it.
How long has it been there?
A day or two.
Very fresh.
You don't want to get lost here.
You definitely don't want to be
on foot outside your car
or injured, for instance.
Nature as they say is a cruel
miscus to take care of
its own without mercy.
The evidence of this cool math
called survival is everywhere.
Non-immediate family, you're not
going to help a brother out.
You would think, huh?
Start limping, first
come the hyenas.
They see the vultures dropping
and that's key to them
there's food up.
And the vultures need the hyenas
to rip open the skin
to start eating it.
By the time they stop ripping
out your soft parts and treating
your femur like a chew toy, they
call them the undertaker birds
that are waiting for their turn.
When I have cause to reflect on
a pack of hyenas ripping out the
guts, I think, you know what?
I could really go for
some Pesto right now.
By late day we pause for lunch.
Penne with Pesto, steamed baby
corn and snow peas, sprinkled
tomatoes with Parmesan
and oh look, brownies.
Boy, the hippos
are coming close.
Yeah, you can smell the pesto.
They are coming ashore.
Yes, Dave.
Over thankfully cold beers, I
learn who is really the most
dangerous animal around here.
Yeah, that's right.
Mr. Lovable funny hippo always
in a tutu in the cartoons.
A vicious, unpredictable and ape
parentally incredibly
fast moving killer.
You happen to leave here and
go to pee behind the tree here
and come face to face with a
hippo, the hippo would easily
outrun you in a big chomp, big
tusks that will go straight
through you, chop you in half.
Just get between them and
their mud hole and they'll be
all over you like Justin
Bieber's bodyguards.
It can get ugly.
What do hippo penises look like?
I don't know.
Do they ever emerge
with a big hard on?
Not that I've said.
They are under water.
I don't go snorkeling.
I find that comforting to know.
They are among the last great
warrior tribes on earth.
Semi-nomatic, they believe all
the cattle are a gift
from the gods to them.
They move with their animals
across the Tanzanian planes
setting up homes where they
find the best grazing.
♪
Their cattle are everything.
The wealth of the family, units
of currency, givers of milk to
live and on special occasions
on meat and blood.
The Masai have strategic hamlets
designed to repel and
discourage predators.
Do you have a lot of
livestock coming in here?
This area is quite famous
for the cats, the big cats.
The big cats, lions,
roam free here.
An area called Indutut.
The lions are an enemy, they
are a competitor, but they are
also something that
they greatly admire.
Swedish native Engela Johnson
with the lion project is trying
to find a balance between the
needs, traditions and the basic
identities of the people and the
outside's world's desire to
protect the beautiful
killing machines.
This is what can happen when a
warrior defending his cattle
takes on a hungry adult lion.
Nobody wants this.
For the Masai, being comprised
of the comings and goings of the
lion population is a useful
thing, good to know in advance.
Respect that the Masai have
always defined themselves and
their identities
but their enemy.
A tribe of proud warriors, what
happens when there's no
one and nothing to fight?
♪
Engela has brought several Masai
onto her team to show them up
close the lions they
share this land with.
So often on my days out when
I'm working with the Masai,
you don't eat at all.
You get a cup of tee in the
morning and then if you're lucky
in the rainy season, you'll
get fresh milk or this.
This is Amasi, by the way, a
lumpy yogurt drink similar
to the Masai diet.
Cheers.
And before you say yuck, it
may be worth noting that between
their nearly 100% protein diet
of meat, blood and dairy,
the Masai are known to have
Olympic-level Stan ma and
condition and can run miles at a
time without rest or water and
can basically kick your ass near
any physical contact
given half the chance.
So help yourself to some
sour lumpy goodness.
A little honey and raisins
in there, good to go.
It's so different here, like
the rainy season, dry season.
Such different challenges.
What do you think of
going under here?
I'm okay with it.
Currently, Engela is tracking
two lions particular.
Ramu ss and pouyo.
Do you see them?
Yes, I do.
I see them.
Wow.
Two of them.
Yeah.
You like them, don't you?
Oh, they are magnificent.
Very admirable.
He's a bit of a
warrior, that one.
Should we try to upright them?
Yeah.
When you go to the lions, you
don't ever drive
straight on them.
You kind of go in at an
angle to relax them.
That's funny how they
pretend they don't see you.
But they are so
completely aware.
So basically what we look at to
identify them are their spots,
like their fingerprint.
Punctured in the face, that
means he's fighting with a
female.
It's too dangerous to go for the
head area if they're fighting.
The reason for the colors, do
you see how lions behave to cope
with threats in the area, to
show that lions and Masai
can stay together.
They will always live together.
For the Masai, one of the
diminish things for them is
large ranges.
The same resource
that the lion needs.
If push came to show and one
would have to go, it wouldn't be
the wildlife that's bringing in
far too much for this
area of the country.
If they can show you they are
actually fundamental to protect
them in this area and to protect
the lions, well, then it's
the better for them as well.
And what's total population
of lions countrywide?
Tanzania probably has 50%
population for the lion,
so it's important.
And best estimates are that
there are 30,000 lions.
It's not so worrisome the
size but the rapid decrease.
We have lost large predators in
the world but the
world carries on.
There would probably be other
predators to take their place,
the hyenas, cheetahs and
leopards.
Lions are a big show of the
ecosystem that is healthy.
They are important to that.
20, 22 hours of the
day they relax.
So when you see sleeping cats...
Man, they are beautiful.
Just a few miles from the
crater's rim, the village,
about 400 Masai live here.
He's the chief, four wives, 12
children, a handful of woman are
old enough to be out
looking after the herds.
I was born in New Jersey
and live in New York.
Oh.
You have a son in
New Jersey, yeah?
Yes, yes.
He's at one of the colleges
known as Montclair state.
Oh, sure, I know Montclair well.
Near where I grew up.
Oh, yes.
There's going to
be some downpours.
Well, do you think
it comes here?
No.
Not us.
It's funny, like they always
know since there are no
weather reports out here.
They have been migrating with
the season since they came to
this part of Africa sometime in
the 15th century, long, long
before this became
a national park.
Here we run into the kind of
conflict that the world will see
as they value the most.
Parts of nature populated
with magnificent, wild but
aggressively protected animals
were the indigenous people.
So when I came here to start
up here, they were suspicious.
They thought it was going to
lead to us being kicked out.
That's a constant
fear in this area.
Because in the past,
they kill them.
But today we stop that.
Or we can kill.
If you have no
other alternative.
Yeah.
That's why we have a sphere.
We are not harmless people but
it is only for protection only.
The Masai know we are here to
work with them and we hope to
start the lion guardian project,
which basically you hire masais
to protect the lions
rather that kill them.
When all of the cattle the
Masai people have, how do you
protect them from the predators?
If you do not bother them,
they will not bother you.
How about when they are grazing?
When they are grazing, we
have people who follow.
And that's enough to
discourage hyenas or lions?
Yes.
But sometimes they are happy
lion, so they are making it loud
to assure they are happy.
And they make sounds to
know they are happy.
And if they catch something, we
can hear very close,
only like... and stop.
And if it's a loud
that's a happy.
That's happy.
The purring noise,
that's not good.
That is not.
That's not a hear
kitty situation.
That's him looking for food.
Okay.
My cat ♪
okay, this, a lot of you are
going to find very disturbing.
I'm guessing the little goat
over there is about
to get the bad news.
Come now.
I try and be a good guest.
I eat what my hosts
put in front of me.
I try to take responsibility if
something dies for my dinner.
Here?
No, no, here.
So when the chief asks if I'd
care to do the honors and tells
me how it has to be
done, I'm not happy.
In fact, as I close off his air
passages, I'm struggling
to not throw up on myself.
Yeah.
Do you know how to skin?
Maybe I can show you.
Go ahead.
The Masai traditionally kill
their goats by suffocation, for
very good reason, it turns out,
to keep the blood, which is a
vital component for the Masai
diet abundant in
the chest cavity.
Let's prepare to
take the skin out.
Oh, good.
Here now.
Then like this.
More?
Everything's intact, beautiful.
So all the blood... it
filled up the cavity and
started to get coagulated.
Yes.
I get it now.
Easier now to take
the blood out.
See?
I've never seen that.
That's super cool.
Some would like to drink fresh.
Sure.
It's good.
♪
People, they eat this one fresh.
That's kidney.
Yeah.
Just a little piece.
Deed done, it's time
for a little kidney.
Enjoy the spoils, then party.
Sweet, actually, I like them
better like this than cooked.
They're smelling good.
That's great.
Not too much of a meat eater,
but this I kind of like.
♪
Even on the Serengeti, it
ain't barbecue if there ain't
some kind of beer.
Normally the Masai, they have
what you call honey beer.
You drink it just very strong.
Love to try some.
Noticed a palpable
change in the mood.
Welcome.
Asante.
Pretty tasty.
Almost refreshing.
Like a palm wine, kind
of pulpy-like taste.
You can definitely
taste the honey.
Welcome to our culture.
Everyone has to
carry a big knife.
Many aspects of their lifestyle
and traditions remain
unchanged.
Awesome.
This does not mean Masai don't
have cell phones, by the way.
Everybody does.
We are talking about how can
we balance this, because they're
now looking to send our children
to school, getting a good
education, but we still
stay a very strong culture.
So it's really a hard
time, but we continue.
That's another question, when
your son comes back from new
Jersey, you know, is your son
going to want a motorcycle?
Is he going to want a car?
A flat screen TV?
I don't know.
As you know, the children, they
quickly change their mind.
They may one day and
say... I don't know.
It's beautiful, this country,
this part of Africa.
Geographically huge,
but not really.
As the world and what we need to
live in it shrinks every day.
Who gets to live here?
Who or what do we want to see,
is for better or worse
going to determine that.
Nearly $1.5 billion is spent
here every year by people who
come wanting to look mostly
at beautiful animals.
That's an amount that's hard to
argue with, and
impossible to outrun.