I feel completely distraught.
I didn't think we'd
go through with it.
Now it's a lot of uncertainty.
It's a shock.
We're all in deep shit.
Better the devil you
know, than you don't.
It goes on.
I feel it's like the
end of the world.
It feels pretty bad.
It's the ramifications
of it all.
There doesn't seem
to be a plan for
what we're going to do now.
You don't know what to do,
because they're all arguing.
It little woken them, but...
I think human beings
are still stupid and
ego gets in the way.
♪ I took a walk through this ♪
♪ Beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain ♪
♪ On my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good ♪
♪ In this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain ♪
♪ Getting colder ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la, la ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la ♪
♪ Sha la, la, la, la, la ♪
I believe some things to be
true about England, other than
that I know I can always
find friends there.
It's where you can
find some of the best
restaurants in Europe.
It's beautiful.
It's... I don't know...
Sophisticated.
They're old.
They've been around.
But on this last trip,
unexpectedly, the mood in London
became darker, more
uncertain about the future.
The British people
spoke last night.
Brutal wake-up call.
It turns out that it
was about immigration,
that more than half of
Britain's immigration
comes from outside the EU.
It's a disaster, a calamity.
The young are very, very
angry about what's happened
and the gamble that's being
taken with their future.
Few in London, anyway, went to
sleep thinking that England
would leave the European Union.
That was for the rubes, the
people from the sticks,
the country people,
old, white people,
people who felt pushed out,
neglected, disenfranchised
by the new, the young, the
foreign, the decidedly
less-white England of today.
The votes were tallied,
and the majority
had decided to Brexit.
♪ And the RAF of England ♪
The ramifications were unclear,
but the financial markets
plummeted, the nation's
credit rating was downgraded,
the prime minister resigned,
and both political parties'
leadership basically
disintegrated overnight.
♪
In uncertain times, I always
look for the comforting
and the familiar, the
things that always, for me,
made England great,
like one of my favorite
restaurants on Earth,
and one of the chefs
I like and respect most.
This restaurant helped
make a persuasive argument
that there is some kind of
merit -to British cooking.
Yes.
It's absolutely true.
Fergus Henderson, the
most influential chef
of the last two decades,
even though you have likely
never heard of him.
He changed everything.
It seems an instinctive
thing to cook old-school,
simple, proud, English
country cooking.
But it started a
quiet revolution.
St. John, I love you and I
need you now more than ever.
It's about the single
ingredient on the plate,
speaking for itself in that
classic Italian sort of way.
And so you can get lost.
Roast bone marrow with
parsley and caper salad,
sourdough bread made here.
A dish that would become
absolutely iconic.
If you've ever eaten
bone marrow anywhere,
it's very likely because
they did it here first.
My dinner companion is food
critic and author Jay Rayner,
a man never with a
shortage of opinions.
Bones.
Thank you, yes.
Salt.
And there you go It's
a simple, good thing,
but it's one of the most
influential dishes,
like, in the last 20 years.
It's a good thing.
You see his imprint everywhere.
It's true.
And what's interesting
is that the aesthetic
gets passed down in other
ways that you don't expect.
Yeah.
As I've become
older, I've noticed
the food that I yearn for
is food that I react to
in an entirely emotional way.
The problem is that it's
so very, very rare.
I'm looking for a suspension...
No-
-...of logic and reason.
This is something that I got
here from the beginning.
Pickled calves tripe with
radish, shaved carrot,
and watercress.
Lovely.
Wow.
Thank you.
There are some tripe
dishes that are just
uniquely wonderful.
And it's a tricky ingredient.
Once you're cooking it,
it smells like wet dog.
The way we smell things and
taste them is very different.
All the best foods stink.
Yeah.
And it's an extraordinary thing.
These foods, there's a faint
whiff of death about them,
are the ones that remind you
that you're the most alive.
The scent of your own mortality.
Of your own mortality.
Skate poached in court bouillon,
with fennel in green sauce
of fresh parsley,
herbs, and anchovies.
Hmm.
It's nice.
Savory treats -in
the form of kidney.
Oh, the little kidneys.
They're so pretty.
And how were these
kidneys done, sir?
Well, seasoned fair... Nice.
And then put sauce...
P'shh, p'shh!
Sizzling.
Chicken stock...
Butter, p'shh, p'shh.
P'shh, shh, and toast.
Done.
Yes, thank you.
Good, wow.
Eat well.
Thank you.
Pig's head and potato pie.
The head brined, slowly
simmered until tender,
stripped away from the bone,
and seasoned then baked
in pastry with potatoes.
Yes, please.
A traditional dish
that exemplifies
everything I believe in.
Wow.
Nice.
Thank you, sir.
Thank you.
All right.
Oh, look at that.
Great joy.
That's working.
Is this a hot water pastry?
So, it's a puff pastry, but
somehow transfers of fats
through the pig's head out
and the [indistinct] in
makes it so the crust...
It's gorgeous.
Indeed.
Oh, God, that's good.
Extraordinary.
You look at this pie, and it's
almost like something out
of a children's book.
Right.
The pie tradition is
something very, very special.
If you go back in history
to the Hogarth painting,
"The Roast Beef of Old England"...
Yup.
...you'll realize that
actually we were far ahead
of the French in the
preparation of beef
and the roasting of meats.
A lot of it was over our
side of the channel.
Yeah.
Which is no reason for
leaving the European Union.
So they call it Great Britain.
What's great about Britain?
I can refer to a certain literacy
and a wry sense of humor,
and a political tradition of
democracy, which, ironically,
the referendum that's caused
so many of us so much pain
is a perfect example of.
Also, a weirdly cosmopolitan,
welcoming environment
in which the history of
immigration into the country
has defined a far
more open culture.
Until this point I was very,
very proud, but that...
I wouldn't be here.
You know, my great-great
grandparents
arrived as shtetl Jews off
the boat into the East End
of London, and here I
am still to this day,
and that's a very,
very important thing.
A very tolerant country.
This is a very traumatic moment.
Will it all work out in the end?
I have no idea.
- Wow.
- It's the honest truth.
Nothing is certain.
♪
You know what I like?
A good pub.
Like the Princess
Victoria in West London,
and stuff like this.
Did you like pork scratchings?
I do.
Hmm. Cheers.
Oh, that's insanely good.
Maybe you wouldn't think that
the legendary cookbook author
Nigella Lawson and I could
be friends, but we are.
We are, admittedly,
very different.
She is the very definition of
kindness, elegance, grace,
the woman who taught
England to cook.
Nice.
What do you get here ordinarily?
Scotch egg.
All right.
Scotch eggs, please,
and some whitebait.
Certainly.
And some chips.
Whitebait? This is, like, the
greatest thing ever. Really?
Oh, yeah. Whitebait
is so good, isn't it?
In a little pub, you
can get whitebait?
Well, I'm sure in Charles
Dickens' time, they used to have
whitebait then.
Mind you, then, they used
to have oysters too, so...
I can't hear you
over the crunching.
I can't hear myself over
the crunch, actually.
I'll be... I lost interest
in what I was saying.
Whitebait, tiny baby herring
lightly battered whole
and fried, tossed
with a little bit
of lemon juice and salt,
the perfect bar food.
There's this
slightly crisp, huh?
Hmm.
Do you have this in the States?
You're starting to see
them, but almost never.
Beautiful, though, aren't they?
And fat chips, always important.
What is the appropriate
condiment with chips?
Being old-fashioned, I
think vinegar and salt.
If I'm in Brussels or Holland,
I'm fine about mayonnaise,
- but if it's here...
- Oh [indistinct] there,
- I'm with you there.
- Yeah.
And what is it, chips
with curry sauce?
Hmm, fantastic. Sorry.
It's really a matter of how
many Guinnesses you've had.
A soft-boiled egg, wrap
it in minced pork,
then roll it in bread crumbs, and what?
Deep-fry it?
It's like a supernova of
unhealthiness and deliciousness.
This is the important thing,
the softness of the yolk.
Right. Who invented this?
It's just fiendish.
One of the explanations,
Scotch used to preserve eggs
and send them to England.
What would happen is that
they would [indistinct]
Some sort of lime on them,
and it would discolor them,
so they then covered
them to hide that.
This is just right.
When I grew up, they were
very low-rent, very cheap,
rather spooky sausage
meat, rock-hard egg,
that sort of tinge like,
you know, -Uranus.
Right.
Uranus, as they prefer to
call it now because they get
embarrassed.
And then deep-fried into those
cheap red bread crumbs.
And then it got rehabilitated.
Very good eggs, very
good pork meat.
All your basic food groups.
- Hmm.
- These are really good.
Hmm, really good.
Salt and fat, nothing better.
Oh, yeah.
This is nice.
It is nice, strangely calm.
It is an argument from England.
Really?
Yeah.
- If you have a good pub...
- Yes.
...and if you're
gonna have a pint,
this is the perfect time.
It's quiet.
It is.
We can pretend all is
right with the universe.
I'm going to pretend.
England, as the
anti-Brexit forces
found out to their
dismay, ain't London.
It's different out
there and a lot of it
is very, very beautiful.
As we get older, we
start to look backwards
in our life and reflect.
When we're young, we
only look forward,
we don't think of our past.
Our past has such a small value.
I'm of an age now,
we become nostalgic,
we become philosophical.
One can, if a successful gentleman
of many accomplishments,
for instance, with a little
bit of money to spend,
make, as Emerson
advised, your own world
far from the madness.
We're in North Wiltshire, and
there's Bath in the distance.
It's really beautiful.
Oh, yeah, nice view.
You'll see how it
just drifts away.
So that's about five
miles as the crow flies.
There are few chefs who set
the world of chefs aflame
like Marco Pierre White.
As young cooks, looking
at his incredible rise
from working-class
boy to the youngest
three-Michelin-starred chef in
the world, we were inspired,
not just by his
accomplishments and his food,
which were amazing, no
great chef had ever
looked like him before
or talked like him.
We were not, it appeared, alone.
I want to turn Rudloe into a house...
Uhhmm.
...not a hotel, so when you
walk inside, it's personal.
Once obsessed with
nothing but working
the hardest, the
longest, being the best,
Marco has transferred
his obsessive nature
to the more pleasurable task
of making the Rudloe Arms
his perfect place.
What's important
about a restaurant
is the feel, not a look.
You could go to the best
restaurant in the world tomorrow.
They could serve the best food.
But if you don't feel comfortable
within that environment,
you'll never enjoy it.
Inside is as much a project
as the grounds, every detail.
Then you can be yourself.
Number one, environment.
Number two, service.
Number three, food.
A pan-roasted filet of
beef with escargot.
Whoa. It's beautiful.
Who do you want to come here?
People who enjoy themselves.
I like a mixed demographic.
- I wanna have everybody.
- Uh-hmm.
I don't want to just
target one market.
Food should be affordable.
Very, very good.
Has your food always reflected
your aspirations and dreams
rather than where you came from?
I was born and bred on the
outskirts of Leeds in a project
housing estate.
Even though I was born into
very humble beginnings,
I used to cross my road,
walk over the golf course,
and there I was on the
Harewood Estates,
designed by the great Capability
Brown, the stately home
of the Earl of Harewood.
That was my playground.
I was fascinated by
the countryside.
I loved the rivers, the
streams, the brooks,
the fields, the woods.
What was within them,
that's what captured me.
It was a dream.
That was my escapism.
My mother died when I was six.
Mother Nature, she became
my surrogate mother.
And so, therefore, I
have this amazing
love affair with nature.
But look, once you go into
a high-end restaurant,
you're about as far as
from nature as you can be.
I mean, it's hard to
rise up the ranks
of a good fine-dining restaurant,
particularly in the time
that you came up.
Shit was not easy.
Everybody in the kitchen
that I started in came from
a housing project.
They were working-class.
They were tough.
They were hard, really hard.
The flip side of that coin...
was nature.
It was all those beautiful
ingredients, that beautiful
contradiction.
Come see my family.
Piggies! Come on,
piggy, piggy, piggies.
Holy crap.
Come on, piggies!
Piggies! What do you think?
They seemed very well-groomed.
They're beautiful.
Don't eat, that's... those
are jeans, not food.
They give you love
bites, trust me.
Piggies, what do you think about
our friends from America?
- Yeah.
- What breed of pig are these?
These are Oxford
Sandy and Black.
They're a traditional
Wiltshire pig.
In four months, this is
how big they've got.
Wow.
They remember your
voice and your smell.
They're really,
really affectionate.
Naturally, they're woodland.
Indeed, beautiful.
It's almost
self-sustaining here.
Well, we will be for
a bacon [indistinct]
Bye, pigs.
Piggies.
I've never been happier here.
I've found somewhere
I'm really happy.
The legendary classic on
Marco's original menu
back in the day, pig's trotter
a la Pierre Koffmann,
an homage to another
great chef and mentor.
It is perfection.
Oh, my God, that is beautiful.
When I was a young cook, we
would look at photographs
of this dish, my
comrades and colleagues,
and gape at it with wonder.
First we'd say, "Oh, my
God, that's gorgeous,"
and, "How did he do it?"
It just got all of
the textural things
that every great cuisine
around the world
understands to be, "Wow."
Pig's trotter has got 24
bones, so you have to remove
all those bones.
And then you braise
it for four hours.
Right.
It's very simple.
People think it's more
complicated than it is.
I know. This is
tricky... tricky dish.
The hero of the dish,
really, is the skin.
Yes.
It's just one of those
great creations.
As the French say, "We never
grow old around the table."
They also say, "Only the
first bottle is expensive."
Cheers.
♪
So this is my big
project I'm working on
because I've fallen in
love with this little part
of England.
I put myself out to
graze, I suppose,
I'm gonna say I'm retired.
And I like to do what I do here.
If I look at the amount of
nature we have here now,
since we've done what
we've done, it's enormous
- -compared to what we had.
- Right.
And I like seeing the
increase of songbirds,
the hens with their young
chicks, the geese they're my...
Fabulous, aren't they?
Amazing.
They're nuts.
They are beautifully,
beautifully nuts.
There's no guarantees how
long we're gonna be here.
Just enjoy life.
♪
The mood in London is like a
collective nervous breakdown.
Drinking seems appropriate.
But first, a proper base must
be established, some food.
All right.
You have saltfish
callaloo, right?
Yeah.
I'll have some of that
and then vegetable patty.
Saltfish, I think I'll
have one of those.
And the mutton would be good.
This is what happens
when I come off tour.
Straight here, stuff my
face, then half a Guinness,
and then the night is
good, so, you know.
Jamie Hince is half the
creative alliance that makes up
the band The Kills.
Maybe you know them from
such shows as... this one.
And this, Peppers and
Spice in Islington,
is his favorite local
joint for Caribbean food.
I'm enjoying your
currency lately.
It's suddenly become very
affordable since yesterday.
You know, I know.
You know, Britain, we've
got a long history
of taking back control of our
country, you know, getting
in the driving seat again.
And then we get in there and
we just let the handbrake off,
and that's it, you know?
Thank you so much.
I'm extremely hungry.
I'm very excited about this.
Yeah, everything's good.
The best Jamaican this
side of Ocho Rios.
Damn, that's tasty.
I've spent so much time
hanging out with people
where you just eat really
posh, gourmet food,
and when I come off tour, I
just get... start salivating
when I'm on Essex Road.
Uh-hmm.
It is a shame they don't
have a bar here, though.
Right.
You have to drink
a lot, don't you?
I know, it's... -In my job as well...
...hard out.
...people don't think
about that, you know?
How much I have to drink
just to do this.
Bastards.
I mean, they should be
more sensitive to that.
They should be.
♪
It's been one of the nastiest
campaigns, so much lying,
so much dissembling.
Catastrophe.
So far, the reaction
has been, well, chaos.
So, yesterday, prime
minister resigned.
England leaving the
European Union.
Honestly, it kind of makes me feel like...
I don't believe
in democracy anymore.
How quickly the pound is
reacting to political news.
We're entering a very
dark, dangerous period.
Politics where things
are decided by the...
People were talking about, "It's
just dumb having a central"
government in Brussels.
"We've got nothing in common
with people from Romania..."
Right.
"...and Bulgaria."
So, I haven't got anything
in common with people
from Sunderland or Wales, you
know, just like they haven't
got anything in common
with people from London.
When some old people in Great
Yarmouth, get them to decide
the budget.
Give, like, the foreign policy,
get the people from
Sunderland to decide that.
London's a lot different from
the rest of the country.
Right.
It's wealthier, for a start.
It's way more cosmopolitan.
And people complain
about it all the time,
between the people that are
struggling and the people
that are doing well.
What it really shone a
light on is how divided
the country is.
People don't just look at
it as a financial thing.
It's an issue of
cultural identity too.
Citizens who have lived
here for 10, 15 years,
for the first time ever, being
the victims of racial abuse.
Are you evil?
British drinking patterns
seem to be driven
by the fact that pubs
close at, what, midnight.
Yeah.
I noticed, as we approach
last call, people start, like,
doubling up.
The drinking starts to
accelerate in a mad panic.
Load as many in.
Do you think if you extend
the drinking hours,
that it would improve
behavior or make it worse?
I mean, let's face it.
Your countrymen have a bad
reputation as far as...
Drinking.
...sensible... yeah,
sensible drinking.
Do you think that's a function of...
Whatever.
♪
You know, when I was 14,
15, "Fear and Loathing"
came out in Rolling Stone.
I think it was the artwork first
that spoke to me in a
really transformative way.
♪
It captured perfectly all of
my rage, all of the absurdity,
all of these things
that I didn't think
anybody else was seeing or responding to...
Yeah.
...in the same way.
It was unlike anything I'd seen.
Artist, author, icon, Ralph
Steadman, continues to make art
every day.
He was the visual expression of Dr.
Hunter S. Thompson's
finest works.
When Hunter came, 1991,
1992, I brought him
down to the pub here.
"Oh, Martin, this is Hunter."
"Hello."
Here would be Ralph's local,
The Chequers Inn in Kent.
"Hunter, what do you like?"
"Chivas Regal, please."
So I said, "Okay, Martin,
could you make [indistinct]"
That a double?"
Well, these optics, you know,
they've got nothing in them.
They're tiny, little
chiclet-size, yeah.
So did that twice with it, put
it down in front of Hunter.
Hunter looked at it and he
said, "What's that, a sample?"
Where are you from originally?
Well, I am Welsh.
My mother, she was Gwenny
Rogers from Rhosllanerchrugog.
Uh-huh, don't ask
me to spell that.
No, I can't even do it myself.
So how English do you feel,
given that you grew up
in Wales?
Well, in a way, you know, it
was not far from Liverpool.
The food is pub fare, a
runny egg wrapped in
Parma ham and breadcrumbs,
prawn cocktail for the man.
I think, it was the Scanlan's
article the first you worked
with Hunter Thompson?
Kentucky Derby?
Yeah.
Wait, before that, would
you say that you were
a respectable figure, making
a living doing your work?
Because you kind of were
transformed very quickly into a
counter-cultural figure.
I think a lot of people
will, appropriately or not,
see you as an outlaw artist.
Yeah, but I didn't start off
wanting to be an artist.
I wanted to be an
aircraft engineer.
I didn't like factory life,
but I had to go every week
to do technical drawing,
and that's where the lines
and circles began.
Right.
I've been doing a book
called "Critical Critters:"
The Beastly Sneers and Callous
Observations by Ceri Levy."
He's writing about the thing.
Articulated bum lice?
Yeah. Oh, yeah.
I don't know whether
they exist, but... Well,
I'm pretty sure they do...
What?
Yeah, I'm pretty sure they do.
Really?
Some sort... there's
definitely bum-seeking insects
that I've encountered,
they [indistinct]
He thinks that I'm obsessed
with things to do with,
you know, lavatorial humor.
That's kind of an English thing.
Is it?
I saw an advert, "You,
too, can learn to draw"
and earn pounds."
I took the course while I
was doing military service.
I was drawing the guys in
the billet playing cards,
blankets on the bed,
boots in the bed.
Very simplistic stuff.
Nevertheless, it got me started.
And have you heard
of an echidna?
I have not.
This is a hedgehog
type of creature.
There aren't many of
these left, you know.
They reach critical stages.
And this is going in,
too, 'cause, "Excuse me",
we're collecting from
endangered species."
We can all learn
to do this first.
- Not this...
- Right.
But this.
That is very difficult.
I don't think I can do that.
I'm quite sure I can't.
My basic motor skills
are not so good.
Here, you got fish and chips.
Oh, blimey.
More old-school on
the main courses.
Fish and chips with
mushy peas over there,
Steak and Stilton pie for me,
because any mystery meat
wrapped in pastry at a pub
is pure crack for me.
Thank you very much.
Oh, you've got the pie, wow.
Oh, yeah.
Hmm.
We don't do this
back in America.
So many people have said to me,
"Do you pencil it in first?"
I said, "No, you
just start drawing."
"But don't you make a mistake?"
I said, "There's no such
thing as a mistake."
A mistake is an opportunity
to do something else.
You have to leave it and let
nature take its course.
Oh, my God, now,
isn't that lovely?
That is... I like... I'm
impressing myself.
It's so good.
All of nature is
impressing me, actually.
That it's just so
wonderful how it works.
It's a kind of natural process
of evolution, isn't it?
It's what we're
doing all the time.
You're certainly your
depiction of politicians
early on. You seemed filled
with rage and disgust,
deservedly, I'd think.
And there were some epic
depictions of Nixon.
Was it Nixon as Godzilla,
was it, that I...
Yeah, he was a great subject.
I mean, I've done him as a
flying Nixon, a vampire Nixon,
bat Nixon... Did you ever
get an official reaction
to your work from
the White House?
Never.
"I am not a giant,
shitting Godzilla."
You don't wanna deny that.
No, it's funny how that was.
And Boris Johnson here.
I think the hair, in
this case, is just...
It's an irresistible impulse.
Well, to do it, I... I've
got to come out
with it more [indistinct]
But it's perfect.
Boris is our Trump.
Well, they're both...
It is a supernova
of incredibly bad hair.
Yeah.
I mean, the two of them together...
What's happening? What's
going on in this country?
Is it gonna be okay?
Not at the moment, no.
Does it say anything about
the country as a whole?
So, I think it does.
Perhaps there's been a
secret desire to really say,
"Wait a minute, what would
it be like to be on a...
The... a great British
Isles again?"
I was doing this last week just
because I can't stand
snakes, so I said,
"Okay, I'll do you one."
I did one snake last week,
decided to do this,
Saint Lucia racer snake.
Ugh, right there.
And then the next day,
we had the referendum.
Friday morning, when people
realized what had happened,
there was a terrible gloom.
There's a scent I...
We all felt it.
This desire to restore
England to its former glory
as the British Isles, it's
certainly given a revived,
a very powerful urge in Scotland...
to reconsider whether
they wanna be a part.
Oh, dear. I think it's
only gonna get worse
- -before it gets better.
- Uh-hmm.
And I'm certain that what we
are experiencing at the moment
is a kind of rather large
hangover from something
that we've still got to come
to terms with and get over.
Do you think some of your
stuff has anger in there,
or exasperation, or...
That's... I think so... look,
I said to... I don't know,
50 years ago that I wanted
to change the world, and
I think, 50 years later,
I succeeded.
It's worse now than it was when
I started, so I changed it,
being that was... This is great.
It's kind of emerging.
You know, it's coming.
I mean, this guy, he
demands a Steadman.
He really... -Something... -He
was born to have you work...
I try to lighten it up a bit.
The sea.
The sea, where a man
can forget his trouble
and the troubles of the
world, commune with something
infinitely larger and more
powerful than himself.
Where he could find himself
locked in an epic struggle
with a creature of the sea,
plumbing the depths for that
most primordial of needs:
food.
Well, let's hope we
have them quick.
Get off, get off.
Oh, my God, there's
the forehook, look.
Oh, my God.
Not good.
Oh, my God, it got the bait.
Nature, it's overrated.
We're in the middle of
the English Channel.
We are designed to find,
kill, tear apart,
and devour the food
we need to survive.
It is why God, in His
wisdom, gave us legs upon
which to run, eyes in
the front of our heads
to seek out prey,
fingernails and thumbs
with which to tear
apart our victims,
teeth to smash flesh and bone
between our mighty jaws.
♪
Here in the coastal
town of Weymouth
at the Marlboro is
where I'll be smashing
deep-fried haddock
between my freaking jaws
with something called a chip.
Sliced white bread and butter
so we can make a chip butty.
Would you like a chip butty?
I don't know that
I've ever had one.
- I've heard of them.
- Delicious.
All right, you're an
easy man to please.
The chef suggests the mushy peas
infused with butter and cream.
I have such fond
memories of Weymouth.
My sons went to school
just down the road.
I used to bring them to the
Marlboro for lunch and that.
And they weren't big
fans of fish and chips
because they were, sort of, 13,
14 and they preferred meat
to fish and chips.
But this is the best restaurant,
in my opinion, in Weymouth.
Thank you.
Thank you, thank you,
that's very kind.
I'll put the mushy
peas in the middle.
You see, this is how
we do it in Yorkshire.
So go ahead and taste the
mushy peas without vinegar.
Bon appétit.
They're all right.
Now, put the vinegar on.
Oh, my... So working-class,
as they say in Yorkshire.
Mmm.
Would you prefer
them with vinegar?
It transforms the whole thing.
Completely different, isn't it?
I love buttering my bread.
Now, this is the best bit.
I can't believe you've
never had a chip butty.
Well, today's the day.
When I was a kid, this
was one of my favorites.
The only fish I ever ate as
a child was fried haddock.
Wouldn't eat any other fish.
And then the vinegar,
quite generous.
And then the salt.
And this is what we call a
chip butty in Yorkshire
where I come from.
Mmm.
I like the cheap bread
because the bread turns
into the same texture
as the potato.
Right.
That's why it's perfect.
If you have posh bread
or crusty bread, -Right.
...it's not the same.
How's your haddock?
Good.
But it's proper working-class
food, is fish and chips.
Yeah, when I was a kid,
we'd eat them twice a week.
They'd cook fish and chips in
dripping, -beef fat, not oil.
Uh-hmm.
It makes a massive, massive
difference in the flavor.
Yeah.
It's quite good.
You were hungry.
We worked hard out there.
Keeping warm.
Indeed.
It's big.
It's too big, look, I'm done.
One more bite, yeah, me too.
That's my problem.
I go for the chip butty
before the fish.
It's the child within me.
Hidden away safely behind
the walls of a former
Victorian-era schoolhouse,
insulated from the moronic
inferno blazing outside,
is Rochelle Canteen,
a green idyll, the
unpretentious brainchild
of Margot Henderson and
her business partner
Melanie Arnold.
How long have you been
up and running here?
Ten years.
- God, I can't believe...
- Ten years, where have you been?
I know, what is wrong with me?
You were a chef
before Fergus, yes?
Yeah. Well, I started
cooking in restaurants
- -when I was 12.
- Yeah.
But this is Fergus,
peas in their pods.
We met when I was
working at the Eagle,
and I said straightaway
to him, "We should open"
a restaurant together."
And he said, "Well,
that's a good idea",
but let's be lovers as well,"
which I always thought
was quite good.
And then we had a restaurant.
The whole area has
changed down to it.
It's very Shoreditch,
groovy guys on little
motorbikes with handlebars.
What was the neighborhood
like before?
Quite a large Bengali community.
Before that, it was quite a
strong Jewish community.
But then they moved out,
next group move in.
It's a poor area.
A lot of people working in the
fabric, clothing industries.
The bandstand in the middle is
all the rubble from the war.
I think the gardeners
still find, you know,
children's shoes and things.
Really?
It is a very interesting area.
Just how beautiful
these blocks are.
It's quite a lot
of building works
- -going on at the moment as well.
- Everywhere in London.
I mean, the whole city seems
to be, kind of, transforming.
It's certainly expensive...
My daughter, she's moving
because of what happened
today about the EU.
She's going to either live
in Scotland or New Zealand.
And she's so embarrassed
and ashamed to be English.
Is it the end of the world?
It feels... right now, it feels
like the end of the world.
We have separated.
We're a little mean
island saying,
"When the going gets
tough, we want to get out
and just look after ourselves."
It's so selfish and disgusting.
It's also, out of London,
there is a lot of people
who are really struggling
and have lost their way
and don't believe in what
the government has done.
So, I don't blame
the people either.
But they're being fed, sort
of, lies, I would say.
Anyway, it's all too depressing.
We must change the subject.
Vitello tonnato, cold-roasted
veal thinly sliced
and covered with a creamy
sauce of tuna and capers.
Oh, this looks good.
These are good.
Hmm.
So, what's going right?
I mean, it's a bad day to ask.
Well, there's lots of great
restaurants opening in the city.
Right, London, and
UK in general.
It's just gotten just better
and better every year, right.
It's brilliant, isn't it?
It's so exciting.
Great chefs... The
people who voted "for,"
was it a sense of people
who feel they just...
They've been screwed?
I mean, young people,
unemployment in the north,
it's dire.
Right.
People haven't got jobs.
But, I mean, everyone's
looking for chefs.
Right.
Why we should turn... We should
set up some great big new
cookery schools in Britain.
I mean, no one can get
enough decent chef.
- Uh-hmm.
- Some more encouragement.
I mean, there is work to be had.
But it's just how you find
it and where you come from.
Lamb chops with lentils
and green sauce.
Hmm, so good.
Where'd this little
lamb come from?
From Wales, Welsh lamb.
Nice. People who dine out now,
do they want food simpler
and more stripped down,
and with less bullshit,
or do you think it's
going the other way?
Simple, but with
a sort of twist.
That have got a story about
where it's come from.
- Right.
- It's very interesting.
You know, they're all
coming up with new dishes.
Should I be buying pounds now with...
No, that's what
I kept thinking.
What do we all do now?
If I were a cruelly
cynical, exploitative...
That little [indistinct]
You know... what would I...
What would I be doing?
Are you selling
or you're buying?
Yeah, I don't... I'm [indistinct]
Look at me, master
of high finance.
You look so well.
Well, thank you.
You must be...
You're making me feel
much better without them.
This meal and the
wine, I have to say,
your company has made me feel
much better about the world
and myself.
Can you reinvent yourself
in England or in London...
I mean, maybe you can.
I'm sure you can.
But people are obsessed
with class here.
Still, really?
Yes, yeah, absolutely.
It's our measure
of authenticity.
So people are always
trying to bust people.
"He's a toff!"
you know.
What is a toff?
An aristocrat, yeah.
Aristocrat? Right.
My friend Adrian wrote a book
called "The Angry Isle,"
and he talks about how
the British are famous
for being polite, apologizing
a lot, but that that actually
masks a deep anger.
Do you think there's any
truth to that at all?
Well, I think... because
I've been spending
a lot of time in California,
which is, you know...
And so when you... when
you come to London...
If you come to London for
a month, you won't make
any friends, and you probably
won't find anywhere to go,
- but after that, the best people
- you've ever met in your life.
When I went to LA, that first
month, I was so popular.
Everyone's... I started,
like, six bands, and then,
nothing comes of it.
There's a kind of real first
impression thing... -Right
...that doesn't go anywhere.
In London, it's just get
it done and deal with it.
Right.
Well, hey!
See, here we go.
We're closing, closing.
[indistinct] closing...
Get [indistinct] some.
Staggering news is
now sinking in.
Markets are giving
a brutal reaction.
When the world seems like
it's spinning out of control,
and the inside of your skull
feels like it's being gnawed on
by angry wolverines.
The sun has risen on a
completely different UK
and a completely different EU.
When you wake up still
tasting tequila,
feeling shame, fear, and
regret in equal measures,
it's good to have a friend...
Europe's weaker,
Britain's divided,
where do we go now?
...who, without judgment, gives
you a shoulder to cry on
and maybe a simple good thing,
like some eggs and sympathy.
I'm horribly and
savagely hungover.
That's very unlike you.
I was feeling shame, and
regret, -and mourning...
Yeah, you're not the only one.
Don't know what's happening.
Okay, I'm gonna give you
some eggs in Purgatory.
Why Purgatory?
Because they're in chili
sauce and tomatoes,
special hangover cure.
I know you need it.
I... yes.
Now, do you know about the
delicacy -of fried slice?
No.
English delicacy which is
like British bruschetta,
you fry plastic bread.
Uh-hmm.
I've got some really
good beef dripping.
Kind of magical.
Pure grease.
It's a... I... that's what
I need right now.
Yeah.
I think that's how
everyone felt a bit
after the referendum too.
I think there's something
very strange about you
because you look normal but
it's all going on inside.
Yes, you have got a slight
pleading look in your eyes.
I do. It's a... Okay, the
whole point of this is,
the plastic bread
soaks in all the fat.
Right.
So when you eat it, it bursts
with grease in your mouth.
It's that good.
I like the noise.
Here, I'm gonna give it to you.
It may still be a bit
runny I like runny.
I need runny today.
Okay.
Just try a bit dry first, so
you can just get the fats
going into your mouth.
Hmm.
There is light and hope
in the universe again.
- Thank you.
- That's what I aim to provide.
Spice, runny eggs, and
grease, just what I needed.
Hmm, so good.
I have something absolvent.
You know that thing in "The
Simpsons" once when he wants
to put on weight so he
doesn't have to go to work?
And he allows himself to eat
things that when you rub it
on something it makes it
go see-through, like that.
"Your window to weight gain."
Yes, here, here,
just make this turn
see-through now if you want.
I can see myself in
about six months.
I do feel quite pleased
that we can be
a corrupting influence.
That's something that
we can be proud of.
These are frightening
times for many.
The world is changing,
and there is no stopping
those changes.
But in such times, there
are always two ways to go,
run and hide, build walls,
cower in fear and suspicion,
point the finger at our
neighbors, look, like desperate,
frightened people do,
for someone to blame,
or stand up and try... at least
try to build a better world,
to look for, instead of a
man on a horse to save us
or a wall to keep us apart,
to our better angels.