Let us take you now...
To the island of short memories
and the small village
of fat hopes.
It hardly featured on any map.
But, thanks to the civil war
of lies,
the small village
of fat hopes had grown
in importance
for all the wrong reasons.
They spoke in color
in the village
as they did in most parts
of the country.
The cost of living
made people purple.
People often felt marooned,
and the jokes were always black.
♪ I took a walk
through this beautiful world ♪
♪ Felt the cool rain
on my shoulder ♪
♪ Found something good
in this beautiful world ♪
♪ I felt the rain
getting colder ♪
♪ Sha la la la la
Sha la la la la la ♪
♪ Sha la la la la la
The war is over.
At the old hotel,
the 50 caliber
in the tower next door
is wrapped up and attended
by one sleepy guard.
The main enemy today
is not the soldiers,
guerillas, fighters, and
suicide bombers of the LTTE
but the black crows
who hover ominously
over the breakfast buffet
on the veranda.
A man with a slingshot
patrols the lawn,
driving them away
with an occasional shot.
Colombo, capital city
of Sri Lanka.
Unlike the last time I came here
nearly a decade ago,
this South Asian island nation
of 20 million
does not feel on lockdown.
There are no longer
the military checkpoints
and heavy equipment,
sandbags or barbed wire
in between the airport
and the center of town.
There's a new democratically
elected government
voted in by a coalition
of former adversaries.
Everywhere you look,
construction, expansion,
new hotels, foreign money,
something that looks
a lot like hope.
Hundreds of thousands
of dead and missing later,
the country is at peace,
and we can go where we want.
Hopefully, people will be able
to talk about their lives.
Last time, they couldn't.
So this is the Galle Face Green.
It used to be a place
for the English families
to come and hang out on Sundays.
And it was also the home
of the first golf course
in Sri Lanka.
This is our Central Park.
Ah.
What are we eating today
by the way? What's good here?
So this is all
Sri Lankan street food.
These kitchens are run
by Muslims.
So, there's no pork dishes.
A lot of seafood.
Dharshan runs several
popular Colombo restaurants,
including The Ministry of Crab.
When not catering
to the needs of his customers,
he enjoys simpler fare.
♪
So what distinguishes
Sri Lankan cuisine and Indian?
I think our curries are lighter,
and I think it's the access
to seafood.
If you look at Mumbai,
it's 20 million people.
The ocean's under pressure.
Here it's so clean
we can have access
to great seafood any time.
When did the war get bad?
It got really bad
I think 2005 onwards,
it was really bad.
Yeah, we were last here
in 2008.
I mean, just to get
to the hotel,
I remember, from the airport
we had to go through
one security cordon
after another.
During those times,
we had no idea
when it was going to end.
I've done business
in this country
never knowing what
a peaceful time would be.
How long have things been quiet?
Well, the war ended in 2009.
It's been eight years.
It takes time for things
to happen.
Things have happened though.
The city's not overgrown.
We aren't overpopulated.
The oceans are still clean.
Whatever the underlying
problems were,
do you think they are
being addressed
or will be addressed?
I think they are
being addressed.
Maybe a bit slow.
But I think you will
find a difference.
So the world has changed,
and it's great to see
stuff like this.
♪
Evening fell
upon the small village
of fat hopes.
Suddenly, they heard a noise
that filled them with dread.
Ah! Ah!
There was honestly
such a culture of fear.
An incredible amount
of self-censorship.
We had death squads,
people, journalists,
so many being disappeared.
This kind of white van
phenomenon
where, you know, your loved
ones were taken from you
and you never heard
from them again.
They're still so many
of those cases going on,
and just a real feeling of fear.
From 1983 until 2009,
Sri Lanka's bloody civil war
divided the island in two,
splitting the country
along religious lines...
Buddhist Sinhalese majority
in the South
versus Hindu Tamil minority
in the North.
Years of mistreatment
and suppression
led to the formation
of the LTTE,
or Liberation Tamil Tigers
of Eelam
and their campaign to seek
an independent state.
The conflict ended in 2009,
but an enormous number of
internally displaced persons,
or IDPs as they were
referred to,
remain in refugee camps.
Ladies and gentlemen,
appearing now
and before it is too late,
the traveling circus
of refugees.
Colombo native Tracy
Holsinger is the founder
of Mind Adventures
Theatre Company.
Not long ago,
to even talk politics
let alone stage a play
deemed controversial,
could be dangerous.
The play that you've been doing
came from a book or...
"Speaks in Numbers"
by Mike Masilamani.
It was first performed
in November 2009.
- Controversial would you say?
- A little.
The play is about
internally displaced people.
After the end of the war,
we had over 300,000 people
in camps.
The largest one of them
was built to house
100,000 people
but ended up housing
227,000 people.
Tents that were designed for
maybe five people to be in
had 10 to 15 people in them.
There were no toilets
in the camp.
There were just these big pits.
Living conditions
for these people
was intolerable.
There are some communities,
Anthony, in this country
that have been displaced
for 25 years.
That means since the '80s
they haven't had a home.
Hurry up!
Don't waste my time.
What's in the bag?
It's just some-
- Can't take anything
inside the camp.
Search this.
Hurry up, next!
It's a play that was staged
at a time
when all this was so raw for us.
And there is no way
to speak directly
about what happened.
I think it's still
very difficult
not just for us
but for people to acknowledge
that these terrible things
were done
to part of our community
and our people.
Was this a perilous thing to do?
And how was it seen at the time?
You know, I didn't think
about whether it was
perilous or not,
and that's probably bad on me
because I involved
all these other people.
That scene is done.
We're moving on.
For me, the important thing
was making sure
that in whatever form
it got out there
the play's out there
and it reminds people
that this happened.
We found the person responsible
for trying to poison the minds
of all you good people
with these lies!
She was sleeping amongst you.
Living amongst you.
And there are many others
like her.
Let this be a lesson to you all.
This is how we deal
with traitors.
Take her away!
No, please, please.
- No!
- Please!
So, are things getting better?
I would say in one sense
we're not so afraid.
You're not afraid to speak out.
But also I wouldn't say
everything is wonderful.
It's not... I think things
are slowly being pushed,
but it's too slow.
So, 20 years from now,
are you optimistic, pessimistic?
What do you think?
Sri Lanka,
formerly known as Ceylon,
was once the crown jewel
of the spice trade.
Its cloves, cardamom,
pepper, nutmeg,
mace, ginger, cinnamon,
chilies, and curry...
...the envy of the world.
These spices built empires.
Wow.
- Chicken curry.
- Marvelous.
Then you have potatoes
that are spicy.
- Right.
- Then you have the beets.
This is one of the traditional
samples of Sri Lanka.
Right.
Kumar Lopez is a Tamil
who works for the Sri Lankan
Press Institute.
We sit down for lunch at
a local rice and curry joint.
So, last time I was here
was nine years ago.
Things have changed a lot.
I think, yes.
I think the fact that
we're able to eat today
without even thinking
that there could be a bomb
that could go off at any moment
is the best peace
that you could expect.
But I believe that peace
can go to another stage,
another level.
In the mindset of those
who have been impacted
by the war,
I think there needs to be
further work to be done.
After World War II,
the British left Sri Lanka.
Over time, the Buddhist
Sinhalese majority
both excluded and repressed
the mostly Hindu Tamil minority
channeling populist fervor
to turn discrimination into law.
What is the generally accepted
underlying reasons
for the conflict
in the first place?
The main cause
or the main objective
was to have a separate land
for the Tamils.
The underlying reason
for that being
there was discrimination,
there was racism,
and that basically brought them
to this stage.
By 1983, the situation
reached its boiling point.
The LTTE began waging
what would become
a 25-year guerilla war
before government forces
crushed them
in a brutal final offensive.
I mean, the war was won
militarily.
Is everybody speaking now?
I think the underlying objective
is definitely to bring about
lasting peace.
They actually encouraged
some of the [indistinct]
To invest in the market
to give job opportunities.
So, peace is something
that everybody is looking for.
So, I'll be taking
the train to Jaffna shortly.
This is a big deal.
Oh, it wasn't running
probably for the last 30 years.
Whoa, whoa, it hasn't
been running for 30 years?
Right, not been running
a minimum of 20 years.
- Because of the conflict?
- Because of the conflict.
Wow.
With the war over,
Sri Lankans can now travel
freely across their country
all the way north to Jaffna.
Last time, we couldn't go there.
Today, we will.
Early morning, Colombo Station.
The platform's bustle
is a mix of commuters,
long distance travelers,
and the occasional tourist.
Breaking free from Colombo's
gravitational pull,
the landscape opens up.
The second and third class
compartments
host a mix of people, smells,
and slices of life.
Commuters get on at one station,
off at another.
Others like me
are in for the long haul,
ten hours to Jaffna.
That the Jaffna Queen
runs at all
is a symbolic move
towards reunification.
As the fight for an
independent Tamil state
in Sri Lanka's north
intensified,
the LTTE destroyed these tracks.
For the last two decades
of the war,
Jaffna was all but cut off
from the rest of the world.
♪
The LTTE, unable to match
the military might
of the Sri Lankan Army,
fought their war by other means,
every means
they deemed necessary.
Acts of terrorism,
suicide bombings,
political assassinations
brought government retaliation.
And collective punishment
of an equally terrible kind
and enormous in scale.
The North suffered
massive bombardments
of civilian areas.
Hundreds of thousands of Tamils
ended up in refugee camps.
By the time it was over,
war crimes had been committed
on both sides,
those caught in the middle
paying the ultimate toll.
In the final weeks alone,
at least 40,000 people
were killed
in a war the outside world
knew little of.
Nearing the end of the line,
weary passengers awake
to find themselves
in a different world.
Out the window, the air is thick
with the smell of salt and sea.
Jaffna is about as far north
as you can go
without hitting India.
This is the homeland
of Sri Lanka's
Tamil ethnic minority
and during the civil war
base of the LTTE Tamil Tigers.
Remnants of the conflict
are hard to miss.
But on any given day
down by the coast,
the fish market buzzes,
a hive of activity and commerce.
Fresh product comes in,
deals are made,
money changes hands,
life goes on.
Initially before the war,
the North and East
contributed 40% of the GDP.
- And now?
- Three percent.
There were so many
industries here.
Everything was destroyed.
There was no electricity
for a long time.
I had a coconut farm,
about 100 acres,
and it was completely destroyed
during the war.
There's not even a single tree
with a bullet hole.
Like many Sri Lankan Tamils,
Janna was born here
but with considerable regret
spent much of his life abroad.
The fighting has stopped.
Absolutely, that's true.
What's changed?
A lot of things
have been rebuilt.
Slowly now they are focusing
on rebuilding infrastructures.
They are renovating
all these ponds
and lagoons,
and now slowly business
is thriving
in this part of the country.
The underlying discontent,
the given reasons for the war,
is there a sense that
those problems
are being addressed?
The war was very brutal,
and people after 30 years
everybody's tired of it.
We have a very affected
population.
There are about
30,000 war widows
and close to 25,000
orphaned children,
about 15,000 people
who were landmine victims.
From the government side,
they are still a bit scared
that there may be
war popping up again.
But slowly now they are
addressing issues
like employment-wise,
opportunities-wise,
and there are a lot
of occupied lands.
Now they are slowly
giving it back.
So, hopeful?
Yeah, I see the progress.
What I see here
is the human resilience,
like after going through
this war for 30 years,
how quickly people here
can rebuild.
So, what's happening today?
First of all, where are we?
This is a Kali temple.
And Kali is?
Kali is the destroyer of evil.
People go and pray
and have Kali temples
in villages
because it destroys evil power.
Both good and bad?
- Yes.
- Protector?
- Protector, destroyer, yes.
- Destroyer.
Because Kali's also known
for courage and valor.
Like when people go to war
and things like that,
they go and pray to Kali
to give them the confidence
and the courage
to go and fight.
After decades of
cultural suppression,
Tamils take great pride
in their customs,
traditions
and religious festivals.
Around here, the Madai Festival
is the most auspicious day
of the year
for Hindus to balance
their spiritual debts.
Believers show devotion
through suffering,
enduring acts
of great pain and hardship
called kavadis
or the burden debts.
Kavadis can take many forms.
You can make a pilgrimage
to the main temple
on shoes made of nails.
Or roll there on the ground
often for a distance
of several kilometers.
These are some of the ways
believers express gratitude
to Kali
or implore her for help.
Ritualistic body piercing
is another such expression.
It's a very interesting thing.
They prepare for a long time...
28 days, they fast.
And they condition themselves
mentally.
And when they come
to the temple,
and there's a special ceremony
which takes place.
And they kind of chant
and play drums and everything,
so you get into a trance.
The greater the pain,
the greater your dedication
to your higher power.
Well, let's just say
viewer discretion is advised.
The islands off Jaffna's coast
were holdouts during
the Tamil resistance
and saw heavy fighting.
The people who remained,
like the landscape itself,
bear heavy scars.
This was a conflict that left
more than 80,000 women widowed.
The whole island is very quiet.
You do not see shops
filled with people
or children playing in yards
or people in fields.
It felt very, very, very quiet.
Is that a good quiet
or a bad quiet?
It's an area that has been
severely depopulated
as you would have noticed
when you came here.
Now, when you say depopulated,
people fled, people were killed,
people were disappeared.
Within three hours in 1991,
the entire area was evacuated
of its population.
People have only started
coming back
to live here
relatively recently.
A very small percentage
of the original population
that has come back.
In Tamil society
as in much of the world,
women have few rights,
no official system
to look after or support them.
The North Ceylon
Community Project
seeks to address that problem
providing a home and training
for women
who might otherwise
be living on the street.
Guari is from this area
and one of the organization's
benefactors.
Culturally, a woman
who's a widow
who has lost her husband
is a total social outcast
and becomes terribly vulnerable
to all other types of abuse
because they have no source
of income.
They have no one
to protect them,
no one to look after them.
So this organization has grown
to be a safe haven.
Now, you provide
food, shelter, job training,
some road
to financial independence?
When they come here,
they are given a place to stay.
There also is a group of them
who come here for daily work.
And there are different projects
that are skills training
projects for the women.
Within this space, they're
given the strength, the skills,
and the opportunities
to change their lives.
So, why stay? I mean,
it's an obvious question.
So many have left.
Why stay here?
Where you come from
is very important.
So I think in this culture
it is about where your
roots are,
where your family history is.
What about these kids?
When they're 16, 17, 18.
They are going to finish
their education,
and then they're going
to be looking for jobs.
And those jobs are not
materializing in these areas.
So, in the past
a number of young people
would find ways and means,
often very risky ways and means,
to leave Sri Lanka
and go abroad.
So, unless there is
some really serious efforts
to revive economic activities
and investment,
life is going to be
very tough for these kids.
Ask anyone in Sri Lanka
where to find the best food,
and they'll say "Nobody cooks
as well as Auntie."
And it's true... trust me.
Often possessing
the strength of ten men,
Sri Lankan aunties are a force
to be reckoned with.
Jaffna crab curry
might be, for me anyway,
the holy grail
of Sri Lankan cuisine.
Spicy and fiery,
in a cuisine known for being
spicy and fiery already.
During the war years,
it was hard to get crabs
like this and still is today,
the majority being exported
to other parts of the country
and abroad.
But, in this time capsule
of a home,
it might as well still be 1953.
I've been invited here
by Dr. Ravi,
his sister, Giva,
and their beloved auntie,
best cook in the family.
So there we have it.
Welcome to Jaffna.
Welcome to paradise.
Thank you. Thank you.
These are delicious, by the way.
- They're great, aren't they?
- Wow. Are they toasted?
They're dipped in yogurt,
dried, sun-dried.
Wow. This is
a beautiful home.
Thank you very much.
Built in the '30s?
In the '30s
or late British period.
How is it that this
remained in the family
that you were able to hang on
and you're still here?
During the war,
the Tigers lived here,
and then the Sri Lankan Army
lived here for a little while.
My father kept coming back here
making sure he made
his presence known.
I think the thing is
that it was...
It has a lot of,
you know, family stories.
So, even a lot of my cousins
have a great attachment
to this house.
Can I get you some more
crab curry?
Please, thank you.
Thank you, so beautiful.
Thank you.
So delicious.
I've been to a lot of places
just after really awful,
awful conflicts.
Some nations, there's
a simmering and boiling sense
of injustice, rage, humiliation,
particularly when you have
large groups of young people
unemployed, wandering around.
Do you think there's
any possibility
that if everybody doesn't
get the recipe right
that we could see
another generation
of adversaries?
Generally speaking,
people want to get along
because my generation,
they certainly don't want
to go back to...
- To that.
♪
I think the generation
that might
are the five, six year olds
at school now
who have forgotten the horrors.
You go back to AK-47,
my six months in the sun.
I think I am optimistic,
but I think that
one of the first things
that we need to build on now
is to build a trust
amongst the people.
There are lots of IDPs still
still in camps,
and they could be given back
their lands
that might be useful
to also jump start the economy.
It should be a paradise, yes.
I mean, look out the window.
- Yeah.
- The potential is incredible.
♪
So, 20 years from now,
are you optimistic
or pessimistic?
What do you think?
You have to be optimistic.
You have to be.
Empathy is everything.
It's part of what
makes us human.
That's what... there's where
we have to connect
and understand each other.
It's all very idealistic,
I know that.
For some people,
the hurts are too deep.
it's too late for forgiveness
or trust.
You know, you have, for example,
communities that have
been displaced
13 times over the past 25 years.
That's what you call
a breeding ground for...
- Trouble, yeah.
- For trouble.
Sri Lanka has been through
and endured a lot,
far more than most.
It's a lot to ask of any place
to put aside such things
as hate, fear,
a desire for revenge.
It might still be too much,
but there is indeed,
it appears, reason to hope.
- Hi, Tony.
- How you doing, man?
- Nice to meet you.
This looks like grouper?
Yeah.
You put it on banana leaf,
is it?
Yeah, that's right, yeah.
Any fishermen here?
Yeah, they're all fishermen.
Okay, so what happened
during the war? Could you fish?
- Yes.
- Straight through?
They only have
to get the permission.
Then they're limited
for one kilometer.
Did people feel safe
anywhere to do what they did?
Anytime nobody feels.
Curfew was installed here.
Four o'clock,
and you can be shot.
These people have
to make a living.
They have to catch fish
to feed their home,
feed their families.
So they have to go.
- Oh.
- All right, what's up, bro?
What's up, young man?
Most of the world
when you've been through
a struggle like this,
so painful and so vicious,
usually at the end of the day
people cannot say,
"Look, I'm exhausted."
Nobody wins here.
We all want to live in a world
where we can take care
of our children.
Are we at that point
in Sri Lanka?
Just now, people never beg,
but they will fight.
Please look at the future.
Don't let the young people
go take up arms.
Invest, develop,
give them some guidance,
these people that ran a war.
These guys have torpedoes,
submarines.
Ingenuity.
They were all so keen
about destroying the world,
terrorism, destroying terrorism.
They never value the strength
of the people.
- Really?
- Yeah.
Is that how this ends?
- That's the story.
- It's a little depressing, no?
- How about a message of hope.
- Yes, yes, yes.
Come on, let's talk about it.
Okay, all right,
and then one day
the civil war of lies
came to an abrupt end.
Yay!
Harsh question:
Why should Americans
watching this,
why should we give a shit?
Why should people care
about Sri Lanka?
I guess...
I don't know why Americans
should care.
I just want Sri Lankans to care.
This story has to go on,
and for it to go on
we have to have some hope.
Citizens were asked
for what they most desired.
And that is how peace came
to the island of short memory.
The warring parties
fast realized
that it didn't matter who won
or who lost
because in the end
they were all on the same side.
So it's been eight or nine years
since I've been
to this beautiful country
filled with lovely people,
incredible food.
Sri Lanka.
♪
Last time I was here...
Let's put it this way,
we couldn't see too much
of the place.
We were here in the middle
of one of most vicious,
unrestrained conflicts
you could imagine.
Well, the war is over.
What is Sri Lanka like now?
♪
Ladies and gentlemen,
appearing now
and before it is too late,
the traveling circus
of refugees.
My name is Tracy Holsinger.
I'm a theatre director.
I started a theatre company
in 1999
called Mind Adventures.
When I was 16 years old,
my first theatre teacher
was abducted and murdered.
His abduction wasn't the first,
but it inspired young people
like me
to think, well,
how can we do something,
how can we make a change?
Suddenly, they heard a noise
that filled them with dread.
Ah! Ah!
The main focus of the play,
"The Traveling Circus,"
is the internally displaced
people.
You know, at any given time
in Sri Lanka since the 1980s,
we've had a population
upward of 200,000 displaced,
people who have lost
their homes,
their families, their lands.
Hurry up!
Don't waste my time.
What's in the bag?
It's just some-
- Can't take anything
inside the camp.
Search this.
Hurry up, next!
This play is in part
acknowledging what happened.
It is a record that
these terrible things
happened to the people
of our country.
But it is also trying
to offer some hope,
and I think that's something
that our company in general
and the play especially
is trying to say.
Never again.
What are we eating today,
by the way? What's good here?
So all these kitchens
are run by Muslims.
So there's no pork dishes here.
A lot of seafood.
Look out the window.
Two of my restaurants
work on no freezers.
We can have access
to great seafood any time.
That's a big cuttlefish.
Put him on the table.
Crabs.
I will definitely take
one of those, thank you.
It's delicious.
That is insanely good.
This is, what,
a rice and curry restaurant?
It's a typical Sri Lankan meal.
Big heavy earthenware vessels
filled with delicious things.
Yes.
You have the vegetables, spicy,
the chicken curry,
the fish curry.
I have three dogs,
and they don't eat dog food.
- No.
- They only eat curry.
- Really?
- Yeah, all of them eat curry.
Local special for you.
I'll take a shot of that.
Cheers.
Ah.
That will do it.